<?xml version="1.0" ?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.3 20210610//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>eLife</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">91774</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.91774</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi" specific-use="version">10.7554/eLife.91774.1</article-id>
<article-version-alternatives>
<article-version article-version-type="publication-state">reviewed preprint</article-version>
<article-version article-version-type="preprint-version">1.2</article-version>
</article-version-alternatives>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Ecology</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Pesticide-induced resurgence in brown planthopper is mediated by action on a suite of genes that promote juvenile hormone biosynthesis and female fecundity</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Yang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<name>
<surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>Shao-Cong</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Zhao-Yu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1147-7766</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Nässel</surname>
<given-names>Dick R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2590-1492</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Bass</surname>
<given-names>Chris</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1991-0322</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Cong-Fen</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0096-147X</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Shun-Fan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="a1"><label>a</label><institution>College of Plant Protection, Nanjing Agricultural University</institution>, Nanjing 210095, <country>China</country></aff>
<aff id="a2"><label>b</label><institution>Department of Zoology, Stockholm University</institution>, Stockholm, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
<aff id="a3"><label>c</label><institution>College of Life and Environmental Sciences, Biosciences, University of Exeter</institution>, Penryn Campus, Penryn, <country>UK</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="section">
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Sen</surname>
<given-names>Sonia Q</given-names>
</name>
<role>Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Tata Institute for Genetics and Society</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Bangalore</city>
<country>India</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="senior_editor">
<name>
<surname>VijayRaghavan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>National Centre for Biological Sciences, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Bangalore</city>
<country>India</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. E-mail address: <email>wusf@njau.edu.cn</email> (S.-F. Wu)</corresp>
<fn id="n1" fn-type="equal"><label>1</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date date-type="original-publication" iso-8601-date="2023-11-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2023</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<elocation-id>RP91774</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="sent-for-review" iso-8601-date="2023-09-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>09</month>
<year>2023</year>
</date>
</history>
<pub-history>
<event>
<event-desc>Preprint posted</event-desc>
<date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2023-10-07">
<day>07</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2023</year>
</date>
<self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.06.21.545881"/>
</event>
</pub-history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2023, Gao et al</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Gao et al</copyright-holder>
<ali:free_to_read/>
<license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-preprint-91774-v1.pdf"/>
<abstract>
<title>Abstract</title><p>Pesticide-induced resurgence, increases in pest insect populations following pesticide application, is a serious threat to the sustainable control of many highly damaging crop pests. Resurgence can result from pesticide-enhanced pest reproduction, however, the molecular mechanisms mediating this process remain unresolved. Here we show that brown planthopper (BPH) resurgence following emamectin benzoate (EB) exposure results from the coordinated action of a diverse suite of actors that regulate juvenile hormone (JH) levels, resulting in increased JH titer in adult females and enhanced fecundity. Following reports of BPH resurgence in rice crops when this species is exposed to EB, we demonstrate that EB treatment results in profound changes in female BPH fitness including enhanced ovarian development and elevated egg production. This enhanced reproductive fitness results from the EB-mediated upregulation of key genes involved in the regulation of JH, including <italic>JHAMT, Met and Kr-h1</italic> and the downregulation of allatostatin (<italic>AstA</italic>) and allatostatin receptor (<italic>AstAR</italic>) expression. The remodulation of gene expression following EB exposure is dependent on the action of this insecticide on its molecular target the glutamate-gated chloride channel (GluCl) receptor. Collectively, these results provide mechanistic insights into the regulation of negative pesticide-induced responses in insects and reveal the key actors involved in the JH-signaling pathway that underpin pesticide resurgence.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract>
<title>Significance</title>
<p>Pesticides remain a key means of controlling many of the world’s insect pests, however, in some cases, pesticide applications can result in resurgence of pest populations due to pesticide-induced increases in fecundity. In the current study we show that pesticide resurgence in the brown planthopper (BPH) following exposure to the insecticide emamectin benzoate results from the transcriptional reprogramming of a diverse suite of positive and negative regulators of juvenile hormone (JH), a critical regulator of insect development and reproduction. This in turn leads to profound increases in female BPH reproductive fitness and enhanced fecundity. Our findings unravel the molecular mechanisms mediating pesticide-induced pest resurgence and inform the development of novel strategies to control highly damaging crop pests.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>resurgence</kwd>
<kwd>reproduction</kwd>
<kwd>pesticide</kwd>
<kwd>brown planthopper</kwd>
</kwd-group>

</article-meta>
<notes>
<notes notes-type="competing-interest-statement">
<title>Competing Interest Statement</title><p>The authors have declared no competing interest.</p></notes>
<fn-group content-type="summary-of-updates">
<title>Summary of Updates:</title>
<fn fn-type="update"><p>I just revise the author name which appears on the website.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Chemical pesticides remain the primary means of controlling many of the world’s most damaging arthropod crop pests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>). However, pesticide applications can result in pest resurgence, increases in pest insect populations that exceed natural, untreated population sizes, following an initial reduction of the pest population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c5">5</xref>). Two mechanisms have been implicated in pest resurgence - the loss of beneficial insects including natural enemies and pesticide-enhanced pest reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>). In the case of the latter, several pesticides, such as the insecticides triazophos, deltamethrin and the fungicide jinggangmycin, have been reported to stimulate pest reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref>). Pesticide-enhanced pest reproduction has been linked to changes in physiology and biochemistry of pest organisms after exposure to pesticides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">4</xref>). However, the molecular mechanisms underlying enhanced reproduction associated with pest resurgence remain poorly resolved.</p>
<p>The brown planthopper (BPH), <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> (Stål), is a notorious pest of rice crops throughout Asia causing annual losses of ∼300 million dollars across major rice producing countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>). BPH inhibits the growth of rice plants by feeding, and also transmits highly damaging plant viruses including rice grassy stunt virus and rice ragged stunt virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">9</xref>). Currently, chemical insecticides play an indispensable role in the control of BPH due to their efficiency, rapid effect, and low cost. However, due to the widespread and intensive use of chemical insecticides, BPH has developed resistance to the majority of compounds used for control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c10">10</xref>).</p>
<p>Emamectin benzoate (EB) and abamectin are avermectin pesticides, and act as allosteric modulators of insect glutamate gated chloride channels (GluCls), inhibiting muscle contractions that lead to the cessation of insect feeding and subsequent death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">11</xref>). These insecticides exhibit particularly strong activity against Lepidoptera such as the rice leaffolder, <italic>Cnaphalocrocis medinalis</italic> Guénee, an important foliage-feeding insect which attacks rice during the vegetative stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>). Both BPH and the rice leaffolder are migratory pests with overlapping migratory paths, however, their occurrence period in the field differs by approximately one month, with leaffolders appearing earlier than BPH. Therefore, the use of EB to control rice leaffolder has the potential to impact BPH arriving later, via exposure to sublethal concentrations of this compound. In this regard, we have observed that when farmers use EB and abamectin to control leaffolders on rice crops in China, BPH outbreaks frequently occur in the same field. While sublethal doses of certain pesticides have been shown to enhance fecundity in BPH, including the insecticides triazophos and deltamethrin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c14">14</xref>) and the fungicides carbendazim and jinggangmycin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref>), whether avermectins trigger resurgence in BPH via insecticide-enhanced reproduction remains unclear.</p>
<p>Reproduction in insects is influenced by external factors such as light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c15">15</xref>), temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">16</xref>), humidity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">17</xref>) and nutrition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>), and endogenous factors such as the juvenile hormone (JH) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>), ecdysone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>), insulin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c21">21</xref>) and TOR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>) pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">24</xref>). Of these, JH has been particularly implicated in insecticide-induced enhanced fecundity, with triazophos and deltamethrin treatments leading to increased circulating JH III titers in BPH females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>). JH is synthesized and secreted by the corpora allata in insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">25</xref>), and can promote reproduction by regulating the synthesis and secretion of vitellogenin (vg) in the female fat body, and stimulating the absorption of vg by the developing oocyte (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>). However, the regulation of JH is complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>) and the key actors involved in JH-mediated pesticide-enhanced reproduction remains an open question. Previous finding reported that GluCl receptor is involved in JH biosynthesis in cockroach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">28</xref>). However, we know little whether insecticide which target on the GluCl can stimulate reproduction in insect pest and how GluCl receptor regulates JH production is still unknown.</p>
<p>In this study, we used a diverse range of approaches to investigate the impact of sublethal doses of avermectins on BPH fecundity, and unravel the molecular mechanisms mediating enhanced reproduction following exposure to this insecticide class. We show that avermectin exposure results in profound changes in the expression of a key suite of genes that in combination regulate JH, resulting in increased JH titer in adult females, which promotes fecundity. Interestingly, we found that GluCl channel modulators can inhibit Ast/AstAR expression and then promotes JH increasing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>GluCl allosteric modulators (emamectin benzoate and abamectin) stimulate fecundity of female <italic>N. lugens</italic></title>
<p>To investigate whether GluCl modulators affect fecundity in BPH, we first determined the sub-lethal and median lethal doses of emamectin benzoate (EB) to 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs, newly emerged males and females of BPH (Table S1). For this we employed two different bioassay methods, the rice seedling dip bioassay method and topical application bioassay method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref>), in order to assess both the systemic and contact toxicity of these insecticides (Table S1). We then systemically treated 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs of BPH with the estimated LC<sub>15</sub> and LC<sub>50</sub> concentrations of EB and examined the fecundity of BPH after these individuals mated with treated or untreated individuals. We use the term “t” to represent individuals treated with EB and “ck” to indicate control individuals that were treated with insecticide diluent minus insecticide. After treatment with the LC<sub>15</sub> and LC<sub>50</sub> concentrations of EB, the number of eggs laid per female of BPH in ♀t × ♂t crosses increased by 1.48 and 1.40 times compared with control ♀ck × ♂ck crosses (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>); the number of eggs laid per female of BPH in ♀t × ♂ck crosses increased by 1.53 and 2.07 times compared with control crosses (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>); However, the number of eggs laid by per female of BPH in ♀ck × ♂t crosses did not increase significantly compared to control ♀ck × ♂ck crosses (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Fecundity of BPH following exposure to sub-lethal (LC<sub>15</sub>) and median lethal (LC<sub>50</sub>) concentrations of emamectin benzoate following system application bioassays (A: ♀t ×♂t; B: ♀t ×♂ck; C: ♀ck ×♂t) and topical application bioassays (D: ♀t ×♂t; E: ♀t ×♂ck; F: ♀ck ×♂t), respectively. The letter “t” represents treatment with insecticide, while “ck” indicates controls that was not treated with insecticide. All data are presented as the mean ± s.e.m. Different lower-case letters above the bars indicate significant differences (One-way ANOVA with Tukey’s Multiple Range Test, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_fig1.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>Exposure of 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs with the LC<sub>15</sub> and LC<sub>50</sub> concentrations of EB in contact bioassays also significantly stimulated fecundity. After treatment with the LC<sub>15</sub> and LC<sub>50</sub> concentrations of EB, the number of eggs laid by per female of BPH in ♀t × ♂t crosses increased by 1.18 and 1.26 times compared with the control (♀ck × ♂ck) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>); The number of eggs laid per female of BPH in ♀t × ♂ck crosses increased by 1.27 and 1.56 times compared with the control crosses (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E</xref>); However, there was no significant difference in egg-laying number between ♀ck × ♂t crosses and controls (♀ck × ♂ck) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F</xref>). These results reveal that EB can stimulate the fecundity of females following both the systemic and contact routes of exposure.</p>
<p>We next examined whether EB treatment of adult BPH also stimulates reproduction. Indeed, treating newly emerged adults with the LC<sub>15</sub> and LC<sub>50</sub> concentrations of EB significantly stimulated the number of eggs laid per female (<xref rid="figs1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1-figure supplement 1A</xref>). Furthermore, sub-lethal exposure of 4<sup>th</sup> instar BPH nymphs to another GluCl allosteric modulator, abamectin (LC<sub>15</sub> and LC<sub>50</sub> concentrations) was also found to significantly enhance reproduction (<xref rid="figs1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1-figure supplement 1B</xref>).</p>
<p>To examine if EB also stimulates egg-laying in other insect species we conducted bioassays on the small brown planthopper, <italic>Laodelphax striatellus</italic>, the white backed planthopper, <italic>Sogatella furcifera</italic> and fruit flies <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>. In contrast to our findings on BPH, we found that sub-lethal doses (LC<sub>15</sub> and LC<sub>50</sub>) of EB inhibits fecundity of female <italic>L. striatellus</italic>, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="figs2">Figure1-figure supplement 2A-C</xref>) and has no impact on the fecundity of <italic>S. furcifera</italic>, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="figs2">Figure1-figure supplement 2D-F</xref>). In addition, we found that sublethal doses (LC<sub>15</sub> or LC<sub>50</sub>) of EB also inhibit fecundity in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="figs2">Figure1-figure supplement 2G and H</xref>). These results indicate that the stimulation of reproduction by EB in BPH is species-specific and does not extend to even related insect species.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2b">
<title>The impact of EB treatment on BPH reproductive fitness</title>
<p>To better understand the effects of EB on the reproductive fitness of BPH, the preoviposition period, emergence rate, female ratio, female longevity and female weight were evaluated following exposure using the systemic bioassay. The preoviposition period of females treated with the LC<sub>50</sub> of EB decreased significantly compared with the control (<xref rid="figs3" ref-type="fig">Figure 1-figure supplement 3A</xref>). In contrast no significant effects of EB on emergence rate and female ratio were observed (<xref rid="figs3" ref-type="fig">Figure 1-figure supplement 3B and C</xref>). Female survival analysis showed that exposure of 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs to the LC<sub>50</sub> of EB has no impact on female longevity (<xref rid="figs3" ref-type="fig">Figure 1-figure supplement 3D</xref>). Interestingly, brachypterism (long-wing) female ratio and female weight were significantly increased after EB exposure (<xref rid="figs3" ref-type="fig">Figure 1-figure supplement 3E and F</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2c">
<title>EB promotes ovarian development in BPH</title>
<p>To investigate the cause of increased female weight following EB exposure we examined if EB influences ovarian development in BPH. We dissected and compared the ovaries of females treated with the LC<sub>50</sub> of EB at 1, 3, 5 and 7 days after eclosion (DAE) with control females. At 3, 5 and 7 DAE, the number of detained eggs of BPH in the EB treated group were significantly higher than that of controls (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A and B</xref>). We also explored whether EB treatment could enhance or impair oogenesis in BPH. However, dissection of various developmental stages revealed that emamectin benzoate treatment has no significant effects on oogenesis (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C and D</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>The impact of emamectin benzoate on ovarian development in BPH. Fourth instar nymphs were treated with the LC<sub>50</sub> concentration of emamectin benzoate in systemic bioassays. (A) Ovarian development in EB treated BPH at 1, 3, 5 and 7 days after eclosion (DAE) compared to untreated controls. Scale bar = 1,000 μm. (B) Number of detained eggs in the ovaries of EB treated BPH females measured at 1, 3, 5 and 7 DAE compared to controls. All data are presented as the mean ± s.e.m. Asterisks indicate values significantly different from the control using student <italic>t</italic> test (ns, no significant; *<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 and **<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). (C) Different developmental stages of BPH eggs. (D) No impairment of emamectin benzoate on oogenesis of BPH. Scale bar = 100 μm.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_fig2.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2d">
<title>EB exposure enhances the abundances of storage macromolecules and circulating sugars in BPH</title>
<p>Nutritional status is an important indicator of reproductive fitness. Thus, to investigate whether EB affects intermediary metabolism and energy storage of BPH, glycogen, triacylglyceride (TAG), total protein content, cholesterol and four circulating carbohydrates were quantified in 4<sup>th</sup> instar BPH nymphs following exposure to the LC<sub>50</sub> of EB.</p>
<p>We found that EB exposure has no impact on glycogen levels (<xref rid="figs4" ref-type="fig">Figure 2-figure supplement 1A</xref>). The amounts of TAG in EB-treated BPH were 27% higher (p &lt; 0.05) than those in controls, but only in BPH of the late fifth instar (5L) stage, with no significant differences observed in subsequent developmental stages (<xref rid="figs4" ref-type="fig">Figure 2-figure supplement 1B</xref>). The amount of total protein content in EB-treated BPH was higher than the control groups in the case of all developmental stages from 5L nymph to 7DAE (<xref rid="figs4" ref-type="fig">Figure 2-figure supplement 1C</xref>). EB exposure also increased cholesterol levels at 4 and 5 DAE (<xref rid="figs4" ref-type="fig">Figure 2-figure supplement 1D</xref>). Compared with the solvent control, EB treatment caused significant increases (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the levels of sucrose, glucose, fructose, and trehalose (<xref rid="figs4" ref-type="fig">Figure 2-figure supplement 1E-H</xref>). Thus, collectively, these data provide evidence that EB exposure leads to energy mobilization and the metabolism of carbohydrates and lipids in BPH.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2e">
<title>EB stimulates egg-laying that is mediated by the JH signaling pathway</title>
<p>Given the important role of juvenile hormone (JH) in vitellogenesis and egg development in insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c30">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">32</xref>), we asked whether EB-treatment could influence the titer of JH in BPH. As measured by ELISA, the juvenile hormone titer of BPH nymphs treated with the LC<sub>50</sub> concentration of EB was significantly lower than that of controls in systemic bioassays during the middle and late stages of the 4<sup>th</sup> instar (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). However, at 2, 3 and 4 DAE, the JH titer in the EB treated group was significantly higher than that of the control (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). Interestingly, the titer of another important insect hormone, the steroid ecdysone, was not significantly different between EB-treated BPH and solvent-treated controls (<xref rid="figs5" ref-type="fig">Figure 3-figure supplement 1</xref>). To independently validate the results of ELISA assays, we employed HPLC-MS/MS to measure JH titer in BPH following EB exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">34</xref>). The results showed that JH III titer significantly decreased after EB-treatment at the late 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymph stage (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A and B</xref>), but significantly increased at the third day after eclosion (3 DAE) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A and C</xref>). To further investigate the role of JH in EB- enhanced fecundity in BPH, we treated BPH with methoprene and pyriproxyfen, JH analogues or biologically active JH mimics respectively, to determine whether they can stimulate fecundity in BPH. Both compounds significantly increased egg-laying in BPH (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D</xref>). Takes together these results reveal that EB stimulates an increase in JH titer that induces fecundity in BPH. Since we found that EB could induce JH synthesis in the BPH, we asked whether EB could influence the expression of genes that are involved in JH synthesis or degradation. For this we treated 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs of BPH with the LC<sub>50</sub> concentration of EB using systemic bioassays, and then collected early (5E), middle (5M) and late (5L) stage of 5<sup>th</sup> instar nymph and 1-7 DAE female adults (DAE) for analysis. Quantitative PCR was then used to examine the expression of key genes previously implicated in the regulation of JH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c36">36</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption><title>EB induced reproduction in BPH is mediated by components of the JH signaling pathway.</title>
<p>(A) The titer of JH III (as measured by ELISA assay) at different developmental stages of BPH when 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs were treated with the median lethal concentrations of EB. (B and C) The titer of JH III (as measured by HPLC-MS/MS) in BPH females at 4L and 3 DAE when treated with median lethal concentrations of EB. (D) Oviposition rate of BPH when 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs were treated with 4 ppm methoprene or 10 ppm pyriproxyfen. (E-J) Expression of selected JH-related genes (<italic>FAMeT</italic>, <italic>JHAMT</italic>, <italic>Met</italic>, <italic>Kr-h1</italic>, <italic>Vg</italic>, and <italic>JHE</italic>) in EB-treated BPH. (K) Egg production following silencing of <italic>JHAMT</italic> with or without EB application. (L) Egg production following silencing of <italic>met</italic> with or without EB application. (M) Egg production after silencing <italic>Kr-h1</italic> with or without EB application. (N) Schematic illustrating the proposed impact of EB on the JH signaling pathway leading to enhanced reproduction. The question mark indicates one or more potential additional signals. All data are presented as means ± s.e.m. Student’s <italic>t</italic> test was used to compare the two samples. One-way ANOVA with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test was used to compare more than two samples. ns, no significant difference; Asterisks indicate values significantly different from the control (ns, no significant; *<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 and ****<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Different lower-case letters above the bars indicate significant differences (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_fig3.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>Farnesoic acid O-methyltransferase (FAMeT) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c37">37</xref>), is known as an important enzyme in the JH biosynthetic pathway, catalyzing methylation of farnesoic acid (FA) to methyl farnesoate (MF) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c36">36</xref>). We found that this gene was significantly upregulated in 5M instar nymph to 4 DAE after EB- treatment (1.0-fold to 3.0-fold) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>). Another gene, juvenile hormone acid methyltransferase (JHAMT) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c38">38</xref>), which is involved in the biosynthesis of JH, was also upregulated in EB-treated BPH at 1 to 5 DAE than controls (1.5-fold to 3.0-fold) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3F</xref>). Methoprene-tolerant (Met), belongs the basic helix–loop–helix Per/Arnt/Sim (bHLH-PAS) family of transcription factors and is the intracellular (nuclear) receptor of JH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">40</xref>). The levels of <italic>met</italic> mRNA increased in EB-treated BPH at the 5M and 5L instar nymph and 1 to 5 DAE stages compared to controls (1.7-fold to 2.9-fold) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3G</xref>). Krüppel homolog 1 (<italic>Kr-h1</italic>), a transcriptional target of JH signaling, is reported to be sensitive to levels of JH and its expression levels are directly correlated with JH titers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">42</xref>). We found that <italic>Kr-h1</italic> was significantly upregulated in the adults of EB-treated BPH at the 5M, 5L nymph and 4 to 5 DAE stages (4.7-fold to 27.2-fold) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3H</xref>). Similarly, the expression levels of vitellogenin (Vg), a key downstream component of JH signaling triggering ovarian development in insects including BPH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c43">43</xref>), was markedly increased in females at 2–5 DAE by EB (1.7-fold to 5.5-fold) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3I</xref>). Juvenile hormone esterase (JHE) is the primary JH-specific degradation enzyme that plays a key role in regulating JH titers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">44</xref>). Interestingly, we observed a significant upregulation of JHE mRNA levels in the early and middle 5<sup>th</sup> instar nymph stage followed by downregulation in 5L instar nymphs of EB-treated BPH (1.3-fold to 2.6-fold) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3J</xref>). In combination these results reveal that EB has profound impacts on the expression of key genes involved in the synthesis of JH or downstream signaling pathway genes that might promote egg development.</p>
<p>To further understand whether these JH pathway-related genes were involved in egg-laying behavior in BPH, we performed RNAi experiments to downregulate the expression of <italic>JHAMT, Met and Kr-h1</italic> (<xref rid="figs6" ref-type="fig">Figure 3-figure supplement 2A-C</xref>). We found that silencing of these three genes downregulated the titer of JH in BPH providing functional evidence of their role in the regulation of JH (<xref rid="figs6" ref-type="fig">Figure 3-figure supplement 2D</xref>). Furthermore, silencing of <italic>Kr-h1</italic> inhibited <italic>FAMeT</italic> and <italic>Vg</italic> gene expression while increasing <italic>JHE</italic> gene expression (<xref rid="figs6" ref-type="fig">Figure 3-figure supplement 2E-H</xref>). Importantly, silencing of <italic>JHAMT</italic>, <italic>Met</italic> and <italic>Kr-h1</italic> gene in female BPH was also found to suppress egg-laying (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3K-M</xref>). However, this phenotype was rescued by EB treatment, which restored egg-laying to normal levels in BPH injected with <italic>JHAMT</italic>, <italic>Met</italic> and <italic>Kr-h1</italic> dsRNA (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3K-M</xref>). Together these results provide a mechanistic understanding of how EB enhances fecundity in BPH by modulating the expression of key genes involved in JH synthesis (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3N</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2f">
<title>EB induces JH biosynthesis through the peptidergic AstA/AstAR signaling pathway</title>
<p>The timing and level of JH biosynthesis can be precisely regulated by the neuropeptides, stimulatory allatotropins (ATs) and inhibitory allatostatins (Asts), in many insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c45">45</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c52">52</xref>). Insects can, in a species-specific manner, produce one type of AT and three types of Asts: FGL-amide Ast (AstA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c53">53</xref>); myoinhibitory peptide (MIP or AstB) and PISCF Ast (AstC) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c54">54</xref>). In some species, there also exists two paralogue genes of AstCs which are named AstCC and AstCCC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c56">56</xref>). Interestingly, the allatostatic activity of these three types of Ast peptides varies between insect species so that in each species only one type of Ast (for example AstA) controls JH production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c57">57</xref>).</p>
<p>Analysis of the BPH neural transcriptome sequence data has revealed the presence of one AT, four types of Asts and four corresponding receptors, allatotropin receptor (A16, ATR), AstA receptor (A2, AstAR), AstB (MIP) receptor (A10, AstBR or MIPR) and AstC receptor (A1, AstCR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c58">58</xref>). We cloned the five neuropeptide genes (AT, AstA, AstB/MIP, AstCC and AstCCC) and confirmed the sequence obtained from transcriptome data (<xref rid="figs7" ref-type="fig">Figure 4-figure supplement 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c58">58</xref>). Interestingly, we found that AstC is missing in the genome of BPH and only AstCC and AstCCC are present (<xref rid="figs7" ref-type="fig">Figure 4-figure supplement 1</xref>). Next, we also cloned their corresponding receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c55">55</xref>) including ATR (A16), AstAR (A2), AstBR (A10) and AstCR (A1) which might be activated by AstCC and/or AstCCC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c59">59</xref>). Sequence alignments and phylogenetic analysis are shown in <xref rid="figs8" ref-type="fig">Figure 4-figure supplement 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption><title>EB induced reproduction in BPH is mediated by the AstA/AstAR and JH signaling pathway.</title>
<p>(A and B) Expression of <italic>AstA</italic> and <italic>AstAR</italic> in different stages of BPH following EB treatment. (C) Downregulation of <italic>AstAR</italic> using RNAi leads to a reduction in mRNA expression level. (D) Egg production in female BPH following silencing of <italic>AstAR</italic> gene. (E-I) Expression of selected JH signaling pathway related genes (<italic>FAMeT</italic>, <italic>JHAMT</italic>, <italic>Met</italic>, <italic>Kr-h1</italic> and <italic>JHE</italic>) in <italic>AstAR</italic> silenced BPH. (J) JHIII titer of BPH females after <italic>AstAR</italic> gene silencing determined by HPLC-MS/MS. (K) Number of eggs laid per female in 48h following injection of six AstA1-AstA6 mature peptides and one AT mature peptide. Fifty nanoliter of PBS (as control) and seven peptides (20 pmol/insect) were injected into female BPH three days after eclosion. (L and M) The JH III titer of BPH females at different time points following AstA or AT injection. (N) Schematic of the proposed role of AstA/AstAR in the regulation of JH following EB exposure. The question mark indicates one or more possible additional signals. All data are presented as means ± s.e.m. Student’s <italic>t</italic> test was used to compare the two samples. One-way ANOVA with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test was used to compare more than two samples. ns, no significant difference; Asterisks indicate values significantly different from the control (ns, no significant; *<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 and ****<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Different lower-case letters above the bars indicate significant differences (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_fig4.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>Quantitative PCR was then used to examine if EB treatment could influence the expression of the genes encoding these neuropeptides and their receptors. Treating BPH with the LC<sub>50</sub> concentration of EB significantly increased the expression of <italic>AT</italic>, <italic>ATR</italic> and <italic>AstCCC</italic> while resulting in the downregulation of <italic>AstA, AstB/mip, AstCC</italic>, AstAR and <italic>AstBR/mipr</italic> at the adult stage (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A and B</xref>, <xref rid="figs9" ref-type="fig">Figure 4-figure supplement 3A-G</xref>). Among these, <italic>AstA</italic> and <italic>AstAR</italic> were the most downregulated genes after EB treatment (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A and B</xref>, <xref rid="figs9" ref-type="fig">Figure 4-figure supplement 3H</xref>) and thus the <italic>AstA/AstAR</italic> signaling system was selected for subsequent functional analysis. Silencing of <italic>AstAR</italic> in female BPH using RNAi (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>), resulted in an increased number of eggs laid per female compared with <italic>dsgfp</italic>-injected controls (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref>). Interestingly, silencing <italic>AstAR</italic> also resulted in the upregulation of <italic>FAMeT, JHAMT, Met</italic> and <italic>Kr-h1</italic> which are involved in the JH biosynthesis/signaling (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4E-H</xref>). However, <italic>JHE</italic> was not influenced by AstAR silencing (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4I</xref>). We therefore investigated whether silencing the <italic>AstAR</italic> gene could influence JH titer in BPH. A significantly increased JH titer was observed in <italic>AstAR</italic> silenced BPH compared with controls (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4J</xref>). Thus, our data strongly suggest that AstA is a key inhibitor of JH production in BPH.</p>
<p>Finally, we investigated whether injection of mature Ast and AT peptides could influence the number of eggs laid and JH titer in BPH. We synthesized one AT, six AstAs (AstA1 to AstA6), one AstCC and one AstCCC peptide according to their determined sequences (<xref rid="figs7" ref-type="fig">Figure 4-figure supplement 1</xref>). Indeed, we found that injection of AstA1 and AstA6 reduced the number of eggs laid per female in 48 h (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4K</xref>). We also observed that AstA1 injection after 16h and 48h decreased the JH titer significantly (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4L</xref>), and AT injection increased the JH titer after 2h but levels returned to normal 4h after injection (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4M</xref>). Collectively, these results provide compelling evidence that EB induces reproduction in BPH through the AstA/AstAR and JH signaling pathways (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4N</xref>) and further supports the role of AstA and AT in regulation of JH titer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2g">
<title>EB-enhanced fecundity in BPH is dependent on its molecular target protein the GluCl</title>
<p>EB and abamectin, are allosteric modulators, which target glutamate-gated chloride channels (GluCls) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c60">60</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c62">62</xref>). Hence, we examined whether EB-stimulated fecundity in BPH is influenced by its molecular target GluCl. The full length <italic>GluCl</italic> coding sequence from BPH was cloned and sequenced (<xref rid="figs10" ref-type="fig">Figure 5-figure supplement 1</xref>) and the impact of EB on <italic>GluCl</italic> gene expression examined using quantitative PCR. Treatment of BPH with the LC<sub>50</sub> concentration of EB significantly downregulated <italic>GluCl</italic> gene expression at the 5E and 5M nymph stages while upregulating <italic>GluCl</italic> gene expression at 2 DAE and 5 DAE in the adult stage (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>). To examine the role of <italic>GluCl</italic> gene in BPH fecundity, RNAi was used to knockdown expression of this gene in female BPH (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>). A significant decrease in the number of eggs laid by per female was observed in <italic>dsGluCl</italic>-injected insects compared with <italic>dsgfp</italic>-injected insects (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref>). However, treatment with EB was found to rescue the decreased egg-laying phenotype induced by <italic>dsGluCl</italic> injection (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref>). To investigate the mechanism by which <italic>GluCl</italic> expression modulates fecundity we examined if silencing <italic>GluCl</italic> influences JH titer and JH-related gene expression. Indeed, we observed that RNAi knockdown of <italic>GluCl</italic> leads to a decrease in JH titer (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D</xref>) and down-regulation of genes including <italic>JHAMT</italic> which is responsible for JH synthesis, and the JH signaling downstream genes <italic>Met and Kr-h1</italic> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5E-G</xref>). In contrast, expression of <italic>FAMeT</italic> and <italic>JHE</italic> were not changed in the <italic>GluCl</italic> silencing insects (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5H and I</xref>). We also examined whether silencing <italic>GluCl</italic> impacts the <italic>AstA</italic>/<italic>AstAR</italic> signaling pathway. Silencing <italic>GluCl</italic> was found to have no impact on the expression of <italic>AT</italic>, <italic>AstA</italic>, <italic>AstB</italic>, <italic>AstCC</italic>, <italic>AstAR</italic>, and <italic>AstBR</italic>. However, the expression of <italic>AstCCC</italic> and <italic>AstCR</italic> was significantly upregulated in <italic>dsGluCl</italic>-injected insects (<xref rid="figs11" ref-type="fig">Figure 5-figure supplement 2A-H</xref>). These results suggest that EB activates <italic>GluCl</italic> which induces JH biosynthesis and release, which in turn stimulates reproduction in BPH (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5J</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption><title>EB induced reproduction in brown planthoppers through its molecular target protein GluCl.</title>
<p>(A) Expression of <italic>GluCl</italic> in EB-treated and untreated BPH. (B) Expression of <italic>GluCl</italic> following injection of <italic>dsGluCl</italic> in BPH. (C) Egg production after <italic>GluCl</italic> gene knockdown in EB-treated and untreated BPH. (D) The JH III titer of BPH females after <italic>GluCl</italic> gene silencing as quantified using the ELISA method. (E-I) Expression patterns of selected JH-related genes (<italic>JHAMT</italic>, <italic>Met</italic>, <italic>Kr-h1</italic>, <italic>FAMeT</italic> and <italic>JHE</italic>) in <italic>GluCl</italic> silenced BPH. (J) Schematic of the proposed role of GluCl as a molecular target of EB and EB-enhanced reproduction in BPH. The question mark indicates one or more possible additional signals. All data are presented as means ± s.e.m. Student’s t test was used to compare the two samples. One-way ANOVA with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test was used to compare more than two samples. ns, no significant difference; Asterisks indicate values significantly different from the control (ns, no significant; *<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 and **<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Different lower-case letters above the bars indicate significant differences (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_fig5.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Pesticide-induced resurgence of pest insects is a serious problem in rice and several other cropping systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>). However, the mechanisms underpinning pesticide-enhanced reproduction in insects remain poorly understood. Here we reveal that a suite of molecular actors underlie this trait that, in combination, mediate profound physiological changes in the reproductive fitness of female BPH. Our data provide fundamental insights into the molecular mechanisms by which xenobiotics modify insect reproduction and have applied implications for the control of a highly damaging crop pest. We discuss these topics below.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Sublethal doses of GluCl modulators, EB and abamectin, stimulates fecundity in BPH</title>
<p>We show that in both contact and systemic assays EB and abamectin stimulate reproduction in BPH. Thus, insecticide-enhanced reproduction is likely a key factor in the BPH resurgence observed when farmers use EB and abamectin to control leaffolders in rice crops in China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref>). Although this is the first report of sublethal doses of avermectins enhancing insect fecundity, our findings are consistent with previous studies which have shown that certain insecticides, herbicides and fungicides stimulate BPH reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c63">63</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c68">68</xref>). Intriguingly, we show that EB only induces fecundity in female adults and is specific to BPH, with EB exposure failing to enhance reproduction in two related species, the small brown planthopper, <italic>L. striatellus</italic> and the white backed planthopper, <italic>S. furcifera</italic>, or the model insect <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>. Thus, the mechanisms underpinning this trait appear to act exclusively on female BPH and may be specific to this species.</p>
<p>Pesticides may stimulate insect reproduction through a variety of physiological and molecular mechanisms. Our data reveal that exposure to sub-lethal concentrations of EB results in profound changes to female BPH fitness, leading to increases in female weight, total protein content, cholesterol content, sugar content and egg production and decreases in duration of the preoviposition period. Some of these findings exhibit parallels with previous studies, which demonstrated that treating third-instar BPH nymphs with either deltamethrin, triazophos, or imidacloprid led to increased soluble sugar levels in the corresponding adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c69">69</xref>). Such metabolites provide the energy that drives BPH reproduction and resurgence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>). Thus, together with prior work, our results suggest that pesticides associated with resurgence stimulate nutritional intake in BPH to fuel enhanced energy-intensive reproduction.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s3b">
<title>The JH signaling pathway plays an essential role in EB-induced fecundity in BPH</title>
<p>JH is a pleiotropic hormone which plays important roles in development and reproduction in insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c70">70</xref>). Circulating JH titers are regulated by factors that control JH production in the corpora allata including biosynthetic enzymes and catabolic enzymes that regulate JH levels. Our results show that EB increases circulating JH III titers in BPH females over 2–4 days after eclosion (DAE) and promotes ovarian development. Previous studies have reported that triazophos and deltamethrin treatments also lead to increased circulating JH III titers in BPH females over 1–3 days post emergence. Similarly, jinggangmycin treatments were found to lead to increased JH titers (by approximately 45–50%) in BPH females over two days post emergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c71">71</xref>). Thus our findings, in combination with these previous studies, demonstrate that insecticide treatments can have dramatic effects on the regulation of key insect hormones involved in pest reproduction which can in turn drive pesticide resurgence.</p>
<p>Although increased JH titers following pesticide exposure have been correlated with reduced levels of active JH esterase during the first three days PE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">6</xref>), the type and number of mechanisms mediating the observed increase in hormone titer has remained an open question. Our data reveal that elevated JH titer in EB-exposed BPH is associated with the upregulation of genes that encode biosynthetic enzymes for JH (<italic>JHAMT</italic>) and downstream signaling genes that can induce <italic>vg</italic> gene expression (<italic>met</italic> and <italic>kr-h1</italic>). Using RNAi we provide functional evidence of the role of these genes in the regulation of JH III and fecundity of female BPH, and demonstrate that EB can restore the reduction in egg production resulting from the knockdown of <italic>JHAMT</italic>, <italic>met</italic> and <italic>kr-h1</italic> expression.</p>
<p>JHMAT is an enzyme that catalyzes the conversion of inactive precursors of JH to active JH in the final stages of JH biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c38">38</xref>). Interestingly, while it has not been previously implicated in pesticide resurgence, treatment of the stored product pest <italic>Sitotroga cerealella</italic> with diallyl trisulfide, an insecticidal compound in garlic essential oil, was found to increase JHAMT mRNA levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c72">72</xref>). Because JHMAT is the key rate-limiting enzyme in regulation of JH titer our results suggest that its enhanced expression is a key molecular mechanism of pesticide resurgence in BPH.</p>
<p>Met is a ligand-activated member of the basic helix–loop–helix Per/Arnt/Sim (bHLH-PAS) transcription factors and is the intracellular receptor for JH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">40</xref>). Kr-h1 is a zinc finger protein that acts downstream of Met and is expressed in response to JH signaling. Although the genes encoding these proteins have not been previously linked to pesticide resurgence, our finding that they are upregulated following EB exposure, and demonstration of their role of in promoting fecundity, is consistent with previous studies. Specifically, treatment of BPH with JH III or the insecticidal analogues methoprene or pyriproxifen was found to induce the expression of <italic>Kr-h1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c73">73</xref>). Furthermore, knockdown of <italic>Met</italic> and <italic>Kr-h1</italic> in BPH brachypterous females was found to result in delayed ovariole development and this was significantly more pronounced than the response observed in BPH treated separately with ds<italic>NlMet</italic> or ds<italic>NlKr-h1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c74">74</xref>). This finding provides evidence of a possible interaction between <italic>Met</italic> and <italic>Kr-h1</italic> and, in combination with our data, suggests that <italic>Met</italic> and <italic>Kr-h1</italic> may act in concert to mediate EB-enhanced fecundity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s3c">
<title>EB-induced fecundity in BPH is dependent on the allatostatin signaling pathway</title>
<p>In addition to regulatory proteins that promote JH production, insects have peptides that inhibit JH biosynthesis. These include the allatostatins: FGLamides (FGLa; AstA), the W(X)6Wamides (AstB), and the PISCFs (AstC) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c76">76</xref>). Interestingly, our results showed that EB exposure results in the marked downregulation of the expression of the genes encoding allatostatin <italic>AstA</italic> and its receptor <italic>AstAR</italic>. We provide clear evidence of the functional impact of this on JH synthesis and BPH fecundity by: i) demonstrating that RNAi knockdown of <italic>AstAR</italic> expression results in increased JH titer and enhanced female egg production, and, ii) showing that injection of female BPH with synthetic AStA peptide reduces JH titer and decreases egg production. Thus, our data provide unequivocal evidence that AstA is a key inhibitor of JH production in BPH. This finding is consistent with previous work which has shown that FGLa/ASTs inhibit JH biosynthesis in cockroaches, and termites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c77">77</xref>). To our knowledge, our study is the first report of insecticides inhibiting the expression of the neuropeptide receptor, <italic>AstAR</italic>, and linking this to increases in JH titer and enhanced reproduction in insects.</p>
<p>Interestingly knockdown of <italic>AstAR</italic> resulted in significant increases in the expression of genes involved in JH synthesis/signaling including <italic>FAMeT</italic> and <italic>JHAMT Met</italic> and <italic>Kr-h1</italic>. Related to this finding, previous work has shown that knockdown of the AstA receptor gene, <italic>Dar-2</italic>, in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> results in changes in the expression of genes encoding Drosophila insulin-like peptides (DILPs) and adipokinetic hormone (AKH) signaling proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c78">78</xref>). Together with our findings, this demonstrates that AstA receptors may modulate the expression of numerous downstream genes involves in metabolism, energy store and reproduction. In the case of pesticide resurgence our results imply significant cross-talk in the expression of genes that inhibit JH production and those that promote it.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s3d">
<title>The GluCl plays an essential role in EB-induced fecundity in BPH</title>
<p>EB and abamectin are allosteric modulators of GluCls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c60">60</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c62">62</xref>). Our data revealed that EB exposure modifies expression of the GluCl in BPH, and knockdown of GluCl expression resulted in a reduction in both JH levels and egg production. Interestingly, the GluCl has been reported to inhibit the biosynthesis of JH in the cockroach, <italic>Diploptera punctata</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">28</xref>). Recent work has also reported that modulation of glutamatergic signals may contribute to the photoperiodic control of reproduction in bean bug, <italic>Riptortus pedestris</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c79">79</xref>). Interestingly, work on <italic>D. punctata</italic> has revealed that application of the GluCl channel agonist ivermectin, which like EB belongs to the avermectin family, caused a decline in JH synthesis in corpus allatum glands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">28</xref>). While the inhibitory effect of ivermectin observed in this previous study differs from the activating effect of EB we observed in our study, it is consistent with our finding of a role for GluCl channel in the regulation of JH regulation. Interestingly, we found that knockdown of <italic>GluCl</italic> gene expression results in the down-regulation of <italic>JHAMT</italic>, <italic>Met and Kr-h1</italic>, further revealing significant convergent relationships between genes underpinning pesticide resurgence.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s4">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Our study has revealed a diverse suite of genes that act in combination to enhance JH titer and thus fecundity following BPH exposure to EB. A schematic of how these factors promote ovarian development in the adult stage of <italic>N. lugens</italic> through the JH signaling pathway is provided in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>. Our findings provide the foundation for further work to understand exactly how these genes interact and the mechanisms by which their expression is activated or repressed by EB. Furthermore, our findings provide fundamental insights into the molecular response in insects to xenobiotic stress and illustrate that pesticides can have unexpected and negative impacts on pest populations. In this regard our findings also have applied implications for the control of a highly damaging crop pest. Previous studies have reported that avermectins such as abamectin are toxic to the wolf spider <italic>Pardosa pseudoannulata</italic>, which is the main predator of BPH in rice crops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c81">81</xref>). Thus, these insecticides both stimulate reproduction in BPH while killing their natural enemies providing a ‘perfect storm’ for damaging BPH outbreaks. Based on these findings, to avoid BPH resurgence, we suggest that the GluCls, EB and abamectin, should not be (or rarely be) applied to rice plants at growth stages when BPHs are present. On a more optimistic note, our findings have identified numerous genes that play key roles in BPH reproduction and thus represent promising targets for the development of novel controls against this important pest.</p>
<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption><title>Schematic of the proposed regulatory pathway of EB-enhanced fecundity in BPH.</title>
<p>Emamectin benzoate (EB) exposure results in the upregulation of genes that promote JH production (<italic>JHAMT, Met and Kr-h1</italic>) and the downregulation of genes that inhibit it (allatostatin, Ast<italic>A</italic> and allatostatin A receptor, <italic>AstAR</italic>). This transcriptome reprograming is dependent on the action of EB on its molecular target the glutamate-gated chloride channel (GluCl) receptor. The resulting increased JH titer promotes vg synthesis and increased fecundity in EB exposed insects. We observe significant cross-talk in the expression of genes that inhibit JH production and those that promote it, with <italic>AstAR</italic> inhibiting the expression of <italic>JHAMT, Met</italic> and <italic>Kr-h1</italic> and <italic>GluCl</italic> activating the expression of <italic>JHAMT</italic> which is responsible for JH synthesis, and the JH signalling downstream genes <italic>Met and Kr-h1</italic>.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_fig6.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s5">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="s5a">
<title>Insects</title>
<p>BPH was initially collected from Wanan, JiangXi Province in 2020, reared on ‘Taichung Native 1’ (TN1) rice seedlings in the laboratory without exposure to any insecticides. The strain was maintained in a climatic chamber at 27 ± 1°C, with relative humidity of 70 ± 10% and a light: dark = 16 h: 8 h photoperiod.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5b">
<title>Chemicals</title>
<p>Emamectin benzoate (95.2%) was obtained from Hebei Weiyuan Co., Ltd. (Hebei, China). Abamectin (96.8%) was obtained from Hebei Weiyuan Co., Ltd. (Hebei, China). Pyriproxyfen (98%) was obtained from Shanghai Shengnong Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). Methoprene (S)-(+) (mx7457-100mg) was purchased from Shanghai MaoKang Biotechnology Co., Ltd., (Shanghai, China). Juvenile hormone standard sample (J912305-10mg) was purchased from Shanghai Macklin Biotechnology Co., Ltd., (Shanghai, China).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5c">
<title>Bioassay</title>
<p>Different life stages of insects were used to perform bioassay to investigate the effects of insecticide on nymphs and adults. To test whether treatment of the nymph stage of insects would promote reproduction in female, we used 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs of BPH or 3<sup>rd</sup> instar nymph of <italic>Laodelphax striatellus</italic> and <italic>Sogatella furcifera</italic> to perform bioassays. To test whether treatment of the adult stage of insects would promote reproduction in female, we used newly emerged male and female BPH.</p>
<sec id="s5c1">
<title>Systemic route</title>
<p>The rice-seeding dipping bioassay method was used to evaluate the susceptibility of BPH, <italic>L. striatellus</italic> and <italic>S. furcifera</italic> to EB. Technical-grade insecticides were dissolved in acetone as stock solution then diluted in a series of six concentrations with water containing 0.1% Triton. Selected rice seedlings at the 6-8 cm growth stage were dipped in insecticide solutions for 30 s and then air-dried at room temperature. The roots of the rice seedlings were wrapped with cotton strips and placed seedlings placed in a plastic cup 5 cm in diameter. Fifteen insects were introduced into each plastic cup for each replicate. The top of the cup was then selaed with gauze to prevent escape. All experiments comprised at least three biological replicates. Control rice seedings were treated with 0.1% Triton X-100 water solution only. All treatments were maintained under standard conditions of 27 ± 1 °C and 70– 80% relative humidity with a 16 h light/8 h dark photoperiod. Mortality was assessed after 4 d for <italic>N. lugens</italic> or 2 d for <italic>L. striatellus</italic> and <italic>S. furcifera</italic> after treatment with insecticides. The insects were considered dead if they were unable to move after a gentle prodding with a fine brush.</p>
<p>For <italic>Drosophila</italic> larvae bioassay, we adopted a method described previously in our lab with minor modifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c82">82</xref>). Briefly, twenty third instar larvae were placed in fly vials containing fly food (based on corn powder, brown sugar, yeast and agar) supplemented with EB of different concentrations. Four concentrations (LC<sub>10</sub>, LC<sub>30</sub> and LC<sub>50</sub>) were tested together with a negative (no insecticide) control. For <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult bioassays, we selected virgin females three days after eclosion. Several concentrations were overlaid onto fly food in standard <italic>Drosophila</italic> vials and allowed to dry overnight at room temperature. 15 adult flies (three days after eclosion) were then added to each vial and mortality assessed after 2 d. Four replicates were carried out for each concentration. Control mortality was assessed using vials containing food with solvent minus insecticide.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5c2">
<title>Contact route</title>
<p>For topical bioassays working insecticide solutions were prepared in acetone. 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs or newly emerged males/females were anesthetized with carbon dioxide for 5 s, and then 0.04 μl/insect test solution applied topically to the dorsal plates with a capillary micro-applicator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref>). Insects were then placed in an artificial climate incubator with a temperature of 27±1°C, a photoperiod of 16:8 h (L:D), and a humidity of 70%±10%. Mortality was determined 2 d after treatment. Data with over 20% mortality in the control treatment were discarded, and the assay was repeated at least three times.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s5d">
<title>Fecundity assays</title>
<p>Fourth instar nymphs of BPH and 3<sup>rd</sup> instar nymph of <italic>L. striatellus</italic> and <italic>S. furcifera</italic> were treated with the LC<sub>15</sub> and LC<sub>50</sub> of EB, and then transferred to fresh rice seedlings. After eclosion, the adults were used in the following experiment. Newly emerged treated adults and untreated adults were paired to produce four groups: untreated males and untreated females (♂ck×♀ck; ck indicates untreated); untreated males and treated females (♂ck×♀t; t indicates insecticide treated); treated males and untreated females (♂t×♀ck); treated males and treated females (♂t×♀t). Each group comprised at least 10 mating pairs. All pairs were transferred to glass cylinders (diameter 5 cm and height 20 cm) containing rice plants (25 days old almost 20 cm high) as a food source for eleven days. The number of eggs and nymphs in plants were counted by a microscope.</p>
<p>For <italic>Drosophila</italic> egg-laying assay, we adopted our previous method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c83">83</xref>). Briefly, insecticide-treated virgin females were paired with untreated males for three days and then the mated females transferred into the <italic>Drosophila</italic> ovipositing apparatus. The number of eggs were counted after 16 hours.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5e">
<title>Fitness analysis</title>
<p>The fitness of EB-treated BPH were analyzed using methods reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c10">10</xref>). We selected two groups, (♂ck×♀ck) and (♂ck×♀t), to study the effects of the LC<sub>50</sub> concentration of EB on BPH fitness. In the case of systemic exposure, 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs of BPH were treated with the LC<sub>50</sub> of EB for 4 days and then transferred to tubes containing untreated rice plants for individual rearing. The rice plants were replaced every three days with untreated plants. The emergence ratio, female ratio, preoviposition period, female longevity, brachypterism female ratio and female weight were calculated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5f">
<title>Examination of ovarian development</title>
<p>Adult females from ♂ck×♀ck control and ♂ck×♀t group on 1, 3, 5, 7 DAE were dissected for observe the ovarian development. The detained eggs in ovary were photographed and recorded. Each group has at least fifteen replicates.</p>
<p>To examination whether EB treated impairs egg maturation, we dissected untreated or EB-treated ovaries and fixed them in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) for 30 min at room temperature. After four washes of 10 min (4 × 10 min) in PAT3 (PBS with 0.5% Triton X-100 and 0.5% bovine serum albumin), the ovaries were then incubated with DAPI (4’,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole, 100 nM) and Actin-stain 670 Fluorescent Phalloidin (200 nM). Imaging was performed using Zeiss LSM980 confocal laser microscope.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5g">
<title>Measurements of glycogen, triglyceride, total protein content, cholesterol and four sugars</title>
<p>The content of glycogen, triglyceride, cholesterol and total protein was determined by spectrophotometry at 620 nm, 510 nm, 510 nm and 562 nm respectively using the glycogen assay kit (A043-1-1), triglyceride reagent kit (A110-1-1), cholesterol assay kit (A111-1-1) and total protein assay kit (A045-2-2) obtained from Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute following to the manufacturer’s instructions. The determined results were normalized to the protein content in the sample, which was determined using BCA Protein Assay Reagent Kit (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, USA). Each sample contained tissue extracts from five adult female BPH, with three biological replicates per sample.</p>
<p>To assess the content of four sugars (sucrose, glucose, fructose and trehalose) in the extract of BPH tissue, the same extraction method was used as above. Sugar content was quantified using the colorimetric method by scanning at 290 nm, 505 nm, 285 nm and 620 nm respectively using the sucrose reagent kit (A099-1-1), glucose reagent kit (F006-1-1), fructose reagent kit (A085-1-1) and trehalose reagent kit (A150-1-1) obtained from Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute based on the manufacturer’s instructions. Each sample contained tissue extracts from five adult female <italic>N. lugens</italic>, with three biological replicates per sample.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5h">
<title>Determination of Juvenile hormone III and ecdysone titers of BPH by ELISA</title>
<p>The titer of Juvenile hormone III in BPH was measured using the Juvenile hormone ELISA Kit (Lot Number: HLE92086, Shanghai HaLing Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China) which employs the dual-antibody sandwich ELISA method. The titer of ecdysone in BPH were measured using the ecdysone ELISA Kit (Lot Number: ZK14705, Shanghai ZhenKe Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China). At least three biological replicates were employed for each treatment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5i">
<title>Determination of Juvenile hormone III titer in BPH using HPLC-MS/MS</title>
<p>The whole bodies of 5 individuals BPH were mixed with 1 ml of n-hexane, followed by centrifugation at 10,000×g for 10 min, the upper hexane layer was then dried with nitrogen, dissolved in methanol and sonicated for 10 min, after centrifugation at 10000×g for 10 min, the supernatant was collected through the organic filter membrane of 0.22 μm into 2 ml vials for JH Ⅲ determination. JH Ⅲ standard sample (J912305-10 mg) purchased from (Shanghai McLean Biochemical Technology Co. Ltd), dissolved in methyl alcohol as stock solution 10,000 mg/L was diluted in a series of six concentration gradients to serve as a reference. Liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) was then carried out using UPLC Xevo TQ-S Micro (Waters technology), quantitative method according to the external standard, the chromatographic column was EC-C18 (4.6 mm×150 mm, 2.7 μm), column temperature was 30°C, injection volume was 20 μl, elution flow rate was 0.3 ml/min, and the mobile phase was acetonitrile:formic acid water (90:10), detection wavelength was 218 nm, the peak height was used for quantification.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5j">
<title>Cloning, sequence and phylogenetic analysis</title>
<p>The NCBI database and BLAST program were used to carry out sequence alignment and analysis. Open Reading Frames (ORFs) were predicted with EditSeq. Primers were designed using the primer design tool in NCBI. Total RNA Extraction was extracted from 30 adults BPH using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. cDNA was synthesized using the Biotech M-MLV reverse transcription kit. Full-length gene sequences were amplified by PCR using cDNA as template and Rapid Taq Master Mix (Vazyme Biotech, Cat# P222-02). The PCR product was purified on a 1% agarose gel, cloned into pClone007 Simple Vector Kit (Tsingke Biotech, Cat# TSV-007S), and then sequenced using the 3730 XL DNA analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Table S2 contains a list of the primers used in this study.</p>
<p>The exon and intron architectures of AT, AstA, AstB, AstCC and AstACCC were predicted based on the alignments of putative ORFs against their corresponding genomic sequences. Sequence similarity/annotations and orthologous gene searches were performed using BLAST programs available in NCBI. Multiple alignments of the complete amino acid sequences were performed with Clustal Omega (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo</ext-link>). Phylogeny was conducted using the maximum likelihood technique to create phylogenetic trees and these were bootstrapped with 1000 replications were used using the MEGA 6 software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c84">84</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5k">
<title>RNA interference</title>
<p>Double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) of <italic>gfp</italic> (green fluorescent protein), <italic>JHAMT</italic> (juvenile hormone acid O-methyltransferase,), <italic>Met</italic> (methoprene-tolerant), <italic>Kr-h1</italic> (krüppel homolog 1), <italic>AstAR</italic> (allatostatin-A receptor) and <italic>GluCl</italic> (glutamate-gated chloride channel) was prepared using Ambion’s MEGAscript T7 kit instructions following the manufacturer’s instructions. The primer sequences for double-stranded RNA synthesis are listed in Table S2. Newly emerged females were injected with 40 nl (5,000 ng/μl) of double-stranded RNA of <italic>gfp</italic> (<italic>dsgfp</italic>) or double-stranded RNA of the target genes in the conjunctive part between prothorax and mesothorax of insects. In the RNAi experiments, BPH were then treated with the LC<sub>50</sub> of EB 24h after dsRNA injection and the whole body sampled for qRT-PCR analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5l">
<title>Quantitative RT-PCR</title>
<p>Fourth instar nymphs of BPH were treated with EB after which total RNA was extracted from 5<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs and 1-7 day post-eclosion females of <italic>N. lugens</italic> using the methods detailed above. The HiScript® II RT SuperMix for qPCR (+gDNA wiper) kit from Vazyme, Nanjing, China, was used to create first-strand cDNA. Primer3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.ut.ee/primer3/">http://bioinfo.ut.ee/primer3/</ext-link>) was used to design real-time quantitative PCR (qPCR) primers listed in Table S2. mRNA levels of candidate genes were detected by qPCR using the UltraSYBR Mixture (with ROX) Kit (CWBIO, Beijing, China). Each reaction contained 2 μL of cDNA template (500 ng), 1 μL each forward and reverse qPCR primer (10 μM), 10 μL of UltraSYBR mixture buffer, and 6 μL of RNase-free water. Q-PCR was run on an ABI 7500 Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) under the following conditions: 5 min at 95°C, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 10 s and 60°C for 30 s. Three independent biological replicates and four technical replicates were used in each qPCR experiment. The housekeeping genes 18S ribosomal RNA of BPH were selected to normalize the expression of candidate genes. The <italic>2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup></italic> method (Ct represents the cycle threshold) was used to measure relative expression levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c85">85</xref>). Three biological replicates were used for statistical comparison between samples. Table S2 contains a list of the primers used in this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5m">
<title>Statistics</title>
<p>PoloPlus v2.0 (LeOra Sofware 2008) was used to calculate the lethal concentration (LC<sub>50</sub>) and 95% fiducial limits (95% F.L.). GraphPad Prism 8.0 software (GraphPad Software Inc., San Diego, USA) was used to generate graphs and perform statistical analysis of data. Data presented in this study were first verified for normal distribution using the D’Agostino–Pearson normality test. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Duncan’s multiple range test was used to test differences among multiple groups of normally distributed groups of data. Student’s t test was used to test the differences between two groups. If not normally distributed, Mann–Whitney test was used for pairwise comparisons, and Kruskal–Wallis test was used for comparisons among multiple groups, followed by Dunn’s multiple comparisons. All data are presented as mean ± s.e.m. The sample sizes and statistical tests used for each experiment are stated in the figures or figure legends.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>This research was funded by the National Key R&amp;D Program of China to SFW (2022YFD1700200) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://service.most.gov.cn/">https://service.most.gov.cn/</ext-link>) and National Natural Science Foundation of China to SFW (32022011) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nsfc.gov.cn/">https://www.nsfc.gov.cn/</ext-link>).</p>
</ack>
<sec id="s6">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China to SFW (No.32022011 &amp; 31772205) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://isisn.nsfc.gov.cn/egrantindex/funcindex/prjsearch-list?locale=zh_CN">https://isisn.nsfc.gov.cn/egrantindex/funcindex/prjsearch-list?locale=zh_CN</ext-link>).</p>
<p>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="c1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Janssen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>P. C. J.</given-names> <surname>van Rijn</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Pesticides do not significantly reduce arthropod pest densities in the presence of natural enemies</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source>. <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>2010</fpage>–<lpage>2024</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>S. F.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>The evolution of insecticide resistance in the brown planthopper (<italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> Stål) of China in the period 2012–2016</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep</source>. <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>4586</fpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names> <surname>Ge</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>F.</given-names> <surname>Liu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Q.</given-names> <surname>Song</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>D.</given-names> <surname>Stanley</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Pesticide-induced planthopper population resurgence in rice cropping systems</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>409</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>R. N. C.</given-names> <surname>Guedes</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>G.</given-names> <surname>Smagghe</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J. D.</given-names> <surname>Stark</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>N.</given-names> <surname>Desneux</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Pesticide-induced stress in arthropod pests for optimized integrated pest management programs</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>M. R.</given-names> <surname>Hardin</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Arthropod pest resurgence: an overview of potential mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Crop Protection</source> <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>L.-Q.</given-names> <surname>Ge</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.-C.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K.-F.</given-names> <surname>Zhao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>G.-Q.</given-names> <surname>Yang</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Induction of Nlvg and suppression of Nljhe gene expression in <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> (Stål) (Hemiptera: Delphacidae) adult females and males exposed to two insecticides</article-title>. <source>Pestic. Biochem. Physiol</source>. <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>Y.-X.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Effects of two pesticides, TZP and JGM, on reproduction of three planthopper species, <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> Stål, <italic>Sogatella furcifera</italic> Horvath, and <italic>Laodelphax striatella</italic> Fallén</article-title>. <source>Pestic. Biochem. Physiol</source>. <volume>115</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Two fungicides alter reproduction of the small brown planthopper <italic>Laodelphax striatellus</italic> by influencing gene and protein expression</article-title>. <source>J Proteome Res</source>. <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>978</fpage>–<lpage>986</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Sōgawa</surname></string-name>, <article-title>The rice brown planthopper: Feeding physiology and host plant interactions</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage> (<year>1982</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Zeng</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>A chitin synthase mutation confers widespread resistance to buprofezin, a chitin synthesis inhibitor, in the brown planthopper</article-title>, <source>Nilaparvata lugens. J. Pest Sci</source>. <volume>96</volume>, <fpage>819</fpage>–<lpage>832</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>I.</given-names> <surname>Ishaaya</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Kontsedalov</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A. R.</given-names> <surname>Horowitz</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Emamectin, a novel insecticide for controlling field crop pests</article-title>. <source>Pest Manag. Sci</source>. <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1091</fpage>–<lpage>1095</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>P.</given-names> <surname>Chintalapati</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>G.</given-names> <surname>Katti</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>R. R.</given-names> <surname>Puskur</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Nagella Venkata</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Neonicotinoid-induced resurgence of rice leaffolder, <italic>Cnaphalocrocis medinalis</italic> (Guénee)</article-title>. <source>Pest Manag. Sci</source>. <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Reproductive outbreaks of <italic>Sogatella furcifera</italic> mediated by overexpression of the nuclear receptor USP under pressure from triflumezopyrim</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>13769</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>L.-Q.</given-names> <surname>Ge</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Molecular basis for insecticide-enhanced thermotolerance in the brown planthopper <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> Stål (Hemiptera:Delphacidae)</article-title>. <source>Mol. Ecol</source>. <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>5624</fpage>–<lpage>5634</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>G.</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Clock genes and environmental cues coordinate <italic>Anopheles</italic> pheromone synthesis, swarming, and mating</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>371</volume>, <issue>411</issue> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>M. R.</given-names> <surname>Meiselman</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Recovery from cold-induced reproductive dormancy is regulated by temperature-dependent AstC signaling</article-title>. <source>Current Biol</source>. <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1362</fpage>–<lpage>1375.e1368</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Roy</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Regulation of gene expression patterns in mosquito reproduction</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e1005450</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>V.</given-names> <surname>Smykal</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A. S.</given-names> <surname>Raikhel</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Nutritional control of insect reproduction</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Insect Sci</source>. <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>C. G.</given-names> <surname>Santos</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>F. C.</given-names> <surname>Humann</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Hartfelder</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Juvenile hormone signaling in insect oogenesis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Insect Sci</source>. <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>L. V.</given-names> <surname>Hun</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Essential functions of mosquito ecdysone importers in development and reproduction</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>119</volume>, <fpage>e2202932119</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>L.</given-names> <surname>Ling</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A. S.</given-names> <surname>Raikhel</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Serotonin signaling regulates insulin-like peptides for growth, reproduction, and metabolism in the disease vector <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>115</volume>, <fpage>E9822</fpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Lu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>X.</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>W.-T.</given-names> <surname>Liu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Q.</given-names> <surname>Zhou</surname></string-name>, <article-title>TOR pathway-mediated juvenile hormone synthesis regulates nutrient-dependent female reproduction in <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> (Stål)</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Mol. Sci</source>. <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>438</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Du</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>D.</given-names> <surname>Ding</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Ma</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>W.</given-names> <surname>Guo</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names> <surname>Kang</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Locust density shapes energy metabolism and oxidative stress resulting in divergence of flight traits</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>119</volume>, <fpage>e2115753118</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>T. H.</given-names> <surname>Ahmed</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T. R.</given-names> <surname>Saunders</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>D.</given-names> <surname>Mullins</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. Z.</given-names> <surname>Rahman</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Zhu</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Molecular action of pyriproxyfen: Role of the Methoprene-tolerant protein in the pyriproxyfen-induced sterilization of adult female mosquitoes</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>. <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>e0008669</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>W.</given-names> <surname>Luo</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Juvenile hormone signaling promotes ovulation and maintains egg shape by inducing expression of extracellular matrix genes</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A</source>. <volume>118</volume>, <fpage>e2104461118</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>A.-S.</given-names> <surname>Chiang</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Insect NMDA receptors mediate juvenile hormone biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>99</volume>, <issue>37</issue> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>A.-S.</given-names> <surname>Chiang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. A.</given-names> <surname>Pszczolkowski</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>H.-P.</given-names> <surname>Liu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.-C.</given-names> <surname>Lin</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Ionotropic glutamate receptors mediate juvenile hormone synthesis in the cockroach, Diploptera punctata</article-title>. <source>Insect Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</source> <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>678</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>H.-P.</given-names> <surname>Liu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.-C.</given-names> <surname>Lin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.-Y.</given-names> <surname>Lin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.-R.</given-names> <surname>Yeh</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.-S.</given-names> <surname>Chiang</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Glutamate-gated chloride channels inhibit juvenile hormone biosynthesis in the cockroach, <italic>Diploptera punctata</italic></article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1260</fpage>–<lpage>1268</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>R.</given-names> <surname>Yao</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Monitoring and mechanisms of insecticide resistance in <italic>Chilo suppressalis</italic> (Lepidoptera: Crambidae), with special reference to diamides</article-title>. <source>Pest Manag. Sci</source>. <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>1169</fpage>–<lpage>1178</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>Y.-P.</given-names> <surname>Jing</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>The vitellogenin receptor functionality of the migratory locust depends on its phosphorylation by juvenile hormone</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>118</volume>, <fpage>e2106908118</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>L.</given-names> <surname>Ling</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A. S.</given-names> <surname>Raikhel</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Cross-talk of insulin-like peptides, juvenile hormone, and 20-hydroxyecdysone in regulation of metabolism in the mosquito Aedes aegypti</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A</source>. <volume>118</volume>, <fpage>e2023470118</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Zheng</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Juvenile hormone promotes paracellular transport of yolk proteins via remodeling zonula adherens at tricellular junctions in the follicular epithelium</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>e1010292</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>W.</given-names> <surname>Guo</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Juvenile hormone suppresses aggregation behavior through influencing antennal gene expression in locusts</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>e1008762</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Bownes</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Rembold</surname></string-name>, <article-title>The titre of juvenile hormone during the pupal and adult stages of the life cycle of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source>. <volume>164</volume>, <fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage> (<year>1987</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Gospocic</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Kr-h1 maintains distinct caste-specific neurotranscriptomes in response to socially regulated hormones</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>184</volume>, <fpage>5807</fpage>–<lpage>5823</lpage>.e5814 (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Nouzova</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Rivera-Pérez</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>F. G.</given-names> <surname>Noriega</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Omics approaches to study juvenile hormone synthesis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Insect Sci</source>. <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Liu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Yang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Gu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Z.</given-names> <surname>Liu</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Cloning and characterization of a putative farnesoic acid O -methyltransferase gene from the brown planthopper, <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic></article-title>. <source>J Insect Sci</source>. <volume>10</volume> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>T.</given-names> <surname>Shinoda</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Itoyama</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Juvenile hormone acid methyltransferase: A key regulatory enzyme for insect metamorphosis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>11986</fpage> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>G.-H.</given-names> <surname>Zhu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Jiao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S. C. R. R.</given-names> <surname>Chereddy</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. Y.</given-names> <surname>Noh</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S. R.</given-names> <surname>Palli</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Knockout of juvenile hormone receptor, Methoprene-tolerant, induces black larval phenotype in the yellow fever mosquito, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1905729116</pub-id>, <fpage>201905729</fpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>L. M.</given-names> <surname>Riddiford</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Rhodnius, golden oil, and met: A history of juvenile hormone research</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Dev Biol</source>. <volume>8</volume> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Jindra</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S. R.</given-names> <surname>Palli</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L. M.</given-names> <surname>Riddiford</surname></string-name>, <article-title>The juvenile hormone signaling pathway in insect development</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A. J.</given-names> <surname>Kim</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Rivera-Perez</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>F. G.</given-names> <surname>Noriega</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names> <surname>Kim</surname></string-name>, <article-title>The insect somatostatin pathway gates vitellogenesis progression during reproductive maturation and the post-mating response</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>969</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Shen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.-Z.</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names> <surname>Lou</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.-X.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Vitellogenin and vitellogenin-like genes in the brown planthopper</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol</source>. <volume>10</volume> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>S. G.</given-names> <surname>Kamita</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Juvenile hormone (JH) esterase: why are you so JH specific?</article-title> <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1261</fpage>–<lpage>1273</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Kataoka</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Identification of an allatotropin from adult <italic>Manduca Sexta</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>243</volume>, <fpage>1481</fpage>–<lpage>1483</lpage> (<year>1989</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>A. P.</given-names> <surname>Woodhead</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Stay</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S. L.</given-names> <surname>Seidel</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. A.</given-names> <surname>Khan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S. S.</given-names> <surname>Tobe</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Primary structure of four allatostatins: neuropeptide inhibitors of juvenile hormone synthesis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>5997</fpage>–<lpage>6001</lpage> (<year>1989</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>S. J.</given-names> <surname>Kramer</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Identification of an allatostatin from the tobacco hornworm <italic>Manduca sexta</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>9458</fpage>–<lpage>9462</lpage> (<year>1991</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>M. W.</given-names> <surname>Lorenz</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>R.</given-names> <surname>Kellner</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K. H.</given-names> <surname>Hoffmann</surname></string-name>, <article-title>A family of neuropeptides that inhibit juvenile hormone biosynthesis in the cricket, <italic>Gryllus bimaculatus</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem</source>. <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>21103</fpage>–<lpage>21108</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>X.</given-names> <surname>Bellés</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>The molecular evolution of the allatostatin precursor in cockroaches</article-title>. <source>Peptides</source> <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Stay</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S. S.</given-names> <surname>Tobe</surname></string-name>, <article-title>The role of allatostatins in juvenile hormone synthesis in insects and crustaceans</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Wegener</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Allatostatin A signalling: Progress and new challenges from a paradigmatic pleiotropic invertebrate neuropeptide family</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol</source>. <volume>13</volume> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Verlinden</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>The pleiotropic allatoregulatory neuropeptides and their receptors: A mini-review</article-title>. <source>J Insect Physiol</source>. <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>G.-L.</given-names> <surname>Yin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.-S.</given-names> <surname>Yang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.-X.</given-names> <surname>Cao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>W.-J.</given-names> <surname>Yang</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of FGLamide allatostatin gene from the prawn, <italic>Macrobrachium rosenbergii</italic></article-title>. <source>Peptides</source> <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1241</fpage>–<lpage>1250</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>I.</given-names> <surname>Chin-Sang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>W. G.</given-names> <surname>Bendena</surname></string-name>, <article-title>The FGLamide-Allatostatins influence foraging behavior in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source> <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e36059</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>J. A.</given-names> <surname>Veenstra</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Allatostatin C and its paralog allatostatin double C: The arthropod somatostatins</article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>J. A.</given-names> <surname>Veenstra</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Allatostatins C, double C and triple C, the result of a local gene triplication in an ancestral arthropod</article-title>. <source>Gen Comp Endocrinol</source>. <volume>230-231</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>D. R.</given-names> <surname>Nässel</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Neuropeptides in the nervous system of <italic>Drosophila</italic> and other insects: multiple roles as neuromodulators and neurohormones</article-title>. <source>Prog Neurobiol</source>. <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Tanaka</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Suetsugu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Yamamoto</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Noda</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names> <surname>Shinoda</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Transcriptome analysis of neuropeptides and G-protein coupled receptors (GPCRs) for neuropeptides in the brown planthopper <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic></article-title>. <source>Peptides</source> <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>N.</given-names> <surname>Audsley</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Characterisation and tissue distribution of the PISCF allatostatin receptor in the red flour beetle, <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>T. C.</given-names> <surname>Sparks</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>N.</given-names> <surname>Storer</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Porter</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>R.</given-names> <surname>Slater</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>R.</given-names> <surname>Nauen</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Insecticide resistance management and industry: the origins and evolution of the Insecticide Resistance Action Committee (IRAC) and the mode of action classification scheme</article-title>. <source>Pest Manag. Sci</source>. <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>2609</fpage>–<lpage>2619</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>T. C.</given-names> <surname>Sparks</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Insecticides, biologics and nematicides: Updates to IRAC’s mode of action classification - a tool for resistance management</article-title>. <source>Pestic. Biochem. Physiol</source>. <volume>167</volume>, <fpage>104587</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>S. F.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Expression pattern and pharmacological characterisation of two novel alternative splice variants of the glutamate-gated chloride channel in the small brown planthopper <italic>Laodelphax striatellus</italic></article-title>. <source>Pest Manag. Sci</source>. <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>590</fpage>–<lpage>597</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>L.-P.</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Insecticide-induced increase in the protein content of male accessory glands and its effect on the fecundity of females in the brown planthopper <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> Stål (Hemiptera: Delphacidae)</article-title>. <source>Crop Protection</source> <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1280</fpage>–<lpage>1285</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>L.-Q.</given-names> <surname>Ge</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Cheng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.-C.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>G. C.</given-names> <surname>Jahn</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Proteomic analysis of insecticide triazophos-induced mating-responsive proteins of <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> Stål (Hemiptera: Delphacidae)</article-title>. <source>J. Proteome Res</source>. <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>4597</fpage>–<lpage>4612</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>K.-F.</given-names> <surname>Zhao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Z.-P.</given-names> <surname>Shi</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.-C.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Insecticide-induced enhancement of flight capacity of the brown planthopper <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> Stål (Hemiptera: Delphacidae)</article-title>. <source>Crop Protection</source> <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>476</fpage>–<lpage>482</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>D.-J.</given-names> <surname>Wan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.-B.</given-names> <surname>Jiang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.-Q.</given-names> <surname>Ge</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.-C.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Effects of the insecticide triazophos on the ultrastructure of the flight muscle of the brown planthopper <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> Stål (Hemiptera: Delphacidae)</article-title>. <source>Crop Protection</source> <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Cheng</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Heat-dependent fecundity enhancement observed in <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> (Hemiptera: Delphacidae) after treatment with triazophos</article-title>. <source>Environ Entomol</source>. <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>474</fpage>–<lpage>481</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Yang</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Sublethal effects of abamectin on the development, fecundity, and wing morphs of the brown planthopper <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic></article-title>. <source>J Asia Pac Entomol</source>. <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1180</fpage>–<lpage>1186</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>J.-L.</given-names> <surname>Yin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>H.-W.</given-names> <surname>Xu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.-C.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.-H.</given-names> <surname>Hu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>G.-Q.</given-names> <surname>Yang</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Cultivar and insecticide applications affect the physiological development of the brown planthopper, <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> (Stål) (Hemiptera: Delphacidae)</article-title>. <source>Environ Entomol</source>. <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>L. M.</given-names> <surname>Riddiford</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Juvenile hormone action: A 2007 perspective</article-title>. <source>J Insect Physiol</source>. <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>895</fpage>–<lpage>901</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Xu</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) observations of female oocytes from <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> (Hemiptera: Delphacidae): Antibiotic jinggangmycin (JGM)-induced stimulation of reproduction and associated changes in hormone levels</article-title>. <source>J Econ Entomol</source>. <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>1677</fpage>–<lpage>1682</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Shah</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Diallyl trisulfide reduced the reproductive capacity of male <italic>Sitotroga cerealella</italic> via the regulation of juvenile and ecdysone hormones</article-title>. <source>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf</source>. <volume>248</volume>, <fpage>114304</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>M.-n. Jin, J. Xue, Y. Yao, X.-d. Lin</collab>, <article-title>Molecular characterization and functional analysis of krüppel-homolog 1 (Kr-h1) in the brown planthopper</article-title>, <source>Nilaparvata lugens (Stål). J Integr Agric</source>. <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>1972</fpage>–<lpage>1981</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>X.</given-names> <surname>Lin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Yao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Methoprene-tolerant (Met) and Krüpple-homologue 1 (Kr-h1) are required for ovariole development and egg maturation in the brown plant hopper</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>18064</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>The neuropeptide allatostatin C from clock-associated DN1p neurons generates the circadian rhythm for oogenesis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>118</volume>, <fpage>e2016878118</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Stay</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Fairbairn</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C. G.</given-names> <surname>Yu</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Role of allatostatins in the regulation of juvenile hormone synthesis</article-title>. <source>Arch Insect Biochem Physiol</source>. <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>K. J.</given-names> <surname>Yagi</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Phe-Gly-Leu-amide allatostatin in the termite <italic>Reticulitermes flavipes</italic>: Content in brain and corpus allatum and effect on juvenile hormone synthesis</article-title>. <source>J Insect Physiol</source>. <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>J. L.</given-names> <surname>Hentze</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. A.</given-names> <surname>Carlsson</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Kondo</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>D. R.</given-names> <surname>Nässel</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K. F.</given-names> <surname>Rewitz</surname></string-name>, <article-title>The neuropeptide allatostatin A regulates metabolism and feeding decisions in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>11680</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Hasebe</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Shiga</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Clock gene-dependent glutamate dynamics in the bean bug brain regulate photoperiodic reproduction</article-title>. <source>PLOS Biol</source>. <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>e3001734</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names> <surname>Wen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Zhao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Liang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>X.</given-names> <surname>Jiao</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Laboratory risk assessment of seven insecticides to the wolf spider <italic>Pardosa pseudoannulata</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Plant Protect</source>. <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>1059</fpage>–<lpage>1060</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Sogawa</surname></string-name>, “<chapter-title>Planthopper outbreaks in different paddy ecosystems in Asia: Man-made hopper plagues that threatened the green revolution in rice</chapter-title>” in <source>Rice Planthoppers: Ecology, Management, Socio Economics and Policy</source>, <string-name><given-names>K. L.</given-names> <surname>Heong</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Cheng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. M.</given-names> <surname>Escalada</surname></string-name>, Eds. (<publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>, <year>2015</year>), <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-017-9535-7_2</pub-id>, pp. <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>J. M.</given-names> <surname>Huang</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal>, <article-title>Multiple target-site mutations occurring in lepidopterans confer resistance to diamide insecticides</article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol</source>. <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>103367</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>S. F.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y. L.</given-names> <surname>Ja</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y. J.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C. H.</given-names> <surname>Yang</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Sweet neurons inhibit texture discrimination by signaling TMC-expressing mechanosensitive neurons in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title>. <source>eLife</source> <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e46165</fpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Tamura</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>G.</given-names> <surname>Stecher</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>D.</given-names> <surname>Peterson</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Filipski</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Kumar</surname></string-name>, <article-title>MEGA6: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2725</fpage>–<lpage>2729</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><given-names>K. J.</given-names> <surname>Livak</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T. D.</given-names> <surname>Schmittgen</surname></string-name>, <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2−ΔΔCT method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source> <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<sec>
<fig id="figs1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 1-figure supplement 1.</label>
<caption><p>(A) Fecundity of BPH when newly emerged adults were treated with sub-lethal (LD<sub>15</sub>) and median lethal (LD<sub>50</sub>) concentrations of emamectin benzoate via topical application. (B) Fecundity of BPH when 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs were treated with sub-lethal (LC<sub>15</sub>) and median lethal (LC<sub>50</sub>) concentrations of abamectin via systemic exposure. All data are presented as the mean ± s.e.m. Different lower-case letters above the bars indicate significant differences (One-way ANOVA with Tukey’s Multiple Range Test, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs1.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs2" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 1-figure supplement 2.</label>
<caption><p>Fecundity of small brown planthopper, <italic>Laodelphax striatellus</italic>, (A-C) white backed planthopper, <italic>Sogatella furcifera</italic> (D-F) and fruit fly, <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (G and H) when larvae and newly emerged adults were treated with sub-lethal concentrations of emamectin benzoate. All data are presented as the mean ± s.e.m. Different lower-case letters above the bars indicate significant differences (One-way ANOVA with Tukey’s Multiple Range Test, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs2.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs3" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 1-figure supplement 3.</label>
<caption><p>The impact of emamectin benzoate on the reproductive fitness of BPH. Fourth instar nymphs were treated with the LC<sub>50</sub> concentration of emamectin benzoate in systemic bioassays. All data are presented as the mean ± s.e.m. Different lower-case letters above the bars indicate significant differences (Student’s <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs3.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs4" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 2-figure supplement 1.</label>
<caption><p>Amounts of Glycogen (A), TAG (B), total protein content (C), cholesterol (D) and four circulating sugars including sucrose, glucose, fructose and trehalose (E-H) after BPH exposure to EB. All data are presented as the mean ± s.e.m. The differences between the EB-treated and solvent-treated BPH were analyzed using unpaired student <italic>t</italic>-test (*, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; **, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; ****, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs4.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs5" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 3-figure supplement 1.</label>
<caption><p>Ecdysone titer at different developmental stages of BPH when 4<sup>th</sup> instar nymphs were treated with median lethal concentrations of EB.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs5.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs6" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 3-figure supplement 2.</label>
<caption><p>(A-C) Expression of <italic>JHAMT</italic> (A), <italic>Met</italic> (B) and <italic>Kr-h1</italic> (C) following RNAi knockdown. (D) The titer of JHⅢ (as measured by HPLC-MS/MS) at 3 DAE when female adults were injected with <italic>dsJHAMT, dsMet,</italic> and <italic>dsKr-h1</italic> at 1 DAE. (E-H) Expression of <italic>FAMeT</italic>, <italic>Vg</italic>, <italic>JHE</italic> and <italic>JHAMT</italic> when <italic>Kr-h1</italic> was silenced in BPH. All data are presented as means ± s.e.m. *<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; Mann–Whitney test.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs6.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs7" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 4-figure supplement 1.</label>
<caption><p>Alignments of the amino acid sequences of: (A) AT, (B) AstA, (C) AstB/MIP, (D) AstCC and (E) AstCCC peptides from select species. AT, AstA, AstB/MIP and AstCCC are predicted to have a C-terminal amide. The mature peptides belonging to the same species have been highlighted with the same color. Species names are as follows: Nillu (<italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic>), Locmi (<italic>Locusta migratoria</italic>), Scham (<italic>Schistocerca americana</italic>), Homvi (<italic>Homalodisca vitripennis</italic>), Manse (<italic>Manduca sexta</italic>), Spofr (<italic>Spodoptera frugiperda</italic>), Drome (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>), Spoex (<italic>Spodoptera exigua</italic>), Nasvi (<italic>Nasonia vitripennis</italic>), Grybi (<italic>Gryllus bimaculatus</italic>), Bommi (<italic>Bombyx mori</italic>); Mesma (<italic>Mesobuthus martensii</italic>), Stear (<italic>Stegodyphus araneomorph</italic>), Limpo (<italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic>), Carma (<italic>Carcinus maenas</italic>), Strma (<italic>Strigamia maritima</italic>), Athro (<italic>Athalia rosae</italic>), Apime (<italic>Apis mellifera</italic>), Dapma (<italic>Daphnia magna</italic>). Black lines under the sequences indicate the locations of the disulfide bridges in the mature peptides. The accession numbers of the sequences are listed in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>-figure supplement 1 source data.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs7.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs8" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 4-figure supplement 2.</label>
<caption><p>Phylogenetic tree of the predicted BPH (*) allatotropin receptor (A16, ATR), allatostatins A receptor (A2, AstAR), AstB (MIP) receptor (A10, AstBR or MIPR) and allatostatins C receptor (A1, AstCR) with other insect species. The tree was generated using the maximum likelihood method. <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> metabotropic glutamate receptor was included as an outgroup. The accession numbers of the sequences used for this phylogenetic tree are listed in Figure 4-figure supplement 2 source data.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs8.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs9" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 4-figure supplement 3.</label>
<caption><title>EB induced changes in the expression of <italic>AT</italic>, <italic>AstB</italic>, <italic>AstCC</italic>, <italic>AstCCC</italic>, <italic>ATR</italic>, <italic>AstBR</italic> and <italic>AstCR</italic> in BPH.</title>
<p>All data are presented as means ± s.e.m. Student’s t test was used to compare the two samples. ns, no significant difference; Asterisks indicate values significantly different from the control (*<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs9.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs10" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 5-figure supplement 1.</label>
<caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of glutamate-gated chloride channels in different species. The numbers at the nodes of the branches represent the percentage bootstrap support (1000 replications) for each branch. The <italic>Sogatella furcifera</italic> GABA-gated chloride channel and <italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> nAchR were used as outgroup. Alignment was performed with amino acid sequences from TM1-7. The receptor names are listed in the tree. The accession numbers of the sequences used for this phylogenetic tree are listed in Figure 5-figure supplement 1 source data.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs10.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs11" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 5-figure supplement 2.</label>
<caption><p>The expression of <italic>AT</italic>, <italic>AstA</italic>, <italic>AstB</italic>, <italic>AstCC</italic>, <italic>AstCCC</italic>, <italic>AstAR</italic>, <italic>AstBR</italic> and <italic>AstCR</italic> in BPH injected with <italic>dsGluCl or dsgfp</italic>. All data are presented as means ± s.e.m. Student’s <italic>t</italic> test was used to compare the two samples. ns, no significant. Different lower-case letters above the bars indicate significant differences (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_figs11.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="tbls1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table S1.</label><caption><title>Determination of the toxicity of emamectin benzoate against BPH in systemic and topical application bioassays.</title></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_tbls1.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_tbls1a.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="tbls2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table S2</label><caption><title>Sequences of oligonucleotide primers used in this study.</title></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_tbls2.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
<graphic xlink:href="545881v2_tbls2a.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</back>
<sub-article id="sa0" article-type="editor-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.91774.1.sa2</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>eLife Assessment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sen</surname>
<given-names>Sonia Q</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Tata Institute for Genetics and Society</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Bangalore</city>
<country>India</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="evidence-strength">
<kwd>Inadequate</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="claim-importance">
<kwd>Useful</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>This <bold>useful</bold> manuscript reports mechanisms behind the increase in fecundity in response to sub-lethal doses of pesticides in the crop pest, the brown plant hopper. The authors hypothesize that the pesticide works by inducing the JH titer, which through the JH signaling pathway induces egg development. Evidence for this is, however, <bold>inadequate</bold>.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa1" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.91774.1.sa1</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #1 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>
Gao et al. have demonstrated that the pesticide emamectin benzoate (EB) treatment of brown planthopper (BPH) leads to increased egg-laying in the insect, which is a common agricultural pest. The authors hypothesize that EB upregulates JH titer resulting in increased fecundity.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>
The finding that a class of pesticide increases the fecundity of brown planthopper is interesting.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>
1. EB is an allosteric modulator of GluCl. That means EB physically interacts with GluCl initiating a structural change in the cannel protein. Yet the authors' central hypothesis here is about how EB can upregulate the mRNA of GluCl. I do not know whether there is any evidence that an allosteric modulator can function as a transcriptional activator for the same receptor protein. The basic premise of the paper sounds counterintuitive. This is a structural problem and should be addressed by the authors by giving sufficient evidence about such demonstrated mechanisms before.</p>
<p>2. I am surprised to see a 4th instar larval application or treatment with EB results in the upregulation of JH in the adult stages. Complicating the results further is the observation that a 4th instar EB application results in an immediate decrease in JH titer. There is a high possibility that this late JH titer increase is an indirect effect.</p>
<p>3. The writing quality of the paper needs improvement. Particularly with respect to describing processes and abbreviations. In several instances the authors have not adequately described the processes they have introduced, thus confusing readers.</p>
<p>4. In the section 'EB promotes ovarian development' the authors have shown that EB treatment results in increased detention of eggs which contradicts their own results which show that EB promotes egg laying. Again, this is a serious contradiction that nullifies their hypothesis.</p>
<p>5. Furthermore, the results suggest that oogenesis is not affected by EB application. The authors should devote a section to discussing how they are observing increased egg numbers in EB-treated insects while not impacting Oogenesis.</p>
<p>6. Met is the receptor of JH and to my understanding, remains mostly constant in terms of its mRNA or protein levels throughout various developmental periods in many different insects. Therefore, the presence of JH becomes the major driving factor for physiological events and not the presence of the receptor Met. Here the authors have demonstrated an increase in Met mRNA as a result of EB treatment. Their central hypothesis is that EB increases JH titer to result in enhanced fecundity. JH action will not result in the activation of Met. Although not contradictory to the hypothesis, the increase in mRNA content of Met is contrary to the findings of the JH field thus far.</p>
<p>7. As pointed out before, it is hard to rationalize how a 4th instar exposure to EB can result in the upregulation of key genes involved in JH synthesis at the adult stage. The authors must consider providing a plausible explanation and discussion in this regard.</p>
<p>8. I have strong reservations against such an irrational hypothesis that Met (the receptor for JH) and JH-Met target gene Kr-h1 regulate JH titer (Line 311, Fig 3 supplemental 2D). This would be the first report of such an event on the JH field and therefore must be analysed in depth. I strongly suggest the authors remove such claims from the manuscript without substantiating it.</p>
<p>9. Kr-h1 is JH/Met target gene. The authors demonstrate that silencing of Kr-h1 results in inhibition of FAMeT, which is a gene involved in JH synthesis. A feedback loop in JH synthesis is unreported. It is the view of this reviewer that the authors must go ahead with a mechanistic detail of Kr-h1 mediated JH upregulation before this can be concluded. Mere qPCR experiments are not sufficient to substantiate a claim that is completely contrary to the current understanding of the JH signalling pathway.</p>
<p>10. The authors have performed knockdowns of JHAMT, Met, and Kr-h1 to demonstrate the effect of these factors on fecundity in BPH. Additionally, they have performed rescue experiments with EB application on these knockdown insects (Figure 3K-M). This, I believe, is a very flawed experiment. The authors demonstrate EB works through JHAMT in upregulating JH titer. In the absence of JHAMT, EB application is not expected to rescue the phenotype. But the authors have reported a complete rescue here. In the absence of Met, the receptor of JH, either EB or JH is not expected to rescue the phenotype. But a complete rescue has been reported. These two experimental results contradict their own hypothesis.</p>
<p>11. A significant section of the paper deals with how EB upregulates JH titer. JH is a hormone synthesized in the Corpora Allata. Yet the authors have chosen to use the whole body for all of their experiment. Changes in the whole body for mRNA of those enzymes involved in JH synthesis may not reflect the situation in Corpora Allata. Although working with Corpora Allata is challenging, discarding the abdomen and thorax region and working with the head and neck region of the insect is easily doable. Results from such sampling are always more convincing when it comes to JH synthesis studies.</p>
<p>12. The phenomenon reported was specific to BPH and not found in other insects. This limits the implications of the study.</p>
<p>13. Overall, the molecular experiments are very poorly designed and can at best be termed superficial. There are several contradictions within the paper and no discussion or explanation has been provided for that.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa2" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.91774.1.sa0</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #2 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>The brown plant hopper (BPH) is a notorious crop pest and pesticides are the most widespread means of controlling its population. This manuscript shows that in response to sublethal doses of the pesticide (EB), BPH females show enhanced fecundity. This is in keeping with field reports of population resurgence post-pesticide treatment. The authors work out the mechanism behind this increase in fecundity. They show that in response to EB exposure, the expression of its target receptor, GluCl, increases. This, they show, results in an increase in the expression of genes that regulate the synthesis of juvenile hormone (JH) and JH itself, which, in turn, results in enhanced egg-production and egg-laying. Interestingly, these effects of EB exposure are species-specific, as the authors report that other species of plant hoppers either don't show enhanced fecundity or show reduced fecundity. As the authors point out, it is unclear how an increase in GluCl levels could result in increased JH regulatory genes.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
</article>