<?xml version="1.0" ?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.3 20210610//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>eLife</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">94578</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.94578</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi" specific-use="version">10.7554/eLife.94578.1</article-id>
<article-version-alternatives>
<article-version article-version-type="publication-state">reviewed preprint</article-version>
<article-version article-version-type="preprint-version">1.1</article-version>
</article-version-alternatives>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Neuroscience</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Shaping the physical world to our ends: The left PF technical-cognition area</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3449-6377</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Osiurak</surname>
<given-names>François</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Federico</surname>
<given-names>Giovanni</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fournel</surname>
<given-names>Arnaud</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gaujoux</surname>
<given-names>Vivien</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lamberton</surname>
<given-names>Franck</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ibarrola</surname>
<given-names>Danièle</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8867-4496</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Rossetti</surname>
<given-names>Yves</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Lesourd</surname>
<given-names>Mathieu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a7">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Laboratoire d’Étude des Mécanismes Cognitifs, Université de Lyon</institution>, Bron, <country>France</country></aff>
<aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Institut Universitaire de France</institution>, Paris, <country>France</country></aff>
<aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>IRCCS Synlab SDN S.p.A.</institution>, Naples, <country>Italy</country></aff>
<aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>CERMEP-Imagerie du vivant, MRI Department and CNRS UMS3453</institution>, Lyon, <country>France</country></aff>
<aff id="a5"><label>5</label><institution>Centre de Recherche en Neurosciences de Lyon (CRNL), Trajectoires Team (Inserm UMR_S 1028-CNRS-UMR 5292-Université de Lyon)</institution>, Bron, <country>France</country></aff>
<aff id="a6"><label>6</label><institution>Mouvement et Handicap and Neuro-Immersion, Hospices Civils de Lyon et Centre de Recherche en Neurosciences de Lyon, Hôpital Henry Gabrielle</institution>, St Genis Laval, <country>France</country></aff>
<aff id="a7"><label>7</label><institution>Université de Franche-Comté, LINC, CNRS</institution>, Besançon, <country>France</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="section">
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Bi</surname>
<given-names>Yanchao</given-names>
</name>
<role>Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Beijing Normal University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Beijing</city>
<country>China</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="senior_editor">
<name>
<surname>Bi</surname>
<given-names>Yanchao</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Beijing Normal University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Beijing</city>
<country>China</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding authors: François Osiurak (<email>francois.osiurak@univ-lyon2.fr</email>) &amp; Mathieu Lesourd (<email>mathieu.lesourd@univ-fcomte.fr</email>)</corresp>
<fn id="n1" fn-type="con"><p>Author contributions: F.O. and M.L. designed the research question. F.O., V.G., and M.L. performed the research. A.F. and M.L. analyzed the data. F.O. wrote the manuscript. G.F., A.F., V.G., F.L., D.I., Y.R., and M.L. reviewed and edited the manuscript. F.O., Y.R., and M.L. acquired the financial support for the project.</p></fn>
<fn id="n2" fn-type="others"><p>Competing interests: The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date date-type="original-publication" iso-8601-date="2024-03-07">
<day>07</day>
<month>03</month>
<year>2024</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<elocation-id>RP94578</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="sent-for-review" iso-8601-date="2023-12-01">
<day>01</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2023</year>
</date>
</history>
<pub-history>
<event>
<event-desc>Preprint posted</event-desc>
<date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2024-01-05">
<day>05</day>
<month>01</month>
<year>2024</year>
</date>
<self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.01.02.573935"/>
</event>
</pub-history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2024, Osiurak et al</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Osiurak et al</copyright-holder>
<ali:free_to_read/>
<license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-preprint-94578-v1.pdf"/>
<abstract>
<title>Abstract</title>
<p>Our propensity to materiality, which consists in using, making, creating, and passing on technologies, has enabled us to shape the physical world according to our ends. To explain this proclivity, scientists have calibrated their lens to either low-level skills such as motor cognition or high-level skills such as language or social cognition. Yet, little has been said about the intermediate-level cognitive processes that are directly involved in mastering this materiality. We aim to focus on this intermediate level for contributing to building a cognitive framework of human technology. Here we show that a technical-reasoning process might be specifically at work in physical problem-solving situations. We found via two distinct neuroimaging studies that the area PF (parietal F) within the left parietal lobe is central for this reasoning process in both tool-use and non-tool-use physical problem-solving and can work along with social-cognitive skills to resolve day-to-day interactions that combine social and physical constraints. Our results demonstrate the existence of a specific cognitive module in the human brain dedicated to materiality, which might be the supporting pillar allowing the accumulation of technical knowledge over generations. Intensifying research on technical cognition could nurture a comprehensive framework that has been missing in fields interested in how early and modern humans have been interacting with the physical world through technology, and how this interaction has shaped our history and culture.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<title>Keywords</title>
<kwd>Physical Understanding</kwd>
<kwd>Technical Reasoning</kwd>
<kwd>Theory of Mind</kwd>
<kwd>Tool Use</kwd>
</kwd-group>

</article-meta>
<notes>
<notes notes-type="competing-interest-statement">
<title>Competing Interest Statement</title><p>The authors have declared no competing interest.</p></notes>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Modern societies heavily rely on and even depend upon technology. From the first lithic industries to the most modern and complex ones, technologies enable us to fulfil elementary needs such as feeding or building shelters, and even more sophisticated ones such as communicating, conquering space, or playing music. Human technology is ubiquitous and this omnipresence reflects how we, as a species, are remarkably skilled at shaping the physical world according to our needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>). A paradox though remains in modern science. Even if this special skill has allowed our prolific expansion, only a little attention has been paid to the cognition needed to practically develop the technology required (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c7">7</xref>). We do make and use advanced technologies, and we also transmit them to the next generations, but the full understanding of the neurocognitive processes implied is still in its infancy.</p>
<p>Most of this understanding has long come from clinical neuropsychology, through the observation of apraxic patients in whom damage to the left inferior part of the parietal lobe leads to tool-use disorders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">9</xref>). These disorders have been initially interpreted as reflecting impaired sensorimotor programs dictating the prototypical manipulation of common tools (e.g., a hammer) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">11</xref>). This manipulation-based approach has provided interesting insights (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">16</xref>) but remains silent on the more general cognitive mechanisms behind human technology that include the use of common tools but must also encompass the use of unfamiliar or novel tools, tool making, construction behaviour, technical innovations, and transmission of technical content.</p>
<p>This silence has been initially broken by a series of studies initiated by Goldenberg and Hagmann (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">9</xref>), which has documented a behavioural link in left brain-damaged patients between common tool use and the ability to solve mechanical problems by using and even sometimes making novel tools (e.g., extracting a target out from a box by bending a wire to create a hook) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">17</xref>). Brain-lesion studies have revealed that this behavioural link has a neural reality because both common and novel tool uses are impaired after damage to the left inferior parietal lobe and particularly the area PF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>). As Goldenberg and Spatt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>) claimed, “[t]hese results support the conclusions that the parietal lobe contribution to tool use concerns general principles of tool use rather than knowledge of the prototypical use of common tools and objects, and the comprehension of mechanical interactions of the tool with other tools, recipients or materials rather than the selection of grip formation and manual movements” (p. 1653). Neuroimaging studies have thereafter extended Goldenberg and Spatt’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>) conclusion to situations other than tool use strictly speaking. For instance, evidence has indicated the preferential activation of the left area PF when people observe others use tools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>) as well as when people view physical events, whether they are instructed or not to reason about them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>). Also, the cortical thickness of the left area PF was found to predict the performance on psychotechnical tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c23">23</xref>) (e.g., water-pouring problems). It is noteworthy that these studies have also reported the involvement of other areas, such as the left inferior frontal gyrus (IFG) or the lateral occipitotemporal cortex (LOTC). However, this involvement seems to be task-dependent, contrary to the systematic involvement of left area PF.</p>
<p>These findings have fuelled the development of the technical-reasoning hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">25</xref>), which offers a larger account of the neurocognitive processes at work for understanding and shaping our physical world and for successfully passing technologies to the next generations in a cumulative manner, forming what has been dubbed the cumulative technological culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">26</xref>). Technical reasoning refers to the ability of reasoning about the physical properties of objects and is nurtured by implicit mechanical knowledge acquired through interactions with objects. It is both causal (i.e., prediction of future events) and analogical (i.e., transfer from one situation to another). To solve a physical problem, an agent can use prior knowledge about mechanical properties and physical laws that apply to the physical world, such as gravity and leverage. Then, this knowledge is combined with the constraints of the current situation, which include the available data and any objects required to achieve the desired goal. The outcome of the technical reasoning process is a simulation of the mechanical action to be performed, which then constrains, if the individual intends to act, their bodily actions through a kind of mechanical-to-motor action cascade, which will ultimately feedback onto the central representations of our body, space, and objects. As mentioned above, the left area PF occupies a central place in the technical-reasoning network, along with additional brain areas such as the left IFG and LOTC.</p>
<p>Here we focus on two important questions that remain to be addressed to promote the technical-reasoning hypothesis as a comprehensive cognitive framework for human technology: Generalizability and specificity. To tackle these two questions, we designed two fMRI experiments that included four different tasks (Experiment 1: Mechanical problem-solving task; <italic>n</italic> = 34; Experiment 2: Psychotechnical task, fluid-cognition task, and mentalizing task; <italic>n</italic> = 35), detailed in the following lines.</p>
<p>The first question concerns the generalizability of the technical-reasoning network to any context that includes physical understanding. As suggested above, neuropsychological studies have supported Goldenberg and Spatt’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>) conclusion about the contribution of the inferior parietal lobe to general principles of tool use, but no neuroimaging study has confirmed this conclusion so far. For this, we designed a first experiment allowing the observation of the cerebral activities related to physical problem solving implying tool use. Participants were presented with mechanical problems, consisting in figuring out how to move, with the help of a novel tool, a small red cubic element trapped in a 3D glass box projected on a screen from its original location into a new target location (<bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref></bold>). This task allowed us to test the involvement of the technical-reasoning network – and particularly of the left area PF – in novel tool use. Nonetheless, the generalizability of technical reasoning implies that its network is recruited beyond tool use and serves as a basis for the physical understanding of the world surrounding us. We tested this assumption by studying the neural correlates tied to the understanding of physical principles, disembodied from any tool-use situation. In a second neuroimaging experiment, participants performed a psychotechnical task in which they had to solve non-tool-use physical problems, such as water-pouring problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c27">27</xref>) (<bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref></bold>). We predicted that the technical-reasoning network and particularly the left area PF should be recruited to perform this psychotechnical task. In addition, as technical reasoning is supposedly a central component of the mechanical problem-solving task and the psychotechnical task, and the INT+PHYS and PHYS-Only conditions of the mentalizing task, which will be described below, we hypothesized that the technical-reasoning network should be commonly activated across these tasks and should be found in a conjunction analysis of the four experimental conditions.</p>
<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 1.</label>
<caption><title>Experimental tasks.</title>
<p><bold>(A)</bold> In the mechanical problem-solving task (Experiment 1), participants had to figure out for 4 seconds how to move a red cube trapped in a 3D glass box from its original location to a new target location. Then, two tools were presented for 3 seconds, and they had to decide which was the correct one to solve the mechanical problem. Before the scanning session, the participants were informed that five distinct tools could be used to solve the mechanical problems. (<bold>B)</bold> In the psychotechnical task (Experiment 2), two situations were displayed for 6 seconds. Participants had to select which of the two displayed situations was the correct one or the most effective one. <bold>(C)</bold> In the fluid-cognition task (Experiment 2), the participants had to select the line of options with the correct one. (<bold>D)</bold> In the mentalizing task (Experiment 2), the superior part of the board was shown for 6 seconds, for the participants to try to make sense of the cartoon first. Then the bottom part was presented for 4 additional seconds, with the top part remaining on display. The participants had to choose the cartoon with the probable ending to the story depicted in the three first drawings. In the PHYS-Only condition, the selection only needed to understand the physical context. In the INT+PHYS condition, the selection needed to understand both the physical context and the social context. Birgit Völlm gave us the permission to reproduce the pictures in <bold>(D)</bold>. No permission was needed for the pictures in <bold>a</bold> as we built this task. The items of the psychotechnical task <bold>(B)</bold> and the fluid-cognition task <bold>(C)</bold> are adapted from commercialized tests and do not correspond to the original items of these tests. For more information, see the Methods section.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="573935v1_fig1.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>The second question concerns the specificity of the technical-reasoning network. As technical reasoning is an implicit and causal form of reasoning, it may be easily conflated with other forms of implicit/non-verbal and/or causal reasoning, such as fluid reasoning or mentalizing. Thus, in the second experiment, we tested its specificity by asking participants to perform fluid-reasoning and mentalizing tasks. Fluid reasoning, hereafter called fluid cognition, refers to temporarily maintaining information to produce adapted responses to solve novel problems or plan and execute directed behaviour based on inductive and deductive relationship (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">28</xref>). Although fluid cognition is a non-verbal form of reasoning, it does not necessitate knowledge of the physical world, its constraints and the mechanical laws governing it. The distinction between technical reasoning and fluid cognition has already been supported by behavioural evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref>) as well as by neuroimaging studies that have shown the recruitment of the prefrontal cortex in fluid cognition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c30">30</xref>), with brain regions that are not commonly reported in the context of tool use or physical understanding (e.g., dorsal prefrontal cortex and medial superior frontal gyrus). The participants in the second experiment had to complete a fluid-cognition task, which was an adaptation of the Raven’s Progressive Matrices test (<bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref></bold>). This test has been widely used to predict performance on a wide range of logical reasoning tasks and has been found to predict the general factor of intelligence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c31">31</xref>). We hypothesized the recruitment of the fluid-cognition network, particularly the prefrontal cortex, in the fluid-cognition task, which should diverge from the network involved in the psychotechnical task. Mentalizing refers to detecting and attributing mental states to others or oneself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>). It is a form of causal reasoning, given that it can be used to infer how hidden mental states can cause some specific behaviours. Depending on the situation, this ability requires the collaboration of several cognitive mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>), such as perspective taking (medial prefrontal cortex), the understanding of communicative gestures (temporoparietal junction including the angular gyrus) or knowledge about the person (temporal pole). Frequently this can also require the indirect involvement of technical reasoning to apprehend the physical dimension of the situation (e.g., it is raining, and two umbrellas can provide shelter from the rain), which can be crucial for inferring mental states (e.g., Alex uses one umbrella but does not give the other to Mary). For the mentalizing task, the participants were shown a comic strip conveying a short story and had to select between two additional cartoons the appropriate ending to that story (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">35</xref>). There were two experimental conditions in this task (<bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref></bold>): Reasoning only on the physical dimension of the event (PHYS-Only condition) and inferring an intention combined with reasoning on the physical dimension of the event (INT+PHYS condition). We predicted that the technical-reasoning network should be recruited in both conditions but the mentalizing network would be only involved in the INT+PHYS condition, allowing us to distinguish the cognitive processes implicated in the causal understanding of physical events versus events implying inferring an intention.</p>
<p>To sum up, the contribution that this study aims to make is to test the idea that technical reasoning might be implicated in the situations in which we need to think about the physical properties of our world. In line with previous work, we predicted that this specific form of technical cognition engages a network of brain areas, among which the area PF within the left supramarginal gyrus plays a central role.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Generalizability of the technical-reasoning network</title>
<p>All the behavioural results are given in <bold>Fig. S1</bold> and all the activations described below are reported with their MNI coordinates in <bold>Tables S1-7</bold>. As explained above, we predicted an implication of the technical-reasoning network in the mechanical problem-solving task of Experiment 1 as well as in the psychotechnical task of Experiment 2. As shown in <bold><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref></bold>, the mechanical problem-solving task engaged an almost all-left network of areas, comprising the left supramarginal gyrus within the inferior parietal lobe (including the area PF), the left IFG (opercular and triangular parts), and the left superior parietal cortex and dorsal premotor cortex. The psychotechnical task of Experiment 2 generated a more bilateral network, with greater activation in both supramarginal gyri (including the left area PF but not the right area PF), the opercular part of both IFG, both LOTC, and both superior parietal and dorsal premotor cortices (<bold><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref></bold>). Taken together, these results validate our prediction in indicating the involvement of the left area PF, which is central to the technical-reasoning network. This confirms that the technical-reasoning network depends upon the recruitment of the left area PF, even if additional cognitive processes involving other peripheral brain areas can be engaged depending on the task. This will be discussed in the final section of this article.</p>
<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 2.</label>
<caption><title>Neuroimaging results.</title>
<p>The generalizability of the technical-reasoning network is supported by the activation of the left area PF in the mechanical problem-solving task <bold>(A)</bold>, the psychotechnical task <bold>(B)</bold>, and the PHYS-Only <bold>(D)</bold> and INT+PHYS <bold>(E)</bold> conditions of the mentalizing task. The conjunction analysis <bold>(G)</bold> also confirmed it. The specificity of the technical-reasoning network is also supported by the absence of activation of the left area PF in the fluid-cognition task <bold>(C)</bold> and in the contrast of the INT+PHYS condition to the PHYS-Only condition <bold>(F)</bold>. In <bold>(B)</bold>, IFG (op.) is indicated on the left hemisphere even if it is not visible on this view. Left, left hemisphere; Right, right hemisphere; PF, parietal area F; IFG, inferior frontal gyrus (op., opercular part; tr., triangular part); dPMC; dorsal premotor cortex; SPC, superior parietal cortex; LOTC, lateral occipitotemporal cortex; dPFC, dorsal prefrontal cortex; TPJ, temporoparietal junction; AG, angular gyrus; TP, temporal pole; mPFC, medial prefrontal cortex.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="573935v1_fig2.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>We also hypothesized that the technical-reasoning network should be recruited in the PHYS-Only and INT+PHYS conditions of the mentalizing task of Experiment 2. Before their extensive subsequent presentation, we will focus here on the results from these conditions allowing us to test our generalizability hypothesis. We found preferential activation in the left supramarginal gyrus (including the left area PF) in both conditions (<bold><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2D-E</xref></bold>). Finally, the conjunction analysis of the four experimental conditions (the mechanical problem-solving task, the psychotechnical task, and the PHYS-Only and INT+PHYS conditions of the mentalizing task) led to the only activation in the left supramarginal gyrus (including the left area PF; <bold><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2G</xref></bold>). Taken together, these findings confirmed that the left area PF, central to the technical-reasoning network, is recruited in any situation requiring physical understanding.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2a1">
<title>Specificity of the technical-reasoning network</title>
<p>Even if technical reasoning is a non-verbal and causal form of reasoning, it must not be conflated with other non-verbal and/or causal forms of reasoning, such as fluid cognition and mentalizing. Therefore, we predicted that distinct cerebral networks are recruited for technical reasoning, fluid cognition, and mentalizing. Results for the fluid-cognition task of Experiment 2 confirmed our prediction (<bold><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref></bold>). We found activation of both dorsal prefrontal cortices and medial superior frontal cortices, which are characteristic to fluid cognition but not to technical reasoning. Additional activation was reported in both LOTC, insulae, superior parietal cortices and dorsal premotor cortices. No activation of the inferior parietal lobes was found. Concerning the mentalizing task of Experiment 2, the PHYS-Only condition revealed a bilateral network of areas, comprising both supramarginal gyri (including the right area PF and the left area PF as described above) and LOTC (<bold><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2D</xref></bold>). The INT+PHYS condition highlighted a bilateral network of areas comprising the left supramarginal gyrus (including the left area PF as described above), both LOTC, the right IFG (opercular and triangular parts), both temporoparietal junctions (including the angular gyri) and the right temporal pole (<bold><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2E</xref></bold>). Importantly, the contrast of the INT+PHYS condition to the PHYS-Only condition revealed a network of bilateral areas that characterize the mentalizing network, namely both temporoparietal junctions (including both angular gyri), both medial prefrontal cortices, and the right temporal pole (<bold><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2F</xref></bold>). No activation of brain areas of the technical-reasoning network survived this contrast.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Humans have created a wide range of technologies that have helped them colonize the whole surface of the Earth and beyond. Capitalizing on early Goldenberg’s intuitions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>), the technical-reasoning hypothesis assumes that this idiosyncratic technological trajectory reflects a specific form of technical cognition that involves a cerebral network in which the left area PF of the inferior parietal lobe is central (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">25</xref>). To authorize ourselves to make such a bold statement as <italic>technical cognition,</italic> we need to demonstrate the generalizable but specific nature of technical reasoning. Here we report two neuroimaging studies that confirmed these two characteristics. In the following lines, we discuss in turn the key findings of the present experiments, by stressing how they allow us to pave the way for future research on technical cognition.</p>
<p>The first key finding is that the left area PF, central to the technical-reasoning network, is systematically recruited in any situations involving physical events, confirming the generalizable dimension of technical reasoning. Neuropsychological evidence has indicated that damage to the left area PF impairs both common and novel tool use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>). Previous neuroimaging studies have also revealed that this brain area is specifically activated when (i) people focus on the mechanical actions between a tool and an object (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c36">36</xref>), (ii) watch another individual use tools with objects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>), (iii) reason about physical events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c21">21</xref>) or (iv) look at physical events without being explicitly instructed to reason about them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>). The present study corroborates these results in showing that this brain area is also preferentially recruited when people use novel tools to solve physical problems, or reason about physical events. More importantly, the conjunction analysis that included the mechanical problem-solving task, the psychotechnical task, and the PHYS-Only and INT+PHYS conditions of the mentalizing task confirmed this finding. Taken together, these findings suggest that the technical-reasoning network <italic>“can provide the foundations for future research on this quintessentially human trait: Using, making, and reasoning about tools and more generally shaping the physical world to our ends”</italic> (Allen et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c37">37</xref>); p. 29309). Future research is nevertheless clearly needed to specify the cognitive reality of technical reasoning, and the centrality of the left area PF in this ability.</p>
<p>It should be clear here that we do not advocate the localizationist position simply stating that activation in the left area PF is the necessary and sufficient condition for technical reasoning. We rather defend the view according to which it requires a network of interacting brain areas, one of them – and of major importance – being the left area PF. This allows the engagement of different configurations of cerebral areas in different technical-reasoning tasks, but with a central process acting as a stable component: The left area PF. The major challenge for future research is to specify the nature of the cognitive process supported by the left area PF and that might be involved in the broad understanding of the physical world. One possibility is that the left area PF might be a hub as is the temporal pole for semantic cognition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c38">38</xref>). Another is derived from the technical-reasoning hypothesis, which was initially developed from the observation of patients with tool-use disorders, who met difficulties in selecting and even making appropriate tools to solve mechanical problems. Although a link between problem solving and reasoning can be drawn, it remains that associative learning is a viable candidate to explain how people solve mechanical problems or even more generally make predictions about physical events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c39">39</xref>). Finally, others have suggested the notion of an “intuitive” physics engine, a kind of simulator able to perform physical inference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">40</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c43">43</xref>). Future research is needed to explore these alternative interpretations and potentially reconcile some of them, which is the essential step for the development of a field dedicated to the study of technical cognition.</p>
<p>The second key finding is that the technical-reasoning network is not recruited in other non-verbal and/or causal reasoning forms, confirming that it is a specific form of reasoning oriented towards the physical world. Indeed, no activation of the left area PF was found for the fluid-cognition task, differentiating the logical-reasoning process engaged for solving this task from technical reasoning. This is in line with previous results dissociating technical reasoning from fluid cognition based on behavioural experiments. For instance, in a recent study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref>), the technical-reasoning skills and fluid-cognition skills of 245 participants were assessed with tasks close to those employed here for assessing these two forms of reasoning. A factor analysis with varimax rotation was conducted and corroborated the orthogonality of technical-reasoning tasks and fluid-cognition tasks. At the cerebral level, previous studies have indicated the key role of the prefrontal cortex in fluid cognition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c30">30</xref>), which is also found in the present results. However, we did not report any engagement of the technical-reasoning network in the fluid-cognition task, confirming that technical reasoning is a non-verbal form of reasoning specific to the physical domain that must be distinguished from fluid cognition. The results of the mentalizing task are also informative in this respect. In the INT+PHYS condition of this task, the attribution of the characters’ intentions was accompanied by the mandatory understanding of the physical event associated. On the contrary, the PHYS-Only condition only implied reasoning about the physical actions performed by the characters of the cartoon. Our results confirmed this “hierarchy” of processes. The left area PF was found for the two conditions as stated previously, but the INT+PHYS condition engaged an additional network of areas previously associated with mentalizing skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c45">45</xref>): The bilateral temporoparietal junctions, the bilateral medial prefrontal cortex, and the right temporal pole. In broad terms, the results of the mentalizing task indicate that causal reasoning has distinct forms and that it recruits distinct networks of the human brain (Social domain: Mentalizing; Physical domain: Technical reasoning), which can nevertheless interact together to solve problems in which several domains are involved, such as in the INT+PHYS condition of the mentalizing task.</p>
<p>The third key finding is that the technical-reasoning network involves brain areas whose recruitment varies according to the task. Understanding the role played by these additional brain areas is crucial not only to describe the flexibility of the technical-reasoning network but also to continue to clarify (by exclusion) the role of the left area PF. The first additional area to consider is the left IFG, particularly its opercular part. This area has been repeatedly found in previous research on technical reasoning. We reported activation of left IFG in the mechanical problem-solving task (−50; 7; 20) and the psychotechnical task (−50; 7; 27). Even if the left IFG activation did not survive corrections in the conjunction analysis, it must be noted that a cluster of a small size (<italic>k</italic> = 68) was located around the peak at (−48; 9; 19). These peaks were situated in the close vicinity of the ones reported in two meta-analyses related to tool-use understanding (−49; 8; 31) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c36">36</xref>) and tool-use observation (−51; 5; 33) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>). The functional role of the left IFG in the context of tool use has been previously discussed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>) and a plausible hypothesis is that the left IFG integrates the multiple constraints posed by the physical situation to set the ground for a correct reasoning process, such as it could be involved in syntactic language processing. It has already been shown that language and tool use share syntactic processes in the basal ganglia of the brain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">46</xref>). This hypothesis of IFG as a “constraint combiner” for language and tool use is currently under investigation in our group and needs solid experimental proof.</p>
<p>Another additional area that has been found in three experimental conditions (psychotechnical task, and the PHYS-Only and INT+PHYS conditions of the mentalizing task) was the LOTC. These specific activations could be related to familiarity with the tools or objects shown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c48">48</xref>). Indeed, we did not find the activation of this brain area in the mechanical problem-solving task, which focused on unfamiliar tool-use situations. The three others experimental conditions included common tools such as hammers or screwdrivers for the psychotechnical task, and common objects used as tools for the mentalizing tasks (e.g., stick, rope, chair). Thus, the activation of the LOTC might reflect the involvement of semantic processes whose involvement would remain to understand.</p>
<p>Finally, activation was also found in the right area PF for the PHYS-Only condition of the mentalizing task. A recent morphometry study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c23">23</xref>) showed that the cortical thickness of the left area PF predicts technical-reasoning and visuospatial performance, whereas the right area PF only predicts visuospatial performance, confirming the distinction between these two abilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c49">49</xref>). These findings suggest that the right area PF is recruited along with the left area PF when the task makes high demands on both technical and visuospatial dimensions, as in the PHYS-Only condition of the mentalizing task. This interpretation, although viable, remains unlikely given that there is no reason to consider that this condition makes heavier demands on both technical and visuospatial dimensions than the mechanical problem-solving task or the psychotechnical task. In broad terms, the role played by the right area PF in the technical-reasoning network remains an open issue.</p>
<p>Following the effort undertaken by others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c50">50</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c56">56</xref>), the present study contributes to integrating cognitive science into the cultural evolution field in which technical cognition – if not cognition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c58">58</xref>) – has remained peripheral to the debate on the origins and evolution of human technology. As Wynn et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">4</xref>) stated, “[e]ven archaeologists, for whom technical remains are the primary data source, have tended to privilege language and symbol use in discussion of the modern mind” (p. 21). Yet, recent accounts have proposed that non-social cognitive skills such as causal understanding or technical reasoning might have played a crucial role in cumulative technological culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c59">59</xref>). Support for these accounts comes from micro-society experiments, which have demonstrated that the improvement of technology over generations is accompanied by an increase in its understanding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c61">61</xref>), or that learners’ technical-reasoning skills are a good predictor of cumulative performance in such micro-societies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c62">62</xref>). While behavioural experiments tend to demonstrate the impact of technical reasoning on cumulative technological culture, the present findings offer a neural reality to these behavioural results and inspire new questions: Which, if any, cognitive subcomponents of technical reasoning are specific to the human species? Can cumulative technological culture emerge without technical reasoning? How to distinguish technical reasoning from associative learning in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c39">39</xref>)? How do humans translate their physical understanding into explanationsAll these and other fascinating questions constitute a research agenda for investigating the co-evolution of the human brain, cognition, and technology.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The study was conducted in the Laboratory for the Study of Cognitive Mechanisms at the University of Lyon (Lyon, France) and in the Lyon Neuroimaging Department (CERMEP, Lyon, France). For both experiments, participants were randomly recruited through advertisements posted on social media websites. One week before the MRI session, the participants signed the informed consent to take part in the study and were seen by a medical doctor to ascertain their eligibility for the neuroimaging session. All the participants were right-handed, had a normal or corrected-to-normal vision, provided informed consent, and reported no history of neurological or psychiatric disorder. All the participants signed written consent and were given a monetary incentive for their time (60€). The study was in line with the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by a French Ethics Committee (N°ID-RCB: 2018-A00734-51). Thirty-four participants (<italic>M<sub>age</sub></italic> = 24.21, <italic>SD</italic> = 4.04, range: 18 to 36; female gender: <italic>n</italic> = 20, male gender: <italic>n</italic> = 14) took part in Experiment 1 and 35 new participants (<italic>M<sub>age</sub></italic> = 24.31, <italic>SD</italic> = 5.37, <italic>range</italic>: 20 to 44; female gender: <italic>n</italic> = 23, male gender: <italic>n</italic> = 12) in Experiment 2. Inclusion in the final sample required that head motion during scanning did not exceed 0.5 mm displacement (i.e., framewise displacement) between consecutive volumes on 90% of volumes. No participants were excluded based on this criterion.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4b">
<title>Stimuli and design</title>
<p>For all experiments, the participants were thoroughly briefed on the instructions for completing the tasks just before the scanning session. Two practice trials per condition were proposed but did not reappear inside the scanner. The first experiment consisted of a <italic>T<sub>1</sub></italic>-weighted anatomical scan and a functional run for the mechanical problem-solving task. The other experiment was scanned in a single session with two functional runs separated with a <italic>T<sub>1</sub></italic>-weighted anatomical scan. The psychotechnical and mentalizing tasks were part of the first run, and the fluid-cognition task was scanned in the second run. We used a within-subject design with blocks of different lengths for each condition for the Experiment 1, and a fixed length of 30 seconds for all the other experiments emanating from the presentation of respectively 5 images, 3 images, and 3 images for respectively 6 seconds, 10 seconds, and 10 seconds each, for the psychotechnical, fluid-cognition and mentalizing tasks. Blocks were separated with a fixation cross for 15 seconds in all conditions. Participants’ answers were collected via a button box held in their right hand.</p>
<sec id="s4b1">
<title>Mechanical problem-solving task</title>
<p>Eight experimental and eight control blocks were either 25 seconds (4 blocks), 32.5 seconds (2 blocks), or 40 seconds (2 blocks) long. Each block consisted of 3, 4, or 5 trials. Each trial was composed as follows: The image of the 3D glass box only was displayed for 4 seconds. In the control condition, a black square mask was applied on the picture. Then, for the next 3 seconds, two tools (experimental condition) or two missing pieces (control condition) were added on the left and right sides of the 3D box (<bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref></bold> and <bold>Fig. S2A</bold>). Before the scanning session, the participants were informed that, in the experimental condition, five distinct tools could be used to solve the mechanical problems (<bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref></bold>), which consisted in moving a small red cubic element trapped in the 3D glass box from its original location into a new target location. In the scanner, the participants had to figure out for 4 seconds and for each mechanical problem how to solve it by using one of the tools shown before the scanning session. Then, two tools were presented for 3 seconds, and they had to decide which was the correct one to solve the mechanical problem by pressing either the left or the right button of the button box. The control condition was a visual completion task. The participants scrutinized the 3D glass box for 4 seconds and then had 3 seconds to decide which of the two missing pieces presented was the correct one to fill the mask. A 500-ms fixation cross separated the trials. On the last trial of each block, a red frame appeared around the visual scene, signalling to the participants that their response was awaited. Consequently, 3 additional seconds were added to the display of the box with tools or pieces on the sides to allow for motor response. Blocks alternated between the experimental condition and the control condition. The items of this task are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/hfrmu/">https://osf.io/hfrmu/</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4b2">
<title>Psychotechnical task</title>
<p>Two images were shown simultaneously for 6 seconds, in blocks of 5 boards. On the last board of each block, a red frame instructed the subjects to physically answer within two seconds by pressing either the left or the right button of the button box, for motor responses. Blocks alternated between the experimental condition and the control condition, 6 times each. The participants had to select which of the two presented situations was the correct one or the most effective one in the experimental condition (<bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref></bold>), whereas, in the control condition, they had to select the situation containing a square (<bold>Fig. S2B</bold>). The items were adapted from the NV5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pearsonclinical.fr/nv5r">https://www.pearsonclinical.fr/nv5r</ext-link>) and NV7 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pearsonclinical.fr/nv7">https://www.pearsonclinical.fr/nv7</ext-link>) batteries. The adaptations consisted in reducing the number of options from 4 to 2 and in modifying one part of the picture to create a square (for the control condition). As these batteries are commercialized, we did not provide the items – even the modified ones – in an open-access repository. Nevertheless, the items can be available on request. As the original items of the NV5 and NV7 batteries, the items used in the study were in black and white. The pictures shown in in <bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref></bold> and <bold>Fig. S2B</bold> are nevertheless deliberately in colour so as to move further away from the original items.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4b3">
<title>Fluid-cognition task</title>
<p>Boards were shown for 10 seconds, in blocks of 3 boards. For the last board of each block, a red frame reminded the participants to answer by pressing either the left or the right button of the button box in the scanner during the last two seconds of the board presentation. Blocks alternated between the experimental condition and the control condition, 6 times each. The experimental condition required fluid reasoning (<bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref></bold>) whereas the control condition required only visuospatial pattern completion (<bold>Fig. S2C</bold>). The items were adapted from the Raven’s Progressive Matrices test (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pearsonclinical.fr/pm-progressive-matrices-de-raven">https://www.pearsonclinical.fr/pm-progressive-matrices-de-raven</ext-link>). The adaptations consisted in presenting two lines of three options, one on the left and the other on the right of the screen. The participants had to select the line with the correct option. As this test is commercialized, we did not provide the items – even the modified ones – in an open-access repository. Nevertheless, the items can be available on request. As the original items of the Raven’s Progressive Matrices test, the items used in the study were in black and white. The pictures shown in in <bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref></bold> and <bold>Fig. S2C</bold> are nevertheless deliberately in colour so as to move further away from the original items.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4b4">
<title>Mentalizing task</title>
<p>For each condition, blocks of 3 boards were constituted, and each board was presented in two different steps. First, the superior part of the board was shown for 6 seconds, for the participants to try to make sense of the cartoon first. Then the bottom part was presented for 4 additional seconds, with the top part remaining on display. On the last image of each block, a red frame appeared, indicating to the participants that a physical answer via the button box was required, during the last 2 seconds of the presentation. Blocks were therefore 30 seconds long and were repeated 6 times each. Half of the cartoons in each condition involved a single character, the other half more than one character (all but one implied two characters, and one implied a character versus a crowd). For the two experimental conditions (i.e., INT+PHYS and PHYS-Only conditions; <bold><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref></bold>), the participants had to choose the cartoon with the probable ending to the story depicted in the three first drawings, and for the control condition, they had to select which cartoon was already present in the first three ones (<bold>Fig. S2D</bold>). In the PHYS-Only condition, the selection only needed to understand the physical context. In the INT+PHYS condition, the selection needed to understand both the physical context and the social context. The items were adapted from the task used by Völlm et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">35</xref>). The main adaptations concerned the control condition, which was not present in Völlm et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">35</xref>). Indeed, in their study, the control conditions were PHYS-Only conditions. Birgit Völlm gave us the permission to make available the items of the task, which can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/hfrmu/">https://osf.io/hfrmu/</ext-link>. Note that the items available at this open-access repository do not correspond to all the items used in the task originally developed by Völlm et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">35</xref>) but only to the items used in the present study.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s4c">
<title>fMRI data acquisition</title>
<p>For all experiments, “neuroimaging data were acquired on a 3T Siemens Prisma Scanner (Siemens, Erlangen, Germany) using a 64-channel head coil. Blood-Oxygen Level Dependent (BOLD) images were recorded with <italic>T<sub>2</sub></italic>*-weighted echo-planar images (EPI) acquired with the multi-band sequence. Functional images were all collected as oblique-axial scans aligned with the anterior commissure–posterior commissure (AC–PC) line with the following parameters” (p. 6529; Lesourd et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c65">65</xref>)): 1030 (mechanical problem-solving task), 1000 (psychotechnical and fluid-cognition tasks), 763 (mentalizing task) volumes per run, 57 slices, TR/TE = 1400/30 ms, flip angle = 70°, field of view = 96 x 96 mm<sup>2</sup>, slice thickness = 2.3 mm, voxel size = 2.3 x 2.3 x 2.3 mm<sup>3</sup>, multiband factor = 2. Structural <italic>T<sub>1</sub></italic>-weighted images were collected using an MPRAGE sequence (224 sagittal slices, TR/TE = 3000/2.93 ms, inversion time = 1100 ms, flip angle = 8°, 224 x 256 mm FOV, slice thickness = 0.8 mm, voxel size = 0.8 x 0.8 x 0.8 mm<sup>3</sup>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4d">
<title>Preprocessing of fMRI data</title>
<p>For all experiments, “[s]tructural T<sub>1</sub>-weighted images were segmented into tissue type (GM: grey matter; WM: white matter; CSF: cerebrospinal fluid tissues) using the Computational Anatomy Toolbox (CAT12; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dbm.neuro.uni-jena.de/cat12/">http://dbm.neuro.uni-jena.de/cat12/</ext-link>) segmentation tool, in order to facilitate the normalization step. Functional data were analyzed using SPM12 (Wellcome Department of Cognitive Neurology, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm">http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm</ext-link>) implemented in MATLAB (Mathworks, Sherborn, MA)” (p. 6529; Lesourd et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c65">65</xref>)). Four steps were followed for the preprocessing for univariate analyses: (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref>) Realignment to the mean EPI image with 6-head motion correction parameters and unwarping using the FieldMap toolbox from SPM12; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>) “co-registration of the individual functional and anatomical images; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>) normalization towards MNI template; and (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">4</xref>) spatial smoothing of functional images (Gaussian kernel with 5-mm FWHM)” (p. 6530; Lesourd et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c65">65</xref>)).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4e">
<title>Group analysis</title>
<p>A general linear model was created using design matrices containing one regressor (explanatory variable) for each condition (i.e., mechanical problem-solving task and its control condition for Experiment 1, and psychotechnical, fluid-cognition and mentalizing tasks and their respective control conditions for Experiment 2) modelled as a boxcar function (with onsets and durations corresponding to the start of each stimulus of that condition) convolved with the canonical hemodynamic response function (HRF) as well as its temporal and derivatives dispersion. Six regressors of non-interest resulting from 3D head motion estimation (<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, <italic>z</italic> translation and three axes of rotation) were added to the design matrix. The model was estimated for each participant, also considering the average signal in the run. After model estimation, we computed contrasts at the first level (i.e., experimental conditions versus control conditions) and then transferred to a second-level group analysis (one-sample <italic>t</italic>-test) to obtain the brain regions more activated in experimental than on the control condition, for the four tasks. We present results maps with a significance threshold set at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 with family-wise error (FWE) correction at the cluster level unless stated otherwise. The maps were thresholded at a minimal size of <italic>k</italic> = 120 voxels per cluster.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4f">
<title>Conjunction analysis</title>
<p>We performed a conjunction analysis using statistical parametric maps testing for the conjunction null hypothesis with the maximum <italic>p</italic>-value statistic over the four contrasts for the mechanical problem-solving task, the psychotechnical task, and the INT+PHYS and PHYS-ONLY conditions of the mentalizing task. A first <italic>p</italic>-value map was computed by intersecting the three contrasts from the psychotechnical task and the two mentalizing tasks as repeated measures on the same subjects. The resulting uncorrected <italic>T</italic>-map from the conjunction-null analysis ran into SPM12 was then transformed into a <italic>p</italic>-value map with the appropriate degrees of freedom. Then, in a second step, the uncorrected <italic>T</italic>-map from the mechanical problem-solving task was transformed into a <italic>p</italic>-value map, taking into account the number of subjects minus 1 as degrees of freedom. The two <italic>p</italic>-value maps were in a third step intersected with a conjunction ran as the maximum <italic>p</italic>-value over the two <italic>p</italic>-value maps, allowing to test for the conjunction-null hypothesis and to infer a conjunction of <italic>k</italic> = 4 effects at significant voxels. The resulting <italic>p</italic>-value map was then thresholded at the level of <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 (FWE corrected) and for a minimum size of <italic>k</italic> = 100 voxels per cluster.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="d1e1023" sec-type="data-availability">
<title>Data availability</title>
<p>The data that support the findings of this study are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/hfrmu/">https://osf.io/hfrmu/</ext-link> (behavioural data) and at (the data will be deposited in an open-access repository as soon as the manuscript is accepted; of course, we will make them available to reviewers if requested) (neuroimaging data).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s6">
<title>Code availability</title>
<p>Codes used in this study are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/hfrmu/">https://osf.io/hfrmu/</ext-link> (behavioural data) and at (the codes will be deposited in an open-access repository as soon as the manuscript is accepted; of course, we will make them available to reviewers if requested) (neuroimaging data).</p>
</sec>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>We warmly thank Emanuelle Reynaud for her precious help in many aspects of the study. We also thank Emmanuel De Oliveira, Boris Alexandre, and Alexandrine Faye for their help in designing the experimental stimuli. We thank Birgit Völlm for giving us the permission to reproduce the items of her tests and to make them available in an open-access repository. This work was supported by grants from the French National Research Agency (ANR; Project TECHNITION: ANR-21-CE28-0023-01; F.O., Y.R., and M.L.) and the Région Auvergne-Rhône-Alpes (NUMERICOG-2017-900-EA 3082 EMC-R-2075; F.O.).</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="c1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boyd</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richerson</surname>, <given-names>P. J.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Henrich</surname>, <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The cultural niche: Why social learning is essential for human adaptation</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>108</volume>, <fpage>10918</fpage>–<lpage>10925</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Lombard</surname>, <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>Mountaineering or ratcheting? Stone Age hunting weapons as proxy for the evolution of human technological, behavioral and cognitive flexibility</chapter-title>. in <source>The nature of culture</source> (eds. <string-name><surname>Haidle</surname>, <given-names>M. N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conard</surname>, <given-names>N. J.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Bolus</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>) <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage> (<publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>, <year>2016</year>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-017-7426-0_12</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Whiten</surname>, <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The scope of culture in chimpanzees, humans and ancestral apes</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</source>. <volume>366</volume>, <fpage>997</fpage>–<lpage>1007</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Wynn</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haidle</surname>, <given-names>M. N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lombard</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Coolidge</surname>, <given-names>F. L.</given-names></string-name> <chapter-title>The expert cognition model in human evolutionary studies</chapter-title>. in <source>Cognitive models in paleolithic archaeology</source> (eds. <string-name><surname>Wynn</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Coolidge</surname>, <given-names>F. L.</given-names></string-name>) <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage> (<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wynn</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Coolidge</surname>, <given-names>F. L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Technical cognition, working memory and creativity</article-title>. <source>Pragmat. Cogn</source>. <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Whiten</surname>, <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Blind alleys and fruitful pathways in the comparative study of cultural cognition</article-title>. <source>Phys. Life Rev</source>. <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Elk</surname>, <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A predictive processing framework of tool use</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source> <volume>139</volume>, <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>De Renzi</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Lucchelli</surname>, <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ideational apraxia</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <volume>111</volume>, <fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1185</lpage> (<year>1988</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goldenberg</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Hagmann</surname>, <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tool use and mechanical problem solving in apraxia</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source> <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Elk</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Schie</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Bekkering</surname>, <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Action semantics: A unifying conceptual framework for the selective use of multimodal and modality-specific object knowledge</article-title>. <source>Phys. Life Rev</source>. <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heilman</surname>, <given-names>K. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rothi</surname>, <given-names>L. J.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Valenstein</surname>, <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Two forms of ideomotor apraxia</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage> (<year>1982</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kleineberg</surname>, <given-names>N. N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tscherpel</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fink</surname>, <given-names>G. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grefkes</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Weiss</surname>, <given-names>P. H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Different facets of object-use pantomime: online TMS evidence on the role of the supramarginal gyrus</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source> <volume>156</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weiss</surname>, <given-names>P. H.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Where language meets meaningful action: a combined behavior and lesion analysis of aphasia and apraxia</article-title>. <source>Brain Struct. Funct</source>. <volume>221</volume>, <fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>576</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kroliczak</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Manual praxis and language-production networks, and their links to handedness</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source> <volume>140</volume>, <fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Michalowski</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buchwald</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klichowski</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ras</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Kroliczak</surname>, <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Action goals and the praxis network: an fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Brain Struct. Funct</source>. <volume>227</volume>, <fpage>2261</fpage>–<lpage>2284</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wheaton</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fridman</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bohlhalter</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vorbach</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Hallett</surname>, <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Left parietal activation related to planning, executing and suppressing praxis hand movements</article-title>. <source>Clin. Neurophysiol</source>. <volume>120</volume>, <fpage>980</fpage>–<lpage>986</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heilman</surname>, <given-names>K. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maher</surname>, <given-names>L. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greenwald</surname>, <given-names>M. L.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Rothi</surname>, <given-names>L. J. G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Conceptual apraxia from lateralized lesions</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goldenberg</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Spatt</surname>, <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The neural basis of tool use</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <volume>132</volume>, <fpage>1645</fpage>–<lpage>1655</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martin</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Differential roles of ventral and dorsal streams for conceptual and production-related components of tool use in acute stroke patients</article-title>. <source>Cereb. Cortex</source> <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>3754</fpage>– <lpage>3771</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reynaud</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Navarro</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lesourd</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Osiurak</surname>, <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>To watch is to work: A review of neuroimaging data on tool use observation network</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychol. Rev</source>. <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>484</fpage>–<lpage>497</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fischer</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mikhael</surname>, <given-names>J. G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname>, <given-names>J. B.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Kanwisher</surname>, <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Functional neuroanatomy of intuitive physical inference</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>113</volume>, <fpage>E5072</fpage>–<lpage>E5081</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pramod</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname>, <given-names>J. B.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Kanwisher</surname>, <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Invariant representation of physical stability in the human brain</article-title>. <source>eLife</source> <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e71736</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Federico</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>The cortical thickness of the area PF of the left inferior parietal cortex mediates technical-reasoning skills</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep</source>. <volume>12</volume>, <issue>11840</issue> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Osiurak</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Reynaud</surname>, <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The elephant in the room: What matters cognitively in cumulative technological culture</article-title>. <source>Behav. Brain Sci</source>. <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>e156</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Osiurak</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Claidière</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Federico</surname>, <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Bringing cumulative technological culture beyond copying versus reasoning</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci</source>. <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tomasello</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kruger</surname>, <given-names>A. C.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Ratner</surname>, <given-names>H. H.</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Cultural learning</article-title>. <source>Behav. Brain Sci.</source> <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage> (<year>1993</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hegarty</surname>, <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mechanical reasoning by mental simulation</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci</source>. <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blair</surname>, <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How similar are fluid cognition and general intelligence? A developmental neuroscience perspective on fluid cognition as an aspect of human cognitive ability</article-title>. <source>Behav. Brain Sci</source>. <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>De Oliveira</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynaud</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Osiurak</surname>, <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Roles of technical reasoning, theory of mind, creativity, and fluid cognition in cumulative technological culture</article-title>. <source>Hum. Nat</source>. <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>326</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hobeika</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diard-Detoeuf</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcin</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levy</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Volle</surname>, <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>General and specialized brain correlates for analogical reasoning: A meta-analysis of functional imaging studies: Meta-analysis of analogy brain networks</article-title>. <source>Hum. Brain Mapp</source>. <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>1953</fpage>–<lpage>1969</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gray</surname>, <given-names>J. R.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>, <given-names>P. M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neurobiology of intelligence: science and ethics</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>482</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gallagher</surname>, <given-names>H. L.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Frith</surname>, <given-names>C. D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Functional imaging of ‘theory of mind’</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci</source>. <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>– <lpage>83</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Overwalle</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Baetens</surname>, <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Understanding others’ actions and goals by mirror and mentalizing systems: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source> <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brunet</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarfati</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hardy-Baylé</surname>, <given-names>M.-C.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Decety</surname>, <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A PET investigation of the attribution of intentions with a nonverbal task</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source> <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Völlm</surname>, <given-names>B. A.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Neuronal correlates of theory of mind and empathy: A functional magnetic resonance imaging study in a nonverbal task</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source> <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reynaud</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lesourd</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Navarro</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Osiurak</surname>, <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>On the neurocognitive origins of human tool use: A critical review of neuroimaging data</article-title>. <source>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev</source>. <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>437</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>, <given-names>K. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>K. A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname>, <given-names>J. B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid trial-and-error learning with simulation supports flexible tool use and physical reasoning</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>29302</fpage>– <lpage>29310</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lambon Ralph</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jefferies</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patterson</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>, <given-names>T. T.</given-names></string-name> <article-title>The neural and computational bases of semantic cognition</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci</source>. <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heyes</surname>, <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The cognitive reality of causal understanding</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci</source>. <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Battaglia</surname>, <given-names>P. W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamrick</surname>, <given-names>J. B.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname>, <given-names>J. B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Simulation as an engine of physical scene understanding</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>. <volume>110</volume>, <fpage>18327</fpage>–<lpage>18332</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yildirim</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kanwisher</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname>, <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An integrative computational architecture for object-driven cortex</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Neurobiol</source>. <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schwettmann</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname>, <given-names>J. B.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Kanwisher</surname>, <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Invariant representations of mass in the human brain</article-title>. <source>eLife</source> <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e46619</fpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fischer</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Mahon</surname>, <given-names>B. Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>What tool representation, intuitive physics, and action have in common: The brain’s first-person physics engine</article-title>. <source>Cogn. Neuropsychol</source>. <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Molenberghs</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henry</surname>, <given-names>J. D.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Mattingley</surname>, <given-names>J. B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Understanding the minds of others: A neuroimaging meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev</source>. <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schurz</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Toward a hierarchical model of social cognition: A neuroimaging meta-analysis and integrative review of empathy and theory of mind</article-title>. <source>Psychol. Bull</source>. <volume>147</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thibault</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Tool use and language share syntactic processes and neural patterns in the basal ganglia</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>374</volume>, <fpage>eabe0874</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vingerhoets</surname>, <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Knowing about tools: Neural correlates of tool familiarity and experience</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source> <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1380</fpage>–<lpage>1391</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lesourd</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Semantic and action tool knowledge in the brain: Identifying common and distinct networks</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source> <volume>159</volume>, <fpage>107918</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mitko</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Fischer</surname>, <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>When it all falls down: The relationship between intuitive physics and spatial cognition</article-title>. <source>Cogn. Res. Princ. Implic</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <issue>24</issue> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bayani</surname>, <given-names>K. Y. T.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Emergence of perceptuomotor relationships during paleolithic stone toolmaking learning: intersections of observation and practice. <italic>Commun</italic></article-title>. <source>Biol</source>. <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1278</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gärdenfors</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Högberg</surname>, <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The archaeology of teaching and the evolution of <italic>Homo docens</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr. Anthropol</source>. <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gärdenfors</surname>, <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Demonstration and pantomime in the evolution of teaching and communication</article-title>. <source>Lang. Commun</source>. <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Strachan</surname>, <given-names>J. W. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curioni</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Constable</surname>, <given-names>M. D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knoblich</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Charbonneau</surname>, <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluating the relative contributions of copying and reconstruction processes in cultural transmission episodes</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>e0256901</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Charbonneau</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curioni</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McEllin</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Strachan</surname>, <given-names>J. W. A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Flexible cultural learning through action coordination</article-title>. <source>Perspect. Psychol. Sci</source>. (<year>2023</year>) doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/17456916231182923</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Sperber</surname>, <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <source>Explaining culture: A naturalistic approach</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name> (<year>1996</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sperber</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Hirschfeld</surname>, <given-names>L. A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The cognitive foundations of cultural stability and diversity</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci</source>. <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heyes</surname>, <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Who knows? Metacognitive social learning strategies</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci</source>. <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>204</fpage>– <lpage>213</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heyes</surname>, <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Enquire within: Cultural evolution and cognitive science</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</source>. <volume>373</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vale</surname>, <given-names>G. L.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Why do chimpanzees have diverse behavioral repertoires yet lack more complex cultures? Invention and social information use in a cumulative task</article-title>. <source>Evol. Hum. Behav</source>. <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Osiurak</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Technical reasoning is important for cumulative technological culture. <italic>Nat</italic></article-title>. <source>Hum. Behav</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1643</fpage>–<lpage>1651</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Osiurak</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Technical reasoning bolsters cumulative technological culture through convergent transformations</article-title>. <source>Sci. Adv</source>. <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>eabl7446</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Osiurak</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Physical intelligence does matter to cumulative technological culture</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Psychol. Gen</source>. <volume>145</volume>, <fpage>941</fpage>–<lpage>948</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McCloskey</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caramazza</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Green</surname>, <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Curvilinear motion in the absence of external forces: Naïve beliefs about the motion of objects</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>210</volume>, <fpage>1139</fpage>–<lpage>1141</lpage> (<year>1980</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kubricht</surname>, <given-names>J. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holyoak</surname>, <given-names>K. J.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>, <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intuitive physics: Current research and controversies</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci</source>. <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>749</fpage>–<lpage>759</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lesourd</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Involvement of the posterior tool processing network during explicit retrieval of action tool and semantic tool knowledge: an fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Cereb. Cortex</source> <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>6526</fpage>– <lpage>6542</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<sub-article id="sa0" article-type="editor-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.94578.1.sa3</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>eLife Assessment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bi</surname>
<given-names>Yanchao</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Beijing Normal University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Beijing</city>
<country>China</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="evidence-strength">
<kwd>Incomplete</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="claim-importance">
<kwd>Useful</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>This <bold>useful</bold> study addresses the brain correlates underlying technical reasoning by a set of fMRI experiments and locates it to PF. If confirmed, this study provides an intriguing framework for our understanding of different types of problem-solving processes. However, the current evidence supporting the claims is <bold>incomplete</bold>, due to the existence of alternative explanations for the main overlapping results and potential confounding variables across conditions.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa1" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.94578.1.sa2</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #1 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>In this study, Osiurak and colleagues investigate the neurocognitive basis of technical reasoning. They use multiple tasks from two neuroimaging studies and overlap analysis to show that the area PF is central for reasoning, and plays an essential role in tool-use and non-tool-use physical problem-solving, as well as both conditions of mentalizing task. They also demonstrate the specificity of the technical reasoning and find that the area PF is not involved in the fluid-cognition task or the mentalizing network (INT+PHYS vs. PHYS-only). This work suggests an understanding of the neurocognitive basis of technical reasoning that supports advanced technologies.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>-The topic this study focuses on is intriguing and can help us understand the neurocognitive processes involved in technical reasoning and advanced technologies.</p>
<p>-The researchers obtained fMRI data from multiple tasks. The data is rich and encompasses the mechanical problem-solving task, psychotechnical task, fluid-cognition task, and mentalizing task.</p>
<p>-The article is well written.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>- Limitations of the overlap analysis method: there are multiple reasons why two tasks might activate the same brain regions. For instance, the two tasks might share cognitive mechanisms, the activated regions of the two tasks might be adjacent but not overlapping at finer resolutions, or the tasks might recruit the same regions for different cognition functions. Thus, although overlap analysis can provide valuable information, it also has limitations. Further analyses that capture the common cognitive components of activation across different tasks are warranted, such as correlating the activation across different tasks within subjects for a region of interest (i.e. the PF).</p>
<p>-Control tasks may be inadequate: the tasks may involve other factors, such as motor/ action-related information. For the psychotechnical task, fluid-cognition task, and mentalizing task, the experiment tasks need not only care about technical-cognition information but also motor-related information, whereas the control tasks do not need to consider motor-related information (mainly visual shape information). Additionally, there may be no difference in motor-related information between the conditions of the fluid-cognition task. Therefore, the regions of interest may be sensitive to motor-related information, affecting the research conclusion.</p>
<p>-Negative results require further validation: the cognitive results for the fluid-cognition task in the study may need more refinement. For instance, when performing ROI analysis, are there any differences between the conditions? Bayesian statistics might also be helpful to account for the negative results.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa2" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.94578.1.sa1</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #2 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>The goal of this project was to test the hypothesis that a common neuroanatomic substrate in the left inferior parietal lobule (area PF) underlies reasoning about the physical properties of actions and objects. Four functional MRI (fMRI) experiments were created to test this hypothesis. Group contrast maps were then obtained for each task, and overlap among the tasks was computed at the voxel level. The principal finding is that the left PF exhibited differentially greater BOLD response in tasks requiring participants to reason about the physical properties of actions and objects (referred to as technical reasoning). In contrast, there was no differential BOLD response in the left PF when participants engaged in fMRI variant of the Raven's progressive matrices to assess fluid cognition.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>This is a well-written manuscript that builds from extensive prior work from this group mapping the brain areas and cognitive mechanisms underlying object manipulation, technical reasoning, and problem-solving. Major strengths of this manuscript include the use of control conditions to demonstrate there are differentially greater BOLD responses in area PF over and above the baseline condition of each task. Another strength is the demonstration that area PF is not responsive in tasks assessing fluid cognition - e.g., it may just be that PF responds to a greater extent in a harder condition relative to an easy condition of a task. The analysis of data from Task 3 rules out this alternative interpretation. The methods and analysis are sufficiently written for others to replicate the study, and the materials and code for data analysis are publicly available.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>The first weakness is that the conclusions of the manuscript rely on there being overlap among group-level contrast maps presented in Figure 2. The problem with this conclusion is that different participants engaged in different tasks. Never is an analysis performed to demonstrate that the PF region identified in e.g., participant 1 in Task 2 is the same PF region identified in Participant 1 in Task 4.</p>
<p>A second weakness is that there is a variance in accuracy between tasks that are not addressed. It is clear from the plots in the supplemental materials that some participants score below chance (~ 50%). This means that half (or more) of the fMRI trials of some participants are incorrect. The methods section does not mention how inaccurate trials were handled. Moreover, if 50% is chance, it suggests that some participants did not understand task instructions and were systematically selecting the incorrect item.</p>
<p>A third weakness is related to the fluid cognition task. In the fMRI task developed here, the participant must press a left or right button to select between 2 rows of 3 stimuli while only one of the 3 stimuli is the correct target. This means that within a 10-second window, the participant must identify the pattern in the 3x3 grid and then separately discriminate among 6 possible shapes to find the matching stimulus. This is a hard task that is qualitatively different from the other tasks in terms of the content being manipulated and the time constraints.</p>
<p>In sum, this is an interesting study that tests a neuro-cognitive model whereby the left PF forms a key node in a network of brain regions supporting technical reasoning for tool and non-tool-based tasks. Localizing area PF at the level of single participants and managing variance in accuracy is critically important before testing the proposed hypotheses.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa3" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.94578.1.sa0</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #3 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>This manuscript reports two neuroimaging experiments assessing commonalities and differences in activation loci across mechanical problem-solving, technical reasoning, fluid cognition, and &quot;mentalizing&quot; tasks. Each task includes a control task. Conjunction analyses are performed to identify regions in common across tasks. As Area PF (a part of the supramarginal gyrus of the inferior parietal lobe) is involved across 3 of the 4 tasks, the investigators claim that it is the hub of technical cognition.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>The aim of finding commonalities and differences across related problem-solving tasks is a useful and interesting one.</p>
<p>The experimental tasks themselves appear relatively well-thought-out, aside from the concern that they are differentially difficult.</p>
<p>The imaging pipeline appears appropriate.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>(1) Methodological</p>
<p>
As indicated in the supplementary tables and figures, the experimental tasks employed differ markedly in 1) difficulty and 2) experimental trial time. Response latencies are not reported (but are of additional concern given the variance in difficulty). There is concern that at least some of the differences in activation patterns across tasks are the result of these fundamental differences in how hard various brain regions have to work to solve the tasks and/or how much of the trial epoch is actually consumed by &quot;on-task&quot; behavior. These difficulty issues should be controlled for by 1) separating correct and incorrect trials, and 2) for correct trials, entering response latency as a regressor in the Generalized Linear Models, 3) entering trial duration in the GLMs.</p>
<p>A related concern is that the control tasks also differ markedly in the degree to which they were easier and faster than their corresponding experimental task. Thus, some of the control tasks seem to control much better for difficulty and time on task than others. For example, the control task for the psychotechnical task simply requires the indication of which array contains a simple square shape (i.e., it is much easier than the psychotechnical task), whereas the control task for mechanical problem-solving requires mentally fitting a shape into a design, much like solving a jigsaw puzzle (i.e., it is only slightly easier than the experimental task).</p>
<p>(2) Theoretical</p>
<p>
The investigators seem to overlook prior research that does not support their perspective and their writing seems to lack scientific objectivity in places. At times they over-reach in the claims that can be made based on the present data. Some claims need to be revised/softened.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
</article>