<?xml version="1.0" ?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.3 20210610//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>eLife</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100822</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.100822</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi" specific-use="version">10.7554/eLife.100822.1</article-id>
<article-version-alternatives>
<article-version article-version-type="publication-state">reviewed preprint</article-version>
<article-version article-version-type="preprint-version">1.1</article-version>
</article-version-alternatives>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Neuroscience</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Dopamine increases protein synthesis in hippocampal neurons enabling dopamine-dependent LTP</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4751-8806</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Fuchsberger</surname>
<given-names>Tania</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stockwell</surname>
<given-names>Imogen</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Woods</surname>
<given-names>Matty</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brzosko</surname>
<given-names>Zuzanna</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7291-2581</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Greger</surname>
<given-names>Ingo H</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2258-5455</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Paulsen</surname>
<given-names>Ole</given-names>
</name>
    <email>op210@cam.ac.uk</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Physiology, Development and Neuroscience, Physiological Laboratory, University of Cambridge</institution>, <country>UK</country></aff>
<aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Neurobiology Division, MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology</institution>, Cambridge, <country>UK</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="section">
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Lourenco</surname>
<given-names>Mychael V</given-names>
</name>
<role>Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Federal University of Rio de Janeiro</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Rio de Janeiro</city>
<country>Brazil</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="senior_editor">
<name>
<surname>Colgin</surname>
<given-names>Laura L</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Texas at Austin</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Austin</city>
<country>United States of America</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding authors: <email>tf337@cam.ac.uk</email>, <email>op210@cam.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date date-type="original-publication" iso-8601-date="2024-09-02">
<day>02</day>
<month>09</month>
<year>2024</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<elocation-id>RP100822</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="sent-for-review" iso-8601-date="2024-06-25">
<day>25</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2024</year>
</date>
</history>
<pub-history>
<event>
<event-desc>Preprint posted</event-desc>
<date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2024-06-26">
<day>26</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2024</year>
</date>
<self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.06.25.600624"/>
</event>
</pub-history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2024, Fuchsberger et al</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Fuchsberger et al</copyright-holder>
<ali:free_to_read/>
<license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-preprint-100822-v1.pdf"/>
<abstract>
<title>Abstract</title>
<p>The reward and novelty related neuromodulator dopamine plays an important role in hippocampal long-term memory, which is thought to involve protein synthesis-dependent synaptic plasticity. However, the direct effects of dopamine on protein synthesis, and the functional implications of newly synthesized proteins for synaptic plasticity, have not yet been investigated. We have previously reported that timing-dependent synaptic depression (t-LTD) can be converted into potentiation by dopamine application during synaptic stimulation (Brzsoko et al., 2015) or postsynaptic burst activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">Fuchsberger et al., 2022</xref>). Here we show that dopamine increases protein synthesis in mouse hippocampal CA1 neurons, enabling dopamine-dependent long-term potentiation (DA-LTP). We found that neuronal activity is required for the dopamine-induced increase in protein synthesis, which is mediated via the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive adenylate cyclase (AC) subtypes 1/8, cAMP, and cAMP-dependent protein kinase (PKA). Furthermore, dopamine induced a protein synthesis-dependent increase in the AMPA receptor subunit GluA1, but not GluA2. We found that DA-LTP is absent in GluA1 knock-out mice and that it requires calcium-permeable AMPA receptors. Taken together, our results suggest that dopamine together with neuronal activity controls synthesis of plasticity-related proteins, including GluA1, which enable DA-LTP via a signalling pathway distinct from that of conventional LTP.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta specific-use="meta-only">
<meta-name>publishing-route</meta-name>
<meta-value>prc</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<notes notes-type="competing-interest-statement">
<title>Competing Interest Statement</title><p>The authors have declared no competing interest.</p></notes>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>An important role of dopamine in hippocampal long-term memory has long been recognised (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c31">O’Carroll et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c39">Rossato et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c43">Shohamy and Adcock., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">Takeuchi et al., 2016</xref>). Long-term memory is thought to be encoded by synaptic plasticity, in particular long-term potentiation (LTP; Bliss and Lømo, 1973) which, based on its duration, has been divided into an early phase and a protein synthesis-dependent late phase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">Frey et al., 1988</xref>). Dopaminergic signalling has been implicated specifically in ‘late-phase’ LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c15">Frey et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">Huang and Kandel, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">Matthies et al., 1997</xref>). Dopamine acts on G-protein-coupled receptors which activate adenylate cyclases (AC) to generate cAMP, which in turn activates several effectors, including the cAMP-dependent protein kinase (PKA). PKA has several downstream targets which ultimately regulate transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">Sassone-Corsi, 1995</xref>; Kebabian and Calne, 1997; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">Mayr and Montminy, 2001</xref>). Although the requirement of dopamine for protein synthesis-dependent LTP has been well established, the underlying cellular mechanisms of how dopamine modulates activated synapses via protein synthesis-dependent mechanisms remains poorly understood.</p>
<p>In order to selectively label newly synthesized proteins, we used a puromycin-based assay for surface sensing of translation (SUnSET) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">Schmidt et al., 2009</xref>) in acute mouse hippocampal slices. We found that dopamine increases protein synthesis in hippocampal neurons. We then investigated whether protein synthesis is required for a recently described dopamine-dependent form of plasticity (DA-LTP) which, although being rapid in onset, otherwise shares properties with ‘late-phase’ LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">Brzosko et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">Fuchsberger et al., 2022</xref>). Whilst conventional ‘early’ LTP induced by a spike-timing-dependent plasticity protocol (t-LTP; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">Bi and Poo, 1998</xref>) was unaffected, DA-LTP was completely abolished by either of two different protein synthesis inhibitors.</p>
<p>A previous study in primary cultured hippocampal neurons reported that dopaminergic signalling increases the surface expression of the AMPA receptor subunit GluA1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">Smith et al., 2005</xref>), which has been widely studied in the context of LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">Huganir and Nicoll, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">Diering and Huganir, 2018</xref>). Whereas most hippocampal AMPA receptors are heteromeric, incorporating the GluA2 subunit, making the receptor calcium-impermeable, GluA1 may form homomeric calcium-permeable AMPA receptors (CP-AMPARs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c5">Burnashev et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c48">Wenthold et al., 1996</xref>). As well as enabling calcium-permeability of the AMPAR, by lacking GluA2, the extracellular N-terminal domain of GluA1 homomers is highly flexible, which alters the gating of the receptor and hinders its synaptic anchoring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c49">Zhang et al., 2023</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c45">Stockwell et al., 2024</xref>). CP-AMPARs have been implicated in some forms of LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">Plant et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">Guire et al., 2008</xref>, Purkey et al., 2020), including a PKA-dependent form of plasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">Park et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
<p>We found that levels of the GluA1 receptor subunit, but not GluA2, were upregulated in response to dopamine in a protein synthesis-dependent manner. Moreover, DA-LTP was absent in a GluA1 genetic knock-out mouse model, while conventional t-LTP remained intact. These findings suggest that newly synthesized GluA1 receptor subunits mediate the expression of DA-LTP, possibly by forming GluA1 homomeric CP-AMPARs. Indeed, while blocking CP-AMPARs did not interfere with conventional t-LTP, they were required for DA-LTP.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Dopamine increases protein synthesis in CA1, which is required for dopamine-dependent long-term potentiation (DA-LTP)</title>
<p>We hypothesized that application of dopamine induces synthesis of proteins that are required for the expression of DA-LTP. To address this, we first investigated whether dopamine directly affects the protein synthesis in hippocampal neurons. In order to exclusively visualise newly synthesized proteins in hippocampal slices we used a puromycin (PMY)-based SUnSET assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">Schmidt et al., 2009</xref>). Labelling was achieved by incubating acute hippocampal slices in artificial cerebrospinal fluid (aCSF) containing 3 µM PMY for 30 minutes (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). As expected, slices incubated with PMY showed a significantly higher PMY intensity than those without (control, 0.39 ± 0.023, n = 9, vs +PMY, 0.54 ± 0.03, t(16) = 3.98, p = 0.001) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B and C</xref>), confirming specificity of the antibody labelling approach. Furthermore, we tested whether PMY incorporation and labelling are specific to protein synthesis by adding the protein synthesis inhibitor cycloheximide (CHX) or anisomycin (AM) to the slices. We found that 30 minutes preincubation with CHX significantly reduced the PMY signal, confirming the specificity of the labelling approach (PMY, 1.8 ± 0.45, n = 7 vs PMY+CHX, 0.4 ± 0.05, n = 8, t(6) = 3.1, p = 0.02) (<xref rid="figs1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1—figure supplement S1A</xref><bold> and B</bold>), as did 2 hr preincubation with AM (PMY, 0.6 ± 0.14, n = 4 vs PMY+AM, 0.16 ± 0.03, n = 5, t(3.2) = 3.1, p = 0.048) (<xref rid="figs1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1—figure supplement S1C</xref><bold> and D</bold>).</p>
<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Dopamine increases protein synthesis in CA1, required for DA-LTP, but not for conventional t-LTP. (<bold>A</bold>), Experimental workflow for protein synthesis labelling in acute hippocampal slices using SUnSET. PMY = puromycin. (<bold>B</bold>), Representative images of the CA1 region of the hippocampus (SP: stratum pyramidale, SR: stratum radiatum) of puromycin-labelled proteins (green) and Dapi (blue) in the following conditions: negative control (no PMY), PMY alone, PMY + dopamine (DA), PMY + SKF38393 (SKF), and PMY +DA + SCH23390 (SCH) + Sulpiride (Sul). The slices show an increase in protein synthesis after DA or SKF38393 application, which is blocked by DA receptor antagonists SCH23390 and Sulpiride. Scale bar, 30 µm. (<bold>C</bold>), Summary of results. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s HSD test, **, p &lt; 0.01; ***, p &lt; 0.001; ns, not significant. (<bold>D</bold>), Representative western blot of newly synthesised proteins detected by PMY Mabe343 antibody shows no signal in negative control (-PMY), and increased PMY signal in the presence of dopamine (+DA). Ponceau stain confirms equal loading of total protein. (<bold>E</bold>), Summary of results. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s HSD test, *, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.01; ***, p &lt; 0.001. (<bold>F</bold>), Dopamine application (DA) after a post-before-pre pairing protocol (Pairing, Δt = –20 ms) leads to synaptic potentiation (green trace), which is blocked by postsynaptically applied anisomycin (AM) (red trace) or cycloheximide (CHX) (blue trace). (<bold>G</bold>), Summary of results. <italic>t</italic>-test, **, p &lt; 0.01. (<bold>H</bold>), Intact conventional t-LTP (Δt = +10 ms, orange trace) in the presence of cycloheximide (CHX). (<bold>I</bold>), Summary of results. <italic>t</italic>-test, **, p &lt; 0.01. Traces show an EPSP before (1) and 40 minutes after (2) pairing. Plots show averages of normalised EPSP slopes ± SEM.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="600624v1_fig1.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<p>Strikingly, when applying dopamine the PMY signal was significantly increased compared to slices without dopamine (PMY, 0.54 ± 0.03, n = 9 vs PMY+DA, 0.8 ± 0.02, n = 16, p &lt; 0.001) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B and C</xref>). We next examined the effect of the D1/D5 receptor agonist SKF38393, and found that it stimulates protein synthesis to a similar extent as dopamine, with no significant difference between those two conditions (PMY+DA, 0.8 ± 0.02, n = 16, vs PMY+SFK, 0.79 ± 0.026, n = 9, p &gt; 0.99), and significantly different to PMY alone (PMY, 0.54 ± 0.03, n = 9 vs PMY+SFK, 0.79 ± 0.026, n = 9, p &lt; 0.001) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B and C</xref>). We next tested whether the dopamine-induced increase in protein synthesis could be prevented by application of D1/5 and D2 receptor antagonists. Using SCH23390, a selective antagonist at D1 (Ki = 0.2 nM) and D5 (Ki = 0.3 nM) receptor subtypes, and Sulpiride, a D2 antagonist (Ki = 8 nM), we found that the dopamine-induced increase in PMY signal was prevented (PMY+DA, 0.8 ± 0.019, n = 16, vs PMY+DA+SCH23390/Sulpiride, 0.61 ± 0.029, n = 8, p &lt; 0.001; all p values reported above from post-hoc Tukey’s HSD test, after confirming a statistically significant difference between at least two groups in one-way ANOVA; F(4, 46) = 49.55, p &lt; 0.001) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B and C</xref>).</p>
<p>To confirm the effect of dopamine on protein synthesis with an alternative quantification method, acute hippocampal slices were incubated as above and homogenates prepared for western blot analysis of the micro-dissected CA1 region. As expected, without PMY incubation the signal was virtually absent compared to samples with PMY (neg control, 5.44 ± 1.84, n = 5, vs +PMY, 97.24 ± 20.72, n = 5, p = 0.01). Dopamine application significantly increased the PMY signal (PMY, 97.24 ± 20.72, n = 5, vs PMY+DA = 201.2 ± 25.3, n = 5, p = 0.006; p values reported from post-hoc Tukey’s HSD test after one-way ANOVA; F(3, 16) = 19.85, p &lt; 0.0001) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D and E</xref>).</p>
<p>We then tested whether newly synthesized proteins are required for DA-LTP, which can be induced by a spike timing-dependent long-term depression (t-LTD) pairing protocol followed by dopamine application during low-frequency afferent stimulation, converting synaptic depression into potentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">Brzosko et al., 2015</xref>). In contrast, conventional t-LTD, induced by a post-before-pre pairing without dopamine application leads to synaptic depression, whereas a pre-before-post t-LTP protocol induces synaptic potentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">Bi and Poo, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">Feldman, 2012</xref>). We confirmed that application of dopamine after the pairing protocol (Δt = -20 ms) induces robust synaptic potentiation (145.4% ± 15.62% vs 100%, t(9) = 2.9, p = 0.0173, n = 10) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F and G</xref>). Dopamine application alone had no effect on synapses that did not undergo prior pairing (107% ± 13.5% vs 100%, t(9) = 0.54, p = 0.60, n = 10) (<xref rid="figs1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1—figure supplement S1E</xref><bold> and G</bold>). When delivering the protein synthesis inhibitor anisomycin (AM) to the postsynaptic cell through the recording pipette, DA-LTP was fully blocked, leaving synaptic depression instead (DA+AM, 56% ± 9% vs 100%, t(5) = 4.8, p = 0.0047, n = 6), which was significantly different from dopamine without AM (DA 145.4% ± 15.62% vs DA+AM 56% ± 9%, t(14) = 4.129, p = 0.001) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F and G</xref>). To exclude the possibility that the effect of AM on blocking DA-LTP is mediated via other signalling pathways affected by AM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c7">Croons et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">Hazzalin et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c27">Kyriakis et al., 1994</xref>) rather than by specific inhibition of protein synthesis, we used cycloheximide (CHX), an alternative blocker of protein synthesis. We found that loading CHX into the postsynaptic cell through the recording pipette also completely blocked DA-LTP, leaving synaptic depression instead (DA+CHX, 55% ± 12% vs 100%, t(5) = 3.7, p = 0.0133, n = 6) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F</xref>), which was significantly different from dopamine without CHX (DA 145.4% ± 15.62% vs DA+CHX 55% ± 12%, t(14) = 4.05, p = 0.001) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F and G</xref>). We also confirmed that postsynaptically applied AM or CHX had no effect on baseline synaptic transmission throughout the 60-minute duration of the experiment in the control pathway (no pairing +AM, 104 ± 17% vs 100%, t(5) = 0.23, p = 0.83, n = 6; and no pairing +CHX, 98 ± 6% vs 100%, t(5) = 0.32, p = 0.76, n = 6) (<xref rid="figs1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1—figure supplement S1F</xref><bold> and G</bold>).</p>
<p>In contrast, when we used a t-LTP protocol (Δt = +10 ms) while CHX was loaded into the postsynaptic cell, we still observed robust potentiation (t-LTP + CHX, 158% ± 19% vs 100%, t(5) = 3.11, p = 0.0265, n = 6, <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1H</xref>), and, as expected, there was no significant effect of CHX on the control pathway (CHX, 87% ± 13% vs 100%, t(5) = 0.97, p = 0.374, n = 6, <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1H</xref>). These results demonstrate that DA-LTP, but not conventional t-LTP, requires postsynaptic protein synthesis, revealing two different signalling pathways for LTP, one of which requires dopamine and protein synthesis, while the other one does not.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2b">
<title>Dopamine and neuronal activity mediate increase in protein synthesis</title>
<p>DA-LTP requires neuronal activation during dopamine application either via subthreshold synaptic stimulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">Brzosko et al., 2015</xref>) or postsynaptic bursts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">Fuchsberger et al., 2022</xref>). Thus, we investigated whether neuronal activity is also required for the dopamine-induced increase in protein synthesis.</p>
<p>To test this, acute hippocampal slices were treated with tetrodotoxin (TTX), a voltage-gated sodium channel blocker, during PMY incubations (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). We confirmed using whole-cell patch clamp recordings that application of TTX inhibits spontaneous EPSPs in CA1 pyramidal neurons in our preparations (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). Using the PMY labelling assay, we found that TTX incubation alone did not significantly alter PMY labelling, suggesting that the baseline level of protein synthesis is not affected by blocking neuronal activity for 30 minutes (control, 0.55 ± 0.033, n = 8, vs TTX, 0.53 ± 0.026, n = 8, p = 0.90) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A and C</xref>). However, TTX significantly diminished the dopamine-induced increase in protein synthesis (DA, 0.83 ± 0.024, n = 9, vs DA+TTX, 0.65 ± 0.017, n = 9, p &lt; 0.001). Nevertheless, the dopamine-induced increase in protein synthesis was not fully blocked by TTX, as it remained significantly higher in the presence of dopamine and TTX compared to TTX alone (TTX+DA, 0.65 ± 0.017, n = 9, vs TTX 0.53 ± 0.026, n = 8, p = 0.005; p values reported from post-hoc Tukey’s HSD test after one-way ANOVA; F (3, 30) = 30.57, p &lt; 0.001) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A and C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Dopamine and neuronal activity mediate increase in protein synthesis via AC1/8 and PKA enabling DA-LTP. (<bold>A</bold>), Representative images of the CA1 region (SR: stratum oriens, SP: stratum pyramidale) of the hippocampus of puromycin-labelled proteins in the following conditions: PMY alone (- DA), PMY+dopamine (+DA), PMY+TTX (-DA+TTX), PMY+dopamine+TTX (+DA+TTX). Images show that the dopamine-induced increase in protein synthesis is reduced in the presence of TTX. Scale bar, 30 µm. (<bold>B</bold>), TTX abolishes spontaneous activity shown in traces of whole-cell patch clamp recording. (<bold>C</bold>), Summary of results. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s HSD test, **, p &lt; 0.01; ***, p &lt; 0.001; ns, not significant. (<bold>D</bold>), Representative images of the CA1 region (SR: stratum oriens, SP: stratum pyramidale) of the hippocampus of puromycin-labelled proteins in the following conditions: PMY alone (-DA), PMY+Rp-cAMPS (-DA+Rp-cAMPS, PMY+dopamine (+DA), and PMY+dopamine+Rp-cAMPS (+DA+Rp-cAMPS). Images show that the dopamine-induced increase in protein synthesis is prevented by Rp-cAMPS. (<bold>E</bold>), Summary of results. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s HSD test, *, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.01; ns, not significant. (<bold>F</bold>), Dopamine application (DA) after a post-before-pre pairing protocol (Pairing, Δt = –20 ms) leads to synaptic potentiation in WT (green trace), but not in AC DKO mice (red trace). (<bold>G</bold>), Postsynaptically applied PKA inhibitor PKI6-22 blocks DA-LTP (red trace), leaving synaptic depression instead. (<bold>H</bold>), Summary of results. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s HSD test, **, p &lt; 0.01; ***, p &lt; 0.001. Traces show an EPSP before (1) and 40 minutes after (2) pairing. Plots show averages of normalised EPSP slopes ± SEM.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="600624v1_fig2.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2c">
<title>Dopamine-induced increase in protein synthesis is mediated via AC1/8 and PKA</title>
<p>We then sought to identify the signalling pathway that mediates the changes in protein synthesis in response to dopamine and neuronal activity. D1 and D5 dopamine receptors are known to activate adenylate cyclases (AC), which increase cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) activating the cAMP-dependent protein kinase (PKA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c41">Sassone-Corsi, 2012</xref>). We used the PMY incubation assay to assess the protein synthesis in the presence of Rp-cAMPS, a cell-permeable cAMP analogue which acts as an inhibitor of PKA. We found that application of Rp-cAMPS had no significant effect on protein synthesis in control conditions (control, 1.16 ± 0.10, n = 10, vs Rp-cAMPS 1.74 ± 0.35, n = 8, p = 0.25), but completely blocked the dopamine-induced increase in PMY levels (DA, 2.16 ± 0.23, n = 10, vs DA+Rp-cAMPS, 1.30 ± 0.12, n = 9, p = 0.029; p values reported from post-hoc Tukey’s HSD test after one-way ANOVA; F (3, 33) = 4.912, p = 0.0062) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D and E</xref>).</p>
<p>AC subtypes 1 and 8 are additionally activated by Ca<sup>2+</sup>, which would make them attractive candidates to mediate activity-dependent dopamine signalling. We therefore tested whether DA-LTP requires these adenylate cyclases using an AC1/AC8 double knock-out (DKO) mouse model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c47">Wang et al., 2003</xref>). We found that DA-LTP was completely absent in AC1/AC8 DKO mice, leaving synaptic depression instead (AC DKO 74.4% ± 10.3% vs 100%, t(6) = 2.6, p = 0.041, n = 7), which was significantly different to DA-LTP in WT mice (WT 125.1% ± 15.8%, n = 6, vs AC DKO 74.4% ± 10.3%, n = 7, t(11) = 4.2, p = 0.0016) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2F and H</xref>). To test whether PKA signalling is required for DA-LTP, we loaded the PKA blocker, protein kinase inhibitor-(6-22)-amide (PKI), into the postsynaptic cell through the recording pipette. Dopamine application after the t-LTD priming protocol followed by subthreshold synaptic stimulation failed to convert depression into potentiation in the presence of PKI (DA+PKI 81% ± 3% vs 100%, t(5) = 6.1, p = 0.0017, n = 6), which was significantly different to the effect of dopamine application without PKI (DA+PKI 81% ± 3.1% vs DA 125.1% ± 15.8%, t(10) = 6.2, p = 0.0001) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2G and H</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2d">
<title>Dopamine increases GluA1, which is required for DA-LTP</title>
<p>It has been reported in hippocampal primary neuronal culture that dopaminergic stimulation enhances surface expression of the AMPA receptor subunit GluA1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">Smith et al., 2005</xref>). To confirm whether this finding holds in an acute slice preparation, we tested the effect of dopamine on GluA1 levels in the micro-dissected CA1 region. Using western blot analysis, we found that dopamine application induces a significant increase in the GluA1 receptor subunit compared to control conditions (control, 0.44 ± 0.071, n = 7, vs DA, 1.03 ± 0.18, n = 7, t(6) = 3.27, p = 0.02) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A and B</xref>). Importantly, when we blocked protein synthesis with cycloheximide, the GluA1 increase was prevented (DA, 1.03 ± 0.18, n = 7, vs DA+CHX, 0.74 ± 0.15, n = 7, t(6) = 3.33, p = 0.02) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A and B</xref>) showing that the dopamine-induced increase in GluA1 is protein synthesis-dependent. In contrast, when we measured the levels of the GluA2 subunit under the same conditions, we could not detect significant differences between dopamine-treated and control CA1 (control, 0.67 ± 0.17, n = 5, vs DA, 0.61 ± 0.15, n = 5, t(4) = 0.69, p = 0.53) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C and D</xref>), nor in the presence of CHX (DA 0.61 ± 0.15, n = 5, vs DA+CHX, 0.60 ± 0.15, n = 5, t(4) = 0.75, p = 0.5) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C and D</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption><p>Dopamine increases GluA1 in a protein synthesis-dependent manner, which is required for DA-LTP. (<bold>A</bold>), Western blot images from tissue homogenates of the hippocampal CA1 region shows increase of GluA1 upon dopamine application (+DA), which is abolished in the presence of cycloheximide (+DA +CHX). α-Actin was used as loading control. (<bold>B</bold>) Summary of results. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s HSD test, *, p &lt; 0.05; ns, not significant. (<bold>C</bold>) Western blot shows unchanged GluA2 following dopamine application (DA) and no change with cycloheximide (+DA +CHX). (<bold>D</bold>), Summary of results. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s HSD test, ns, not significant. (<bold>E</bold>), A t-LTP pairing protocol (Δt = +10 ms) induces potentiation (dark blue trace), and a t-LTD protocol (Δt = –20 ms) induces depression (light blue trace) in GluA1 KO mice, (<bold>F</bold>) No DA-LTP in GluA1 KO mice. (<bold>G</bold>), Summary of results. All traces show an EPSP before (1) and 40 minutes after (2) pairing. Plots show averages of normalised EPSP slopes ± SEM. <italic>t</italic>-test, *, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.01; ns, not significant.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="600624v1_fig3.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<p>We next investigated the functional implications of GluA1 for DA-LTP using a GluA1 knock-out (KO) mouse model. GluA1 plays an important role in synaptic plasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c50">Zamanillo et al., 1999</xref>;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Granger et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">Park et al., 2019</xref>, Purkey et al., 2020), but is not required for all forms of LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c21">Hoffman et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c38">Romberg et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Frey et al., 2009</xref>). Thus, we first tested whether we could induce conventional t-LTP and t-LTD in slices of GluA1 KO mice. We found that a t-LTP protocol (Δt = +10 ms) led to synaptic potentiation, albeit of somewhat reduced magnitude (t-LTP GluA1 KO, 125% ± 9.4% vs 100%, t(5) = 2.6, p = 0.046, n = 6) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E and G</xref>), while a t-LTD protocol (Δt = -20 ms) induced synaptic depression (t-LTD GluA1 KO, 65.9% ± 8.8% vs 100%, t(12) = 3.9, p = 0.002, n = 13) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E and G</xref>). Strikingly, however, in the GluA1 KO mice, application of dopamine failed to convert t-LTD into LTP (DA-LTP GluA1 KO, 90% ± 7.2%, n = 8; <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3F</xref>) and the resulting depression was not significantly different from t-LTD without dopamine (t-LTD vs DA-LTP, t(19) = 1.905, p = 0.07) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3G</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that newly synthesized GluA1 subunits are required for expression of DA-LTP.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2e">
<title>DA-LTP requires CP-AMPARs</title>
<p>GluA1 homomers may form CP-AMPARs in the hippocampus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c48">Wenthold et al., 1996</xref>). A transient increase in CP-AMPARs has been reported in some forms of LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">Plant et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">Guire et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">Park et al., 2019</xref>; Purkey et al., 2020), including a PKA-dependent form of plasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">Park et al., 2021</xref>). Since we observed a protein synthesis-dependent increase in the GluA1, but not GluA2, AMPA receptor subunit after dopamine application, we hypothesised that CP-AMPA receptors might be involved in DA-LTP.</p>
<p>We compared the effect of NASPM, a selective CP-AMPAR antagonist, on conventional t-LTP (Δt = +10 ms) to the effect of NASPM on DA-LTP. We found that robust t-LTP was elicited in the presence of extracellular NASPM (139.6% ± 10.9% vs 100%, t(5) = 3.6, p = 0.015, n = 6) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A and C</xref>). In contrast, when applying NASPM during a DA-LTP protocol, potentiation was completely prevented (74.86% ± 15.18 vs 100%, t(5) = 1.66, p = 0.16, n = 6) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B and C</xref>). This shows that CP-AMPARs are indeed required for DA-LTP. The selective increase of GluA1 receptor subunit levels seen in response to dopamine (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A-D</xref>) suggests that CP-AMPARs are required for expression of DA-LTP.</p>
<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption><p>CP-AMPARs are required for DA-LTP but not for conventional t-LTP. (<bold>A</bold>), A t-LTP pairing protocol (Δt = +10 ms) induces synaptic potentiation in the presence of extracellularly applied NASPM. (<bold>B</bold>), NASPM blocks DA-LTP. (<bold>C</bold>), Summary of results. <italic>t</italic>-test, *, p &lt; 0.05. (<bold>D</bold>), Burst-induced DA-LTP is blocked by NASPM. (<bold>E</bold>) Burst-induced DA-LTP potentiation decreases when NASPM is applied 7 minutes afterwards. (<bold>F</bold>), Summary of results. <italic>t</italic>-test, *, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.01; ns, not significant. Traces in (<bold>A, B</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) show an EPSP before (1) and 40 minutes after pairing (2). Traces in (<bold>E</bold>) show an EPSP before (1), 5 minutes after DA and burst stimulation (2), and 40 minutes after pairing (3). Plots show averages of normalised EPSP slopes ± SEM.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="600624v1_fig4.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<p>We have recently reported that, in addition to synaptic activation, postsynaptic burst stimulation can also induce DA-LTP, which is mediated via the same AC-PKA signalling pathway and also requires protein synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">Fuchsberger et al., 2022</xref>). Synaptically induced DA-LTP develops gradually, while burst-induced DA-LTP shows rapid potentiation. We therefore used burst-induced DA-LTP to test whether a transient increase in CP-AMPARs may be required for potentiation. We applied NASPM during or shortly after the plasticity protocol to test whether this affects the expression of DA-LTP. We found that application of NASPM during burst stimulation completely prevented synaptic potentiation (78.17% ± 10.87% vs 100%, t(6) = 2.01, p = 0.091, n = 7) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D and F</xref>). However, when applying NASPM 7 minutes <italic>after</italic> burst stimulation, we observed an initial potentiation (117.6% ± 3.88% vs 100%, t(6) = 4.52, p = 0.0063, n = 6), which gradually returned to baseline in the presence of NASPM (91.1% ± 10.9% vs 100%, t(5) = 0.815, p = 0.45, n = 6) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4E and F</xref>).</p>
<p>To confirm these results with an alternative CP-AMPAR blocker we applied IEM1460 extracellularly. Conventional t-LTP (Δt = +10 ms) was compared to DA-LTP in the presence of IEM1460 throughout the recording, which were significantly different (t-LTP+IEM1460, 142.0% ± 20.93%, n = 7, vs DA- LTP+IEM1460, 80.3% ± 8.1%, n = 7, t(12) = 2.75, p = 0.02) (<xref rid="figs4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4—figure supplement S4A, B</xref><bold> and D</bold>). When applied immediately <italic>after</italic> the pairing protocol, IEM1460 still prevented DA-LTP and left a synaptic depression instead (DA-LTP+IEM after, 67.5% ± 12.11% vs 100%, t(8) = 2.68, p = 0.028, n = 9) (<xref rid="figs4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4—figure supplement S4C</xref><bold> and D</bold>). Taken together, these results suggest that DA-LTP, but not conventional t-LTP, requires CP-AMPARs for expression of synaptic potentiation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In summary, we investigated the effect of dopamine on protein synthesis in hippocampal neurons and how protein synthesis enables dopamine-dependent long-term potentiation (DA-LTP). We report four main findings: (1) Dopamine increases protein synthesis in an activity-dependent manner through the activation of PKA. (2) Dopamine enables a rapid onset protein synthesis-dependent form of synaptic potentiation (DA-LTP). (3) Dopamine increases the level of GluA1 but not GluA2 subunit of AMPA receptors. (4) Expression of DA-LTP requires GluA1 AMPA receptor subunit and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeable (CP)-AMPARs, whereas t-LTP does not, suggesting the existence of two distinct forms of LTP.</p>
<p>Recent developments of protein synthesis labelling techniques enabled us to directly monitor protein synthesis in neurons in response to dopamine. We report that dopamine increases protein synthesis in pyramidal neurons in CA1 of acute hippocampal slices within minutes. This is consistent with previous reports from hippocampal and cortical neuronal cell culture systems, which showed that dopamine receptor agonist SKF-38393 enhances protein synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">Smith et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c10">David et al., 2020</xref>). We found that the dopamine-induced increase in protein synthesis is mediated by D1/D5 receptors via the AC-cAMP-PKA pathway (Mayr et al., 2001; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">Sassone-Corsi, 1995</xref>), which is also consistent with previously reported hippocampal cell culture results which showed that application of Sp-cAMPS, an activator of PKA, was sufficient to induce an increase in protein synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">Smith et al., 2005</xref>). In addition, the AC-cAMP-PKA pathway induced by dopamine may affect several downstream targets and interact with other signalling pathways that could enhance protein synthesis. It has been reported in cortical primary neuronal cultures that D1, but not D2 receptors, increase protein synthesis via the mTOR-ERK pathway resulting in dephosphorylation of eEF2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c10">David et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
<p>Consistent with our previous results that burst-induced potentiation in the presence of dopamine requires postsynaptic PKA and protein synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">Fuchsberger et al., 2022</xref>), we found here that synaptic potentiation induced by low frequency synaptic stimulation in the presence of dopamine following a priming protocol, which would otherwise induce synaptic depression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">Brzosko et al., 2015</xref>), also requires postsynaptic PKA and new protein synthesis. While conventional t-LTP remained intact, blocking protein synthesis in the postsynaptic neurons completely prevented DA-LTP, suggesting that dopamine induces the synthesis of plasticity-related proteins required for converting synaptic depression into potentiation.</p>
<p>DA-LTP shares properties with ‘late-phase’ LTP (L-LTP), which also requires dopamine signalling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c15">Frey et al., 1990</xref>), PKA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c14">Frey et al., 1993</xref>) and protein synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">Frey et al., 1988</xref>), and it was reported that protein synthesis was required hours after LTP induction for the maintenance of synaptic strength (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">Frey et al., 1988</xref>). In contrast, for the form of dopamine-dependent LTP studied here, protein synthesis was required ahead of or within the first few minutes of the induction protocol. Moreover, while previous studies have used extracellular application of protein synthesis inhibitors, here we specifically loaded the protein synthesis inhibitors into the postsynaptic neuron via the patch pipette, suggesting it is specifically postsynaptic protein synthesis that is required for DA-LTP.</p>
<p>We found that neuronal activity was also required for dopamine to increase protein synthesis, and we identified the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent AC subtypes AC1/AC8 as coincidence detector for the two signals, Gs-coupled dopamine D1/D5 receptor activation and Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx. Our results show that the AC1/AC8 subtypes and PKA are required for DA-LTP. These results suggest that dopamine application during neuronal activity induces the synthesis of plasticity-related proteins that enable synaptic potentiation.</p>
<p>Western blots showed that dopamine increased the levels of the AMPA receptor GluA1 subunit in a protein synthesis-dependent manner, but that the GluA2 subunit remained unchanged. This is consistent with a previous study in primary hippocampal cultured neurons which reported that dopaminergic signalling increases the surface expression of AMPA receptor subunit GluA1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">Smith et al., 2005</xref>). The selective increase of the GluA1 over GluA2 subunit is interesting because of the important role ascribed to the GluA1 subunit in LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">Huganir and Nicoll, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">Diering and Huganir, 2018</xref>).</p>
<p>We report here that although conventional t-LTP could still be induced in a GluA1 KO mouse model, GluA1 was required for DA-LTP. These observations revealed a possible mechanism through which dopamine can modulate synaptic strength. Furthermore, the findings indicated another intriguing possibility, namely that GluA1 homomeric AMPA receptors, which are calcium-permeable, mediate the expression of DA-LTP. CPAMPA receptors appear to be required for some forms of LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">Plant et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">Guire et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Frey et al., 2009</xref>), while other studies found no involvement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">Adesnik and Nicoll, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">Gray et al., 2007</xref>). Their role in synaptic plasticity remains controversial. We report here that they are required for DA-LTP, but not for conventional t-LTP. Importantly, even blocking CP-AMPARs after the pairing paradigm reversed DA-LTP, which strongly supports the possibility that they are required for expression of DA-LTP. Whether they also contribute to the induction of the dopamine-dependent potentiation induced by low-frequency afferent stimulation following a t-LTD priming protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">Brzosko et al., 2015</xref>) remains unresolved.</p>
<p>In summary, our findings suggest a possible mechanism for how the reward-related neuromodulator dopamine may contribute to protein synthesis-dependent synaptic plasticity facilitating hippocampal long-term memory. However, understanding the signalling mechanisms underlying dopaminergic control of protein synthesis and synaptic weights is not only important for studying learning and memory mechanisms, but may also be important for pathophysiological processes. Dysregulation in dopamine systems has been long been implicated in drug addiction (for review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">Dalley and Everitt, 2009</xref>), schizophrenia (for review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">Kahn et al., 2015</xref>) as well as neurodegenerative diseases such as Parkinson’s disease (for review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c36">Poewe et al., 2017</xref>), and, more recently, also Alzheimer’s disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c30">Nobili et al., 2017</xref>). Understanding signalling pathways underlying dopamine-dependent synaptic plasticity may help guide future research into alternative treatment options.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Animals</title>
<p>Mice used for this study were housed at the Combined Animal Facility, Cambridge University. They were held on a 12-hr light/dark cycle at 19–23 °C and were provided with water and food ad libitum. Experiments were carried out using wildtype C57BL/6 J mice (Charles River Laboratories, UK), and the transgenic mouse lines adenylate cyclase (AC) subtypes 1 and 8 double knockout (AC1/AC8 DKO) mice and GluA1 knockout mice (GluA1 KO). The AC1/AC8 DKO mice have the genes for both AC1 and AC8 deleted globally. The mouse line was generated as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c47">Wang, et al., 2003</xref>) and was imported from Michigan State University, MI, US. The GluA1 KO mouse line was generated as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c50">Zamanillo et al., 1999</xref>) and was imported from the MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Cambridge, UK.</p>
<p>All procedures were performed in accordance with the animal care guidelines of the UK Home Office regulations of the UK Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986, and Amendment Regulations 2012, following ethical review by the University of Cambridge Animal Welfare and Ethical Review Body (AWERB). Animal procedures were authorized under Personal and Project licences held by the authors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4b">
<title>Preparation of acute hippocampal slices</title>
<p>Male and female mice at postnatal days 12-19 were briefly anaesthetised with isoflurane (4% isoflurane in oxygen) and decapitated. The brain was rapidly removed into ice-cold artificial cerebrospinal fluid (aCSF) (10 mM glucose, 26.4 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, 126 mM NaCl, 1.25 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 3 mM KCl, 2 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>) bubbled with carbogen gas (95% O<sub>2</sub>/5% CO<sub>2</sub>) (pH 7.2, 270–290 mOsm/L) and glued to a vibrating microtome stage. Horizontal slices (350 μm) were sectioned with a vibratome (Leica VT 1200S, Leica Biosystems, Wetzlar, Germany) and were subsequently submerged in aCSF for at least 1 hr at room temperature (RT) in a storage chamber. Slices were used 1–6 hr after preparation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4c">
<title>Electrophysiology</title>
<sec id="s4c1">
<title>Whole-cell recordings and synaptic plasticity</title>
<p>Individual slices were transferred to a submersion-type chamber for recordings, and superfused with aCSF (2 ml/min) at RT (24–26 °C). Neurons were visualized with an infrared differential interference contrast (DIC) microscope using a 40x water-immersion objective. Hippocampal subfields were identified and whole-cell patch-clamp recordings were performed on CA1 pyramidal neurons. Monopolar stimulation electrodes were placed in stratum radiatum for stimulation of Schaffer collaterals. Electrodes for test and control pathways were placed at the same distance (&gt;100 µm) from either side of the recorded neuron. Patch pipettes (pipette resistance 4–7 MΩ) were pulled from borosilicate glass capillaries (0.68 mm inner diameter, 1.2 mm outer diameter) using a P-97 Flaming/Brown micropipette puller (Sutter Instruments Co., Novato, California, USA). Pipettes were filled with intracellular solution containing: 110 mM potassium gluconate, 4 mM NaCl, 40 mM HEPES, 2 mM ATP-Mg, 0.3 mM GTP (pH 7.2–7.3, 270–285 mOsm/L). The liquid junction potential was not corrected.</p>
<p>All experiments were performed in current-clamp mode. Cells were accepted for the experiment if their resting membrane potential was between −55 and −70 mV. Throughout the recording the membrane potential was held at −70 mV by direct current application via the recording electrode. All cells were tested for regular spiking responses to positive current steps (20 pA, 800 ms) characteristic of pyramidal neurons before the start of each recording.</p>
<p>TTX experiments were performed measuring spontaneous EPSPs for 5 minutes before and after adding 1 μM TTX to superfusing aCSF for 15 minutes.</p>
<p>Plasticity recordings were carried out as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">Brzosko et al., 2015</xref>). Briefly, excitatory postsynaptic potentials (EPSPs) were evoked alternately in two input pathways (test and control) by direct current pulses at 0.2 Hz (stimulus duration 50 μs) through metal stimulation electrodes. The stimulation intensity was adjusted (100 μA – 500 µA) to evoke an EPSP with peak amplitude between 3 and 8 mV. After a stable EPSP baseline period of at least 10 minutes, spike-timing-dependent plasticity (STDP) was induced in the test pathway by repeated pairings (100 times at 0.2 Hz) of single evoked EPSPs and single postsynaptic action potentials elicited with the minimum somatic current pulse (1 – 1.8 nA, 3 ms) via the recording electrode. Spike-timing intervals (Δt in ms) were measured between the onset of the EPSP and the onset of the action potential. Alternate stimulation of test and control EPSPs was resumed immediately after the pairing protocol and monitored for at least 40 minutes, except when the burst stimulation protocol was used for plasticity induction. In that case, stimulation of EPSPs was not resumed for an additional 10 minutes in the test pathway, and at the end of that period, five bursts, each of five action potentials at 50 Hz, were elicited with an inter-burst interval of 0.1 Hz by somatic current pulses (1.8 nA, 10 ms) via the recording electrode. Immediately after the bursts, stimulation of EPSPs was resumed and monitored for at least 30 minutes. Presynaptic stimulation frequency to evoke EPSPs remained constant throughout the experiment. The unpaired control pathway served as a stability control.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s4d">
<title>Drug application</title>
<p>Drugs were bath-applied to the whole slice through the perfusion system by dilution of concentrated stock solutions in aCSF, or by adding the drugs to the patch pipette solution when it was applied intracellularly to the postsynaptic cell only. For each set of recordings, interleaved control and drug conditions were carried out and were pseudo-randomly chosen. The following drugs were used in this study: 100 μM dopamine hydrochloride (Sigma–Aldrich, Dorset, United Kingdom), 10 µM cycloheximide (Tocris Bioscience), 0.5 mM anisomycin (stock solution in EtOH; Tocris Bioscience), 1 µM PKA inhibitor fragment (6-22) amide (Tocris Bioscience), 100 μM 1-naphthyl acetyl spermine trihydrochloride (NASPM trihydrochloride; Tocris Bioscience), 10 µM N,N,H,-trimethyl-5-[(tricyclo[3.3.1.13,7]dec-1-ylmethyl)amino]-1- pentanaminiumbromide hydrobromide (IEM1460; Tocris Bioscience).</p>
<sec id="s4d1">
<title>Data acquisition and data analysis of slice recordings</title>
<p>Data were collected using an Axon Multiclamp 700B amplifier (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, California, USA). Data were filtered at 2 kHz and were acquired and digitized at 5 kHz using an Instrutech ITC-18 A/D interface board (Instrutech, Port Washington, New York, USA) and custom-made acquisition procedures in Igor Pro (WaveMetrics, Lake Oswego, Oregon, USA).</p>
<p>All experiments were carried out in current clamp mode, and only cells with an initial series resistance between 9 – 16 MΩ were included. Series resistance was compensated for by adjusting the bridge balance, and recordings were discarded if series resistance changed by more than 30%. Offline analyses of plasticity recordings were done using custom-made procedures in Igor Pro. EPSP slopes were measured on the rising phase of the EPSP as a linear fit between the time points corresponding to 25–30% and 70–75% of the peak amplitude.</p>
<p>For quantifications, the mean EPSP slope per minute of the recording was calculated from 12 consecutive sweeps and normalised to the baseline (each data point in source data files is the mean of 12 averaged EPSPs). Normalised EPSP slopes from the last 5 minutes of the baseline (immediately before pairing) and from the last 5 minutes of the recording were averaged. The magnitude of plasticity, as an indicator of change in synaptic weights, was defined as the average EPSP slope 40 minutes after the plasticity protocol expressed as a percentage of the average EPSP slope during baseline. In case of the burst-induction protocol, the change in synaptic weights, was defined as the average EPSP slope 30 minutes after the plasticity protocol expressed as a percentage of the average EPSP slope during baseline.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s4e">
<title>Statistical analysis of slice recordings</title>
<p>Statistical comparisons were performed using one-sample two-tailed, paired two-tailed, or unpaired two-tailed Student’s <italic>t</italic>-test, with a significance level of α = 0.05. Data are presented as mean ± SEM. Significance levels are indicated by *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4f">
<title>Protein synthesis labelling in acute hippocampal slices</title>
<p>Incubation chambers were set up to submerge slices in oxygenated (95% O<sub>2</sub>, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>) aCSF containing a selection from the following drugs: 3 µM puromycin dihydrochloride (Sigma P8833), 100 µM dopamine hydrochloride (Sigma H8502), 10 µM SKF38393 (Sigma D047), 10 μM SCH23390 hydrochloride (Sigma D054), 50 μM sulpiride (Sigma S8010), 1 µM TTX (Tocris Bioscience), 10 µM cycloheximide (Tocris Bioscience), 0.5 mM anisomycin (stock solution in EtOH; Tocris Bioscience), 30 µM Rp-cAMPS (Tocris Bioscience).</p>
<p>Protein synthesis was measured using a puromycin labelling assay, based on the SUnSET method, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">Schmidt et al., 2009</xref>). Briefly, 3 µM puromycin was used to incorporate into proteins during the elongation phase of synthesis (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). After exactly 30 minutes of incubation with puromycin, samples were washed in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), and further processed for immunohistochemistry or western blotting as described below. The specificity of the conjugated puromycin monoclonal antibody was confirmed with incubations of no-puromycin controls and protein synthesis inhibitors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4g">
<title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
<p>Immediately after incubations with puromycin slices were washed in PBS and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in 1x PBS for 24 hr at 4 °C. Slices were subsequently washed 3 x 5 minutes in PBST 0.01% (DPBS ThermoFisher, Tween P1379 Sigma), permeabilised for 15 minutes in PBST 0.5% and washed in PBST 0.01% a further three times. Slices were incubated for 2 hr at room temperature in a blocking solution of 5% goat serum in PBST 0.0.1% (SigmaAldrich G9023) followed by an incubation overnight at 4 °C in blocking solution with anti-puromycin antibody (clone 12D10, MABE343; 1:500) AlexaFluor 488 or AlexaFluor 647 (MABE343-AF488 or MABE343-AF647; Merck). On the following day, slices were left on a shaker for 2 hr at RT, followed by 3 x 5 minutes washes in PBST 0.01%. Finally, slices were mounted onto microscope slides (ThermoScientific J1810AMNZ), allowed to dry for at least 2 hr at RT, then covered with Fluoroshield with Dapi mounting medium for nuclear staining (Sigma F6057) and sealed with coverslip sealant (Biotium 23005).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4h">
<title>Imaging and image analysis</title>
<p>Immunohistochemical preparations were visualised using a confocal laser-scanning microscope (Leica TCS SP8). Z-stacks of hippocampal CA1 region were taken using an HC PL APO 20x/0.75 CS2 objective using the same exposure settings for all conditions that were compared to each other. AlexaFluor 647 was excited at 638 nm and emission detected at 671 nm; AlexaFluor488 was excited at 495 nm and emission detected at 519 nm, Dapi was excited at 359 nm, emission detected at 461 nm. Images were analysed using ImageJ. To obtain normalised integrated density, the maximum intensity Z-projection of slices were extracted, from which the integrated density was measured and normalised to the corresponding nuclear staining (Dapi) Z-projection measurement. Normalised integrated density was plotted and statistical analysis was performed using one-way ANOVA and post-hoc Tukey’s HSD test, following adherence to tests for normality and equality of variance. Significance level used was α = 0.05 and indicated as *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4i">
<title>Western blot analysis</title>
<p>Acute hippocampal slices were prepared and incubated with various compounds as described above. After 30 minutes incubation, slices were rapidly dissected in aCSF to obtain the CA1 region, which were pooled for slices from each condition and flash frozen in liquid N2. Protein extraction buffer (150 mM NaCl, 1% Triton x-100, 50 mM TrisHCl pH 7.4 with protease inhibitor (11836170001 Roche)), at a volume adjusted to the tissue weight for each sample, was added to lyse the tissue for 1 hr at 4°C with frequent vortexing. Samples were centrifuged at 16,000 x g for 30 minutes at 4 °C and the supernatant was retained. Lysate was mixed with LDS sample buffer (Invitrogen NP0007) and boiled at 95 °C for 5 min, after which it was loaded onto a polyacrylamide gel (Bolt 4-12% Bis-Tris NW04127BOX). Loading was adjusted to achieve comparable actin signal. Proteins were transferred onto a nitrocellulose membrane using Trans-Blot Turbo Transfer (BioRad 1704158) and membranes were then blocked for 30 minutes at room temperature with 5% milk in TBST. Membranes were incubated with primary antibodies (anti-actin MAB1501R, anti-puromycin MABE343, anti-GluA1 AB1504, anti-GluA2 AF1050), washed 3 times in TBST, incubated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-coupled secondary antibody (Sigma) and washed a further 3 times. Membranes were developed using enhanced chemiluminescence and imaged with a ChemiDoc MP Imaging System (Biorad). Quantification of antibody staining was made using ImageJ. Integrated density of GluA1/2 bands was normalised to integrated density of actin in the corresponding lane. Statistical analysis was performed using one-way ANOVA and post-hoc Tukey’s HSD test, following adherence to tests for normality and equality of variance. Significance level used was α = 0.05 and indicated as *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="c1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Adesnik</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Nicoll</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Conservation of glutamate receptor 2-containing AMPA receptors during long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci</source>. <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>4598</fpage>–<lpage>4602</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bi</surname> <given-names>GQ</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Poo</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Synaptic modifications in cultured hippocampal neurons: dependence on spike timing, synaptic strength, and postsynaptic cell type</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>10464</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bliss</surname> <given-names>TV</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Lomo</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Long-lasting potentiation of synaptic transmission in the dentate area of the anaesthetized rabbit following stimulation of the perforant path</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>. <volume>232</volume>:<fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brzosko</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schultz</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulsen</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Retroactive modulation of spike timing-dependent plasticity by dopamine</article-title>. <source>Elife</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e09685</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Burnashev</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monyer</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seeburg</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sakmann</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Divalent ion permeability of AMPA receptor channels is dominated by the edited form of a single subunit</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Coombs</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bats</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sexton</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Studniarczyk</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cull-Candy</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farrant</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2023</year>) <article-title>Enhanced functional detection of synaptic calcium-permeable AMPA receptors using intracellular NASPM</article-title>. <source>Elife</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e66765</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Croons</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinet</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herman</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Timmermans</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Meyer</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The protein synthesis inhibitor anisomycin induces macrophage apoptosis in rabbit atherosclerotic plaques through p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase</article-title>. <source>J.Pharmacol.Exp.Ther</source>. <volume>329</volume>:<fpage>856</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Diering</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huganir</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>The AMPA Receptor Code of Synaptic Plasticity</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dalley</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Everitt</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dopamine receptors in the learning, memory and drug reward circuitry</article-title>. <source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source>. <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>David</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrera</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gould</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gal-Ben-Ari</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenblum</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>D1 dopamine receptor activation induces neuronal eEF2 pathway-dependent protein synthesis</article-title>. <source>Front Mol Neurosci</source>. <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Feldman</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The spike-timing dependence of plasticity</article-title> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Neuron</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sprengel</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nevian</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Activity pattern-dependent long-term potentiation in neocortex and hippocampus of GluA1 (GluR-A) subunit-deficient mice</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>5587</fpage>–<lpage>5596</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krug</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reymann</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthies</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Anisomycin, an inhibitor of protein synthesis, blocks late phases of LTP phenomena in the hippocampal CA1 region in vitro</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>. <volume>452</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Effects of cAMP simulate a late stage of LTP in hippocampal CA1 neurons</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>260</volume>:<fpage>1661</fpage>–<lpage>1664</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schroeder</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthies</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Dopaminergic antagonists prevent long-term maintenance of posttetanic LTP in the CA1 region of rat hippocampal slices</article-title>. <source>Brain Research</source> <volume>522</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fuchsberger</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clopath</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jarzebowski</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brzosko</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulsen</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Postsynaptic burst reactivation of hippocampal neurons enables associative plasticity of temporally discontiguous inputs</article-title>. <source>Elife</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e81071</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Granger</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cerpas</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicoll</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>LTP requires a reserve pool of glutamate receptors independent of subunit type</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>493</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fink</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarinaña</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vissel</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Dell</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Long-term potentiation in the hippocampal CA1 region does not require insertion and activation of GluR2-lacking AMPA receptors</article-title>. <source>J. Neurophysiol</source>. <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>2488</fpage>–<lpage>2492</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Guire</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oh</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soderling</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Derkach</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Recruitment of calcium-permeable AMPA receptors during synaptic potentiation is regulated by CaM-kinase I</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>6000</fpage>–<lpage>6009</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hazzalin</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le Panse</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cano</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahadevan</surname> <given-names>LC</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Anisomycin selectively desensitizes signalling components involved in stress kinase activation and fos and jun induction</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>. <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1844</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hoffman</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sprengel</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sakmann</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular dissection of hippocampal theta-burst pairing potentiation</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source> <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>7740</fpage>–<lpage>7745</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>YY</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>D1/D5 receptor agonists induce a protein synthesis-dependent late potentiation in the CA1 region of the hippocampus</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source> <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>2446</fpage>–<lpage>2450</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huber</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kayser</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bear</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Role for rapid dendritic protein synthesis in hippocampal mGluR-dependent long-term depression</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>288</volume>:<fpage>1254</fpage>–<lpage>1257</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huganir</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Nicoll</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>AMPARs and synaptic plasticity: the last 25 years</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>704</fpage>–<lpage>717</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kahn</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sommer</surname> <given-names>IE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murray</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meyer-Lindenberg</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinberger</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cannon</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Donovan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Correll</surname> <given-names>CU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kane</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Os</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Insel</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source>. <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>15067</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kebabian</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Calne</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Multiple receptors for dopamine</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>277</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kyriakis</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banerjee</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nikolakaki</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dai</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rubie</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmad</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Avruch</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodgett</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The stress-activated protein kinase subfamily of c-Jun kinases</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>369</volume>:<fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Matthies</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Becker</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schröeder</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kraus</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Höllt</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krug</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Dopamine D1-deficient mutant mice do not express the late phase of hippocampal long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Neuroreport</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>3533</fpage>–<lpage>3535</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mayr</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Montminy</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional regulation by the phosphorylation-dependent factor CREB</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>. <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nobili</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Latagliata</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Viscomi</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cavallucci</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cutuli</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giacovazzo</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krashia</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rizzo</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marino</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Federici</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Bartolo</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aversa</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dell’Acqua</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cordella</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sancandi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keller</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petrosini</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Puglisi-Allegra</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mercuri</surname> <given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coccurello</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berretta</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Amelio</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Dopamine neuronal loss contributes to memory and reward dysfunction in a model of Alzheimer’s disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <volume>8</volume>:<issue>14727</issue>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>O’Carroll</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frenguelli</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Dopaminergic modulation of the persistence of one-trial hippocampus-dependent memory</article-title>. <source>Learn Mem</source>. <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>760</fpage>–<lpage>769</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Otmakhova</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><surname>Lisman</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>D1/D5 dopamine receptors inhibit depotentiation at CA1 synapses via cAMP-dependent mechanism</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci</source>. <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1270</fpage>–<lpage>1279</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Georgiou</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanderson</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ko</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bradley</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bortolotto</surname> <given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhuo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaang</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collingridge</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>PKA drives an increase in AMPA receptor unitary conductance during LTP in the hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanderson</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bortolotto</surname> <given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Georgiou</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhuo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaang</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collingridge</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>On the Role of Calcium-Permeable AMPARs in Long-Term Potentiation and Synaptic Tagging in the Rodent Hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Front Synaptic Neurosci</source>. <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Plant</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pelkey</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bortolotto</surname> <given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morita</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Terashima</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McBain</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collingridge</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Isaac</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transient incorporation of native GluR2-lacking AMPA receptors during hippocampal long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>604</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Poewe</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seppi</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanner</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halliday</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brundin</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Volkmann</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schrag</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lang</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Parkinson disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>17013</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Purkey</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dell’Acqua</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Phosphorylation-Dependent Regulation of Ca2+-Permeable AMPA Receptors During Hippocampal Synaptic Plasticity</article-title>. <source>Front Synaptic Neurosci</source>. <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Romberg</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raffel</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sprengel</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seeburg</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rawlins</surname> <given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bannerman</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulsen</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Induction and expression of GluA1 (GluR-A)-independent LTP in the hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Eur J Neurosci</source>. <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1141</fpage>–<lpage>1152</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rossato</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bevilaqua</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Izquierdo</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Medina</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cammarota</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dopamine controls persistence of long-term memory storage</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>325</volume>:<fpage>1017</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Transcription factors responsive to cAMP</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The cyclic AMP pathway</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>a011148</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clavarino</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ceppi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pierre</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>SUnSET, a nonradioactive method to monitor protein synthesis</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shohamy</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Adcock</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Dopamine and adaptive memory</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn Sci</source>. <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>464</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Starck</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schuman</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Dopaminergic stimulation of local protein synthesis enhances surface expression of GluR1 and synaptic transmission in hippocampal neurons</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stockwell</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watson</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greger</surname> <given-names>IH</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2024</year>) <article-title>Tuning synaptic strength by regulation of AMPA glutamate receptor localization</article-title>. <source>Bioessays</source>. <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>e2400006</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Takeuchi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duszkiewicz</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sonneborn</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spooner</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamasaki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernández</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deisseroth</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greene</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Locus coeruleus and dopaminergic consolidation of everyday memory</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>537</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pineda</surname> <given-names>VV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muglia</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Storm</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Type 8 adenylyl cyclase is targeted to excitatory synapses and required for mossy fiber long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>9710</fpage>– <lpage>9718</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wenthold</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petralia</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blahos J</surname> <given-names>II</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niedzielski</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Evidence for multiple AMPA receptor complexes in hippocampal CA1/CA2 neurons</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1982</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ivica</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krieger</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamashita</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stockwell</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baradaran</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cais</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greger</surname> <given-names>IH</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2023</year>) <article-title>Structural mobility tunes signalling of the GluA1 AMPA glutamate receptor</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>621</volume>: <fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>882</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zamanillo</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sprengel</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hvalby</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burnashev</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rozov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaiser</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Köster</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borchardt</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Worley</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lübke</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frotscher</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sommer</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andersen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seeburg</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sakmann</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Importance of AMPA receptors for hippocampal synaptic plasticity but not for spatial learning</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>284</volume>:<fpage>1805</fpage>–<lpage>1811</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<sec>
<fig id="figs1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 1S.</label>
<caption><p>SUnSET assay is specific to protein synthesis and protein synthesis inhibitors do not affect baseline synaptic transmission within 60 minutes of recording. (<bold>A, C</bold>), Representative images of the CA1 region of the hippocampus (SP: stratum pyramidale, SR: stratum radiatum) of puromycin-labelled proteins (PMY, red) and Dapi (blue). Puromycin incorporation is significantly reduced in the presence of the protein synthesis inhibitors (<bold>A</bold>) cycloheximide (CHX) or (<bold>C</bold>) anisomycin (AM). Scale bar, 80 µm (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold>), Summary of results. t-test, *, p &lt; 0.05 (<bold>E</bold>), Dopamine application alone, without prior pairing, does not affect synaptic weights in control pathway (green trace). (<bold>F</bold>), Postsynaptically applied anisomycin (AM) (red trace) or cycloheximide (CHX) (blue trace) does not affect synaptic weights throughout recording. Traces show an EPSP before (1) and 40 minutes after (2) pairing. Plots show averages of normalised EPSP slopes ± SEM. (G), Summary of results. <italic>t</italic>-test, ns, not significant.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="600624v1_figs1.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs4" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 4S.</label>
<caption><p>CP-AMPARs blocker IEM-1460 confirms that CP-AMPARs are required for DA-LTP but not for conventional t-LTP. (<bold>A</bold>), A t-LTP pairing protocol (Δt = +10 ms) induces synaptic potentiation in the presence of extracellularly applied IEM-1460. (<bold>B, C</bold>), IEM-1460 blocks DA-LTP, whether applied throughout (<bold>B</bold>) or after the pairing protocol (<bold>C</bold>). (<bold>D</bold>), Summary of results. <italic>t</italic>-test, *, p &lt; 0.05. Traces show an EPSP before (1) and 40 minutes after pairing (2). Plots show averages of normalised EPSP slopes ± SEM.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="600624v1_figs4.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</back>
<sub-article id="sa0" article-type="editor-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.100822.1.sa3</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>eLife Assessment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lourenco</surname>
<given-names>Mychael V</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Federal University of Rio de Janeiro</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Rio de Janeiro</city>
<country>Brazil</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="evidence-strength">
<kwd>Convincing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="claim-importance">
<kwd>Valuable</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>This manuscript addresses a mechanism by which dopamine (DA) regulates synaptic plasticity. The authors build upon their previous finding that DA applied after a timing pattern that ordinarily induces long-term depression (LTD) now induces long-term potentiation (LTP). The new findings that this &quot;DA-dependent LTP&quot; involves de novo protein synthesis, a cyclicAMP signalling pathway, and calcium-permeable AMPA receptors (CP-AMPARs) are of <bold>valuable</bold> significance. The conclusions are <bold>convincing</bold> and largely supported by the evidence provided.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa1" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.100822.1.sa2</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #1 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>In this manuscript, Fuchsberger et al. demonstrate a set of experiments that ultimately identifies the de novo synthesis of GluA1-, but not GluA2-containing Ca2+ permeable AMPA receptors as a key driver of dopamine-dependent LTP (DA-LTP) during conventional post-before-pre spike-timing dependent (t-LTD) induction. The authors further identify adenylate cyclase 1/8, cAMP, and PKA as the crucial mitigators of these actions. While some comments have been identified below, the experiments presented are thorough and address the aims of the manuscript, figures are presented clearly (with minor comments), and experimental sample sizes and statistical analyses are suitable. Suitable controls have been utilized to confirm the role of Ca2+ permeable AMPAR. This work provides a valuable step forward built on convincing data toward understanding the underlying mechanisms of spike-timing-dependent plasticity and dopamine.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>Appropriate controls were used.</p>
<p>The flow of data presented is logical and easy to follow.</p>
<p>The quality of the data, except for a few minor issues, is solid.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>The drug treatment duration of anisomycin is longer than the standard 30-45 minute duration (as is the 500uM vs 40uM concentration) typically used in the field. Given the toxicity of these kinds of drugs long term it's unclear why the authors used such a long and intense drug treatment.</p>
<p>With some of the normalizations (such as those in S1) there are dramatic differences in the baseline &quot;untreated&quot; puromycin intensities - raising some questions about the overall health of slices used in the experiments.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa2" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.100822.1.sa1</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #2 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>The aim was to identify the mechanisms that underlie a form of long-term potentiation (LTP) that requires the activation of dopamine (DA).</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>The authors have provided multiple lines of evidence that support their conclusions; namely that this pathway involves the activation of a cAMP / PKA pathway that leads to the insertion of calcium-permeable AMPA receptors.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>Some of the experiments could have been conducted in a more convincing manner.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa3" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.100822.1.sa0</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #3 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>The manuscript of Fuchsberger et al. investigates the cellular mechanisms underlying dopamine-dependent long-term potentiation (DA-LTP) in mouse hippocampal CA1 neurons. The authors conducted a series of experiments to measure the effect of dopamine on the protein synthesis rate in hippocampal neurons and its role in enabling DA-LTP. The key results indicate that protein synthesis is increased in response to dopamine and neuronal activity in the pyramidal neurons of the CA1 hippocampal area, mediated via the activation of adenylate cyclases subtypes 1 and 8 (AC1/8) and the cAMP-dependent protein kinase (PKA) pathway. Additionally, the authors show that postsynaptic DA-induced increases in protein synthesis are required to express DA-LTP, while not required for conventional t-LTP.</p>
<p>The increased expression of the newly synthesized GluA1 receptor subunit in response to DA supports the formation of homomeric calcium-permeable AMPA receptors (CP-AMPARs). This evidence aligns well with data showing that DA-LTP expression requires the GluA1 AMPA subunit and CP-AMPARs, as DA-LTP is absent in the hippocampus of a GluA1 genetic knock-out mouse model. Overall, the study is solid, and the evidence provided is compelling. The authors clearly and concisely explain the research objectives, methodologies, and findings. The study is scientifically robust, and the writing is engaging. The authors' conclusions and interpretation of the results are insightful and align well with the literature. The discussion effectively places the findings in a meaningful context, highlighting a possible mechanism for dopamine's role in the modulation of protein-synthesis-dependent hippocampal synaptic plasticity and its implications for the field. Although the study expands on previous works from the same laboratory, the findings are novel and provide valuable insights into the dynamics governing hippocampal synaptic plasticity.</p>
<p>The claim that GluA1 homomeric CP-AMPA receptors mediate the expression of DA-LTP is fascinating, and although the electrophysiology data on GluA1 knock-out mice are convincing, more evidence is needed to support this hypothesis. Western blotting provides useful information on the expression level of GluA1, which is not necessarily associated with cell surface expression of GluA1 and therefore CP-AMPARs. Validating this hypothesis by localizing the protein using immunofluorescence and confocal microscopy detection could strengthen the claim. The authors should briefly discuss the limitations of the study.</p>
<p>Additional comments to address:</p>
<p>(1) In Figure 2A, the representative image with PMY alone shows a very weak PMY signal. Consequently, the image with TTX alone seems to potentiate the PMY signal, suggesting a counterintuitive increase in protein synthesis.</p>
<p>(2) In Figures 3A-B, the Western blotting representative images have poor quality, especially regarding GluA1 and α-actin in Figure 3A. The quantification graph (Figure 3B) raises some concerns about a potential outlier in both the DA alone and DA+CHX groups. The authors should consider running a statistical test to detect outlier data. Full blot images, including ladder lines, should be added to the supplementary data.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
</article>