<?xml version="1.0" ?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.3 20210610//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>eLife</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">93423</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.93423</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi" specific-use="version">10.7554/eLife.93423.1</article-id>
<article-version-alternatives>
<article-version article-version-type="publication-state">reviewed preprint</article-version>
<article-version article-version-type="preprint-version">1.1</article-version>
</article-version-alternatives>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Microbiology and Infectious Disease</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title><italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 alleviates <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium-induced colitis by improving intestinal barrier integrity and reducing inflammation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Linkang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Haiyan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Xinxin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Mengyuan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Dongyang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Dayue</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xiong</surname>
<given-names>Zhixuan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Xiangmin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2">#</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Qian</surname>
<given-names>Ping</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>National Key Laboratory of Agricultural Microbiology, Hubei Hongshan Laboratory, Huazhong Agricultural University</institution>, Wuhan, Hubei, 430070, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
<aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>College of Veterinary Medicine, Huazhong Agricultural University</institution>, Wuhan, Hubei, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
<aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Key Laboratory of Preventive Veterinary Medicine in Hubei Province, the Cooperative Innovation Center for Sustainable Pig Production</institution>, Wuhan, Hubei, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="section">
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kana</surname>
<given-names>Bavesh D</given-names>
</name>
<role>Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of the Witwatersrand</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Johannesburg</city>
<country>South Africa</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="senior_editor">
<name>
<surname>Kana</surname>
<given-names>Bavesh D</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of the Witwatersrand</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Johannesburg</city>
<country>South Africa</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: Ping Qian: Tel: 86-27-87282608; Fax: 86-27-87282608; E-mail: <email>qianp@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email>. Address: No. 1, Shizishan Street, Hongshan District, Wuhan City, Hubei Province, China.</corresp>
<corresp id="cor2"><label>#</label>Co-corresponding author: Xiang-min Li: Tel: 86-27-87282608; Fax: 86-27-87282608; E-mail: <email>lixiangmin@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email>. Address: No. 1, Shizishan Street, Hongshan District, Wuhan City, Hubei Province, China.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date date-type="original-publication" iso-8601-date="2024-03-12">
<day>12</day>
<month>03</month>
<year>2024</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<elocation-id>RP93423</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="sent-for-review" iso-8601-date="2023-11-21">
<day>21</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2023</year>
</date>
</history>
<pub-history>
<event>
<event-desc>Preprint posted</event-desc>
<date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2023-11-21">
<day>21</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2023</year>
</date>
<self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.11.21.568052"/>
</event>
</pub-history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2024, Wang et al</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Wang et al</copyright-holder>
<ali:free_to_read/>
<license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-preprint-93423-v1.pdf"/>
<abstract>
<title>Abstract</title><p><italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> is a novel species of Bacillus that has been widely investigated because of its broad-spectrum antimicrobial activity. However, most studies on <italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> have focused on biocontrol of plant diseases, with few reports on antagonizing <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium infections. In this study, <italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was isolated from healthy black piglets and was found to exhibit broad-spectrum antibacterial activity and robust anti-stress capabilities. Importantly, <italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 did not cause any adverse side effects in mice when administered at various doses (1 × 10<sup>7</sup>, 1 × 10<sup>8</sup>, and 1 × 10<sup>9</sup> CFU) for 14 days. In a <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium ATCC14028-induced mice colitis model, either curative or prophylactic, supplementing <italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores significantly lowered the levels of <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium ATCC14028 in their feces, ileum, cecum, and colon, and the disease activity index (DAI). Importantly, supplementing <italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic>HBXN2020 spores significantly regulated cytokine levels (TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, and IL-10) and maintained the expression of tight junction proteins and mucin protein. More importantly, supplementing <italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores also significantly enhanced the homeostasis of colonic microbiota and the abundance of beneficial bacteria. Collectively, <italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 can alleviate bacterial colitis by enhancing intestinal homeostasis and gut barrier integrity and reducing inflammation.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<title>Key words</title>
<kwd><italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic></kwd>
<kwd>antibacterial activity</kwd>
<kwd><italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced colitis</kwd>
<kwd>infections</kwd>
<kwd>gut health</kwd>
</kwd-group>

</article-meta>
<notes>
<notes notes-type="competing-interest-statement">
<title>Competing Interest Statement</title><p>The authors have declared no competing interest.</p></notes>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p><italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium (<italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium) is a major foodborne zoonotic pathogen that can cause diarrhea and colitis in humans and animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>). It has been reported that <italic>Salmonella</italic> infections often occur in both developing and developed countries, which poses a substantial risk to public health and causes huge economic loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">4</xref>). At present, antibiotic therapies is one of the most effective strategies for <italic>Salmonella</italic> infections. However, numerous studies have reported that the prolonged use or misuse of antibiotics can lead to environmental pollution, an increase in multi-drug-resistant (MDR) bacteria, as well as gastrointestinal microbiota dysbiosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c7">7</xref>). Therefore, there is an emergent search for novel antimicrobial agents to combat <italic>Salmonella</italic> infections.</p>
<p>Recently, an increasing number of studies have shown that gut microbiota plays an important role in alleviating intestinal inflammation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref>) and repairing the intestinal barrier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c10">10</xref>). The use of probiotics is a popular approach to modulate intestinal microbiota nowadays. Among all probiotics, Bacillus is one of the most popular probiotic species because of their ability to form endospores that survive gastric transit, storage and delivery conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">11</xref>). In addition, Bacillus species can also produce antimicrobial metabolites against enteric pathogens and provide extracellular enzymes, thereby reducing infection risk and improving nutrient utilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>).</p>
<p><italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> (<italic>B. velezensis</italic>), a newly discovered species of the <italic>Bacillus</italic> genus, can produce an abundance of secondary metabolites with broad-spectrum antibacterial activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c14">14</xref>). Previous studies have reported that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> exhibits varying degrees of probiotic effects on plants, livestock, poultry and fish. For instance, the combined use of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> SQR9 mutant and FZB42 improved root colonization and the production of secondary metabolites that are beneficial to cucumber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c15">15</xref>). <italic>B. velezensis</italic> isolated from yaks was shown to enhance growth performance and ameliorate blood parameters related to inflammation and immunity in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">16</xref>). The dietary <italic>B. velezensis</italic> supplementation can regulate the innate immune response in the intestine of crucian carp and reduce the degree of intestinal inflammation damage induce by <italic>A. veronii</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">17</xref>). However, most studies on <italic>B. velezensis</italic> were mainly biocontrol of plant fungal diseases, with few reports on the treatment or prevention of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced colitis.</p>
<p>In this study, we have screened a strain of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 with broad-spectrum antibacterial activity from a large number of <italic>Bacillus</italic> strains. We aimed to investigate the effectiveness of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 in alleviating <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced mouse colitis and assessed the biological safety of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020. Notably, <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 can alleviate symptoms and colon tissue damage in experimental colitis, as indicated by markers such as <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium loads, TNF-α and ZO-1 levels. Moreover, <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was also enhanced the homeostasis of colonic microbiota and the abundance of beneficial bacteria (<italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Akkermansia</italic>). Therefore, this study provides support for the development of probiotic-based microbial products as an alternative prevention strategy for <italic>Salmonella</italic> infection.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Genomic Characteristics</title>
<p>The Illumina Hiseq and PacBio platforms were used to perform whole genome sequencing of HBXN2020, yielding a total of 8,194,986 Illumina clean reads (1,237,442,886 bases) and 225,593 PacBio reads (1,807,288,759 bases). Following a quality assessment via k-mer and a GC-depth analysis, the whole genome was assembled <italic>de novo</italic> using Unicycler (Version 0.4.8). The results showed that HBXN2020 has a circular chromosome of 3,929,792 bp (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>) with a GC content of 46.5%. The genome of HBXN2020 was predicted to contain 3,857 genes, including 3,744 protein-coding genes (CDS), 86 tRNA genes, and 27 rRNA genes (Table S1).</p>
<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 1</label>
<caption><title>Genomic characteristics and phylogenetic relationships of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) The whole-genome map of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 with its genomic features. The map consists of 6 circles. From the inner circle to the outer circle: (1) GC-skew, (2) GC content, (3) reverse protein-coding genes, different colors represents different COG functional classifications, (4) genes transcribed in reverse direction, (5) genes transcribed in forward direction, (6) forward protein-coding genes, different colors represents different COG functional classifications. (<bold>B</bold>) The whole genome phylogenetic tree was constructed based on genome-wide data from 14 bacillus strains. <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 are indicated in bold. (<bold>C</bold>) The heatmap based on the ANIb value of strain HBXN2020 and other Bacillus species. The <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was labeled in red letters.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig1.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>A phylogenetic tree based on genome-wide data from all 14 Bacillus strains demonstrated that the HBXN2020 belongs to the <italic>B. velezensis</italic> species (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>). To further understand the classification status of HBXN2020, the online tool JSpeciesWS was used to calculate the average nucleotide identity (ANI) based on the BLAST (ANIb) method. As shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref>, HBXN2020 was found to be a member of the <italic>B. velezensis</italic> species due to the high percentage of ANIb (more than 97%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2b">
<title>Growth curve of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 and its <italic>in vitro</italic> resistance against environmental assaults</title>
<p>The growth of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was assessed in flat-bottomed 100-well microtiter plates by measuring the values of OD<sub>600</sub> every hour using an automatic growth curve analyzer. The OD<sub>600</sub> value of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 showed slight fluctuations within the first 2 h, followed by a logarithmic growth phase that reached a stable phase after 10 h (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). Despite environmental restrictions such as limited space and nutrients, the OD<sub>600</sub> value of the bacteria was not significantly reduced even after 22 h, indicating that the growth of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was relatively stable.</p>
<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 2</label>
<caption><title>Growth curve of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 and its <italic>in vitro</italic> resistance against environmental assaults.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Growth curves of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 cultured in LB medium at 37°C, detection of OD<sub>600</sub> values at 1 h intervals in microplate reader. (<bold>B</bold>) Survival rate of endospore and vegetative cells of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 after 30 min at different temperatures (37°C, 45°C, 55°C, 65°C, 75°C, 85°C or 95°C). Equal amounts of endospore and vegetative cells of HBXN2020 were exposed to the following: (<bold>C</bold>) acid solution (pH 2 to 7), (<bold>D</bold>) 0.3% bile salts, (<bold>E</bold>) SGF (pH 1.2) supplemented with pepsin, and (<bold>F</bold>) SIF (pH 6.8) containing trypsin at 37°C. At predetermined time points, 100 μL was taken from each sample, and tenfold serially diluted with sterile PBS (pH 7.2), and then spread on LB agar plates and cultured at 37°C for 12 h before bacterial counting. Each group was repeated three times (n = 3).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig2.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>Next, we evaluated the effect of physical, chemical, and biological sterilization conditions such as high temperature, strong acidity, and enzyme preparation on the survival of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020. The survival rate of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 showed a decreasing trend with increasing temperature. At 65°C, the survival rate of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was less than 1%, while the spores of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 exceeded 90% (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>). The survival rate of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores was also above 80% even under high-temperature conditions (95°C). Similar results were observed following exposure to a strong acid environment (pH 2.0) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref>), whereby <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores were found to effectively tolerate strong acidic conditions and exhibited improved survival rate. Based on these results, we hypothesized that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores might also exhibit improved survival in gastrointestinal tract environments. Therefore, we further evaluated the survival rate of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 in bile salt (0.3%, v/v), simulated gastric fluid (pepsin 1 mg mL<sup>-1</sup>, pH 1.2), and simulated intestinal fluid (trypsin 1 mg mL<sup>-1</sup>, pH 6.8). As shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2D-F</xref>, <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores demonstrated significantly improved tolerance to these simulated gastrointestinal tract environments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2c">
<title>Antibiotic susceptibility of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 and bacteriostasis effect <italic>in vitro</italic></title>
<p>To evaluate the drug resistance of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020, 19 commonly used antibiotics in clinical practice were selected. The results indicated that only polymyxin B had a relatively small inhibition zone diameter (less than 15 mm). Ampicillin, meropenem, minocycline, ofloxacin, and trimethoprim had the strongest inhibition on <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020, with an inhibition zone diameter exceeding 30 mm (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). In addition, the experimental results showed that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was extremely sensitive to β-lactams, tetracyclines, and quinolone drugs. Then, we performed an inhibition test of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 against seven common clinical pathogenic bacteria. The results showed that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 had a similar inhibitory effect on standard and wild strains of <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>Salmonella</italic>, <italic>S. aureus</italic>, and <italic>C. perfringens</italic>, as well as wild strains of <italic>S. suis</italic>, <italic>P. multocida</italic>, and <italic>A. pleuropneumoniae</italic>. Except for the wild strains of <italic>S. suis</italic> and <italic>A. pleuropneumoniae</italic>, the diameter of the inhibition zone of other strains was above 15 mm (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>, S3), while the size of the inhibition zone of <italic>S. suis</italic> and <italic>A. pleuropneumoniae</italic> was also more than 12 mm.</p>
<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 3</label>
<caption><title>Antibiotic susceptibility of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 and bacteriostasis assay <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) The diameter of the antibacterial zone indicates the extent of sensitivity to antibiotics. (<bold>B</bold>) The diameter of the antibacterial zone indicates the extent of inhibition against pathogenic bacteria. The diameter of the antibacterial zone was measured with vernier caliper. Each group was repeated three times (n = 3). R, resistant; I, moderately sensitive; S, sensitive.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig3.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2d">
<title>Biosafety evaluation of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020</title>
<p>To determine the safety of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020, we evaluated its biological safety in a mouse model. After gavage with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores for two weeks, we observed no significant difference in the body weight of each group of mice (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>). The gene expression levels of TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, and IL-10 of colon from all groups of mice exhibited no remarkable changes (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>). However, in the colon, mRNA levels of the barrier proteins ZO-1 and occludin were trending towards an increase compared with the control group (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4C</xref>). Additionally, blood routine tests and serum biochemistry tests were performed for mice in the control group and H-HBXN2020 group on the 14<sup>th</sup> day after oral administration of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores multiple times. As shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D</xref> and S1, the blood parameters of mice after <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 treatment, including red blood cells (RBC), mean corpuscular volume (MCV), mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH), hemoglobin (HGB), white blood cells (WBC), platelets (PLT), hematocrit (HCT), and mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC), were consistent with those of healthy mice. The serum biochemical parameters, including alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), albumin (ALB), total bilirubin (TBIL), serum creatinine (CREA), and blood urea nitrogen (BUN), were also within normal limits (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4E</xref>). The corresponding histological analysis of colon tissue from mice receiving low, medium, and high doses of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores (L-HBXN2020, M-HBXN2020, and H-HBXN2020 groups, respectively) is presented in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4F</xref>. The colon tissue sections of mice in the test groups showed no significant differences compared to the control group. Additionally, there were no observable differences in the major organ tissues (heart, liver, spleen, lung, and kidney) of mice treated with the high dose of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores compared to healthy mice (Fig. S2). Collectively, these experimental results indicate that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 is safe for use and does not cause any adverse side effects in mice.</p>
<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 4</label>
<caption><title><italic>In vivo</italic> safety evaluation of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 in a mouse model.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Body weights changes of mice during gavage with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores. Mice were treated with sterile PBS (Control group) or low-dose (L-HBXN2020 group), medium dose (M-HBXN2020 group), and high-dose (H-HBXN2020 group) of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores. Weighing and gavage were performed once every two days during the experimental period (15 days). Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 5). (<bold>B</bold>) The relative gene expression levels of inflammatory cytokines in the colon of mice measured by RT-qPCR. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 5). (<bold>C</bold>) The relative gene expression levels of barrier protein ZO-1, occludin, claudin and Muc2 in the colon of mice measured by RT-qPCR. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 5). (<bold>D</bold>) Major blood routine parameters and (<bold>E</bold>) serum biochemical parameters of mice in the control group and H-HBXN2020 group. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 3). (<bold>F</bold>) H&amp;E stained colon sections in the different groups. Scale bar: 200 μm.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig4.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2e">
<title>Oral administration of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores alleviated <italic>S</italic>. Typhimurium-induced colitis</title>
<p>To investigate whether <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 could inhibit <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium ATCC14028 (STm), solid and liquid co-culture tests were conducted, and the results showed that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 inhibited the growth of STm in a dose-dependent manner (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>, S4A-B, S4D). Next, the therapeutic potential of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was evaluated in an STm-induced mouse colitis model. At days 1, 3, and 5 after STm infection, mice in the STm + HBXN2020 group were orally administered <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores by gavage (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5B</xref>), while the control group and STm + PBS group were treated with sterile PBS. Also, the number of excreted STm in feces was counted daily at the designated time points. As shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5C</xref>, there was a significant and continuous reduction in the number of STm in feces following treatment with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores, while the number of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 viable bacteria in feces is also gradually decreasing (Fig. S5A). The number of STm in mouse feces was reduced by 10 to 50 times compared to the STm + PBS group from day 2 to 7 post-treatment. <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spore treatment also resulted in a 5 to 10-fold reduction in the number of STm in the ileum, cecum, and colon, respectively (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5D-E</xref>, S5B). The increased inhibition of STm after <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spore treatment also resulted in less weight loss and a marked reduction (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) in DAI scores in STm + HBXN2020 group mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5F-G</xref>). In addition, we also measured the colon length of the mice and found that the STm + PBS group had a significantly shorter colon length (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) than the control group. However, compared to the STm + PBS group, the STm + HBXN2020 group exhibited a longer colon (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5H-I</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 5</label>
<caption><title>Oral <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores alleviated <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced experimental mouse colitis.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) <italic>In vitro</italic> Bacterial competition between STm and <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020. STm were co-incubated with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 at various ratios at 37°C with shaking. The growth of STm was reflected by bacterial counting per hour. (<bold>B</bold>) Experimental design for treatment in this study. Orally administrated with either PBS, or <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores by gavage at days 1, 3, and 5 after STm infection (5× 10<sup>7</sup> CFU/mouse), respectively. All mice were euthanized at day 7 after STm infection. (<bold>C</bold>) Bacterial count of STm in mouse feces. Fecal samples were collected per day after STm infection and resuspended in sterile PBS (0.1 g of fecal resuspended in 1 mL of sterile PBS). One hundred microliters of each sample performed a serial of 10-fold dilutions and spread on selective agar plates (50 µg mL<sup>-1</sup> kanamycin) and incubated at 37°C for 12 h before bacterial counting. The bacterial loads of STm in (<bold>D</bold>) cecum, and (<bold>E</bold>) colon. The cecum and colon were harvested and then homogenized. One hundred microliters of each sample performed a serial of 10-fold dilutions and spread on selective agar plates (50 µg mL<sup>-1</sup> kanamycin) and incubated at 37°C for 12 h before bacterial counting. Statistical signifcance was evaluated using Student’s t-test (*, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). (<bold>F</bold>) Daily body weight changes and (<bold>G</bold>) daily disease activity index (DAI) scores of mice with different treatment groups. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 8). Statistical signifcance was evaluated using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test. *, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 relative to Control group; <sup>#</sup>, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <sup>##</sup>, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <sup>###</sup>, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 relative to STm + HBXN2020 group. (<bold>H</bold>) Colonic tissue images. (<bold>I</bold>) The length of the colon from per group (n = 8). Statistical signifcance was evaluated using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test (*, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig5.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>To further assess the impact of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 on the intestinal tract, we histologically analyzed their colonic tissues. The results showed that mice treated with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores exhibited a lower histology score (total scoring) (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (Fig. S5C) than mice not treated with the spores and were similar to that of healthy mice (control group). The colon tissue of mice not treated with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores displayed higher histological scores, with significant crypt deformation, severe mucosal damage, and obvious inflammatory cell infiltration. These findings suggest that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 can alleviate colon tissue damage. Moreover, we measured the mRNA levels of inflammatory cytokines, including tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), interleukin-1 β (IL-1 β), interleukin-6 (IL-6), and interleukin-10 (IL-10) in colon tissue using RT-qPCR analysis. As shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6B-D</xref>, the mRNA levels of TNF-α (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), IL-1β (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and IL-6 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the colon tissue of STm-infected mice were significantly upregulated, indicating the successful establishment of the STm-induced colitis model. As expected, treatment with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores led to a significant reduction in the mRNA levels of these pro-inflammatory cytokines, while the mRNA levels of the anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 were significantly increased (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6E</xref>), suggesting that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores can alleviate the inflammatory reaction of the colon. Moreover, the mRNA expression levels of colonic epithelial barrier proteins, including ZO-1, ocludin, claudin, and Muc2, were also measured by RT-qPCR. Compared with the PBS-treated group, the <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores treatment group exhibited significantly upregulated mRNA expression levels of ZO-1 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), occludin (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), claudin (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and Muc2 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) in the colon tissue (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6F-I</xref>), further demonstrating the ability of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 to reduce damage to the colon epithelial barrier.</p>
<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 6</label>
<caption><title>Oral <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores attenuated colonic damage and inflammatory reaction.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) H&amp;E stained colon tissue sections. Scale bar: 200 μm. The relative gene expression levels of TNF-α (<bold>B</bold>), IL-1β (<bold>C</bold>), IL-6 (<bold>D</bold>), and IL-10 (<bold>E</bold>) were detected by RT-qPCR. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 6). The relative gene expression levels of ZO-1 (<bold>F</bold>), ocludin (<bold>G</bold>), claudin (<bold>H</bold>), and Muc2 (<bold>I</bold>) in colon tissue were detected by RT-qPCR. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 6). Statistical signifcance was evaluated using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test (*, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig6.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>Next, we further explored the effect of HBXN2020 spores on the intestinal microbiota composition of STm-treated mice via 16S rRNA gene sequencing. The alpha diversity of colonic microbiota was evaluated using Sobs, Chao1, Shannon, and Simpson indices (OTU levels). Compared with the control and HBXN2020 group, the Sobs, Chao1, and Shannon indices of the STm + PBS group clearly decreased (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7A-C</xref>), while the Simpson index significantly increased (P &lt; 0.05, <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7D</xref>). Principle component analysis (PCA) based on Bray–Curtis distance showed that compared with the STm + PBS group, the gut microbiota composition of the STm + HBXN2020 group and the control group were more closer together (R= 0.3988, P = 0.001, <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7E</xref>). We analyzed the significance of differences among groups at different classification levels (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7F-G</xref>), and the results revealed that the composition of the gut microbiota changed markedly after STm-induced mice. At the phylum level, the STm + PBS group increased the abundance of <italic>Verrucomicrobiota</italic> and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> and decreased the abundance of <italic>Firmicutes</italic>, <italic>Patescibacteria</italic>, <italic>Desulfobacterota</italic>, and <italic>Actinobacteriota</italic> compared to the Control group (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7F</xref>). The HBXN2020 group increased the abundance of <italic>Bacteroidota</italic> and <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and decreased the abundance of <italic>Verrucomicrobiota</italic> compared with the Control group. On the contrary, the relative abundance of <italic>Firmicutes</italic>, <italic>Patescibacteria</italic>, <italic>Desulfobacterota</italic>, and <italic>Actinobacteriota</italic> in the STm + HBXN2020 group was significantly higher than that in the STm + PBS group. At the genus level, infection with <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium ATCC14028 in the STm + PBS group dramatically reduced the relative abundance of <italic>norank_f_Muribaculaceae</italic> and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7H-I</xref>) and enhanced the abundance of <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Escherichia-Shigella</italic>, <italic>Salmonella</italic>, <italic>Alistipes</italic>, and <italic>Enterococcus</italic> compared to the Control group (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7J-K</xref>, S6B). The HBXN2020 group increased the abundance of <italic>norank_f_Muribaculaceae</italic> and <italic>Alloprevotella</italic> compared to the Control group. In contrast, STm + HBXN2020 group significantly improved the relative abundance of <italic>norank_f_Muribaculaceae</italic> and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> compared with the STm + PBS group (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7H-I</xref>). In addition, LEfSe analysis was also performed to identify specialized microbial communities between the STm + HBXN2020 group and the STm + PBS group, and found that there was a clear difference in gut microbiota composition between them. The microbiota that played a major role in the STm + PBS group were harmful <italic>Enterobacterales</italic> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7L</xref>), while the STm + HBXN2020 group was <italic>Candidatus_Saccharimonas</italic> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7L</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 7</label>
<caption><title>Oral <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores regulated the composition of intestinal microbiota.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold> to <bold>D</bold>) The α-diversity of the gut microbiota, determined by the (<bold>A</bold>) Sobs, (<bold>B</bold>) Chao1, (<bold>C</bold>) Shannon, and (<bold>D</bold>) Simpson diversity index. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 5). (<bold>E</bold>) The PCA plot showed the β-diversity of the gut microbiota based on Bray-Curtis distance at the OTU level. (<bold>F</bold> and <bold>G</bold>) The relative abundance of colonic microbiota at the phylum (<bold>F</bold>) and genus (<bold>G</bold>) levels. (<bold>H-K</bold>) Relative abundance of selected taxa (<bold>H</bold>) <italic>norank_f_Muribaculaceae</italic>, (<bold>I</bold>) <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, (<bold>J</bold>) <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, and (<bold>K</bold>) <italic>Escherichia-Shigella</italic>. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 5). (<bold>L</bold>) Analysis of differences in the microbial communities by LEfSe (linear discriminant analysis (LDA) score &gt; 3.5) among different groups. Signifcance was evaluated by the Kruskal-Wallis test or ANOVA with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test (*, P &lt; 0.05, **, P &lt; 0.01, and ***, P &lt; 0.001).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig7.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2f">
<title>Prophylactic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores alleviated <italic>S</italic>. Typhimurium-induced colitis</title>
<p>Based on the improved therapeutic efficacy of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 in the treatment of STm-induced colitis in mice, we further explored its potential for disease prevention by evaluating pre-treatment. Mice in the PBS + STm group and HBXN2020 + STm group were given the same amount of sterile PBS and <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores by gavage one week in advance. As shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, compared with the PBS + STm group, oral administration of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores as a preventive measure remarkably alleviated STm-induced colitis, including weight loss of mice (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8B</xref>), a significant reduction in DAI (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (the comprehensive score of weight loss, stool consistency, and blood in the feces, <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8C</xref>), and the prevention of colon length shortening (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8D-E</xref>). However, the number of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 viable bacteria in feces is also gradually decreasing with the time prolonging (Fig. S7A). Furthermore, compared with the PBS + STm group, oral administration of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores not only reduced the number of STm in mouse feces (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8F</xref>) but also decreased STm colonization in the ileum, cecum, and colon (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8G-H</xref>, S7B).</p>
<fig id="fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 8</label>
<caption><title>Prophylactic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores attenuated the symptoms of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced mouse colitis.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental design for treatment in this study. At days 1, 3, 5, and 7, each mouse in the HBXN2020 + STm group and PBS + STm group were received 200 μL (1×10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mouse) of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores or sterile PBS by gavage. Then, mice in PBS + STm group and HBXN2020 + STm group were orally inoculated with 200 μL (5×10<sup>7</sup> CFU/mouse) of STm on day 7. On day 12, all mice were euthanized. (<bold>B</bold>) Daily body weight changes and (<bold>C</bold>) daily disease activity index (DAI) scores of mice with different groups following STm treatment. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 8). Statistical signifcance was evaluated using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test. *, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 relative to Control group; <sup>#</sup>, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <sup>##</sup>, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <sup>###</sup>, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 relative to HBXN2020 + STm group. (<bold>D</bold>) Colonic tissue images. (<bold>E</bold>) The length of the colon from per group (n = 8). (<bold>F</bold>) Bacterial count of STm in mouse feces. Fecal samples were collected every day after STm infection and resuspended in sterile PBS (0.1 g of fecal resuspended in 1 mL of sterile PBS). One hundred microliters of each sample performed a serial of 10-fold dilutions and spread on selective agar plates (50 µg mL<sup>-1</sup> kanamycin) and incubated at 37°C for 12 h before bacterial counting. The bacterial loads of STm in (<bold>G</bold>)cecum and (<bold>H</bold>)colon. The cecum and colon were harvested and then homogenized. One hundred microliters of each sample performed a serial of 10-fold dilutions and spread on selective agar plates (50 µg mL<sup>-1</sup> kanamycin) and incubated at 37°C for 12 h before bacterial counting. Statistical signifcance was evaluated using Student’s t-test (*, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig8.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>Histological analysis further revealed that oral administration of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 significantly reduced the infiltration of inflammatory cells, mucosal damage and the overall histological score of colon tissue (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9A</xref>, S7C). Additionally, the mRNA expression levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines, including TNF-α (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), IL-1β (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and IL-6 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), in the colon tissue of mice pretreated with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores were significantly decreased (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9B-D</xref>), while the mRNA levels of anti-inflammatory cytokine (IL-10) were significantly higher (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9E</xref>) than mice pretreated with PBS. In addition, compared to the group pretreated with PBS, the group pretreated with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores showed a significant increase in mRNA expression levels of ZO-1 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), ocludin (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and claudin (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the colon tissue of mice (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9F-H</xref>). While there was no significant difference in Muc2 expression (<italic>p</italic>=0.252) (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9I</xref>), the results were consistent with those of the therapeutic experiments. Overall, these findings suggest that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 can effectively alleviate the symptoms of STm-induced colitis and the associated damage to colon tissue.</p>
<fig id="fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 9</label>
<caption><title>Prophylactic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores attenuated colonic damage and inflammatory reaction.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) H&amp;E stained colon tissue sections. Scale bar: 200 μm. The relative gene expression levels of TNF-α (<bold>B</bold>), IL-1β (<bold>C</bold>), IL-6 (<bold>D</bold>), and IL-10 (<bold>E</bold>) were detected by RT-qPCR. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 6). The relative gene expression levels of ZO-1 (<bold>F</bold>), ocludin (<bold>G</bold>), claudin (<bold>H</bold>), and Muc2 (<bold>I</bold>) in colon tissue were detected by RT-qPCR. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 6). Statistical signifcance was evaluated using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test (*, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig9.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>Next, we examined the impact of prophylactic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 on the intestinal microbiota composition of STm-treated mice. Sobs, Chao1 index and Shannon index have changed to some extent between groups, but differences were not significant (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10A-C</xref>). Compared with the Control group, the Simpson index significantly decreased in the PBS+STm group (P &lt; 0.05, <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10D</xref>). However, compared to the PBS+STm group, Simpson index in the HBXN2020+STm group did not change (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10D</xref>). PCA analysis showed a significant separation between control and PBS+STm groups, while the HBXN2020+STm group, HBXN2020 group, and the control group were clustered together (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10E</xref>). Next, we analyzed microbial community composition at the phylum and genus levels (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10F-G</xref>). At the phylum level, the PBS + STm group increased the abundance of <italic>Bacteroidota</italic>, <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>, <italic>Actinobacteriota</italic>, and <italic>Deferribacterota</italic> and reduced the abundance of <italic>Verrucomicrobiota</italic>, <italic>Firmicutes</italic>, <italic>Patescibacteria</italic>, and <italic>Desulfobacterota</italic> compared with the Control group(<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10F</xref>, S8A). The HBXN2020 group increased the abundance of <italic>Bacteroidota</italic> compared to the control group. In contrast, compared to the PBS+STm group, the abundance of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> in the HBXN2020+STm group was significantly increased (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). At the genus level, a depletion of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Akkermansia</italic> (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10H-I</xref>) and an enrichment of <italic>Alistipes</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Escherichia-Shigella</italic>, <italic>Alloprevotella</italic>, <italic>Helicobacter</italic>, <italic>Enterococcus</italic>, and <italic>Salmonella</italic> were observed in PBS + STm group compared with the control (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10J-M</xref>, 8SB). The enrichment with <italic>norank_f_Muribaculaceae</italic> and <italic>Alloprevotella</italic> were observed in HBXN2020 group compared to the control. In contrast, an enrichment of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Akkermansia</italic>, and <italic>Lachnospiraceae_NK4A136_group</italic> and a sharp decrease of <italic>Alistipes</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Escherichia-Shigella</italic>, and <italic>Enterococcus</italic> were observed in HBXN2020 + STm group compared to the PBS + STm group. LEfSe analysis showed that the abundance of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> in the intestinal microbiota of mice was significantly increased after <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 treatment, while the abundance of harmful <italic>Enterobacterales</italic> in the untreated group was clearly increased (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10N</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 10</label>
<caption><title>Prophylactic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores regulated the composition of gut microbiota.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold> to <bold>D</bold>) Alpha diversity of the intestinal microbiota. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 5). (<bold>E</bold>) The PCA plot showed the β-diversity among different microbial community groups based on Bray-Curtis distance at the OTU level. (<bold>F</bold> and <bold>G</bold>) The relative abundance of colonic microbiota at the phylum (<bold>F</bold>) and genus (<bold>G</bold>) levels. (<bold>H-M</bold>) Relative abundance of selected taxa (<bold>H</bold>) <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, (<bold>I</bold>) <italic>Akkermansia</italic>, (<bold>J</bold>) <italic>Alistipes</italic>, (<bold>K</bold>) <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, (<bold>L</bold>) <italic>Escherichia-Shigella</italic>, and (<bold>M</bold>) <italic>Enterococcus</italic>. Data were shown as mean values ± SEM (n = 5). (<bold>N</bold>) Analysis of differences in the microbial taxa by LEfSe (LDA score &gt; 3.5) in different groups. Signifcance was evaluated by the Kruskal-Wallis test or ANOVA with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test (*, P &lt; 0.05, **, P &lt; 0.01, and ***, P &lt; 0.001).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="568052v1_fig10.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p><italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium is an important intestinal pathogen that can cause invasive intestinal diseases such as bacterial colitis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>). Although antibiotics are commonly used to treat bacterial-induced colitis, their overuse has significantly increased bacterial resistance in recent years, resulting in serious environmental pollution. A recent study showed that antibiotic-resistance genes in probiotics could be transmitted to the intestinal microbiota, which may threaten human health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>). Therefore, the source of probiotics is particularly important. Black pigs are an excellent domestic breed in China, with strong environmental adaptability and disease resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c21">21</xref>). In this study, <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was isolated from the free-range feces of black piglets in a mountain village in Xianning City (Hubei, China) and exhibited excellent antibacterial activity. Previous studies have demonstrated that the difficidins isolated from <italic>B. subtilis</italic> can inhibit bacterial protein synthesis, giving it broad-spectrum antibacterial activity against <italic>Gram positive</italic> and <italic>Gram negative</italic> bacteria. Therefore, we speculate that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 has the ability to synthesize Difficidin or its derivatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>). Otherwise, <italic>in vitro</italic> tolerance assays showed that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores have good tolerance to high temperature, strong acids, bile salts, and simulated gastric and intestinal fluid, which was similar to previous research results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c23">23</xref>). Furthermore, antibiotic susceptibility tests showed that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 does not exhibit antibiotic resistance.</p>
<p>Probiotics are unique in that they are alive when consumed, and unlike food or drug, they have the potential to produce toxins or infections in the body (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">25</xref>). Therefore, assessing the biosafety of probiotics is crucial. In this study, the safety of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was evaluated by measuring the body weight, intestinal barrier proteins, and inflammatory cytokines of the experimented mice, as well as conducting routine blood and biochemical tests. The results showed that the expression levels of ZO-1 and occludin in the colon of mice increased after treatment with different doses of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores. It has been reported that ZO-1, occludin and claudin are the three most important tight junction proteins in intercellular connections, which play a crucial role in maintaining the intestinal epithelial barrier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c27">27</xref>). Therefore, upregulating the expression levels of ZO-1 and Occludin might enhance intestinal barrier function.</p>
<p>Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) are important aminotransferases in animals and are considered key parameters for evaluating liver function injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref>). Under normal circumstances, the levels of ALT and AST are in dynamic balance without notable changes. However, when the liver is damaged or becomes dysfunctional, the levels of aminotransferases (ALT and AST) increase significantly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c30">30</xref>). Previous studies have shown that CCL4-induced liver injury strongly increases plasma ALT/AST levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c31">31</xref>). Zhang et al. reported that the addition of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> to chicken diets significantly decreased the serum levels of ALT and AST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">32</xref>). In this present study, the levels of ALT and AST in the probiotic-treated group were slightly lower than those in the control group, indicating that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 had no negative effect on liver health in mice. Furthermore, routine blood tests found that the blood indices of the <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 treatment group were within the normal reference range, similar to that of the control group.</p>
<p>To further evaluate the potential of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores in alleviating <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced colitis, mice were challenged with <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium ATCC14028 and then treated with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores via oral administration. Our experimental results demonstrated that oral treatment with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores could alleviate <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced colitis, as evidenced by decreased weight loss, DAI, and histological damage, which is similar with prior studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">34</xref>). Previous research showed that macrophages are the first line of host defense against bacterial infection. They release pro-inflammatory cytokines, which are critical in initiating adaptive immune responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c36">36</xref>). Nevertheless, pro-inflammatory cytokines have immunological properties that can be beneficial for the host to resist the invasion of bacteria and other microbes in the surrounding environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c37">37</xref>). For instance, pre-treatment with recombinant murine TNF-α was shown to protect mice against lethal bacterial (<italic>E. coli</italic>) infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c38">38</xref>). PJ-34 exerted protective effects on intestinal epithelial cells against invasive <italic>Salmonella</italic> infection by upregulating IL-6 expression through the ERK and NF-κB signal pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c39">39</xref>). However, some studies have shown that excessive immune cell activation can lead to tissue damage, multi-organ malfunction, systemic or chronic inflammation, and autoimmune disorders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c41">41</xref>). IL-10 is a recognized anti-inflammatory mediator that plays a crucial role in maintaining intestinal microbe-immune homeostasis, regulating the release of inflammatory mediators, and inhibiting pro-inflammatory responses of innate and adaptive immunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">42</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">44</xref>). For instance, previous studies have shown that <italic>Clostridium butyrate</italic> can induce the production of IL-10 in the intestine, thereby alleviating experimental colitis in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c45">45</xref>). Similar results were observed in our study, where oral administration of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores reduced the expression levels of TNF-α, IL-1β and IL-6 while increasing the levels of IL-10 in the colon of mice. Furthermore, oral administration of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores improved the functional damage and integrity of the intestinal barrier caused by <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium infection, as evidenced by the upregulated expression levels of intestinal barrier proteins and reduced histological damage.</p>
<p>Subsequently, we further analyzed the colon microbiome and it was noteworthy that oral <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 markedly increased alpha diversity of the colonic microbiota. As reported in prior studies, elevated alpha diversity associates with enhanced anti-interference ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">46</xref>). PCA analysis Results showed that oral administration of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 significantly affected the structure of the intestinal microbiota. Further analysis at the phylum/genus level revealed that <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 treatment reduced the increase of <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Escherichia-Shigella</italic>, and <italic>Salmonella</italic> (harmful to intestinal homeostasis) in colitis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c47">47</xref>), but enhanced the relative abundance of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> (known for enhancing the epithelial barrier by increasing mucus secretion and upregulating the expression of tight junction proteins such as claudin-1, occludin, and ZO-1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c48">48</xref>) and <italic>Akkermansia</italic> (known for modulating intestinal immune response by producing short chain fatty acids and reducing the secretion of pro-inflammatory cytokines) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c49">49</xref>). <italic>Bacteroides</italic> is generally ‘friendly’ commensals in the intestine, but they can enter normal tissues through the intestinal mucosa when intestinal barrier function becomes compromised (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c50">50</xref>), leading to inflammation, diarrhea, and abdominal abscess (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c51">51</xref>). <italic>Escherichia-Shigella</italic> is a common intestinal pathogen, and its relative abundance is associated with pro-inflammatory states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c52">52</xref>). <italic>Salmonella</italic> can secrete bacterial virulence proteins, which are directly delivered to the host cell cytosol through the Type III secretion system and induce the expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c53">53</xref>), leading to inflammation. Overall, the structure of the colon microbiota was disrupted by <italic>S</italic>. Typhimurium ATCC14028 infection and increased the relative abundance of harmful bacteria, while therapeutic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 enhanced the abundance of beneficial bacteria, reduced inflammation, and improved intestinal barrier function.</p>
<p>Due to the improved efficacy of treating <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced colitis, we further investigated the potential of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores for disease prevention by evaluating pre-treatment. Similarly to the therapeutic effect of oral <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020, pre-treatment with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores effectively alleviated the symptoms of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced colitis and reduced the expression levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines and increased anti-inflammatory cytokine levels in the colon of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-infected mice. Furthermore, pre-treatment with <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores also promoted the expression levels of intestinal barrier proteins in the colon of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-infected mice. In addition, the microbiota composition was also dramatically modulated by prophylactic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 in mice with colitis, although the community richness and diversity revealed by alpha diversity index was not significantly impacted in mice with colitis by prophylactic-treatment. Further analysis at the genus level revealed that prophylactic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 clearly increased SCFAs-producing bacteria including <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Akkermansia</italic>, which was consistent with the results of therapeutic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020. Similarly, harmful bacteria such as <italic>Alistipes</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Escherichia-Shigella</italic>, and <italic>Enterococcus</italic> were significantly enriched in the PBS+STm group. <italic>Alistipes</italic> is a facultative - pathogenic bacteria and promotes the development of inflammation, obesity, and colorectal cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c54">54</xref>). Based on those results, we found that prophylactic <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 alleviates <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium induced colitis by increasing the abundance of beneficial bacteria, attenuating pro-inflammatory response of the intestine, and increasing intestinal barrier function.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In conclusion, infection with <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium ATCC14028 disrupts the intestinal mucosal barrier, and leading to intestinal inflammation. Both therapeutic and prophylactic, supplementing <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores alleviates <italic>S</italic>. Typhimurium-induced colonic injury by reducing Salmonella colonization, and enhancing the abundance of beneficial bacteria (especially <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Akkermansia</italic>) and intestinal barrier integrity, and decreasing inflammation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5">
<title>Experimental procedures</title>
<sec id="s5a">
<title>Animals and bacterial strains</title>
<p>Female specific-pathogen-free (SPF) C57BL/6 mice aged 6 to 8 weeks were purchased from the Animal Experimental Center of Huazhong Agricultural University. All mice experiments were conducted in the standard SPF facility of Huazhong Agricultural University, with 12 h of light and 12 h of darkness at a temperature of 25°C and ad libitum access to food and water. The use of animals in this experiment was approved by the Animal Care and Ethics Committee of Huazhong Agricultural University (Ethics Approval Number: HZAUMO-2023-0089).</p>
<p>The strains used in this study are listed in Table S2, and all the primers used in Table S3. <italic>Clostridium perfringens</italic> were cultured in a fluid thioglycollate medium (FTG) (Hopebio, Qingdao, China) at 45°C. <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic>, <italic>Pasteurella multocida</italic>, and <italic>Actinobacillus pleuropneumoniae</italic> were cultured in tryptic soy broth (TSB) (BD Biosciences, MD, United States) medium supplemented with 5% (v/v) sheep serum (Solarbio, Beijing, China) at 37°C, while the other bacterial strains were cultured in Luria Bertani (LB) medium (Solarbio, Beijing, China) at 37°C. In addition, the Difco sporulation medium (DSM) was used for inducing the sporulation of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 via the nutrient depletion method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c55">55</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5b">
<title>Stain isolation, growth conditions and strain identification</title>
<p>In this study, we isolated 362 <italic>Bacillus</italic> strains from the feces of healthy black piglets that were free-ranging in a mountain village in Xianning City, Hubei Province, China, and 4 <italic>Bacillus</italic> strains were screened through initial antibacterial tests. Then, a strain with broad-spectrum antimicrobial activity was ultimately screened out by the antibacterial spectrum assay (Table S4), and named as <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020. The strain was stored in 28% glycerol at −80°C. For culturing the bacterial cells, Luria-Bertani (LB) media or agar plates supplemented with 1.5% agar were used and incubated at 37°C.</p>
<p>A single bacterial colony was inoculated into 10 mL of LB medium and incubated overnight at 37°C with shaking (180 rpm). Then, the 16S rRNA sequence was amplified by the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using forward primer 27F and reverse primer 1492R and similarity analysis with the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) alignment tool (BLAST) was used to identify the species.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5c">
<title>Genome sequencing, annotation and analysis</title>
<p>The complete genome of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was sequenced using the Illumina HiSeq PE and PacBio RSII (SMRT) platforms (Shanghai Majorbio Bio-pharm Technology Co., Ltd.). Briefly, the short reads from the Illumina HiSeq PE were assembled into contigs using SPAdenovo (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://soap.genomics.org.cn/">http://soap.genomics.org.cn/</ext-link>). The long reads from the PacBio RSII and the Illumina contigs were then aligned using the miniasm and Racon tools in Unicycler (version 0.4.8, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/rrwick/Unicycler">https://github.com/rrwick/Unicycler</ext-link>) to generate long-read sequences. During the assembly process, sequence correction was performed using Pilon (version 1.22, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/broadinstitute/pilon/wiki/Standard-Output">https://github.com/broadinstitute/pilon/wiki/Standard-Output</ext-link>). Lastly, a complete genome with seamless chromosomes was obtained.</p>
<p>The coding sequences (CDs) of the <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 genome were predicted using Glimmer (version 3.02, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ccb.jhu.edu/software/glimmer/index.shtml">http://ccb.jhu.edu/software/glimmer/index.shtml</ext-link>). The tRNA and rRNA genes were predicted using TRNAscan-SE (version 2.0, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://trna.ucsc.edu/software/">http://trna.ucsc.edu/software/</ext-link>) and Barrnap (version 0.8, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/tseemann/barrnap">https://github.com/tseemann/barrnap</ext-link>), respectively. The functional annotation of all CDSs was performed using various databases, including Swiss-Prot Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.expasy.org/docs/swiss-prot_guideline.html">https://web.expasy.org/docs/swiss-prot_guideline.html</ext-link>), Pfam Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pfam.xfam.org/">http://pfam.xfam.org/</ext-link>), EggNOG Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://eggnog.embl.de/">http://eggnog.embl.de/</ext-link>), GO Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org/">http://www.geneontology.org/</ext-link>), and KEGG Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link>). The circular map of the <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 genome was generated using CGView (version 2, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wishart.biology.ualberta.ca/cgview/">http://wishart.biology.ualberta.ca/cgview/</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c56">56</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5d">
<title>Comparative genomic analysis</title>
<p>To elucidate the phylogenetic relationships from a whole-genome perspective, a phylogenetic tree based on the whole genome was constructed using the Type (Strain) Genome Server (TYGS) online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ggdc.dsmz.de/">https://ggdc.dsmz.de/</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c57">57</xref>). The average nucleotide identity (ANI) values of genome to genome were calculated using the JSpeciesWS online service (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c58">58</xref>), and a heatmap was then generated using TBtools (version 1.113) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c59">59</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5e">
<title>Growth curves of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020</title>
<p>The growth curve of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was recorded in flat-bottomed 100-well microtiter plates via detecting optical density at 600 nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) at 1 h intervals using the automatic growth curve analyzer (Bioscreen, Helsinki, Finland).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5f">
<title>Antimicrobial Assays</title>
<p>The <italic>in vitro</italic> antagonistic activity of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 was tested using the agar well-diffusion method against 18 indicator strains (pathogens), which included 7 standard strains (<italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922, <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 35150, <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium ATCC 14028 (STm), <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium SL1344, <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 29213, <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 43300, and <italic>C. perfringens</italic> CVCC 2030) and 11 clinical isolates (<italic>E. coli</italic> EC024, <italic>S.</italic> Enteritidis SE006, <italic>S. aureus</italic> S21, <italic>C. perfringens</italic> CP023, <italic>C. perfringens</italic> CP002, <italic>S. suis</italic> SC19, <italic>S. suis</italic> SS006, <italic>P. multocida</italic> PM002, <italic>P. multocida</italic> PM008, <italic>A.</italic> pleuropneumoniae APP015, and <italic>A.</italic> pleuropneumoniae APP017). All plates were cultured at 37°C for 16 h before observing the inhibition zone, and the diameter of the inhibition zone was measured using a vernier caliper. The presence of a clear zone indicated antagonistic activity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5g">
<title>Antibiotic susceptibility assays</title>
<p>Antimicrobial susceptibility testing was performed using the Kirby-Bauer (KB) disk diffusion method in accordance with the Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) guidelines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c60">60</xref>). The antimicrobial agents tested were: Ampicillin, Meropenem, Piperacillin, Gentamycin, Tetracycline, Doxycycline, Minocycline, Erythromycin, Enrofloxacin, Ofloxacin, Sulfamethoxazole, Trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole, Polymyxin B, Teicoplanin, Trimethoprim, Florfenicol, Spectinomycin, Nitrofurantoin, and Rifampicin. The diameter of the inhibition zone was measured using a vernier caliper.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5h">
<title><italic>In vitro</italic> resistance assay of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020</title>
<p><italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores (100 μL) or vegetative cells (100 μL) were separately resuspended in 900 μL of LB medium supplemented with different pH values (2, 3, 4, 5 or 6), bile salts (0.85% NaCl, 0.3%), simulated gastric fluid (SGF, HCl, pH 1.2) containing 10 g L<sup>-1</sup> of pepsin in 0.85% NaCl solution, or simulated intestinal fluid (SIF, NaOH, pH 6.8) containing 10 g L<sup>-1</sup> of trypsin in 0.05 M KH2PO4 solution, and incubated at 37 °C. A normal LB medium (pH 7.0) was used as the control. At predetermined time points, 100 μL was taken from each sample, serially diluted 10-fold with sterile PBS (pH 7.2), and then spread onto LB agar plates. The plates were incubated overnight in a constant temperature incubator at 37°C, and the bacterial colonies were counted. The survival rate was calculated using the following formula: Survival rate = (number of bacteria in the treatment group/number of bacteria in the control group) × 100%.</p>
<p>One milliliter of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores or vegetative cells were separately placed in water baths at different temperatures (37°C, 45°C, 55°C, 65°C, 75°C, 85°C or 95°C) for 20 min, with a 37°C water bath used as the control. The survival rate was calculated as described above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5i">
<title><italic>In vitro</italic> bacterial competition</title>
<p>To investigate whether <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 directly inhibited the growth of STm, we performed spot-on lawn and agar-well diffusion assays, as well as co-culture assays in liquid culture medium. In the spot-on lawn antimicrobial assays, we prepared double layers of agar by first pouring LB agar into the plate as the bottom layer. The top layer consisted of 10 mL TSB broth containing 0.7% agar with STm overnight culture. Then, 10 μL of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 overnight culture and cell-free supernatant (CFS) were respectively spotted onto TSB agar and incubated at 37°C for 12 h to measure the inhibition zone. A transparent zone of at least 1 mm around the spot was considered positive.</p>
<p>The antagonistic effect of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020-CFS against STm was determined using the agar-well diffusion assays. To collect <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020-CFS, the culture was centrifuged at 9,000g for 15 min at 4°C, and the supernatant was filtered through a 0.22 μm membrane filter (Millipore, USA). The STm lawn medium was prepared by mixing 10 mL of TSB broth containing 0.7% agar with STm overnight culture and then poured into a sterile plate covered with LB agar and Oxford cups, 8 mm diameter wells were prepared in the TSB agar after removing the cups. The wells were filled with 100 μL of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020-CFS, LB medium or ampicillin (100 µg mL<sup>-1</sup>). The plates were incubated at 37°C for 14 h, and the inhibition zone was measured.</p>
<p>The co-culture assay was conducted by incubating <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 and <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium ATCC14028 (carry pET28a (+), kanamycin resistance) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>) separately overnight at 37°C and diluting them to 10<sup>4</sup> CFU/mL. Then, the two strains were mixed at different ratios (1:1, 1:10, 1:50 or 1:100) and co-cultured at 37°C with shaking (180 rpm). At predetermined time points, serial 10-fold dilutions were prepared for all samples and spread onto selective (kanamycin 50 µg mL<sup>-1</sup>) LB agar plates and cultured at 37°C for 12 h before bacterial counting. Viable colony counts ranged from 30 to 300 per plate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5j">
<title>Biosafety assessment</title>
<p>After a 7-day acclimation period (free access to water and food), mice were randomly divided into four treatment groups (n = 5): low-dose <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores group (L-HBXN2020 group, 10<sup>7</sup> CFU/mouse), medium-dose <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores group (M-HBXN2020 group, 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mouse), high-dose <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores group (H-HBXN2020 group, 10<sup>9</sup> CFU/mouse), and a control group. During the experimental period (15 days), mice were weighed and orally gavaged with their respective treatments once every two days. On day 15, all mice were euthanized, and blood, heart, liver, spleen, lung, kidney, ileum, cecum, and colon were collected. Blood samples were used for routine blood and biochemistry tests. Major organ tissues (heart, liver, spleen, lung, and kidney) and a 5-mm distal segment of the colon were used for histopathology. The remaining colonic tissues were rapidly frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C for cytokine and tight junction protein expression analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5k">
<title><italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium-induced mouse model of colitis</title>
<p>After 7 days of acclimation (free access to water and food), mice were randomly divided into three treatment groups (n = 8): Control group, STm + PBS group, and STm + HBXN2020 group. The <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium-induced colitis was performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c61">61</xref>), with slight modifications. On the first day of the experiment, all mice in the STm + PBS group and STm + HBXN2020 group were orally inoculated with 200 μL (5×10<sup>7</sup> CFU/mouse) of STm. On days 1, 3 and 5 following STm infection, each mouse in the STm + HBXN2020 group received 200 μL (1×10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mouse) of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores via gavage administration. In contrast, the control group and STm + PBS group received 200 μL of sterile PBS by oral gavage. Fecal samples were collected daily following STm infection and resuspended in sterile PBS. The number of STm in mice feces from both the STm + PBS and STm + HBXN2020 groups was then determined by spreading a serial 10-fold dilution on selective LB agar plates containing 50 µg mL<sup>-1</sup> kanamycin. Throughout the entire experiment, the body weight, stool consistency and fecal occult blood of all mice were monitored daily. As shown in Table S5, disease activity index (DAI) was calculated by the sum of the scores from three parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c62">62</xref>). On day 7 after STm infection, all mice were euthanized, their ileum, cecum and colon were collected. The length of colon was measured, and a 5-mm distal segment of the colon was fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for further histopathology. The remaining colon was then rapidly frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C for cytokine and tight junction protein expression analysis. Then, the number of STm in the ileum, cecum, and colon was determined by spreading serial 10-fold dilutions on selective LB agar plates.</p>
<p>To investigate the prophylactic efficacy of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 in ameliorating STm-induced colitis, another independent experiment was conducted using six-week-old female C57BL/6 mice (SPF). After a seven-day acclimation period, mice were randomly assigned to three groups (n = 8): control group, PBS + STm group and HBXN2020 + STm group. On days 1, 3, 5 and 7, each mouse in the HBXN2020 + STm group received 200 μL (1×10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mouse) of <italic>B. velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 spores via gavage administration. Meanwhile, mice in the control group and PBS + STm group received 200 μL of sterile PBS by oral gavage. On day 7, all mice in the PBS + STm group and HBXN2020 + STm group were orally inoculated with 200 μL (5×10<sup>7</sup> CFU/mouse) of STm. Fecal samples were collected daily following STm infection from both groups and resuspended in sterile PBS. The number of STm in the feces of mice was then determined by spreading serial 10-fold dilutions on selective LB agar plates (50 µg mL<sup>-1</sup> kanamycin). Throughout the entire experiment, the body weight and DAI scores of all mice were monitored daily. On day 12, all mice were euthanized, and the ileum, cecum, and colon were collected. The colon length was measured, and a 5-mm distal segment of the colon was fixed in 4% formalin for sectioning and staining. The remaining colon was stored at −80°C for future analysis. Lastly, the number of STm in the ileum, cecum, and colon was determined using a selective LB agar plate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5l">
<title>Determination of cytokines and tight junction protein expression in colon tissue</title>
<p>Total RNA was extracted from colon tissues using TRIpure reagent (Aidlab, China), and cDNA was obtained using HiScript<sup>®</sup> III RT SuperMix for qPCR (+gDNA wiper) (Vazyme, China). RT-qPCR for each gene was performed in triplicate using qPCR SYBR Green Master Mix (Yeasen Biotechnology, Shanghai, China). The relative expression level of cytokine and tight junction protein genes was calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> method with β-actin and GAPDH as reference genes. The primer sequences used in the RT-qPCR test are listed in Table S3.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5m">
<title>Histopathology analysis</title>
<p>Colon tissue samples (0.5 cm) were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 24 h, and the fixed tissues were then embedded in paraffin and sectioned. The sections were stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) and observed and imaged using an optical microscope (Olympus Optical, Tokyo, Japan). The histopathological score included the degree of inflammatory infiltration, changes in crypt structures, and the presence or absence of ulceration and edema. The scoring criteria were determined as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">34</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5n">
<title>16S rRNA gene sequencing and analysis</title>
<p>According to the manufacturer’s instructions, colon microbial community genomes were extracted using E.Z-N.A ® Stool DNA Kit (Omega; D4015-01), and quality was detected by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis. The 16S rRNA V3-V4 variable region was amplified by PCR using universal primers 338F (5’-ACTCCTACGGGGGGCAG-3’) and 806R (5’-GACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3’). The PCR products were examined by electrophoresis on 2% agarose gels and then purified with the AxyPrep DNA gel extraction kit (Axygen Biosciences, USA). A sequencing library was constructed using the NEXTFLEX® Rapid DNA-Seq Kit, and sequencing was performed using the Illumina MiSeq platform. Raw reads were quality evaluated and filtered by fastp (version 0.20.0) and merged using FLASH (version 1.2.7). The optimized sequences were clustered into operational taxonomic units (OTUs) based on 97% sequence similarity using UPARSE (version 7.1). The representative sequences of each OTU was classified by RDP classifier (version 2.2; confidence threshold value, 0.7). Alpha diversity was assessed using the ACE, chao, Shannon, and Simpson indices. The β-diversity analysis was performed using Bray-Curtis distances and visualized through principal component analysis (PCA). Linear discriminant analysis (LDA) effect size (LefSe) was used to identify differential microbiota between groups.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s6">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism 8.3.0 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA) and Excel (Microsoft, Redmond, USA). Data are presented as mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM). Differences between two groups were evaluated using two-tailed unpaired Student’s t-test, and all other comparisons were conducted using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test. For all analyses, significance differences are denoted as: *, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and ***, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s7">
<title>Data availability</title>
<p>The complete genome sequence of <italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic> HBXN2020 has been deposited in GenBank and assigned accession numbers: CP119399.1</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s8">
<title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p>We declare no conflict of interest.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>This work was supported by grants from the National Program on Key Research Project of China (2021YFD1800300, 2022YFD1800800), “Yingzi Tech &amp; Huazhong Agricultural University Intelligent Research Institute of Food Health” (No. IRIFH202209; IRIFH202301), and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (2662016PY004).</p>
</ack>
<sec id="s9">
<title>Author contributions</title>
<p><bold>Linkang Wang</bold>: Conceptualization, Methodology, Data curation, Formal analysis, Writing - original draft. <bold>Haiyan Wang, Xinxin Li, Mengyuan Zhu</bold>: Methodology, Data curation, Planned and performed the experiments. <bold>Dongyang Gao, Dayue Hu, Zhixuan Xiong</bold>: Methodology, Writing - Reviewing and Editing. <bold>Xiangmin Li</bold>: Supervision, Writing-reviewing and editing. <bold>Ping Qian</bold>: Conceptualization, Funding acquisition, Project administration, Supervision, Writing-Reviewing and Editing. All authors read and approved the submitted version of the paper.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s10">
<title>Funding information</title>
<p>This work was supported by grants from the National Program on Key Research Project of China (2021YFD1800300, 2022YFD1800800), “Yingzi Tech &amp; Huazhong Agricultural University Intelligent Research Institute of Food Health” (No. IRIFH202209; IRIFH202301), and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (2662016PY004).</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="c1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fabrega</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vila</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2013</year>. <article-title>Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium skills to succeed in the host: virulence and regulation</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source> <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westman</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heithoff</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sperandio</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahan</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marth</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Neu3 neuraminidase induction triggers intestinal inflammation and colitis in a model of recurrent human food-poisoning</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>118</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Katiyo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muller-Pebody</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minaji</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Powell</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Pinna</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Day</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Godbole</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Epidemiology and Outcomes of Nontyphoidal Salmonella Bacteremias from England, 2004 to 2015</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source> <volume>57</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mohan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Munusamy</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname> <given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muthuvelu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashim</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chien</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khairuddin</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Podin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lau</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ng</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ooi</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Invasive Salmonella infections among children in Bintulu, Sarawak, Malaysian Borneo: a 6-year retrospective review</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect Dis</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>330</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferri</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ranucci</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romagnoli</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giaccone</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Antimicrobial resistance: A global emerging threat to public health systems</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr</source> <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>2857</fpage>–<lpage>2876</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Paulson</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zaoutis</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <collab>Council on Environmental H</collab>, <collab>Committee on Infectious D</collab>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>Nontherapeutic Use of Antimicrobial Agents in Animal Agriculture: Implications for Pediatrics</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source> <volume>136</volume>:<fpage>e1670</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reyman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Houten</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watson</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arp</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Waal</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schiering</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plotz</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Willems</surname> <given-names>RJL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Schaik</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanders</surname> <given-names>EAM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bogaert</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Effects of early-life antibiotics on the developing infant gut microbiome and resistome: a randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>893</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cristofori</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dargenio</surname> <given-names>VN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dargenio</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miniello</surname> <given-names>VL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Francavilla</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Anti-Inflammatory and Immunomodulatory Effects of Probiotics in Gut Inflammation: A Door to the Body</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>578386</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ning</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiang</surname> <given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cui</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Combination of probiotics with different functions alleviate DSS-induced colitis by regulating intestinal microbiota, IL-10, and barrier function</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source> <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohland</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macnaughton</surname> <given-names>WK</given-names></string-name>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Probiotic bacteria and intestinal epithelial barrier function</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source> <volume>298</volume>:<fpage>G807</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>LN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>Potential probiotic attributes of a new strain of Bacillus coagulans CGMCC 9951 isolated from healthy piglet feces</article-title>. <source>World J Microbiol Biotechnol</source> <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>851</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ouattara</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reverchon</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niamke</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nasser</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Regulation of the synthesis of pulp degrading enzymes in Bacillus isolated from cocoa fermentation</article-title>. <source>Food Microbiol</source> <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abdhul</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ganesh</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shanmughapriya</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vanithamani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kanagavel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anbarasu</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Natarajaseenivasan</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>Bacteriocinogenic potential of a probiotic strain Bacillus coagulans [BDU3] from Ngari</article-title>. <source>Int J Biol Macromol</source> <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>800</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ye</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tao</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <year>2018</year>. <article-title>Characteristics and Application of a Novel Species of Bacillus: Bacillus velezensis</article-title>. <source>ACS Chem Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stefanic</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lv</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mandic-Mulec</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Annulment of Bacterial Antagonism Improves Plant Beneficial Activity of a Bacillus velezensis Consortium</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>e0024022</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qamar</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mehmood</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Probiotics isolated from yaks improves the growth performance, antioxidant activity, and cytokines related to immunity and inflammation in mice</article-title>. <source>Microb Cell Fact</source> <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>DX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>ZL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>GQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shan</surname> <given-names>XF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qian</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Effect of Bacillus velezensis on Aeromonas veronii-Induced Intestinal Mucosal Barrier Function Damage and Inflammation in Crucian Carp (Carassius auratus)</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2663</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Herp</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brugiroux</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garzetti</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ring</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jochum</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beutler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eberl</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hussain</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walter</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerlach</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruscheweyh</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sellin</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Slack</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loy</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baines</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rausch</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basic</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bleich</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berry</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stecher</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Mucispirillum schaedleri Antagonizes Salmonella Virulence to Protect Mice against Colitis</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source> <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>681</fpage>–<lpage>694 e8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schultz</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paduro</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salazar</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salazar-Echegarai</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sebastian</surname> <given-names>VP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riedel</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kalergis</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alvarez-Lobos</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bueno</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>A Potential Role of Salmonella Infection in the Onset of Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Crits-Christoph</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hallowell</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koutouvalis</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suez</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Good microbes, bad genes? The dissemination of antimicrobial resistance in the human microbiome</article-title>. <source>Gut Microbes</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>2055944</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Du</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jing</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Population Genetic Structure and Selection Signature Analysis of Beijing Black Pig</article-title>. <source>Front Genet</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>860669</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaspar</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neubauer</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gimpel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Bioactive Secondary Metabolites from Bacillus subtilis: A Comprehensive Review</article-title>. <source>J Nat Prod</source> <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>2038</fpage>–<lpage>2053</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Du</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kulyar</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhutta</surname> <given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Effects of Bacillus amyloliquefaciens TL106 Isolated from Tibetan Pigs on Probiotic Potential and Intestinal Microbes in Weaned Piglets</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0120521</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sanders</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akkermans</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haller</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammerman</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heimbach</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hormannsperger</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huys</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levy</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lutgendorff</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mack</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phothirath</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solano-Aguilar</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaughan</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Safety assessment of probiotics for human use</article-title>. <source>Gut Microbes</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Snydman</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>The safety of probiotics</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source> <volume>46</volume> <issue>Suppl 2</issue>:<fpage>S104</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>; discussion S144-51.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bazzoni</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez-Estrada</surname> <given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orsenigo</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cordenonsi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Citi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dejana</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <year>2000</year>. <article-title>Interaction of junctional adhesion molecule with the tight junction components ZO-1, cingulin, and occludin</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>275</volume>:<fpage>20520</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zihni</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mills</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matter</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balda</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Tight junctions: from simple barriers to multifunctional molecular gates</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gou</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ying</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dai</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ke</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiao</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Multi-responsive nanotheranostics with enhanced tumor penetration and oxygen self-producing capacities for multimodal synergistic cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Acta Pharm Sin B</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ozer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ratner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shaw</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bailey</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schomaker</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>The current state of serum biomarkers of hepatotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Toxicology</source> <volume>245</volume>:<fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xing</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>Quercetin prevents ethanol-induced dyslipidemia and mitochondrial oxidative damage</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1194</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Singhal</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inverso</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dai</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartels</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdul Pari</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gengenbacher</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Besemfelder</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hui</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Augustin</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2018</year>. <article-title>Endothelial cell fitness dictates the source of regenerating liver vasculature</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> <volume>215</volume>:<fpage>2497</fpage>–<lpage>2508</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Dietary effects of Bacillus subtilis fmbj on the antioxidant capacity of broilers at an early age</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source> <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>3564</fpage>–<lpage>3573</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Biointerfacial self-assembly generates lipid membrane coated bacteria for enhanced oral delivery and treatment</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>5783</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnston</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Limosilactobacillus reuteri SLZX19-12 Protects the Colon from Infection by Enhancing Stability of the Gut Microbiota and Barrier Integrity and Reducing Inflammation</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0212421</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dinarello</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <year>2000</year>. <article-title>Proinflammatory cytokines</article-title>. <source>Chest</source> <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tian</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Polyphenols from blueberries modulate inflammation cytokines in LPS-induced RAW264.7 macrophages</article-title>. <source>Int J Biol Macromol</source> <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kalantar-Zadeh</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>George</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Cytokines: From Clinical Significance to Quantification</article-title>. <source>Adv Sci (Weinh)</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e2004433</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cross</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadoff</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bernton</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gemski</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <year>1989</year>. <article-title>Pretreatment with recombinant murine tumor necrosis factor alpha/cachectin and murine interleukin 1 alpha protects mice from lethal bacterial infection</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> <volume>169</volume>:<fpage>2021</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Upregulation of Salmonella-induced IL-6 production in Caco-2 cells by PJ-34, PARP-1 inhibitor: involvement of PI3K, p38 MAPK, ERK, JNK, and NF-kappaB</article-title>. <source>Mediators Inflamm</source> <volume>2009</volume>:<fpage>103890</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Karki</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharma</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tuladhar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>EP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zalduondo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samir</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sundaram</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banoth</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malireddi</surname> <given-names>RKS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schreiner</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neale</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vogel</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Webby</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jonsson</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kanneganti</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Synergism of TNF-alpha and IFN-gamma Triggers Inflammatory Cell Death, Tissue Damage, and Mortality in SARS-CoV-2 Infection and Cytokine Shock Syndromes</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>184</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>168 e17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kotas</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Medzhitov</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>Homeostasis, inflammation, and disease susceptibility</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>160</volume>:<fpage>816</fpage>–<lpage>827</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ouyang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rutz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crellin</surname> <given-names>NK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valdez</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hymowitz</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Regulation and functions of the IL-10 family of cytokines in inflammation and disease</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Immunol</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saraiva</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vieira</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Garra</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Biology and therapeutic potential of interleukin-10</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> <volume>217</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maloy</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Powrie</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Intestinal homeostasis and its breakdown in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>474</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hayashi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sato</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kamada</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mikami</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsuoka</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hisamatsu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hibi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roers</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yagita</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohteki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshimura</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kanai</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <year>2013</year>. <article-title>A single strain of Clostridium butyricum induces intestinal IL-10-producing macrophages to suppress acute experimental colitis in mice</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garmaeva</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kurilshikov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vich Vila</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gacesa</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinha</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Segal</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weersma</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wijmenga</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhernakova</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>The long-term genetic stability and individual specificity of the human gut microbiome</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>184</volume>:<fpage>2302</fpage>–<lpage>2315.e12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gou</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Du</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <year>2023</year>. <article-title>The interplay between herbal medicines and gut microbiota in metabolic diseases</article-title>. <source>Front Pharmacol</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1105405</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaur</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapila</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapila</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Protective effects of potential probiotic Lactobacillus rhamnosus (MTCC-5897) fermented whey on reinforcement of intestinal epithelial barrier function in a colitis-induced murine model</article-title>. <source>Food Funct</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>6102</fpage>–<lpage>6116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cani</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Depommier</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Derrien</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Everard</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Vos</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Akkermansia muciniphila: paradigm for next-generation beneficial microorganisms</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>637</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Polk</surname> <given-names>BF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kasper</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <year>1977</year>. <article-title>Bacteroides fragilis subspecies in clinical isolates</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pickard</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname> <given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caruso</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Núñez</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Gut microbiota: Role in pathogen colonization, immune responses, and inflammatory disease</article-title>. <source>Immunol Rev</source> <volume>279</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morgan</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>. <year>2013</year>. <article-title>Infection, illness, and fenugreek seeds: was illness a good enough proxy for infection in the 2011 outbreak of shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O104:H4 in France?</article-title> <source>Clin Infect Dis</source> <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1055</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hardt</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schuebel</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bustelo</surname> <given-names>XR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galán</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>. <year>1998</year>. <article-title>S. typhimurium encodes an activator of Rho GTPases that induces membrane ruffling and nuclear responses in host cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>815</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Parker</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wearsch</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veloo</surname> <given-names>ACM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodriguez-Palacios</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>The Genus Alistipes: Gut Bacteria With Emerging Implications to Inflammation, Cancer, and Mental Health</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>906</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Oral delivery of Bacillus subtilis spores expressing cysteine protease of Clonorchis sinensis to grass carp (Ctenopharyngodon idellus): Induces immune responses and has no damage on liver and intestine function</article-title>. <source>Fish Shellfish Immunol</source> <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stothard</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wishart</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>Circular genome visualization and exploration using CGView</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meier-Kolthoff</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carbasse</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peinado-Olarte</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goker</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>TYGS and LPSN: a database tandem for fast and reliable genome-based classification and nomenclature of prokaryotes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>D801</fpage>–<lpage>D807</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Richter</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rossello-Mora</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oliver Glockner</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peplies</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>JSpeciesWS: a web server for prokaryotic species circumscription based on pairwise genome comparison</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>929</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frank</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xia</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>TBtools: An Integrative Toolkit Developed for Interactive Analyses of Big Biological Data</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1194</fpage>–<lpage>1202</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>CLSI</collab>. <year>2018</year>. <source>Performance standards for antimicrobial disk susceptibility tests, M02</source>, <edition>13th ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Wayne, PA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stecher</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macpherson</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hapfelmeier</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kremer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stallmach</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hardt</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></string-name>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>Comparison of Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium colitis in germfree mice and mice pretreated with streptomycin</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>3228</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Praveschotinunt</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duraj-Thatte</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gelfat</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bahl</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chou</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joshi</surname> <given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Engineered E. coli Nissle 1917 for the delivery of matrix-tethered therapeutic domains to the gut</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>5580</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<sub-article id="sa0" article-type="editor-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.93423.1.sa3</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>eLife Assessment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kana</surname>
<given-names>Bavesh D</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of the Witwatersrand</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Johannesburg</city>
<country>South Africa</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="evidence-strength">
<kwd>Solid</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="claim-importance">
<kwd>Useful</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>In this <bold>useful</bold> study, Wang and colleagues investigate the potential probiotic effects of Bacillus velezensis to prevent colitis in a mouse model. They provide <bold>solid</bold> evidence that B. velezensis limits the growth of Salmonella typhimurium in lab culture and in mice, together with beneficial effects on the microbiota. The work will be of interest to infectious disease researchers and those studying the microbiome.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa1" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.93423.1.sa2</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #1 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>Wang and colleagues presented an investigation of pig-origin bacteria Bacillus velezensis HBXN2020, for its released genome sequence, in vivo safety issue, probiotic effects in vitro, and protection against Salmonella infection in a murine model. Various techniques and assays are performed.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>An extensive study on the probiotic properties of the Bacillus velezensis strain HBXN2020.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>- The main results are all descriptive, without new insight advancing the field or a mechanistic understanding of the observed protection.</p>
<p>- Most of the results and analysis parts are separated without a link or any story-telling to deliver a concise message.</p>
<p>- For the Salmonella Typhimurium-induced mouse model of colitis, it is not clear how an oral infection of C57BL/6 would lead to colitis. Streptomycin is always pretreated (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://link.springer.com/protocol/10.1007/978-1-0716-1971-1_17">https://link.springer.com/protocol/10.1007/978-1-0716-1971-1_17</ext-link>).</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa2" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.93423.1.sa1</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #2 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>In this study, Wang and colleagues study the potential probiotic effects of Bacillus velezensis. Bacillus species have the potential benefit of serving as probiotics due to their ability to form endospores and synthesize secondary metabolites. B. velezensis has been shown to have probiotic effects in plants and animals but data for human use are scarce, particularly with respect to salmonella-induced colitis. In this work, the authors identify a strain of B. velezensis and test it for its ability to control colitis in mice.</p>
<p>Key findings:</p>
<p>(1) The authors sequence an isolate for B. velezensis - HBXN2020 and describe its genome (roughly 4 mb, 46% GC-content etc).</p>
<p>(2) The authors next describe the growth of this strain in broth culture and survival under acid and temperature stress. The susceptibility of HBXN2020 was tested against various antibiotics and against various pathogenic bacteria. In the case of the latter, the authors set out to determine if HBXN2020 could directly inhibit the growth of pathogenic bacteria. Convincing data, indicating that this is indeed the case, are presented.</p>
<p>(3) To determine the safety profile of BHXN2020 (for possible use as a probiotic), the authors infected the strain in mice and monitored weight, together with cytokine profiles. Infected mice displayed no significant weight loss and expression of inflammatory cytokines remained unchanged. Blood cell profiles of infected mice were consistent with that of uninfected mice. No significant differences in tissues, including the colon were observed.</p>
<p>(4) Next, the authors tested the ability of HBXN2020 to inhibit the growth of Salmonella typhimurium (STm) and demonstrate that HBXN2020 inhibits STm in a dose-dependent manner. Following this, the authors infect mice with STm to induce colitis and measure the ability of HBXN2020 to control colitis. The first outcome measure was a reduction in STm in faeces. Consistent with this, HBXN2020 reduced STm loads in the ileum, cecum, and colon. Colon length was also affected by HBXN2020 treatment. In addition, treatment with HBXN2020 reduced the appearance of colon pathological features associated with colitis, together with a reduction in inflammatory cytokines.</p>
<p>(5) After noting the beneficial (and anti-inflammatory effects) of HBXN2020, the authors set out to investigate the effects on microbiota during treatment. Using a variety of algorithms, the authors demonstrate that upon HXBN2020 treatment, microbiota composition is restored to levels akin to that seen in healthy mice.</p>
<p>(6) Finally, the authors assessed the effect of using HBXN2020 as prophylactic treatment for colitis by first treating mice with the spores and then infecting them with STm. Their data indicate that treatment with HBXN2020 reduced colitis. A similar beneficial impact was seen with the gut microbiota.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>(1) Good use of in vitro and animal models to demonstrate a beneficial probiotic effect.</p>
<p>(2) Most observations are supported using multiple approaches.</p>
<p>(3) The mouse experiments are very convincing.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>(1) Whilst a beneficial effect is observed, there is no investigation of the mechanism that underpins this.</p>
<p>(2) The mouse experiments would have benefited from the use of standard anti-inflammatory therapies to control colitis. That way the authors could compare their approach of using bacillus spores with the current gold standard for treatment.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa3" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.93423.1.sa0</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #3 (Public Review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>
The manuscript by Wang et al. investigates the effects of B. velezensis HBXN2020 in alleviating S. Typhimurium-induced mouse colitis. The results showed that B. velezensis HBXN2020 could alleviate bacterial colitis by enhancing intestinal homeostasis (decreasing harmful bacteria and enhancing the abundance of Lactobacillus and Akkermansia) and gut barrier integrity and reducing inflammation. Overall, the manuscript is of potential interest to readers.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>
B. velezensis HBXN2020 is a novel species of Bacillus that can produce a great variety of secondary metabolites and exhibit high antibacterial activity against several pathogens. B. velezensis HBXN2020 is able to form endospores and has strong anti-stress capabilities. B. velezensis HBXN2020 has a synergistic effect with other beneficial microorganisms, which can improve intestinal homeostasis.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>
There are few studies about the clinical application of Bacillus velezensis. Thus, more studies are still needed to explore the effectiveness of Bacillus velezensis before clinical application.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
</article>