<?xml version="1.0" ?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.3 20210610//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>eLife</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">106261</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106261</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi" specific-use="version">10.7554/eLife.106261.1</article-id>
<article-version-alternatives>
<article-version article-version-type="publication-state">reviewed preprint</article-version>
<article-version article-version-type="preprint-version">1.3</article-version>
</article-version-alternatives>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Structural Biology and Molecular Biophysics</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Microbiology and Infectious Disease</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Navigating contradictions: <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium chemotactic responses to conflicting effector stimuli</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4719-225X</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Franco</surname>
<given-names>Kailie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0350-7494</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Gentry-Lear</surname>
<given-names>Zealon</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0395-8578</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Shavlik</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0241-4122</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Harms</surname>
<given-names>Michael J</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5522-769X</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Baylink</surname>
<given-names>Arden</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">a</xref>
<email>arden.baylink@wsu.edu</email>
</contrib>
<aff id="a1"><label>a</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05dk0ce17</institution-id><institution>Department of Veterinary Microbiology and Pathology, Washington State University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Pullman</city>, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
<aff id="a2"><label>b</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0293rh119</institution-id><institution>Institute of Molecular Biology, University of Oregon</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Eugene</city>, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
<aff id="a3"><label>c</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0293rh119</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemistry &amp; Biochemistry, University of Oregon</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Eugene</city>, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="section">
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Antunes</surname>
<given-names>Caetano</given-names>
</name>
<role>Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Kansas</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Lawrence</city>
<country>United States of America</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="senior_editor">
<name>
<surname>Garrett</surname>
<given-names>Wendy S</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Boston</city>
<country>United States of America</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn id="n1" fn-type="present-address"><label>*</label><p>Present address: Zealon Gentry-Lear, Department of Microbiology, University of Washington, Washington, USA</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="coi-statement"><p>Competing interests: A.B. owns Amethyst Antimicrobials, LLC. The other authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date date-type="original-publication" iso-8601-date="2025-03-26">
<day>26</day>
<month>03</month>
<year>2025</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<elocation-id>RP106261</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="sent-for-review" iso-8601-date="2025-02-09">
<day>09</day>
<month>02</month>
<year>2025</year>
</date>
</history>
<pub-history>
<event>
<event-desc>Preprint posted</event-desc>
<date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2025-02-10">
<day>10</day>
<month>02</month>
<year>2025</year>
</date>
<self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.01.18.576330"/>
</event>
</pub-history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2025, Franco et al</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Franco et al</copyright-holder>
<ali:free_to_read/>
<license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-preprint-106261-v1.pdf"/>
<abstract>
<title>Abstract</title><p>Chemotaxis controls motility and colonization in many enteric pathogens, yet most studies have examined bacterial responses to single effectors in isolation. Previously, we reported that <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium uses the chemoreceptor Tsr to detect L-serine (L-Ser) in human blood serum, promoting invasion of damaged vasculature (<italic>Glenn et al., eLife</italic> 2024 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>). Tsr also mediates sensing of indole, a microbiota-derived chemorepellent and bactericide proposed to protect against enteric infection by deterring pathogen colonization. The major biological reservoir of indole in the gut is feces, where it accumulates to millimolar levels. Here, we tested whether indole-rich human fecal material is protective against infection and found that exposure to feces instead enhances intestinal invasion in an explant model. Surprisingly, diverse non-typhoidal <italic>Salmonella</italic> serovars were strongly attracted to feces despite its high indole content. We found that while pure indole is a strong repellent sensed through Tsr, its effects are overridden in the presence of nutrient attractants, including L-Ser. Moreover, indole only minimally impairs growth in the presence of sufficient nutrients. Using video microscopy, we observed that Tsr integrates L-Ser and indole signals in real time, biasing bacterial movement based on the relative concentrations of attractant and repellent. We propose that this chemotactic compromise optimizes pathogen fitness by guiding bacteria to niches with a favorable L-Ser-to-indole ratio, balancing nutrient acquisition and avoidance of high microbial competitor density. These findings highlight the limitations of single-effector studies in predicting bacterial navigation in complex environments, where chemotaxis is shaped by the integration of multiple, often opposing, chemical cues.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta specific-use="meta-only">
<meta-name>publishing-route</meta-name>
<meta-value>prc</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<fn-group content-type="summary-of-updates">
<title>Summary of Updates:</title>
<fn fn-type="update"><p>This is a revised version with text and figure changes based on feedback from colleagues in the field.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Many bacteria that colonize the gastrointestinal tracts of humans and other animals employ chemotaxis to sense chemical effectors in the gut lumen and swim to environments conducive for growth and colonization <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">6</xref></sup>. This process is controlled by chemoreceptor proteins, which recognize chemical effectors and transduce signals through a phosphorylation cascade to regulate flagellar rotation and swimming direction, ultimately determining the spatial and temporal patterns of bacterial colonization (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref></sup>. In turn, the colonization topography of bacteria within the gut influences the health of the host through nutrient absorption, developmental regulation, and resistance to pathogens <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">11</xref></sup>. While many effectors have been studied and characterized in isolation as attractants or repellents <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref></sup>, natural environments contain mixtures of opposing signals. In the enteric lumen, bacteria encounter a complex milieu of conflicting effector stimuli, including nutrients, molecular cues, and toxins <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c5">5</xref></sup>. Only a handful of studies have investigated how bacteria navigate conflicting chemical gradients and there remains much to learn about how bacteria prioritize these signals to direct their movement and colonization (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref></sup>.</p>
<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 1.</label>
<caption><title>Tsr and chemotaxis mediate efficient pathogen invasion of colonic tissue.</title><p>A-B. Overview of the role of Tsr in chemotactic responses and premise of this study. C. Experimental design of colonic explant infections. See Materials &amp; Methods for experiment details such as tissue dimensions. D. Serine (presumed to be nearly 100% LSer, see Materials &amp; Methods) and indole content of liquid human fecal treatments, as measured by mass spectrometry. E-I. Competitive indices (CI) of colony-forming units (CFUs) recovered from co-infected swine explant tissue, either from the total homogenate (open box and whiskers plots), or from tissue washed with gentamicin to kill extracellular and attached cells, which we refer to as the “invaded” intracellular population (checkered box and whisker plots), as indicated. Each data point represents a single experiment of a section of tissue infected with bacteria, and the CI of CFUs recovered from that tissue (n=5). Boxes show median values (line) and upper and lower quartiles, and whiskers show max and min values. Effect size (Cohen’s d) and statistical significance are noted for each experiment in relation to competitive advantage, i.e. deviation from a CI of 1 (not significant, ns; * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001, **** p &lt; 0.0001). See also Figure S1 for disaggregated CFU enumerations for each experimental group prior to CI calculation. Data S1 contains all numerical CFU measurements.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_fig1.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<p>A chemical effector of major importance for enteric bacterial communities is indole, an interbacterial signaling molecule that regulates diverse aspects of physiology and lifestyle <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref></sup>. Indole is excreted by gut microbiota as a byproduct of tryptophan metabolism and accumulates to millimolar levels in human feces (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A-B</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">24</xref></sup>. Indole is amphipathic and can transit bacterial membranes to regulate biofilm formation and motility, suppress virulence programs, and exerts bacteriostatic and bactericidal effects at high concentrations <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">26</xref></sup>. Indole was one of the earliest identified chemorepellents, and subsequent work has extensively explored its role in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> chemotaxis (Table S1) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c27">27</xref></sup>. Recent studies have advanced our understanding of the molecular mechanisms underlying <italic>E. coli</italic> indole taxis and the involvement of the chemoreceptor taxis to serine and repellents (Tsr) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A-B</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref></sup>. From this body of research, the hypothesis emerged that indole from the gut microbiota repels pathogens and restricts their growth as a mechanism of colonization resistance conferred by the microbiome <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref></sup>. If true, this could represent an interesting avenue for cultivating healthy microbiomes more robust against pathogen infiltration. However, indole taxis has only been studied in <italic>E. coli</italic> and no prior work has tested whether human fecal material, the major biological source of indole in the gut, induces frank pathogen chemorepulsion or inhibits pathogen growth at physiologically relevant levels (Table S1).</p>
<p>We were interested in further studying the role of Tsr in navigating contradictory effector stimuli because this chemoreceptor possesses an interesting dual function: it senses chemorepellents and also the amino acid and nutrient L-Ser as a chemoattractant (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A-B</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c30">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">32</xref></sup>. Tsr plays important roles during enteric invasion <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">35</xref></sup>, but questions remain about how the chemoreceptor regulates pathogen colonization in the presence of conflicting signals. We recently mapped the biological distribution of Tsr and reported that many enteric pathogens and pathobionts possess Tsr orthologues, including the genera <italic>Salmonella</italic>, <italic>Citrobacter</italic>, and <italic>Enterobacter</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. Whether these and other bacteria respond to indole as a chemorepellent has remained unclear because all prior studies of indole taxis focused on <italic>E. coli</italic> (Table S1). Prior <italic>in vitro</italic> work with purified effectors showed when both attractants and repellents are present, Tsr facilitates so-called “intermediate” responses between chemoattraction and chemorepulsion, suggesting that, in some cases, navigating conflicting stimuli is regulated at the single chemoreceptor level <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref></sup>. These types of chemotactic compromises, such as those that have been referred to as bet-hedging, trade-off, and simultaneous sensing, remain insufficiently studied, but could be relevant to enteric infections because the gut lumen contains conflicting effectors <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref></sup>. Earlier work posited that bacteria sum conflicting signals and ultimately perform attraction or repulsion responses based on the relative concentrations and sensitivity to the individual effectors, which, if true, would enable straight-forward predictions for behaviors to effector mixtures <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref></sup>. But, this binary model of chemotaxis seems too coarse to explain recent observations of population structures that emerge in response to conflicting signals that are clearly distinct from either attraction or repulsion <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref></sup>.</p>
<p>In this study, we aimed to gain a deeper understanding into how chemotaxis directs bacterial localization to naturally-occurring stimuli that contain conflicting effectors, the types of population structures that arise and their dynamics of formation, and their potential relevance in enteric infections. <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium is a frank pathogen that relies on chemotaxis for enteric infection and employs an array of strategies to compete with the native microbiota for nutrients and colonization niches, ultimately invading the intestinal tissue and becoming intracellular <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c38">38</xref></sup>. <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium also differs fundamentally from <italic>E. coli</italic> because it lacks tryptophanase genes and cannot itself produce indole, and thereby could provide a novel perspective on indole taxis <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">40</xref></sup>. In this study, we used the pathogen <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium as a model system to: (1) test the hypothesis that the microbiota secretion product indole is protective against enteric invasion, (2) investigate if pathogens are repelled by indole-containing fecal material, and (3) learn how the chemoreceptor Tsr regulates pathogen spatial localization in response to conflicting chemotactic stimuli of the intestinal environ. Using live imaging, we directly visualized how enteric pathogen populations dynamically restructure in response to physiological mixtures of attractants and repellents. We demonstrate that chemotaxis responses to natural biological combinations of effectors, and their impacts on infection outcomes, are not easily predicted based on responses to individual effectors alone.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Impact of opposing chemoeffector stimuli on pathogen invasion in swine colonic explants</title>
<p>We sought to test whether indole in human fecal matter protects against <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium infection and whether this involves chemorepulsion mediated by the chemoreceptor Tsr. <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium preferentially invades tissue of the distal ileum, but also infects the cecum and colon <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c41">41</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">44</xref></sup>. We presume the amount of indole is greatest in the lower gastrointestinal tract where tryptophan has been maximally digested by microbiota tryptophanases, and so we developed a swine colonic explant model that mimics the architecture and size of adult human colonic tissue <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c45">45</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c49">49</xref></sup>. We based this model on a prior study of explant tissue used to characterize invasion through gentamicin washes that kill extracellular and attached bacteria <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c50">50</xref></sup>; gentamicin washing is also a commonly-used method to quantify <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium intracellular populations in cell culture experiments <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c52">52</xref></sup>. A section of colonic tissue was prepared for each experiment with gentle cleaning and treated with various effector solutions: solubilized human feces, purified indole and/or L-Ser at fecal-relevant concentrations, or buffer as a control (see Materials &amp; Methods for tissue dimensions and other experiment details). This experimental setup simulates a biological gradient in which the effector concentration is initially highest near the tissue and diffuses outward into the buffer solution.</p>
<p>Following treatment with effectors, the tissue was subsequently exposed to co-infection with wild-type (WT) <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium strain IR715 and either a <italic>cheY</italic> mutant (motile but non-responsive to chemoeffector stimuli) or <italic>tsr</italic> deletion mutant (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C-D</xref>, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref></sup>. The functionality of these mutants have been confirmed through <italic>in vivo</italic> infection studies using genetically complemented strains <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">34</xref></sup>. To assess the role of chemotaxis in infection, we quantified total bacteria harvested from tissue homogenates and also enumerated bacteria following a gentamicin wash, which we presume to reflect bacteria that were intracellular and evaded killing by the gentamicin wash, at 1, 3, and 6 h post-infection (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref>, Materials &amp; Methods) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c54">54</xref></sup>. For buffer-treated explant experiments, WT <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium showed a modest time-dependent advantage in colonization and invasion compared to chemotactic mutants, indicating that chemotaxis, and specifically Tsr, promotes tissue colonization under baseline conditions (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1E</xref>, Fig. S1A-B, Data S1).</p>
<table-wrap id="tbl1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table 1:</label>
<caption><title>Bacterial Strains</title></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_tbl1.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</table-wrap>
<p>The hypothesis that indole protects against pathogen colonization predicts that feces, the major biological repository of gut indole, will protect against invasion. Contrary to this, we found that fecal treatment significantly enhances intracellular invasion of WT <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium (compared to buffer treatment), providing a &gt;100-fold competitive advantage mediated by Tsr (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1F</xref>, Fig. S1C-D). Analysis of the liquified human fecal matter used in this study revealed an indole concentration of 862 µM, consistent with previously reported ranges (0.5–5 mM) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>, Materials &amp; Methods) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c23">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">26</xref></sup>. However, when colonic tissue was treated with purified indole at the same concentration, the competitive advantage of WT over the chemotactic mutants was abolished compared to fecal-treated tissue (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1G</xref>, Fig. S1E-F, Data S1). Given that Tsr mediates attraction to L-Ser for both <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium, we hypothesized that L-Ser present in feces might be responsible for increased colonization of fecal-treated tissue <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c56">56</xref></sup>. However, treatment with 338 µM L-Ser, the concentration present in our fecal sample (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>, Materials &amp; Methods), actually shows a decrease in WT advantage compared to fecal treatment, similar to the effect of indole alone (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1H</xref>, Data S1). While treatments with either indole or L-Ser decrease the WT advantage, total bacterial loads are similar, suggesting that neither effector is “protective” in terms of infection burden (Fig. S1, Data S1). Since both effectors individually alter invasion, but do not on their own recapitulate the efficient invasion phenotype observed with fecal treatment, we then wondered whether the combination of indole and L-Ser might be sufficient. Interestingly, we found that treatment with a mixture of indole and L-Ser effectively neutralized their individual effects, resulting in a response nearly identical to buffer-treated tissue, and the WT advantage observed with fecal treatment was not recapitulated (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1I</xref>, Fig. S1I-J, Data S1).</p>
<p>These results provide insights into the relationship between chemotactic sensing of fecal material and its role in invasion, while also revealing complex behaviors that raise further questions. The key takeaway is that although pure indole reduces WT colonization advantage in a chemotaxis– and Tsr-dependent manner, indole within feces does not elicit the same response, nor does indole-rich fecal material provide protection against invasion in this model (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, Fig. S1). This may be explained by our observation that L-Ser can cancel out the effects of indole (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1G</xref>, <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1I</xref>, Data S1). These findings suggest that the presence of multiple chemical signals within complex biological effector sources can make it challenging to predict chemotactic behavior based on how the bacteria respond to singular effectors.</p>
<p>Curiously, when L-Ser and indole are present together, the magnitude of the WT advantage over the <italic>cheY</italic> and <italic>tsr</italic> mutants resembles a null response (i. e. similar to buffer treatment), rather than providing an additive fitness advantage like occurs with fecal treatment (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, Data S1). One possible explanation is that fecal material contains other metabolites that influence sensing and growth <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c57">57</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c61">61</xref></sup>. Additionally, the WT advantage in the presence of fecal material could relate to Tsr-mediated energy taxis <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">34</xref></sup>, swimming regulation that encourages invasion <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c38">38</xref></sup>, or experimental treatment conditions that may impact bacterial growth. To further investigate these behaviors, the following sections examine chemotactic responses to these treatments and their effects on growth.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2b">
<title>Non-typhoidal S. enterica are attracted to human feces despite high indole content</title>
<p>Having found that Tsr mediates efficient colonic invasion for <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium in our explant system when exposed to fecal material, we next sought to learn what chemotactic behaviors this chemoreceptor orchestrates in response to feces; given that this represents the highest concentration of indole <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium might natively encounter, we expected to observe chemorepulsion (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>, Table S1) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">32</xref></sup>. We employed the chemosensory injection rig assay (CIRA) for live-imaging of bacterial chemotaxis responses to a source of effectors injected through a glass microcapillary <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. The flow and dynamic nature of the gut lumen make this a suitable approach for modeling and studying enteric chemotaxis responses <italic>in vitro</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>.</p>
<p>In this assay, chemoattraction is observed as an influx of cells toward the effector source and chemorepulsion as decreasing cells (Figure S2). As described previously, effector injection introduces a steep microgradient, and, using mathematical modeling of the diffusion of the fecal sources of indole and L-Ser, we can approximate the local concentrations experienced by bacteria at a given distance from the injection source, which for most of the field of view is in the picomolar to low nanomolar range (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>, Materials &amp; Methods) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. Using experiments with fluorescent dye we previously confirmed our calculated local effector concentrations to be in the range of 5-10% within 300 µm of the injection source <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. Further, we showed using a set of controls of buffers at different pH, and chemotaxis mutants, that the low flow-rate of our apparatus (approximately 300 femtoliters per minute) does not itself meaningfully perturb the bacterial population relative to the much larger shifts that occur due to chemotaxis responses <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>.</p>
<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 2.</label>
<caption><title><italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium exhibits attraction toward liquid human fecal material.</title><p>A. Diffusion modeling showing calculated local concentrations in CIRA experiments with liquid human fecal material based on distance from the central injection source. B. Max projections of representative S. Typhimurium IR715 responses to a central source of injected liquid human fecal material. C-E. Bacterial population density over time in response to fecal treatment. The initial uniform population density in these plots is indicated with the blue line (time 0), and the final mean distributions with the red line (time 280 s), with the mean distributions between these displayed as a blue-tored spectrum at 10 s intervals. F-G. Temporal analyses of area under the curve (AUC) or relative number of bacteria within 150 μm of the source. Effect size (Cohen’s d) comparing responses of WT and tsr attraction at 120 s posttreatment is indicated. Data are means and error bars are standard error of the mean (SEM, n=3-5). See also Movie 1, Table S1, and Figure S2.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_fig2.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<p>Over five minutes, we found both WT and <italic>tsr</italic> exhibit strong chemoattraction to fecal material, whereas <italic>cheY</italic> remains randomly distributed (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>, Movie 1). By examining the radial distribution of the bacterial populations, we found WT more tightly centers around the treatment source than <italic>tsr</italic> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C-E</xref>, Movie 1). In terms of the rate of bacterial accumulation, the chemoattraction of <italic>tsr</italic> lags behind the WT for the first 120 s (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2F-G</xref>, Movie 1). We wondered how these deficiencies in fecal attraction might translate to direct competition, where different strains are experiencing the same treatment source simultaneously. To address this, we performed CIRA with solubilized human feces and two strains present in the same pond, which we tracked independently through fluorescent markers (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. As expected, WT shows a strong chemoattraction response versus <italic>cheY</italic> (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>, Movie 2). Interestingly, we found that when competed directly, WT vastly outperforms <italic>tsr</italic>, with the maximal bacterial distribution in proximity to the treatment source higher by about 4-fold (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>, Movie 2). These data confirm that despite its high indole content, <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium is attracted to human fecal material through chemotaxis, and this response involves Tsr, although not as the sole mediator. We expect the attraction of the <italic>tsr</italic> mutant is explained by the fact that <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium possesses other chemoreceptors that detect glucose, galactose, and L-Asp as chemoattractants, which are present in human feces <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c57">57</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c61">61</xref></sup>.</p>
<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 3.</label>
<caption><title>Fecal indole is insufficient for chemorepulsion but indole in isolation is a strong chemorepellent.</title><p>A-E. Dualchannel imaging of chemotactic responses to solubilized human feces by WT S. Typhimurium IR715 (pink) and isogenic mutants or clinical isolate strains (green), as indicated. Shown are max projections at time 295-300 s posttreatment. Data are means and error bars are standard error of the mean (SEM, n=3-5). See also Movies 2-3. F. Representative max projections of responses at 295-300 s of indole treatment. G-H. Quantification of chemorepulsion as a function of indole concentration (n=3-5). I-K. Comparison of WT and tsr mutant responses to L-Ser or indole. See also Fig. S2. L-M. Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) experiments with 50 μM S. Typhimurium Tsr ligand-binding domain (LBD) and indole, or with L-Ser in the presence of 500 μM indole. Data are means and error bars are standard error of the mean (SEM, n=3-5). AUC indicates area under the curve. Scale bars are 100 μm. See also Movies 2-3.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_fig3.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<p>Recent work highlights how genetic diversity among strains and differences in Tsr expression, even within isogenic populations, modulate chemotaxis function <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">35</xref></sup>. To gain a broader perspective on fecal taxis, we examined the responses among diverse <italic>Salmonella</italic> serovars and strains responsible for human infections. Using dual-channel imaging, we compared <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 with a clinical isolate of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium, SARA1, and found both strains exhibit attraction to feces, although SARA1 shows a slightly weaker response (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref>, Movie 3). We then tested a clinical isolate of <italic>S.</italic> Newport, an emerging cause of salmonellosis in the United States and Europe <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c63">63</xref></sup>. This strain is strongly attracted to fecal material, with a tighter accumulation of cells at the treatment source than <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3D</xref>, Movie 3). Lastly, we examined a clinical isolate of <italic>S.</italic> Enteritidis, a zoonotic pathogen commonly transmitted from poultry, which displays weak attraction to fecal material (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3E</xref>, Movie 3) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c63">63</xref></sup>. Overall, we found that chemoattraction to fecal material is conserved among diverse non-typhoidal <italic>Salmonella</italic> serovars responsible for human infections, although the degree of attraction varies. Notably, despite the high indole content in feces, none of the strains tested exhibit chemorepulsion.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2c">
<title>Mediation of opposing chemotactic responses by Tsr</title>
<p>We wondered if our inability to observe repulsion from fecal material might be due to <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium not sensing indole as a chemorepellent, since this chemotactic response has only been previously described for <italic>E. coli</italic> (Table S1). We again employed CIRA to address this question, comparing chemotaxis responses to either 5 mM L-Ser or 5 mM indole, and found that <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium responds rapidly to these two effectors as chemoattractants and chemorepellents, respectively (Fig. S2H-I). Treatment with 5 mM indole, a concentration at the upper end of what occurs in the human gut <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">26</xref></sup>, induces rapid chemorepulsion with the bacteria vacating the region proximal to the source (Fig. S2B). Interestingly, the chemorepulsion response occurs faster than chemoattraction, with a zone of avoidance clearly visible within the first 10 s of indole exposure (Fig. S2I, Movie 4).</p>
<p>We next wondered if perhaps our fecal treatments contained insufficient indole to elicit chemorepulsion from <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium. To identify the effective source concentrations that drive indole chemorepulsion and understand the temporal dynamics of this response, we performed a titration of indole across 0.05-10 mM (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3F</xref>). At all concentrations tested, indole induces chemorepulsion, and the bacteria avoid the treatment source for the duration of the 5-minute experiment (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3F-G</xref>). At source concentrations exceeding 3 mM, essentially all motile cells vacate the field of view within 60 s (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3F-G</xref>). Integrating these chemorepulsion responses and fitting them to a Monad curve suggests an indole source concentration of approximately 67 µM is sufficient for half-maximal (K<sub>1/2</sub>) chemorepulsion (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3H</xref>). These data show that even though we observe strong attraction to fecal material, pure indole at the concentration present in fecal material, and far lower, is indeed a strong chemorepellent for <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium.</p>
<p>Based on its function in <italic>E. coli</italic>, we hypothesized that both indole chemorepulsion and L-Ser chemoattraction for <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium could be partly or fully mediated through Tsr <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c31">31</xref></sup>. We compared the chemotactic responses of the WT and <italic>tsr</italic> strains when exposed to sources of these effectors and found Tsr to be required for both chemorepulsion from indole and chemoattraction to L-Ser (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3I-K</xref>). The canonical mode of chemoreceptor effector recognition involves binding of the effector to the ligand-binding domain (LBD) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c64">64</xref></sup>, but the mechanism by which indole is sensed through Tsr in <italic>Salmonella</italic> has not been elucidated. We recently reported the first crystal structure of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium Tsr LBD, which clearly defines how the binding site recognizes the L-Ser ligand (PDB code: 8fyv), and we thought it unlikely indole can be accommodated at the same site <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. To our knowledge, no prior study has tested whether the Tsr LBD binds indole directly, so we expressed and purified the LBD, corresponding to the soluble periplasmic portion, and performed isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC). These data show that no binding occurs between the Tsr LBD and indole (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3L</xref>).</p>
<p>We next wondered if indole acts as an allosteric regulator of the LBD, possibly through interacting with the L-Ser-bound form or interfering with L-Ser recognition. To address these possibilities, we performed ITC of 50 μM Tsr LBD with L-Ser in the presence of 500 μM indole and observed a robust exothermic binding curve and K<sub>D</sub> of 5 µM, identical to the binding of L-Ser alone (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3M</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. These data indicate that indole does not alter the Tsr LBD affinity for L-Ser. We conclude that Tsr senses indole through an atypical mechanism, which might either involve regulation through a solute-binding protein <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c65">65</xref></sup>, responsiveness to perturbation in the proton motor force <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref></sup>, or binding to a different region other than the periplasmic LBD. Our findings reveal that while indole acts as a chemorepellent for <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium in isolation, sensed through Tsr, its presence within fecal material mixed with other effectors is insufficient to elicit chemorepulsion.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2d">
<title>Compromising between conflicting effector signals through chemohalation</title>
<p>Earlier work with <italic>E. coli</italic> revealed that exposure to mixtures of L-Ser and indole can elicit intermediate chemotactic responses between chemoattraction and chemorepulsion after prolonged exposure (1-6 h, Table S1) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref></sup>. Having confirmed that Tsr in <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium mediates opposing responses to the chemoattractant L-Ser and the chemorepellent indole in isolation, we next sought to learn how the bacterial population behaves on rapid timescales when confronted with physiological combinations of these effectors. To address this, we performed a series of CIRA experiments with 500 µM L-Ser and increasing concentrations of indole at L-Ser:indole molar ratios of 10:1, 1:1, or 1:10 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A-D</xref>, Movie 4).</p>
<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 4.</label>
<caption><title><italic>S</italic>. Typhimurium mediates distinct chemotactic responses based on the ratio of L-Ser to indole.</title><p>A-D. Representative max projections of responses to treatments of L-Ser and indole at 295-300 s, as indicated. Scale bars are 100 μm. E. Relative bacterial distribution in response to treatments of 500 μM L-Ser and varying amounts of indole, from panels A-D, with the mean value normalized to 100%. Data are means and error bars are standard error of the mean (SEM, n=3-5). F. Diffusion modeling of local effector concentrations based on sources of 5 mM indole (dark brown), 500 μM L-Ser (blue), 500 μM indole (light brown), and 50 μM indole (yellow) are shown as dashed lines. The approximate local concentration of indole that elicits a transition in chemotactic behavior is highlighted in light blue. G-H. Bacterial growth as a function of L-Ser or indole, at the time point where the untreated culture reaches A600 of 0.5. I-J. Bacterial growth +/-pretreatment with 500 μM indole or L-Ser, and increasing concentrations of indole or L-Ser, as indicated at the time point where the untreated culture reaches A600 of 0.5. Data are means and error bars are standard error of the mean (SEM, n=8-24).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_fig4.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<p>These experiments reveal a fascinating transition in the distribution of the pathogen population as a function of increasing chemorepellent, which occurs within minutes of exposure (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A-D</xref>, Movie 4). With only chemoattractant present, the bacterial population organizes tightly around the effector source (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>, Movie 4). When indole is introduced at a concentration 10-fold lower than L-Ser, the bacterial distribution still exhibits chemoattraction but becomes more diffuse (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>, Movie 4). At a 1:1 ratio of chemoattractant and chemorepellent, a novel population structure emerges, in which the swimming bacteria are attracted toward the source but form a halo around the treatment with an interior region of avoidance (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4C</xref>, <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4E</xref>, Movie 4). When the concentration of indole is 10-fold higher than L-Ser, the bacteria exhibit a wider zone of avoidance (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D-E</xref>, Movie 4). Interestingly, whereas 5 mM indole on its own induces strong chemorepulsion (Fig. S2I, Movie 4), the addition of 10-fold lower L-Ser effectively converts the behavior to a null response (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D-E</xref>, Movie 4). This demonstrates that even at the highest concentrations of indole <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium might encounter in the gut, the presence of chemoattractant can override indole chemorepulsion.</p>
<p>The intermediate responses to opposing effector mixtures bear similarities to CIRA experiments with fecal material, some of which also exhibited a halo-like structure around the treatment source (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A-E</xref>, Movies 2-3). As mentioned earlier, previous studies have also observed responses that are neither attraction nor repulsion, and they have been referred to by a variety of names. We do not claim here that the responses we observe to mixtures of L-Ser and indole are wholly distinct or unrelated to earlier work <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref></sup>, but to our knowledge, no other study has so clearly captured the spectrum of behaviors that occur in the transition between attraction and repulsion (Movie 4). There exists no consensus term for taxis of this nature, and so we suggest “chemohalation,” in reference to the halo formed by the cell population, and which is congruent with the commonly-used terms chemoattraction and chemorepulsion. We expect chemohalation is a compromise in positional location at the population level between the chemoattraction driven by L-Ser and the chemorepulsion driven by indole. Across these experiments, the interior zone of avoidance roughly corresponds to where the local concentration of indole exceeds 10 nM (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4E</xref>-F). In a biological setting, we presume that the distribution bias orchestrated by chemohalation regulates the probability that cells will colonize, adhere, and transition to sessility at a given site; the greater the local indole content, the wider the zone of avoidance and the less likely tissue invasion occurs.</p>
<p>We questioned why non-typhoidal <italic>Salmonella</italic> are attracted to a biological solution with high amounts of indole, a chemical reported to inhibit bacterial growth <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c66">66</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c67">67</xref></sup>. We examined how bacterial growth is affected by 0-25 mM indole or L-Ser in a background of minimal media (MM, Materials &amp; Methods). As expected, increasing amounts of the nutrient L-Ser provide a growth advantage for all <italic>Salmonella</italic> strains analyzed, with maximal benefit achieved by approximately 500 µM (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4G</xref>). Equivalent treatments with indole show tolerance up to approximately 1 mM, with growth inhibition occurring in the 1-5 mM range and lethality occurring at indole concentrations greater than 5 mM (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4H</xref>). However, adding L-Ser in a background of 500 µM indole provides only a small growth enhancement (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4I</xref>), and addition of 500 µM L-Ser increases tolerance for indole up to about 1 mM, above which indole toxicity is unavoidable (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4J</xref>). So, we conclude that mixtures of these effectors also impact growth differently than the effectors in isolation, and the relative attraction to combinations of these effectors relates to their propensity to enhance or inhibit growth. Overall, the bacteria still obtain growth benefits from L-Ser so long as the concentration of indole is under 1 mM, and we expect this growth advantage is even greater in the presence of the many other nutrients accessible to the bacteria in fecal material.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Bacteria in the human gastrointestinal tract encounter complex chemical landscapes that contain both chemoattractants and chemorepellents. However, chemotaxis responses are often studied in isolation, outside of their biological and ecological contexts, which can lead to an over-or underestimation of the roles specific interactions play in natural settings. In the present work, we contribute to an emerging understanding that bacteria exhibit rapid and well-orchestrated responses to conflicting stimuli distinct from chemoattraction or chemorepulsion, and relate these chemotactic compromises to enteric infection and pathogen growth (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c68">68</xref></sup>. In this study, we provide evidence that despite the microbiota metabolite indole being a strong repellent in isolation, fecal indole is insufficient to elicit pathogen repulsion or protect against invasion.</p>
<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. 5.</label>
<caption><title>A. Working model for chemotactic compromise orchestrated by Tsr during enteric invasion.</title><p>In the intestinal lumen, fecal material contains the nutrient <sub>L</sub>-Ser, derived from digested food, and bacteriostatic indole, secreted by the gut microbiota. Tsr detects these metabolites as chemoattractant (<sub>L</sub>-Ser, dark blue arrows) and chemorepellent (indole, brown arrows) signals, respectively. While <sub>L</sub>-Ser is directly sensed by Tsr via the ligand-binding domain (LBD, yellow), indole is detected through a different mechanism. Tsr integrates these conflicting signals to bias colonization through a behavior termed chemohalation, which promotes taxis toward regions with higher <sub>L</sub>-Ser-to-indole ratios (large blue and brown arrows, width of arrows denotes the degree of colonization bias). Increased indole levels result in a larger central zone of avoidance and greater bias against colonization. B. During early infection, the attractant-to-repellent ratio in the intestinal lumen is high. <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium (gray cells) uses chemotaxis to seek <sub>L</sub>-Ser (dark blue circles) and other nutrients (light blue circles), promoting proliferation. In the presence of abundant nutrients, the bacteria tolerate exposure to indole (brown circles). C. As infection progresses, nutrient consumption by the proliferating bacteria reduces the attractant-to-repellent ratio in the lumen. D. Once nutrients are sufficiently depleted, the bacteria can no longer tolerate indole exposure, and chemorepulsion from indole increases. This repulsion drives bacteria out of the lumen and into contact with the intestinal mucosa, promoting colonic invasion. In the artificial scenario where only <sub>L</sub>-Ser is present, chemotaxis offers little advantage for invasion; the bacteria proliferate, but there is no incentive to leave the lumen. Conversely, with only indole present, chemotaxis similarly provides no advantage; although indole repels the bacteria from the lumen, it inhibits bacterial proliferation. In the presence of <sub>L</sub>-Ser, and likely other attractants, indole repulsion is nullified.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_fig5.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>New insights into indole taxis from a non-E. coli system</title>
<p>Indole is an important and abundant regulator of enteric microbial communities known to modulate motility and virulence and has been proposed to deter pathogen invasion through chemorepulsion <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref></sup>. Previously, no study had addressed whether bacteria other than <italic>E. coli</italic> sense indole as a chemorepellent. In the model system we investigated, we confirm that <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium utilizes the chemoreceptor Tsr to respond to indole as a chemorepellent (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Further, we add to the understanding of indole taxis by having visualized and measured the rapid temporal dimension of indole repulsion, which is relevant in the highly turbulent intestinal environment where bacteria experience shifting and dynamic chemical gradients <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">2</xref></sup>. We found naïve <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium are repelled from indole sources within 10 s of exposure. The rapidity of this response, which exceeds that of attraction to L-Ser, has not been previously reported (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3G</xref>). We also tested whether indole-sensing occurs through the canonical chemoreceptor mechanism of direct binding through the Tsr LBD, which does not seem to occur, nor does antagonism or inhibition of binding of L-Ser to the LBD (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3L-M</xref>). These data support that a non-canonical sensing mechanism is employed by Tsr to respond to indole, as suggested by others <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c65">65</xref></sup>.</p>
<p>Having characterized and confirmed the role of Tsr in indole-sensing for <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium, and shown it to be generally similar to its function in <italic>E. coli</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref></sup>, we can speculate that the diverse bacterial species that possess Tsr orthologues, particularly common among <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>, also sense, and are repelled, by indole, further supporting indole as a key regulator of polymicrobial communities of the gut <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">25</xref></sup>. However, <italic>in vivo</italic> Tsr-mediated indole-sensing is integrated with L-Ser-sensing and responses to other stimuli. As discussed further below, this integration may serve to bias colonization toward specific niches based on the local attractant-to-repellent ratio, rather than triggering the outright repulsion we observe <italic>in vitro</italic> with pure indole sources (Fig, 5). While Tsr appears to function similarly in coordinating indole taxis in both <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium and <italic>E. coli</italic>, its impact on colonization is likely different. Unlike <italic>Salmonella</italic>, <italic>E. coli</italic> produces indole <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">40</xref></sup>, which may allow it to use indole not only to regulate colonization based on microbiota activity but also as a self-sensing signal. This could enable <italic>E. coli</italic> to regulate its dispersal or expansion in response to self-generated indole.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s3b">
<title>Indole taxis amidst opposing stimuli and implications for pathogen invasion</title>
<p>We investigated the chemotaxis behaviors of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium to human fecal material as a test case for how pathogens make decisions when faced with biological sources of effectors that contain a mixture of conflicting stimuli (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). We predicted that feces, rich in indole, would elicit chemorepulsion, inhibit pathogen growth, and protect against infection <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">29</xref></sup>. Instead, we find that chemotactic sensing of human fecal material promotes colonic invasion in an explant model, and liquid feces predominantly elicits chemoattraction or chemohalation (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, Fig. S1, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, Movies 1-S). We also find that while both invasion and chemotaxis are regulated by the presence of the fecal effectors indole or L-Ser alone, these effectors in combination cancel out, leading to a null response (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). These findings help clarify why indole-rich fecal material does not trigger repulsion or prevent invasion. While indole is abundant in feces, it is only one component within a complex biological mixture, and other effectors ultimately mediate chemoattraction or chemohalation to fecal material (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
<p>To better understand how chemotaxis responses change when sensing mixtures of opposing effectors, we examined bacterial behavior <italic>in vitro</italic> in the presence of physiological mixtures of the fecal metabolites indole and L-Ser and captured a series of real-time videos (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A-D</xref>, Movie 4). These videos reveal how, upon sensing the conflicting stimuli, the pathogen population structure rapidly evolves based on the ratio of attractant to repellent, ranging from chemoattraction, diffuse chemoattraction, chemohalation, diffuse chemohalation, and chemorepulsion (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A-D</xref>, <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, Fig. S2, Movie 4). We found particularly interesting the response we refer to as chemohalation, which occurs when the bacteria encounter near equimolar attractant and repellent. Under these conditions, the cells accumulate at a distance from the treatment source and form a halo with an interior zone of avoidance (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, Movie 4). The zone of avoidance apparently increases as a function of increasing indole, thereby biasing cells against colonizing and invading a specific niche (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>). Whereas we observe chemohalation <italic>in vitro</italic> with only two fecal metabolites, we expect this mechanism is at play when the bacteria are selecting among niches in the intestinal lumen, where the indole repulsion signal is integrated alongside information about nutrient attractant signals to ultimately coordinate contact with, and invasion of, intestinal tissue (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s3c">
<title>Potential roles for chemohalation in gastrointestinal infections</title>
<p>The dynamic micron-scale chemohalation population structures, that in effect are a compromise between attraction and repulsion, would be difficult or impossible to detect without directly viewing them through live imaging, which may explain why they were unappreciated earlier in binary models of chemotaxis <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c15">15</xref></sup>. To be clear, we suggest chemohalation as a useful term to generally describe intermediate chemotaxis responses to conflicting stimuli that are neither chemoattraction nor chemorepulsion, but others have also contributed to studying how chemotaxis functions in confounding chemical landscapes <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref></sup>. The chemohalation responses we report here are most similar to what was referred to as a “trade-off” response in a prior study with <italic>E. coli</italic> and attractant-repellent mixtures; interestingly those authors also observed another response termed “bet-hedging” where a portion of the population within an isogenic culture remained attracted despite the presence of the chemorepellent, but we did not observe this behavior in our experiments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">13</xref></sup>. For <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium, the source concentration required for half-maximal responses are similar for the opposing effectors, 105 and 67 µM for L-Ser <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup> and indole, respectively, but the presence of other attractants in feces overall biases behavior toward attraction <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c57">57</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c61">61</xref></sup>.</p>
<p>In the context of non-typhoidal <italic>Salmonella</italic> infections, it is clear there exists complex relationships between chemotactic sensing of effectors, bacterial growth, and invasion. As it pertains specifically to sensing the opposing effectors L-Ser and indole, we propose that Tsr functions to measure the ratio of exogenous attractant to repellent, and, through chemohalation, orchestrates an appropriate spatial bias in the population. Ultimately, this serves to improve pathogen fitness through colonizing niches rich in nutrients, signaled by local L-Ser concentrations, while avoiding niches with high microbial competition, indicated by local indole concentrations (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Chemorepulsion from indole can be overridden by the presence of chemoattractants, and <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium growth is quite tolerant of indole within physiological ranges, suggesting the bacteria generally prioritize nutrient acquisition over the inhibitory effects of indole (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). This agrees with the premise that nutrient-seeking, rather than avoidance of toxins, may generally be the major function of chemotaxis <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">18</xref></sup>. We expect that the distinction between chemoattraction and chemohalation, in terms of regulating colonization and infection outcomes, also depends on the duration of stimuli exposure and adaptation <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">12</xref></sup>. Based on data from colonic explant experiments, chemotaxis studies, and growth analyses, we propose a new model describing how the opposing signals from L-Ser and indole are sensed and integrated by Tsr to mediate pathogen invasion (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). In addition to sensing of these two effectors, our data support that Tsr and chemotaxis are involved in L-Ser and indole-independent functions in the presence of fecal material that mediate colonization (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). This could potentially relate to other characterized functions of Tsr in redox and energy taxis and/or biasing swimming toward a running phenotype, which is associated with increased invasion <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c38">38</xref></sup>.</p>
<p>Recently, we reported on <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> chemotactic sensing of blood serum, another complex biological effector source at the host-pathogen interface, and those responses appear to involve chemohalation <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. Evidence of chemohalation is also seen in the case of the gastric pathogen <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> responding to mixtures of urea, a chemoattractant, and acid, a chemorepellent <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c69">69</xref></sup>. Continuing to investigate chemohalation behaviors and understanding how they coordinate bacterial colonization may provide important insights into how chemotaxis confers fitness advantages in natural environments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s3d">
<title>Limitations of this study</title>
<p>This study provides insights into the roles of chemotaxis in <italic>Salmonella</italic> responses to fecal material and indole; however, several limitations should be considered. First, our experiments were conducted <italic>in vitro</italic> and utilized swine tissue explants, which do not fully capture the complexities of <italic>in vivo</italic> infection dynamics in the human gut. Additionally, while explant assays provided insight into how chemotaxis relates to tissue colonization, these experiments exhibited variability. To mitigate this, we used multiple sections of tissue from a single animal to exert greater experimental control of the system, but this approach limits our ability to assess how host tissue diversity might influence bacterial responses. It would be interesting to assess invasion using tissue of the distal ileum, a major site of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium invasion, which is known to have distinct chemical cues and foreseeably differences in indole and L-Ser <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c41">41</xref></sup>. Another experimental limitation is the difference in timescales between our assays. Chemotaxis experiments were conducted over short time frames, whereas tissue explant experiments required longer incubation periods for significant differences in colonization and invasion to be observed. Lastly, while we confirmed that non-typhoidal <italic>Salmonella</italic> are attracted to human fecal material, we only determined the dependency on Tsr in our model strain (IR715). Although we expect that other WT clinical isolates also rely on chemotaxis and Tsr for attraction, this remains uncertain without targeted genetic analyses in each strain background.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s4">
<title>Materials &amp; Methods</title>
<p>All methods were carried out in accordance with relevant guidelines, regulations, and state and federal law. Experimental protocols were approved by the Institutional Biosafety Committee (IBC) of Washington State University (#1372).</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title>
<p>Bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study are listed in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. As previously described <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>, bacteria intended for chemotaxis assays were grown overnight in tryptone broth (TB) with antibiotic selection, as appropriate. Motile bacteria were prepared with a 1:1000 back-dilution and grown shaking for approximately 4 hours at 37°C to reach A<sub>600</sub> of 0.5. Cells were centrifuged, washed, and resuspended in a chemotaxis buffer (CB) containing 10 mM potassium phosphate (pH 7), 10 mM sodium lactate, and 100 µM EDTA to A<sub>600</sub> of 0.2 and rocked gently at room temperature until fully motile. For <italic>in vitro</italic> growth analyses, cultures were grown overnight in Lysogeny Broth (LB) at 37°C. Subsequently, 5 µl of A<sub>600</sub> 2.0 cells were used to inoculate 200 µl of minimal media (MM), containing 47 mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 22 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 8 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.4% glucose (w/v) 11.35 mM (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 100 μM CaCl<sub>2</sub> and L-Ser and/or indole at the described concentrations, and cultured in a 96-well microtiter plate. Cultures were grown at 37°C and monitored by A<sub>600</sub> readings at 5-minute intervals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4b">
<title>Chemosensory injection rig assay (CIRA)</title>
<p>CIRA was performed as described previously <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. Briefly, an Eppendorf Femtotip 2 microcapillary containing the treatment of interest was lowered into a pond of 50 µl of motile cells using a Sutter micromanipulator. An injection flow of effector into the pond at approximately 300 fl per minute was achieved using a Femtojet 4i set to P<sub>c</sub> 35. Solubilized fecal treatments were prepared by dissolving 1 g of commercially obtained human feces (Lee Biosolutions) in 10 ml of CB. The solution was clarified by centrifugation at 10,000 g for 20 minutes, followed by sterile filtration through a 0.2 µm filter. Treatment solutions of indole and L-Ser were also diluted into CB and sterile-filtered before application. Videos were recorded using an inverted Nikon Ti2 microscope with heated sample chamber at 37 °C.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4c">
<title>CIRA microgradient modeling</title>
<p>Modeling the microgradient generated through CIRA was performed as described earlier <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>, based on the continual injection and diffusion of an effector from a fixed-point source. Briefly, diffusion is modeled as a 3D process where the diffusing substance is gradually and continuously introduced at a fixed point within a large surrounding fluid volume. The substance is prepared at a concentration of <italic>M</italic><sub>s</sub> (typically between 0.5 µM and 5 mM) and injected at a volume rate of <italic>Q</italic> = 305.5 fl/min. The species then diffuses into the ambient fluid with a diffusion constant <italic>D</italic>:
<disp-formula>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_ueqn1.gif" mime-subtype="gif" mimetype="image"/>
</disp-formula>
Here, <italic>r</italic> is the distance from the point source, <italic>t</italic> is the time from initial injections, <italic>q</italic> is the injection rate of the species (equal to <italic>M</italic><sub>s</sub><italic>Q</italic>), and <italic>C</italic> is the species concentration. In earlier work <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>, we reported using fluorescent dye that the concentrations predicted by this model appear to be accurate within 5% in the range of 70-270 µm from the source, whereas at distances less than 70 µm the measured concentrations are about 10% lower than predicted. At the point where the effector treatment is injected into the larger volume the local concentration drops precipitously, hence why the concentration reported at distance 0 is not that of the concentration within the microcapillary.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4d">
<title>Isothermal titration calorimetry ligand binding studies (ITC)</title>
<p>Purification of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium Tsr LBD was performed as described previously <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. ITC experiments were performed using a Microcal ITC200 instrument (GE Healthcare). Either 500 μM indole or L-Ser was titrated in 2.5 μL injections into a 200 μL sample cell containing 50 μM Tsr LBD. For the indole/L-Ser competition experiment, 500 μM indole was added to both the titrant and sample cell, thus providing a constant excess background concentration of indole. For all experimental conditions, blank titrations were also collected in which indole or L-Ser was titrated into a cell containing buffer alone. All experiments were performed using thoroughly degassed samples at 25 °C in 50 mM Tris, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, pH 7.5. The reference power was set to 5 μcal/sec. The resulting power curves were integrated using the Origin analysis software included with the instrument. The heat of dilution was subtracted from each point using the blank. A single-site binding model was then fit to the data, floating parameters describing the binding enthalpy (ΔH), equilibrium constant (K<sub>D</sub>), and apparent binding stoichiometry (n). The instrument software was used for this purpose.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4e">
<title>Quantification of indole and serine in human fecal samples</title>
<p>Solubilized human feces was prepared as described above for CIRA and analyzed by mass spectrometry to determine the molar serine content as a service through the University of Washington Mass Spectrometry Center. This measurement reflects total serine, of which close to 100% is expected to be L-Ser <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. As described in earlier work, the indole content of solubilized human fecal samples was determined using a hydroxylamine-based calorimetric assay with purified indole as a reference and standard <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c72">72</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4f">
<title>Explant infection assays</title>
<p>Swine intestinal tissue was acquired from the descending colon of an 8-week-old animal, pursuant to animal protocol ASAF #7128, approved through the Washington State University IACUC. Before infection, the luminal side of an approximately 20 by 20 mm piece of swine intestinal explant tissue was gently washed with PBS to remove fecal matter. Next, the tissue section was bathed in 2 ml of chemoeffector solution (solubilized human fecal matter (Lee Biosolutions), a mixture of 338 µM L-Ser and 862 µM indole, 338 µM L-Ser alone, 862 µM indole alone, or chemotaxis buffer) in a 6-well tissue culture plate (Celltreat) and incubated at 4°C for 1 h. Then, tissue was transferred to a 35 mm Mattek dish where the luminal side of the tissue was exposed to a bacterial solution containing a 1:1 mixture (10<sup>9</sup> CFU each) of WT <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 and either the isogenic <italic>tsr</italic> or <italic>cheY</italic> mutant, suspended in CB at a volume of 300 µl. The tissue was then incubated in the dish with the competing bacteria at 37 °C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 1, 3, or 6 h. After, half of the tissue was transferred into screwcap tubes containing 500 µl LB media and 5-10 2.3 mm zirconia beads (BioSpec Products) on ice and homogenized using a Bead Mill 24 (Fisher Scientific) at 6.5 m/s for 60 s, repeated four times. To enumerate the intracellular bacteria, the other half of the tissue was washed in PBS and incubated in PBS containing 100 µg/ml gentamicin for 1 h at 37 °C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, then washed twice in PBS, as done previously <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c73">73</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c74">74</xref></sup>. The homogenization process was then repeated for the gentamicin-treated tissue. CFUs were enumerated by plating 10-fold dilutions on LB agar plates containing the appropriate antibiotic <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c75">75</xref></sup>. Competitive index values were calculated by dividing the number of mutant CFUs by the number of WT CFUs for each treatment and time point <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c76">76</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c77">77</xref></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4g">
<title>Quantification of CIRA data</title>
<p>Videos of chemotactic responses were quantified as described previously <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. The number of cells in each frame were calculated by determining a fluorescence intensity ratio per cell for frames pre-treatment and extrapolated using the ‘plot profile’ function of ImageJ. The distribution of the bacteria was calculated using the Radial Profile ImageJ plugin. Local background subtraction was performed based on experiments with the non-chemotactic <italic>cheY</italic> strain to control for autofluorescence in solubilized fecal samples.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4h">
<title>Statistical Analyses</title>
<p>Competitive indices (CIs) for explant experiments were calculated for each treatment group at each time point. Log-transformed CI values were obtained by taking the logarithm (log<sub>10</sub>) of the original CI measurements. These log-transformed values were then subjected to statistical analysis. First, a one-sample t-test was performed to determine whether the mean of the log-transformed CIs significantly differed from zero. In cases where the assumption of normality was violated, the non-parametric Wilcoxon rank sum test was applied as an alternative. Effect size was assessed using Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> and calculated using the same log-transformed CIs.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="s8">
<title>Supplementary tables and figures</title>
<table-wrap id="tbls1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Table S1.</label>
<caption><title>Summary of prior studies related to indole chemotaxis, related to <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.</title><p><sup>a</sup> Source concentration, or ranges, used in experiment.</p><p><sup>b</sup> The motility or chemotactic response as reported by the study authors; note that some methods employed may not be able to distinguish between responses as a consequence bacterial growth versus chemotaxis.</p><p><sup>c</sup> The assay may have limitations in its ability to report on either rapid temporal responses, or localization to or from an effector source.</p><p><sup>d</sup> In this work, we refer to behaviors of this type as “chemohalation” to be similar to the widely-used terms chemoattraction and chemorepulsion.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_tbls1.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="figs1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. S1.</label>
<caption><title>Colony-forming units (CFU) recovered from swine colonic explant infections, related to <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.</title><p>Shown are disaggregated CFU enumerations for each co-infection experiment with <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 WT and mutant strains following tissue treatments, as indicated. CFUs extracted either using the entire tissue homogenate (total) or extracted from tissue treated with a gentamicin wash to kill exterior non-invaded cells (invaded) are noted separately (see Materials &amp; Methods). Each data point represents CFUs recovered from a single explant experiment (n=5). Box and whisker plots represent the sample median (line), the edges are the upper and lower quartiles, and whiskers extend to the max and min values. The limit of detection was 1 x 10<sup>5</sup> CFUs. Samples with no CFUs detected are noted on the plot at this limit.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_figs1.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
<fig id="figs2" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Fig. S2.</label>
<caption><title>Chemotactic responses to L-Ser or indole, related to <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>.</title><p>A. CIRA experimental design. B. CIRA microgradient diffusion model, simulated with a source of 1.13 mM A488 dye after 30 s of injection. Image rendered on a pink (100% source concentration)-blue-black (0%) color intensity scale, based on previous work <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">1</xref></sup>. C. CIRA quantification overview, with blue lines corresponding to chemoattraction, null chemotactic response corresponding to gray dashed lines, and chemorepulsion corresponding to brown lines. D-G. Microgradient models of the local effector concentration for treatments with 5 mM L-Ser or indole, respectively, at Δ300 s. Color gradient corresponds to gradually decreasing effector concentrations from yellow to blue. H-I. Representative 10 s max projections of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 response to sources of L-Ser (strong chemoattraction) or indole (strong chemorepulsion) using CIRA. The glass microcapillary that injects the treatment solution is centered within the field of view. Note that cells contain a plasmid expressing mPlum (see Materials &amp; Methods), and fluorescence data are collected in the far-red channel, so the glass microcapillary is poorly visible.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="576330v3_figs2.tif" mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>Funding for this research was provided by NIAID through awards 1K99AI148587 and 4R00AI148587-03, and funding from the College of Veterinary Medicine at Washington State University to AB. Bacterial strains were provided by Nikki Shariat (University of Georgia, Athens), Nkuchia Mikanatha and Pennsylvania NARMS and GenomeTrakr Programs, and Andreas Bäumler (University of California, Davis). All research on human and animal samples was performed in accordance with, and approval of, the Institutional Biosafety Committee and Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at Washington State University.</p>
</ack>
<sec id="d1e1884" sec-type="additional-information">
<title>Additional information</title>
<sec id="s5">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p>K.F. performed the microgradient modeling and explant experiments. A.B. conducted the CIRA experiments and purification of Tsr-LBD. Z.G. performed bacterial growth experiments. M.S. and</p>
<p>M.J.H. performed the ITC experiments. All authors contributed to data analyses and writing of the manuscript.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="suppd1e1884" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Additional files</title>
<supplementary-material id="d1e1875">
<label>Data S1</label>
<caption>
<title>Enumeration of colony-forming units (CFUs) from explant studies.</title>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="supplements/576330_file07.xlsx"/>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="video1">
<label>Movie 1.</label>
<caption>
<title>Chemotactic response of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 to solubilized human feces, related to <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>.</title>
<p>Representative CIRA experiments showing <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 WT and mutant strains responding to a source over 300 s (shown at 10x speed)</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="576330v3_video1.mp4" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4"/>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="video2">
<label>Movie 2.</label>
<caption>
<title>Chemotactic response of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 WT and chemotactic mutant strains to solubilized human feces, related to <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>.</title>
<p>Representative CIRA experiments showing competition between <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 (mPlum) and <italic>cheY</italic>, or <italic>tsr</italic>, as indicated (GFP), over 300 s.</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="576330v3_video2.mp4" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4"/>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="video3">
<label>Movie 3.</label>
<caption>
<title>Chemotactic response of <italic>S. enterica</italic> clinical isolates to solubilized human feces, related to <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>.</title>
<p>Representative CIRA experiments showing competition between <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 (mPlum) and clinical isolates, as indicated (GFP), responding to a source of solubilized human feces over 300 s.</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="576330v3_video3.mp4" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4"/>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="video4">
<label>Movie 4.</label>
<caption>
<title>Chemotactic response of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium IR715 to L-Ser and indole treatments, related to <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> and Figure S2.</title>
<p>Representative CIRA experiments with treatment sources as indicated, over 300 s.</p>
</caption>
<media xlink:href="576330v3_video4.mp4" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="c1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Glenn</surname>, <given-names>S. J.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Bacterial vampirism mediated through taxis to serum</article-title>. <source>eLife</source> <volume>12</volume>, <elocation-id>RP93178</elocation-id> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szymanski</surname>, <given-names>C. M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Baylink</surname>, <given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial chemotaxis in human diseases</article-title>. <source>Trends in Microbiology</source> <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Keegstra</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrara</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Stocker</surname>, <given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The ecological roles of bacterial chemotaxis</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source> (<year>2022</year>) doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00709-w</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Sourjik</surname>, <given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Stimulus sensing and signal processing in bacterial chemotaxis</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Microbiology</source> <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Matilla</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Krell</surname>, <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of bacterial chemotaxis on host infection and pathogenicity</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiology Reviews</source> <volume>42</volume>, (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Matilla</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gavira</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Krell</surname>, <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Accessing nutrients as the primary benefit arising from chemotaxis</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Microbiology</source> <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>102358</fpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Matilla</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Krell</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group> <article-title>Chemoreceptor-based signal sensing</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Biotechnology</source> <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ortega</surname>, <given-names>Á.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhulin</surname>, <given-names>I. B.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Krell</surname>, <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Sensory Repertoire of Bacterial Chemoreceptors</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source> <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>e00033</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>, <given-names>A. W. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsolis</surname>, <given-names>R. M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Bäumler</surname>, <given-names>A. J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Salmonella versus the Microbiome</article-title>. <source>Microbiology and Molecular Biology Reviews</source> <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>e00027</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vos</surname>, <given-names>W. M. de</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tilg</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hul</surname>, <given-names>M. V.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Cani</surname>, <given-names>P. D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> <article-title>Gut microbiome and health: mechanistic insights</article-title>. <source>Gut</source> <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>1020</fpage>–<lpage>1032</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hill</surname>, <given-names>J. H.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>BefA, a microbiota-secreted membrane disrupter, disseminates to the pancreas and increases β cell mass</article-title>. <source>Cell Metabolism</source> <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1779</fpage>–<lpage>1791.e9</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Biphasic chemotaxis of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to the microbiota metabolite indole</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source>. <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>6114</fpage>–<lpage>6120</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Livne</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Vaknin</surname>, <given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Collective responses of bacteria to a local source of conflicting effectors</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source> <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>4928</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Keller</surname>, <given-names>E. F.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Segel</surname>, <given-names>L. A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Traveling bands of chemotactic bacteria: A theoretical analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source> <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage> (<year>1971</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Adler</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Tso</surname>, <given-names>W.-W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>‘Decision’-Making in Bacteria: Chemotactic Response of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to Conflicting Stimuli</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>184</volume>, <fpage>1292</fpage>–<lpage>1294</lpage> (<year>1974</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Escape band in Escherichia coli chemotaxis in opposing attractant and nutrient gradients</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>116</volume>, <fpage>2253</fpage>–<lpage>2258</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kalinin</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neumann</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sourjik</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>, <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Responses of Escherichia coli Bacteria to Two Opposing Chemoattractant Gradients Depend on the Chemoreceptor Ratio</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source> <volume>192</volume>, <fpage>1796</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Englert</surname>, <given-names>D. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manson</surname>, <given-names>M. D.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Jayaraman</surname>, <given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Flow-Based Microfluidic Device for Quantifying Bacterial Chemotaxis in Stable, Competing Gradients</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>4557</fpage>–<lpage>4564</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>J. Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sweeney</surname>, <given-names>E. G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guillemin</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Amieva</surname>, <given-names>M. R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple Acid Sensors Control Helicobacter pylori Colonization of the Stomach</article-title>. <source>PLOS Pathogens</source> <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>e1006118</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>, <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>New Insights Into Gut-Bacteria-Derived Indole and Its Derivatives in Intestinal and Liver Diseases</article-title>. <source>Front. Pharmacol</source>. <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>769501</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>J.-H.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Indole as an intercellular signal in microbial communities</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source> <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gupta</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Indole modulates cooperative protein–protein interactions in the flagellar motor</article-title>. <source>PNAS Nexus</source> <volume>1</volume>:<elocation-id>pgac035</elocation-id> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Darkoh</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chappell</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonzales</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Okhuysen</surname>, <given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A Rapid and Specific Method for the Detection of Indole in Complex Biological Samples</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>8093</fpage>–<lpage>8097</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chappell</surname>, <given-names>C. L.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Fecal Indole as a Biomarker of Susceptibility to Cryptosporidium Infection</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>2299</fpage>–<lpage>2306</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ye</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Dual Role of Indoles Derived From Intestinal Microbiota on Human Health</article-title>. <source>Front. Immunol</source>. <volume>13</volume>, <issue>903526</issue> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Sperandio</surname>, <given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Indole Signaling at the Host-Microbiota-Pathogen Interface</article-title>. <source>mBio</source> <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e01031</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bansal</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Differential Effects of Epinephrine, Norepinephrine, and Indole on Escherichia coli O157:H7 Chemotaxis, Colonization, and Gene Expression</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>4597</fpage>–<lpage>4607</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kohli</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>The microbiota metabolite indole inhibits Salmonella virulence: Involvement of the PhoPQ two-component system</article-title>. <source>PLOS One</source> <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>e0190613</fpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nikaido</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Effects of indole on drug resistance and virulence of Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium revealed by genome-wide analyses</article-title>. <source>Gut Pathog</source> <volume>4</volume>, <issue>5</issue> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Piñas</surname>, <given-names>G. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeSantis</surname>, <given-names>M. D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cassidy</surname>, <given-names>C. K.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Parkinson</surname>, <given-names>J. S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Hexameric rings of the scaffolding protein CheW enhance response sensitivity and cooperativity in Escherichia coli chemoreceptor arrays</article-title>. <source>Science Signaling</source> <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>eabj1737</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Burt</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Complete structure of the chemosensory array core signalling unit in an E. coli minicell strain</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>743</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sourjik</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Lai</surname>, <given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Discovery of a New Chemoeffector for Escherichia coli Chemoreceptor Tsr and Identification of a Molecular Mechanism of Repellent Sensing</article-title>. <source>ACS Bio Med Chem Au</source> <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>386</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rivera-Chávez</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Salmonella Uses Energy Taxis to Benefit from Intestinal Inflammation</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source> <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e1003267</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rivera-Chávez</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Energy Taxis toward Host-Derived Nitrate Supports a Salmonella Pathogenicity Island 1-Independent Mechanism of Invasion</article-title>. <source>mBio</source> <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e00960</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gül</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Salmonella T3SS-2 virulence enhances gut-luminal colonization by enabling chemotaxis-dependent exploitation of intestinal inflammation</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source> <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>113925</fpage> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Winter</surname>, <given-names>S. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lopez</surname>, <given-names>C. A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Bäumler</surname>, <given-names>A. J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The dynamics of gut-associated microbial communities during inflammation</article-title>. <source>EMBO Reports</source> <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Winter</surname>, <given-names>S. E.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Gut inflammation provides a respiratory electron acceptor for Salmonella</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>467</volume>, <fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>, <given-names>K. G.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Regulatory protein HilD stimulates Salmonella Typhimurium invasiveness by promoting smooth swimming via the methyl-accepting chemotaxis protein McpC</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> <volume>12</volume>, <issue>348</issue> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vega</surname>, <given-names>N. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allison</surname>, <given-names>K. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samuels</surname>, <given-names>A. N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klempner</surname>, <given-names>M. S.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Collins</surname>, <given-names>J. J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title><italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> intercepts <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> signaling to enhance antibiotic tolerance</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source>. <volume>110</volume>, <fpage>14420</fpage>–<lpage>14425</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Roager</surname>, <given-names>H. M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Licht</surname>, <given-names>T. R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial tryptophan catabolites in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>3294</fpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chowdhury</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pavinski Bitar</surname>, <given-names>P. D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chapman</surname>, <given-names>H. M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Altier</surname>, <given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Salmonella Invasion Is Controlled by Competition among Intestinal Chemical Signals</article-title>. <source>mBio</source> <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>e00012</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ehrhardt</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Grassl</surname>, <given-names>G. A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mouse Model to Study Salmonella-Induced Colitis</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source> <volume>2427</volume>, <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Grassl</surname>, <given-names>G. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valdez</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bergstrom</surname>, <given-names>K. S. B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vallance</surname>, <given-names>B. A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Finlay</surname>, <given-names>B. B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic enteric salmonella infection in mice leads to severe and persistent intestinal fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> <volume>134</volume>, <fpage>768</fpage>–<lpage>780</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Radlinski</surname>, <given-names>L. C.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Salmonella virulence factors induce amino acid malabsorption in the ileum to promote ecosystem invasion of the large intestine</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>e2417232121</fpage> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kronsteiner</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Helicobacter pylori Infection in a Pig Model Is Dominated by Th1 and Cytotoxic CD8 <sup>+</sup> T Cell Responses</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>3803</fpage>–<lpage>3813</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>A. C.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Swindle</surname>, <given-names>M. M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Preparation of Swine for the Laboratory</article-title>. <source>ILAR Journal</source> <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>358</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Poutahidis</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title><italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> –induced Gastritis in Experimentally Infected Conventional Piglets</article-title>. <source>Vet Pathol</source> <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>678</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boyen</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Porcine <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> models to assess the virulence of <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium for pigs</article-title>. <source>Lab Anim</source> <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boyen</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Coated fatty acids alter virulence properties of Salmonella Typhimurium and decrease intestinal colonization of pigs</article-title>. <source>Veterinary Microbiology</source> <volume>132</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Köppen</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Ex vivo infection model for Francisella using human lung tissue</article-title>. <source>Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol</source>. <volume>13</volume>, (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bomjan</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>, <given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>YshB Promotes Intracellular Replication and Is Required for Salmonella Virulence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source> <volume>201</volume>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.00314-19</pub-id> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Birhanu</surname>, <given-names>B. T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>, <given-names>N.-H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>S.-J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hossain</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Park</surname>, <given-names>S.-C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Inhibition of Salmonella Typhimurium adhesion, invasion, and intracellular survival via treatment with methyl gallate alone and in combination with marbofloxacin</article-title>. <source>Veterinary Research</source> <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>MacBeth</surname>, <given-names>K. J.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>C. A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prolonged inhibition of bacterial protein synthesis abolishes Salmonella invasion</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>1544</fpage>–<lpage>1546</lpage> (<year>1993</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sharma</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Puhar</surname>, <given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Gentamicin Protection Assay to Determine the Number of Intracellular Bacteria during Infection of Human TC7 Intestinal Epithelial Cells by Shigella flexneri</article-title>. <source>Bio-protocol</source> <volume>9</volume>, (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kitamoto</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Dietary l-serine confers a competitive fitness advantage to Enterobacteriaceae in the inflamed gut</article-title>. <source>Nature Microbiology</source> <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sugihara</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Kamada</surname>, <given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of dietary L-serine in the regulation of intestinal mucus barrier during inflammation</article-title>. <source>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</source> <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>S42</fpage>–<lpage>S42</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ranque</surname>, <given-names>C. L.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Examination of Carbohydrate Products in Feces Reveals Potential Biomarkers Distinguishing Exclusive and Nonexclusive Breastfeeding Practices in Infants</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source> <volume>150</volume>, <fpage>1051</fpage>–<lpage>1057</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ke</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Tong</surname>, <given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal glucose excretion: A potential mechanism for glycemic control</article-title>. <source>Metabolism</source> <volume>152</volume>, <fpage>155743</fpage> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Larke</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Dietary Intake of Monosaccharides from Foods is Associated with Characteristics of the Gut Microbiota and Gastrointestinal Inflammation in Healthy US Adults</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Nutrition</source> <volume>153</volume>, <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shen</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Asparagine, colorectal cancer, and the role of sex, genes, microbes, and diet: A narrative review</article-title>. <source>Front Mol Biosci</source> <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>958666</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yoo</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title><italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium expansion in the inflamed murine gut is dependent on aspartate derived from ROS-mediated microbiota lysis</article-title>. <source>Cell Host &amp; Microbe</source> <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>887</fpage>–<lpage>899.e6</lpage> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shariat</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Subtyping of Salmonella enterica Serovar Newport Outbreak Isolates by CRISPR-MVLST and Determination of the Relationship between CRISPR-MVLST and PFGE Results</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source> <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>2328</fpage>–<lpage>2336</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ferrari</surname>, <given-names>R. G.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Worldwide Epidemiology of <italic>Salmonella</italic> Serovars in Animal-Based Foods: a Meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>e00591</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gavira</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>How Bacterial Chemoreceptors Evolve Novel Ligand Specificities</article-title>. <source>mBio</source> <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e03066</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Matilla</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ortega</surname>, <given-names>Á.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Krell</surname>, <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of solute binding proteins in signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Computational and Structural Biotechnology Journal</source> <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1786</fpage>–<lpage>1805</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chimerel</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Field</surname>, <given-names>C. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Piñero-Fernandez</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keyser</surname>, <given-names>U. F.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Summers</surname>, <given-names>D. K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Indole prevents Escherichia coli cell division by modulating membrane potential</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1818</volume>, <fpage>1590</fpage>–<lpage>1594</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Melander</surname>, <given-names>R. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minvielle</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Melander</surname>, <given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Controlling bacterial behavior with indole-containing natural products and derivatives</article-title>. <source>Tetrahedron</source> <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>6363</fpage>–<lpage>6372</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Moore</surname>, <given-names>J. P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kamino</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kottou</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimizu</surname>, <given-names>T. S.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Emonet</surname>, <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Signal integration and adaptive sensory diversity tuning in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> chemotaxis</article-title>. <source>Cell Systems</source> <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>628</fpage>–<lpage>638.e8</lpage> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>J. Y.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Chemodetection and Destruction of Host Urea Allows Helicobacter pylori to Locate the Epithelium</article-title>. <source>Cell Host &amp; Microbe</source> <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Khan</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Trentham</surname>, <given-names>D. R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Biphasic Excitation by Leucine in Escherichia coli Chemotaxis</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>186</volume>, <fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Beltran</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Reference collection of strains of the Salmonella typhimurium complex from natural populations</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Microbiology</source> <volume>137</volume>, <fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage> (<year>1991</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sugihara</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <article-title>Mucolytic bacteria license pathobionts to acquire host-derived nutrients during dietary nutrient restriction</article-title>. <source>Cell Reports</source> <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>111093</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chandra</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> <article-title>Gentamicin Protection assay (Intracellular Survival Assay) for Salmonella Typhimurium/Typhi</article-title> <source>protocols.io</source>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17504/protocols.io.b4zmqx46/v1</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rivera Calo</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rubinelli</surname>, <given-names>P. M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Ricke</surname>, <given-names>S. C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> <article-title>Gentamicin Susceptibility and Comparison of Adhesion and Invasion of Caco-2 and HD11 Cell Lines by Salmonella enterica Serotypes</article-title>. <source>Applied Sciences</source> <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>3305</fpage> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ben-David</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Davidson</surname>, <given-names>C. E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimation method for serial dilution experiments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Microbiological Methods</source> <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Macho</surname>, <given-names>A. P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zumaquero</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ortiz-Martín</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Beuzón</surname>, <given-names>C. R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> <article-title>Competitive index in mixed infections: a sensitive and accurate assay for the genetic analysis of <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> – plant interactions</article-title>. <source>Molecular Plant Pathology</source> <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>450</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Auerbuch</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lenz</surname>, <given-names>L. L.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Portnoy</surname>, <given-names>D. A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a competitive index assay to evaluate the virulence of Listeria monocytogenes actA mutants during primary and secondary infection of mice</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>5953</fpage>–<lpage>5957</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<sub-article id="sa0" article-type="editor-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106261.1.sa4</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>eLife Assessment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Antunes</surname>
<given-names>Caetano</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Kansas</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Lawrence</city>
<country>United States of America</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="evidence-strength">
<kwd>Solid</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="claim-importance">
<kwd>Valuable</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>In this manuscript, Franco and colleagues describe <bold>valuable</bold> findings about the chemotactic response of Salmonella to serine and indole, conflicting chemotactic signals. Although the evidence presented is <bold>solid</bold>, concerns were raised about the novelty of the chemotactic phenomena observed with these two compounds. Also, although the induction of invasion by feces is a novel and interesting finding, the lack of follow-up to this observation was also noted.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa1" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106261.1.sa3</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #1 (Public review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>The study shows, perhaps surprisingly, that human fecal homogenates enhance the invasiveness of Salmonella typhimurium into cells of a swine colonic explant. This effect is only seen with chemotactic cells that express the chemoreceptor Tsr. However, two molecules sensed by Tsr that are present at significant concentrations in the fecal homogenates, the repellent indole and the attractant serine, do not, either by themselves or together at the concentrations in which they are present in the fecal homogenates, show this same effect. The authors then go on to study the conflicting repellent response to indole and attractant response to serine in a number of different in vitro assays.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>The demonstration that homogenates of human feces enhance the invasiveness of chemotactic Salmonella Typhimurium in a colonic explant is unexpected and interesting. The authors then go on to document the conflicting responses to the repellent indole and the attractant serine, both sensed by the Tsr chemoreceptor, as a function of their relative concentration and the spatial distribution of gradients.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>The authors do not identify what is the critical compound or combination of compounds in the fecal homogenate that gives the reported response of increased invasiveness. They show it is not indole alone, serine alone, or both in combination that have this effect, although both are sensed by Tsr and both are present in the fecal homogenates. Some of the responses to conflicting stimuli by indole and serine in the in vitro experiments yield interesting results, but they do little to explain the initial interesting observation that fecal homogenates enhance invasiveness.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa2" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106261.1.sa2</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #2 (Public review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>The manuscript presents experiments using an ex vivo colonic tissue assay, clearly showing that fecal material promotes Salmonella cell invasion into the tissue. It also shows that serine and indole can modulate the invasion, although their effects are much smaller. In addition, the authors characterized the direct chemotactic responses of these cells to serine and indole using a capillary assay, demonstrating repellent and attractant responses elicited by indole and serine, respectively, and that serine can dominate when both are present. These behaviors are generally consistent with those observed in E. coli, as well as with the observed effects on cell invasion.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>The most compelling finding reported here is the strong influence of fecal material on cell invasion. Also, the local and time-resolved capillary assay provides a new perspective on the cell's responses.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>The weakness is that indole and serine chemotaxis does not seem to control the fecal-mediated cell invasion and thus the underlying cause of this effect remains unclear.</p>
<p>In addition, the fact that serine alone, which clearly acts as a strong attractant, did not affect cell invasion (compared to buffer) is somewhat puzzling. Additionally, wild-type cells showed nearly a tenfold advantage even without any ligand (in buffer), suggesting that factors other than chemotaxis might control cell invasion in this assay, particularly in the serine and indole conditions. These observations should probably be discussed.</p>
<p>Final comment. As shown in reference 12, Tar mediates attractant responses to indole, which appear to be absent here (Figure 3J). Is it clear why? Could it be related to receptor expression?</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa3" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106261.1.sa1</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #3 (Public review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>In this manuscript, Franco and colleagues describe careful analyses of Salmonella chemotactic behavior in the presence of conflicting environmental stimuli. By doing so, the authors describe that this human pathogen integrates signals from a chemoattractant and a chemorepellent into an intermediate &quot;chemohalation&quot; phenotype.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>The study was clearly well-designed and well-executed. The methods used are appropriate and powerful. The manuscript is very well written and the analyses are sound. This is an interesting area of research and this work is a positive contribution to the field.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>Although the authors do a great job in discussing their data and the observed bacterial behavior through the lens of chemoattraction and chemorepulsion to serine and indole specifically, the manuscript lacks, to some extent, a deeper discussion on how other effectors may play a role in this phenomenon. Specifically, many other compounds in the mammalian gut are known to exhibit bioactivity against Salmonella. This includes compounds with antibacterial activity, chemoattractants, chemorepellers, and chemical cues that control the expression of invasion genes. Therefore, authors should be careful when making conclusions regarding the effect of these 2 compounds on invasive behavior. It is important that the word invasion is used in the manuscript only in its strictest sense, the ability displayed by Salmonella to enter non-phagocytic host cells. With that in mind, authors should discuss how other signals that feed into the control of Salmonella invasion can be at play here.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa4" article-type="author-comment">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106261.1.sa0</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response:</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Franco</surname>
<given-names>Kailie</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4719-225X</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gentry-Lear</surname>
<given-names>Zealon</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0350-7494</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shavlik</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0395-8578</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harms</surname>
<given-names>Michael J</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0241-4122</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baylink</surname>
<given-names>Arden</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5522-769X</contrib-id></contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>We thank the reviewers of this manuscript for their thoughtful and detailed feedback, and agree that they bring up valid points. We also thank them for their suggestions on how to improve this study. We intend to revise this manuscript to help address these concerns and in the future will submit a revised version that will hopefully be improved in terms of the clarity of the text and rigor of the experimental findings.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
</article>