<?xml version="1.0" ?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.3 20210610//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>eLife</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">106484</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106484</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi" specific-use="version">10.7554/eLife.106484.2</article-id>
<article-version-alternatives>
<article-version article-version-type="publication-state">reviewed preprint</article-version>
<article-version article-version-type="preprint-version">1.2</article-version>
</article-version-alternatives>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Biochemistry and Chemical Biology</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories><title-group>
<article-title>Coupled equilibria of dimerization and lipid binding modulate SARS Cov 2 Orf9b interactions and interferon response</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2695-5951</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>San Felipe</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Batra</surname>
<given-names>Jyoti</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9401-0397</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Muralidharan</surname>
<given-names>Monita</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Malpotra</surname>
<given-names>Shivali</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Anand</surname>
<given-names>Durga</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bauer</surname>
<given-names>Rachel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2238-8590</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Verba</surname>
<given-names>Kliment A</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6119-6084</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Swaney</surname>
<given-names>Danielle L</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4902-337X</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Krogan</surname>
<given-names>Nevan J</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3509-5997</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Grabe</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref>
<email>michael.grabe@ucsf.edu</email>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5080-2859</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Fraser</surname>
<given-names>James S</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
<email>jfraser@fraserlab.com</email>
</contrib>
<aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/043mz5j54</institution-id><institution>Department of Bioengineering and Therapeutic Sciences, University of California, San Francisco</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>San Francisco</city>, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
<aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/043mz5j54</institution-id><institution>Quantitative Biosciences Institute, University of California San Francisco</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>San Francisco</city>, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
<aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/038321296</institution-id><institution>Gladstone Institute of Data Science and Biotechnology, J. David Gladstone Institutes</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>San Francisco</city>, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
<aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/043mz5j54</institution-id><institution>Department of Cellular and Molecular Pharmacology, University of California San Francisco</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>San Francisco</city>, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
<aff id="a5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/043mz5j54</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, University of California San Francisco</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>San Francisco</city>, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="section">
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Sohn</surname>
<given-names>Jungsan</given-names>
</name>
<role>Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Baltimore</city>
<country country="US">United States</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="senior_editor">
<name>
<surname>Dötsch</surname>
<given-names>Volker</given-names>
</name>
<role>Senior Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Goethe University Frankfurt</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Frankfurt am Main</city>
<country country="DE">Germany</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="coi-statement"><p>Competing interests: The Krogan Laboratory has received research support from Vir Biotechnology, F. Hoffmann-La Roche, and Rezo Therapeutics. Nevan Krogan has a financially compensated consulting agreement with Maze Therapeutics. Nevan is the President and is on the Board of Directors of Rezo Therapeutics, and he is a shareholder in Tenaya Therapeutics, Maze Therapeutics, Rezo Therapeutics, GEn1E Lifesciences, and Interline Therapeutics. J.S.F. is a consultant to, shareholder of, and receives sponsored research support from Relay Therapeutics. Michael Grabe is a developer for Berkeley Madonna.
</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date date-type="original-publication" iso-8601-date="2025-05-07">
<day>07</day>
<month>05</month>
<year>2025</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date date-type="update" iso-8601-date="2025-08-12">
<day>12</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2025</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<elocation-id>RP106484</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="sent-for-review" iso-8601-date="2025-02-27">
<day>27</day>
<month>02</month>
<year>2025</year>
</date>
</history>
<pub-history>
<event>
<event-desc>Preprint posted</event-desc>
<date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2025-02-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>02</month>
<year>2025</year>
</date>
<self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.02.16.638509"/>
</event>
<event>
<event-desc>Reviewed preprint v1</event-desc>
<date date-type="reviewed-preprint" iso-8601-date="2025-05-07">
<day>07</day>
<month>05</month>
<year>2025</year>
</date>
<self-uri content-type="reviewed-preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.106484.1"/>
<self-uri content-type="editor-report" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.106484.1.sa2">eLife Assessment</self-uri>
<self-uri content-type="referee-report" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.106484.1.sa1">Reviewer #1 (Public review):</self-uri>
<self-uri content-type="referee-report" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.106484.1.sa0">Reviewer #2 (Public review):</self-uri>
</event>
</pub-history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2025, San Felipe et al</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>San Felipe et al</copyright-holder>
<ali:free_to_read/>
<license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
<license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-preprint-106484-v2.pdf"/>
<abstract>
<title>Abstract</title><p>Open Reading Frame 9b (Orf9b), an accessory protein of SARS-CoV and -2, is involved in innate immune suppression through its binding to the mitochondrial receptor Translocase of Outer Membrane 70 (Tom70). Previous structural studies of Orf9b in isolation revealed a β-sheet-rich homodimer, however, structures of Orf9b in complex with Tom70 revealed a monomeric helical fold. Here, we developed a biophysical model that quantifies how Orf9b switches between these conformations and binds to Tom70, a requirement for suppressing the type 1 interferon response. We used this model to characterize the effect of lipid binding and mutations in variants of concern to the Orf9b:Tom70 equilibrium. We found that the binding of a lipid to the Orf9b homodimer biases the Orf9b monomer:dimer equilibrium towards the dimer by reducing the dimer dissociation rate ∼100-fold. We also found that mutations in variants of concern can alter different microscopic rate constants without significantly affecting binding to Tom70. Together our results highlight how perturbations to different steps in these coupled equilibria can affect the apparent affinity of Orf9b to Tom70, with potential downstream implications for interferon signaling in coronavirus infection.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="funding-1">
<funding-source>
<institution-wrap>
<institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01cwqze88</institution-id>
<institution>National Institutes of Health</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
<award-id>GM145238</award-id>
</award-group>
</funding-group>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta specific-use="meta-only">
<meta-name>publishing-route</meta-name>
<meta-value>prc</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<fn-group content-type="summary-of-updates">
<title>Summary of Updates:</title>
<fn fn-type="update"><p>In this revised version, we have strengthened the quantitative modeling by including additional sensitivity analyses and residual plots, added clarification on the kinetic and structural interpretations, and expanded our discussion of limitations and alternative hypotheses. We have also updated figures and supplemental materials to enhance clarity and transparency.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Activation of the innate immune system is a critical step to defending host cells from pathogens such as viruses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c41">Takeuchi and Akira 2009</xref>). One feature of the innate immune system is the activation of the interferon response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c40">Stetson and Medzhitov 2006</xref>). Upon viral infection, viral RNA is detected in the cytosol through intracellular MDA5/RIG-I like receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c34">Pichlmair et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c20">Kang et al. 2002</xref>) which triggers the localization of the mitochondrial antiviral signaling (MAVS) protein to the mitochondrial outer membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c37">Seth et al. 2005</xref>). At the membrane, MAVS functions as a scaffold for the recruitment of additional adaptor proteins that promote the activation of transcription factors such as IRF3 that localize to the nucleus and drive the expression of innate immune genes such as IFN-β (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c37">Seth et al. 2005</xref>) inducing an antiviral state. A prominent feature of both SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 is that viral infection triggers a weak type 1 interferon response (IFN-I) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c3">Blanco-Melo et al. 2020</xref>). Several studies have illustrated the roles of both viral non-structural and accessory proteins in antagonizing different aspects of the innate immune response during viral infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c44">Wang et al. 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c13">Han et al. 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c9">Felgenhauer et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c38">Shemesh et al. 2021</xref>; Y. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c27">Liu et al. 2021</xref>).</p>
<p>Open Reading Frame 9b (Orf9b) is a 11kDa protein encoded through an alternative open reading frame within the N gene of both SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2. Orf9b localizes to the outer mitochondrial membrane during SARS-CoV and 2 infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">Meier et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Gordon et al. 2020</xref>). Large scale interactome profiling of SARS-CoV-2 proteins identified the mitochondrial import receptor Tom70 (Translocase of Outer Membrane 70) as interacting with Orf9b (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Gordon et al. 2020</xref>). As part of the TOM complex, Tom70 facilitates translocation of cytoplasmic proteins across the mitochondrial outer membrane and the biogenesis of mitochondrial membrane proteins in a chaperone dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">Backes et al. 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">2021</xref>). In addition, Tom70 has also been identified as an important adaptor that binds MAVS and TBK1 leading to the induction of IFN-b (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">Lin, Paz, and Hiscott 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c45">Wei et al. 2015</xref>; X.-Y. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">Liu et al. 2010</xref>). Both SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 Orf9b have been shown to bind to Tom70 during infection and this is sufficient to suppress the IFN response in the absence of additional viral factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">Jiang et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Gordon et al. 2020</xref>). Therefore, Tom70 is an important target for Orf9b mediated suppression of the innate immune response.</p>
<p>Tom70 possesses two distinct binding sites: a large C-terminal groove for the binding of amphipathic helices that form Mitochondrial Targeting Sequences (MTS) (Young, Hoogenraad, and Hartl 2003; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">Backes et al. 2018</xref>) and an N-terminal chaperone binding site that recognizes the EEVD motif of Hsp70/90 (Young, Hoogenraad, and Hartl 2003). The loss (either by truncation or mutation) of either of these binding sites impairs the import of proteins to the mitochondria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">Backes et al. 2021</xref>). In the context of IFN signaling, the loss of the chaperone binding site is sufficient to suppress IFN signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">Lin, Paz, and Hiscott 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c45">Wei et al. 2015</xref>; X.-Y. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">Liu et al. 2010</xref>). Cyro-EM and X-ray structures of SARS-CoV-2 Orf9b:Tom70 showed Orf9b as a monomeric amphipathic helix bound to Tom70 at the C-terminal MTS binding site in a 1:1 interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Gordon et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">Gao et al. 2021</xref>). This was surprising because the crystal structures of both SARS-CoV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">Meier et al. 2006</xref>) and SARS-CoV-2 ((<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Jin et al. 2022</xref>) 7YE7, 7YE8, and unpublished structure 6Z4U) show Orf9b adopting a β-sheet-rich homodimer. This suggests that there is an equilibrium between the two Orf9b conformations (monomeric LJ-helix and β-sheet homodimer), but it is not clear how this equilibrium relates to IFN suppression or is regulated during viral infection.</p>
<p>X-ray and Cryo-EM structures of the Orf9b:Tom70 complex show that a key residue in the N-terminal chaperone binding site of Tom70 (R192) is displaced which was hypothesized to impair binding of chaperones during IFN signaling. This allosteric conformational change is relevant because the kinase TBK1 binds to Tom70 in an Hsp90 dependent manner and is necessary for phosphorylation of the transcription factor IRF3 (X.-Y. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">Liu et al. 2010</xref>). The loss of Tom70 or its chaperone binding ability through point mutation is sufficient to produce a loss in interferon signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">Lin, Paz, and Hiscott 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c45">Wei et al. 2015</xref>; X.-Y. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">Liu et al. 2010</xref>). In vitro studies have shown that when Orf9b is pre-bound to Tom70, peptides of the chaperone EEVD motif have a reduced affinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">Gao et al. 2021</xref>). However, the pre-binding of Hsp70 to the chaperone motif does not inhibit binding of MTS-containing substrates to the C-terminal domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c33">Mills et al. 2009</xref>). Two groups have separately reported that the Orf9b:Tom70 complex formed by co-expressing the two proteins together (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Gordon et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">Gao et al. 2021</xref>). Further, both reported that incubating separately purified Orf9b and Tom70 does not result in complex formation. These data suggested a model where Orf9b expressed alone purified as a very stable homodimer with no ability to form a complex when incubated with Tom70 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Gordon et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">Gao et al. 2021</xref>). Given that Tom70-binding results in a suppression of type 1 IFN, it is unclear how Orf9b homodimers (which do not directly bind to Tom70) affect viral replication.</p>
<p>The existence of two distinct folding conformations and oligomeric states suggests that Orf9b is in a complex equilibrium between homodimer and monomer states. Two copies of Orf9b can homodimerize, or, each Orf9b monomer can bind to a single Tom70, which leads to the suppression of IFN signalling. The final equilibrium between Orf9b homodimer and Orf9b:Tom70 can be regulated by the host cell in at least two distinct ways. First, Orf9b can be phosphorylated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">Bouhaddou et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">Thorne et al. 2022</xref>) at S53 by a host kinase which prevents binding to Tom70, restoring IFN signaling. Second, crystal structures of the Orf9b homodimer show a hydrophobic central channel that runs the length of the dimer that is occupied by a lipid-like ligand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">Meier et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Jin et al. 2022</xref>). This led to an initial characterization of the Orf9b homodimer as a membrane binding protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">Gao et al. 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">Meier et al. 2006</xref>) with subsequent work showing that lipids co-purified with recombinantly expressed Orf9b in both E.coli and mammalian cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Jin et al. 2022</xref>). The lipid-bound homodimer is very stable and seems to not readily dissociate into monomers to bind Tom70 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Gordon et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">Gao et al. 2021</xref>). Previous efforts to isolate the lipid-free Orf9b homodimer by refolding purified protein from inclusion bodies using E.coli expression systems suggested that the lipid remains tightly associated during purification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Jin et al. 2022</xref>). Presumably, the stability afforded by lipid-binding biases the equilibrium towards the homodimeric state, which does not directly bind to Tom70. However, the potential regulatory role of lipid binding to Orf9b during viral infection is unknown.</p>
<p>In addition, Orf9b has acquired mutations at both the protein and RNA level through several variants of concern (VOC) (J. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c49">Yang et al. 2023</xref>), however, none of the coding mutations have been characterized for their effect on either affinity for Tom70 or on homodimer stability. Assigning a functional role to these mutations is complicated by the fact that Orf9b is encoded through an alternative open reading frame within the nucleocapsid (N) gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c36">Rota et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c29">Marra et al. 2003</xref>). Thus, whether these mutations have an effect on Orf9b’s role in innate immune suppression or are selected due to their effect on nucleocapsid function is unknown. Mutations that regulate the expression of Orf9b have been shown to result in an increase in the expression of Orf9b at both the transcriptomic and protein levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">Thorne et al. 2022</xref>; J. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c49">Yang et al. 2023</xref>) which also leads to more potent suppression of IFN signaling. This result suggests that increases in Orf9b expression and coding mutations could alter the monomer:dimer equilibrium, and consequently interferon signalling.</p>
<p>In this work, we developed a series of ordinary differential equations (ODE) that describe the complex equilibrium between Orf9b oligomerization status and binding to Tom70. We experimentally identified model parameters for the coupled equilibrium using both surface plasmon resonance (SPR) and a fluorescent polarization peptide displacement assay that we developed. We used this model to characterize the effect of lipid-binding and mutations present in VOC on Orf9b homodimer stability. We observed that mutations to Orf9b can either slow or accelerate the time to reach equilibrium, but do not greatly affect the affinity of the interaction between Orf9b and Tom70. In contrast, we found that lipid binding strongly shifts the equilibrium towards the dimer and slows Orf9b binding to Tom70 by stabilizing the Orf9b homodimer in vitro. In summary, our model can provide biophysical insights into mutation and ligand-based shifts in the Orf9b monomer:dimer equilibrium, which has downstream implications for understanding the course of interferon signaling in coronavirus infection</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Orf9b derived peptides inform on the monomer:Tom70 equilibrium</title>
<p>The existence of two distinct structures suggests that Orf9b is in equilibrium between a dimeric and monomeric form. From this equilibrium, two copies of Orf9b homodimerize or one copy of Orf9b can bind to Tom70 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). We started developing a biophysical model by considering a monomeric intermediate state as Orf9b undergoes conformational transitions between its LJ-helical Tom70 binding form and its β-sheet-rich homodimer form. To constrain this model, we first measured the equilibrium between Tom70 and the Orf9b monomer binding.</p>
<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 1:</label>
<caption><title>Peptides of Orf9b can be used to model the behavior of monomeric Orf9b to Tom70</title>
<p>A. Initial model of the Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium.</p><p>B. (Left) Schematic of SPR binding interaction between Tom70 and Orf9b peptide. (Right) Surface plasmon resonance sensorgram of Orf9b peptide binding to immobilized Tom70 (orange) with model fits (black) showing kinetics and dissociation constant.</p><p>C. (Left) Schematic of SPR binding interaction between Tom70 and Orf9b-FITC. (Right) Surface plasmon resonance sensorgram of Orf9b-FITC peptide binding to immobilized Tom70 (green) with model fits (black) showing kinetics and dissociation constant.</p><p>D. (Left) Diagram of Orf9b-Tom70 fluorescent polarization assay. (Right) Model ODE (solid lines) overlaid with Orf9b peptide competition kinetics (circles) and model parameters used to generate results.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="638509v2_fig1.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>We used a previously characterized peptide for Orf9b that retains the residues that form the helix to bind Tom70, but does not have the core residues needed to form the β-sheet-rich homodimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">Gao et al. 2021</xref>). This peptide represents approximately ⅓ of the full length Orf9b sequence and can be used as a proxy for studying the behavior of the monomeric Orf9b intermediate. We determined the rate constants of the peptide Orf9b monomer binding to Tom70 with surface plasmon resonance (SPR) using immobilized Tom70 and the Orf9b peptide as the analyte. Global fitting of the Orf9b peptide:Tom70 binding curves resulted in a K<sub>D</sub> of 653±2 nM (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). These fits were associated with kinetic rates of k<sub>on</sub> = 6.2×10<sup>4</sup> M<sup>-1</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> and k<sub>off</sub> = 4.1×10<sup>-2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup>, however, the fitting procedure used by our SPR setup does not generate individual error estimates for these rates. The Orf9b peptide:Tom70 association rate was much slower than the diffusion limit which may suggest that a conformational change occurs either by the peptide when adopting the helical conformation or by Tom70 to open up the C-terminal binding site.</p>
<p>As a complementary method for measuring Orf9b binding to Tom70, we appended a C-terminal fluorescein fluorophore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c11">Gao et al. 2021</xref>) to the Orf9b peptide (Orf9b-FITC) to measure changes in fluorescence polarization (FP) upon Tom70 binding. When the probe is bound to Tom70, the slower tumbling of the Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 complex results in emission of more polarized light compared to the isolated Orf9b-FITC in solution. When the unlabeled Orf9b peptide is added to the pre-equilibrated Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 solution as a competitor, the polarization decreases. This decrease could be used to indirectly measure the time it takes for the Orf9b monomer to reach equilibrium with Tom70. First we verified Orf9b-FITC binding to Tom70 using the same SPR format as the Orf9b peptide. Globally fitting a 1:1 Langmuir binding model to Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 resulted in a K<sub>D</sub> of 288±1nM with kinetic rates k<sub>on</sub> = 7.4×10<sup>4</sup> M<sup>-1</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> and k<sub>off</sub> = 2.1×10<sup>-2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>). Next, we used FP to orthogonally determine the probe’s affinity for Tom70 by titrating Tom70 against a fixed concentration of Orf9b-FITC. Fitting with a 1:1 binding model yielded a K<sub>D</sub> of 240±7nM (Figure 1 - figure supplement 1A), which is in good agreement with the SPR result and suggests that the FITC moiety slightly favors binding relative to the unlabeled peptide.</p>
<p>To further confirm that the fluorophore strengthened the interaction with Tom70, we competed unlabeled Orf9b peptide against the pre-equilibrated Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 complex. In this mode, the affinity of the unlabeled peptide can be determined by titrating it against a fixed concentration of the pre-equilibrated Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 solution by measuring the decrease in polarization signal upon displacement of Orf9b-FITC by unlabeled Orf9b peptide. We fit a one-site competitive binding model to this dataset, which yielded a K<sub>i</sub> of 880±5nM which is consistent with the SPR measurement of the K<sub>D</sub> for Orf9b peptide:Tom70 (Figure 1 - figure supplement 1B). As a negative control, we used an Orf9b peptide with an S53E phosphomimetic mutation (Figure 1-figure supplement 2B). S53 on Orf9b is positioned deep within the C-terminal Tom70 binding site and has been shown to undergo phosphorylation in cells infected with SARS-CoV-2 ((<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c4">Bouhaddou et al. 2020</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c5">2023</xref>) - Figure 1 - figure supplement 2A). As expected, we did not see any decrease in FP signal confirming that the S53E mutation directly blocks Orf9b from binding Tom70 (Figure 1 - figure supplement 2C).</p>
<p>With the long term goal of expanding to a kinetic model that incorporates Orf9b dimerization, we wanted to assess the agreement with the rates measured by SPR and the competition experiment. We used Berkeley Madonna to construct a series of differential equations that describe the time evolution of the binding of unlabeled peptide to Tom70 and concomitant displacement of Orf9b-FITC. The model was fit to the Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 concentration time series data (abbreviated as “[PT]” for Orf9b probe:Tom70), which decreases over time as the unlabeled Orf9b peptide saturates Tom70. We converted the polarization values from our assay to concentrations of the Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 fluorescent complex (see methods) and derived the following differential equations, which were used to model the experimental data (where all bracketed values are concentrations):
<list list-type="order">
<list-item><p>d[Orf9b-FITC]/dt=-k1[Orf9b-FITC][Tom70]+k2[Orf9b-FITC:Tom70]</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>d[Orf9b peptide:Tom70]/dt=k5[Orf9b peptide][Tom70]-k6[Orf9b peptide:Tom70]</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>d[Orf9b peptide]/dt=-k5[Orf9b peptide][Tom70]+k6[Orf9b peptide:Tom70]</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>d[Tom70]/dt=-k1[Orf9b-FITC][Tom70]-k5[Orf9b peptide][Tom70]+k6[Orf9b peptide:Tom70]+k2[Orf9b-FITC:Tom70]</p></list-item>
</list>
We used the on and off rates determined from the SPR experiments as initial model parameters and then manually adjusted the rates to achieve the closest agreement with the 100µM peptide condition. With the parameter set obtained from the 100µM condition, we then held all parameters fixed and simply changed the peptide concentrations in the model to fit the remaining conditions by hand. We note that this process saw the model parameter values change between 3% at the lowest end up to 70% at the highest end from the experimentally derived values but remained within an order of magnitude of the experimental SPR values. We speculate that this arises due to the differences in experimental setup between SPR and FP-based methods of measuring kinetics. The solutions generated from the model closely match the experimental data (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>) suggesting that the model parameters used describe our other conditions where only the concentration of the peptide changes. While methods exist for predicting confidence intervals (CIs) on parameter estimates generated from ODE analysis, such as bootstrapping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">Joshi, Seidel-Morgenstern, and Kremling 2006</xref>), they are computationally demanding and often only produce questionable confidence estimates for ODEs that are often difficult to interpret (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c22">Kreutz, Raue, and Timmer 2012</xref>). As an alternative to attempting to place CIs on the parameters, we performed sensitivity analysis to determine which parameters the model was most sensitive to (see methods and Figure 1 - figure supplemental 3). Additionally, we note that the model parameters were derived from the fit of only one concentration (100uM), but fit the other concentrations equally well. We observed that the model parameter that was most sensitive to change was the rate of Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 ([PT]) dissociation when subjected to a 10% increase or decrease whereas all other model parameters showed no sensitivity to change (Figure 1 - Supplemental 3). This analysis, coupled with inspection of the residuals, provides strong support for the accuracy of the model and the fitted parameters.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2b">
<title>A refolding procedure to generate lipid-free Orf9b homodimers</title>
<p>Crystal structures of the Orf9b homodimer for both SARS-CoV ((<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">Meier et al. 2006</xref>), PDB 2CME) and SARS-CoV-2 ((<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Jin et al. 2022</xref>) 7YE7, 7YE8, and unpublished structure 6Z4U) show a central channel that is formed by the two copies of the Orf9b homodimer. Within the central channel, there is additional electron density that has been modeled as either a linear alkane or polyethylene glycol (PEG). Presumably, an alkane could bind in the expression organism and persist during the purification, whereas the PEG would bind from crystallization conditions that include it as a precipitant. However, additional structures of the Orf9b homodimer show the same density in crystallization conditions that lack PEGs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Jin et al. 2022</xref>), PDB: 7YE7 and 7YE8). This suggests that the additional density within the Orf9b homodimer central channel does not arise from the crystallization conditions, but rather from the expressing organisms and are retained during the purification of the protein. Indeed, mass spectrometry suggests that recombinantly purified Orf9b binds lipids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Jin et al. 2022</xref>). We hypothesized that the binding of lipids to the Orf9b homodimer could stabilize the homodimer and prevent dissociation into monomeric Orf9b. This stabilization could explain previous observations that separately purified Orf9b homodimer and Tom70 do not readily form an Orf9b:Tom70 complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Gordon et al. 2020</xref>).</p>
<p>To test this idea, we attempted to isolate the lipid-free Orf9b homodimer by performing a denaturing and refolding purification process (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). We note that our approach has key differences from the previous efforts by Jin et al., who refolded recombinantly expressed Orf9b isolated from inclusion bodies in E.coli expression systems. Their crystal structure (PDB ID: 7YE8) still shows clear density within the hydrophobic central channel, supporting the placement of an 8-carbon alkane. Unlike Jin et al., we purified Orf9b in the presence of Guanidine HCl and detergent so that the Orf9b isolated by nickel column chromatography was completely denatured. This step ensures the loss of co-purifying lipids prior to refolding. The SEC elution profile and retention volume of refolded Orf9b directly overlapped with natively folded homodimeric Orf9b with the early eluting peaks corresponding to either a chaperone-bound species (natively folded) or misfolded protein (refolded) as judged by SDS-PAGE (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). Together, the overlap in elution peaks corresponding to the folded homodimer suggested a high recovery of the homodimer from the refolding conditions.</p>
<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 2:</label>
<caption><title>The Orf9b homodimer can be refolded to eliminate a co-purifying lipid</title>
<p>A. Schematic of Orf9b denaturing purification, refolding, and tag-cleavage process.</p><p>B. Size exclusion chromatography chromatogram overlay of WT natively folded (black) and WT refolded (blue) Orf9b homodimer. Both proteins purify as a dimer and have identical retention volumes indicating high recovery of refolded Orf9b homodimer.</p><p>C. Structural overlay of WT Orf9b homodimer (green-PDB 6Z4U) and WT refolded Orf9b homodimer (magenta/gray-PDB 9MZB).</p><p>D. Zoomed in view of the natively folded Orf9b homodimer central channel. 2Fo-Fc (contoured to 1σ) and Fo-Fc (+/-3σ) density maps show continuous density that supports the placement of a ligand in the dimer central channel.</p><p>E. Zoomed in view of the refolded Orf9b homodimer central channel: 2Fo-Fc (1σ) and Fo-Fc (+/-3σ) density maps show diffuse peaks within the central channel of the refolded Orf9b homodimer</p><p>F. Deconvolved native mass spectra of refolded and natively folded Orf9b homodimers in negative-polarity mode. Lipid-bound homodimers are observed only in the natively folded sample. Both preparations display +60 Da and +257 Da adducts of unknown origin.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="638509v2_fig2.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2c">
<title>Crystal structure of refolded Orf9b homodimer reveals that lipid stabilizes the dimer, but is not essential for its formation</title>
<p>The electron density assigned to the lipid molecule is in a central channel between the two chains of the Orf9b homodimer. This channel is approximately 22Å in length and lined with primarily hydrophobic residues. The potential for complementary hydrophobic interactions with the lipid along the channel led us to hypothesize that such interactions could stabilize the Orf9b homodimer, biasing the Orf9b monomer:dimer equilibrium. To further confirm that the refolding process resulted in an Orf9b homodimer, we crystallized the refolded homodimer and determined a 2.8Å structure (Table 1). We performed molecular replacement using the WT reference structure and observed that the refolded homodimer structure closely aligned with the lipid-bound reference structure which shows that the homodimer fold can be recovered after denaturing (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>). Aligning the structure of the Orf9b homodimer (PDB 6Z4U) with our structure of the refolded Orf9b homodimer (9N55) in Pymol resulted in an RMSD of 1.1Å. Further, we also searched our structures of the refolded Orf9b homodimer on the Dali server against the existing structures of the lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer which yielded a Z-score of 2.2 which shows good correspondence between the structures.Compared to the reference PDB structure, we were also able to resolve one of two disordered loops, which is likely due to the refolded homodimer crystallizing in a different crystal form and space group than the reference structure.</p>
<p>As we hypothesized, when we inspected the central channel of the refolded homodimer we did not observe significant electron density in the central hydrophobic channel to support the placement of the lipid but did observe some diffuse density peaks in both the Fo-Fc and 2Fo-Fc maps (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2E</xref>). Given that our crystallization conditions contained glycine and the SEC buffer contained glycerol, we attempted to model different buffer components into the density peaks. We also crystallized natively purified Orf9b to generate electron density maps that we could compare to the refolded homodimer. The natively purified Orf9b homodimer had clear density in the central channel just like the existing structures which supported modeling of an 8-carbon alkane (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D</xref>, Table 1). We generated Polder maps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">Liebschner et al. 2017</xref>) for both the natively folded lipid-bound structure as well as the refolded structure with either glycine or an 8-carbon alkane (representing the lipid) model to confirm that the diffuse electron density in the refolded homodimer was not due to lipid density being obscured by the bulk solvent mask. For the natively folded structure, the Polder maps clearly supported the presence of an 8-carbon alkane (Figure 2-figure supplement 2A), however, for the refolded structure, Polder maps did not support the placement of the 8-carbon alkane (Figure 2 - figure supplement 2B). We next modeled glycine into one of the density peaks and noted a good fit with little residual difference density (Figure 2 - figure supplement 2C). Therefore, we conclude that the remaining density peaks in the channel are likely attributed to noise or crystallization buffer components. These results also suggest that the lipid-binding is not necessary for Orf9b dimerization; however, we cannot definitively rule out the possibility that the presence of lipids can also induce Orf9b dimerization.</p>
<p>We speculate that the reason why our structure of the refolded Orf9b homodimer lacks density to support lipid placement, but the refolded structure of Jin et al. has density consistent with a lipid is due to differences in methods for refolding the homodimer. We differed from Jin et al. by purifying in the presence of strong denaturant to ensure that co-purifying lipids could not remain bound whereas Jin et al. purified from inclusion bodies. Purifying from inclusion bodies may not result in fully unfolded protein and may contain enough lipid-bound homodimers to produce clear lipid density when resolved by X-ray crystallography.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2d">
<title>Native Mass Spectrometry reveals lipid species bound to Orf9b homodimers</title>
<p>Next, we utilized native mass spectrometry to confirm lipid binding to Orf9b homodimer. The deconvoluted native mass spectra revealed that the natively folded Orf9b exhibits unique peaks at +332 and +358 Da, which are absent in the refolded sample (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2F</xref>). To characterize the bound lipids, we performed a lipid extraction on the natively folded Orf9b homodimer purified from E. coli and analyzed the resulting lipids by mass spectrometry. The MS and MS/MS of the extracted lipids confirmed that the bound lipids are 1-palmitoyl-sn-glycerol (MG 16:0) or 1-stearoyl-sn-glycerol (MG 18:0) (Figure 2 - supplemental 2A). These assignments are consistent with the observed mass shifts from the native mass spectrometry data and previous results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Jin et al. 2022</xref>). To test whether these co-purifying lipids were bound to Orf9b purified from more physiologically relevant cell types, we expressed and purified WT Orf9b from mammalian cells. Similarly to Jin et al, our sample displayed similar MS patterns to the E. coli-derived sample and the assignments were consistent with 1-palmitoyl-sn-glycerol or 1-stearoyl-sn-glycerol (Figure 2 - supplemental figure 2B and C). Collectively, these results suggest that Orf9b homodimer lipid-binding is not limited to the cell types it is expressed in. We also conclude that the lipid can unbind when Orf9b is completely unfolded and that Orf9b can form homodimers in the absence of lipid. Going forward, we will refer to the refolded Orf9b homodimer as the apo-homodimer and the natively folded Orf9b homodimer as the lipid-bound homodimer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2e">
<title>Lipid binding shifts the Orf9b dimer:monomer equilibrium towards the dimer</title>
<p>To test whether there was a difference in homodimer stability between apo and lipid-bound Orf9b homodimers, we first monitored the concentration dependence of SEC elution profiles. Performing SEC on diluted apo-Orf9b homodimer sample produced two peaks on the chromatogram: the first peak corresponded to the homodimer and the second peak corresponded to the monomer (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). For the Orf9b homodimer, the retention volume was consistent with molecular weight standards based on the expected molecular weight of the homodimer (∼21kDa) and the standard (∼29kDa). In the case of the Orf9b monomer, although we would expect the retention volume of the monomer (∼10.6kDA) to be between the molecular weight standards of 13.4kDa and 6.5kDa, the greater retention volume could be explained by non-specific hydrophobic interactions between the monomeric Orf9b and the column. We confirmed that both peaks were Orf9b by SDS-PAGE (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). In contrast, the lipid-bound homodimer remains homodimeric at multiple concentrations (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>). We next sought to determine the dissociation constant of the apo-homodimer by monitoring the concentration dependence of the SEC elution profiles. As the concentration of apo-Orf9b homodimer decreased, the ratio between the area under the dimer elution peak and the monomer elution peak decreased (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D</xref>). We fit the total concentration of Orf9b versus the fraction of Orf9b in the homodimer form with a non-linear regression and determined a K<sub>D</sub> of 1.2 ± 0.1uM (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>). Although we were limited by the sensitivity of SEC at low micromolar concentrations, the stark difference between apo (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>) and lipid-bound (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>) Orf9b at low micromolar concentrations suggests that the binding of the lipid tightly stabilizes the Orf9b homodimer, preventing dissociation and monomer formation.</p>
<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 3:</label>
<caption><title>Serial dilution allows for estimation of Orf9b homodimer dissociation constant</title>
<p>A. Size exclusion chromatography overlay of Orf9b homodimer (black) with molecular weight standards (blue). Apo-Orf9b forms two distinct peaks corresponding to the dimer (peak 1) and the monomer (peak 2).</p><p>B. Coomasie stain of SDS-PAGE gel from peaks 1 and 2 (from <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">figure 3A</xref>) showing Orf9b is present in each peak.</p><p>C. Size exclusion chromatography chromatogram of serially diluted WT lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer showing no monomer species present.</p><p>D. Size exclusion chromatography chromatogram of serially diluted WT apo-Orf9b showing both homodimer and monomer peaks. Running molecular weight standards further supported our observation that the first peak was the Orf9b homodimer due to its close overlap with a 29kDa standard, however, the monomeric peak eluted after a 6.5kDa standard rather than between the 13.7kDa and 6.5kDA standards as we would expect. We hypothesize that this discrepancy is due to two possibilities: hydrophobic interactions between the monomer and the column could increase the retention volume or monomeric Orf9b has a smaller hydrodynamic radius than expected.</p><p>E. Nonlinear regression analysis of the fraction of Orf9b in the homodimer versus the total concentration of Orf9b (from <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">figure 3D</xref>) injected over the size exclusion column yields a K<sub>D</sub> of 1.2 ± 0.1uM.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="638509v2_fig3.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>We also confirmed that apo-Orf9b homodimer could be used to produce the Orf9b:Tom70 complex when incubated with Tom70. We incubated separately purified Tom70 and refolded (apo) Orf9b homodimer together and then ran them over an SEC column. We ran Tom70 alone followed by the Orf9b:Tom70 incubation and saw a left-shifted retention volume relative to Tom70 alone with a right-handed shoulder indicating a mix between Orf9b:Tom70 and Tom70 alone (Figure 3 - figure supplement 1A). SDS-PAGE gel of the fractions showed that the first fractions contained both Orf9b and Tom70 followed by a fraction containing mostly Tom70 alone and finally Orf9b alone (Figure 3 - figure supplement 1B). This suggests that the formation of the Orf9b:Tom70 complex is strongly influenced by the presence (or absence) of the lipid when starting with the Orf9b homodimer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2f">
<title>Lipid binding to the Orf9b homodimer substantially slows Orf9b binding to Tom70</title>
<p>To quantify the stabilization afforded by lipid binding, we returned to our FP assay (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>). Our hypothesis was that the elimination of the lipid would allow Orf9b homodimers to dissociate into monomers more rapidly and that this could be monitored by binding to Tom70 more readily. We used the FP assay with lipid-bound and apo-Orf9b homodimer as the competitors to pre-equilibrated Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 fluorescent complexes. The apo-Orf9b homodimer equilibrated rapidly (500-1000 seconds) with Orf9b-FITC:Tom70. These conditions showed concentration-dependent behavior, consistent with the coupled equilibria (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4Aii</xref>): at high total Orf9b concentration the displacement curves resembled a single exponential; however, at lower concentrations a more pronounced sigmoidal behavior appeared. We next performed the competition experiment with lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer. Strikingly, we observed that the lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer was much slower to bind to Tom70 (as monitored by the decrease in fluorescent polarization) than for the apo protein, with equilibrium reached only after several hours of incubation (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4Ai</xref>). As a negative control, we purified homodimeric Orf9b S53E. As we observed for the control Orf9b-S53E peptide, experiments with purified homodimeric Orf9b S53E did not cause any decrease in FP signal (Figure 4 - figure supplement 1). These results support our hypothesis that the decrease in FP signal over time is driven by the Orf9b homodimer dissociating into monomers and the monomers binding to Tom70 to displace the Orf9b-FITC probe with the difference in equilibration time driven by the lipid slowing the dissociation of the homodimer. We next sought to incorporate the rates from our SPR data into a model that describes how this more complex equilibrium is reached in our FP assay when lipid is either present or absent.</p>
<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 4:</label>
<caption><title>Modeling the effect of lipid-binding on Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium using SPR and FP based assays</title>
<p>A. I. Mathematical model overlay to FP competition kinetic assay using the lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer as the competitor. II. Mathematical model overlay to FP competition kinetic assay using the apo-Orf9b homodimer as the competitor.</p><p>B. (Left) Schematic diagram of monomeric Orf9b binding to immobilized monomeric Orf9b to determine dimerization rate constants. (Right) Surface plasmon resonance sensorgram of full-length Orf9b binding to full-length Orf9b monomer and their interaction kinetics. Experimental binding curves (blue) were globally fit (black) using a 1:1 binding model.</p><p>C. (Left) Schematic of full-length apo-Orf9b homodimer in exchange with Orf9b monomers. Monomeric Orf9b binds to immobilized Tom70 to determine rate constants of full-length Orf9b binding to Tom70. (Right) Surface plasmon resonance sensorgram of refolded apo-Orf9b binding to Tom70 and their interaction kinetics. Experimental binding curves (dark blue) were globally fit (black) using a 1:1 binding model.</p><p>D. Proposed kinetic model of Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium. Orf9b homodimer dissociates into Orf9b monomers which undergo a conformational change from β-sheet to L-helix. L-helical Orf9b binds to Tom70.</p><p>E. Table of model parameters used to model ODE’s to both apo and lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer competition binding kinetics.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="638509v2_fig4.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s2g">
<title>SPR measurements for Orf9b dimerization and Tom70 binding constrain models of the coupled equilibria</title>
<p>To model the competition FP data, we can leverage our prior SPR experiments, which report on the k<sub>on</sub>/k<sub>off</sub> for either Orf9b monomer or Orf9b-FITC interacting with Tom70. However, we also needed initial estimates of the rate constants for Orf9b oligomerization to constrain the model. To derive this rate, we isolated the monomeric fraction of biotinylated Orf9b and immobilized it on an SPR chip surface. We used a low immobilization signal of 15 RU to minimize the chance of biotinylated Orf9b monomers cross-dimerizing on the chip. To obtain the unlabeled monomeric Orf9b, purified WT Orf9b homodimer was denatured in 6M Guanidine HCl overnight followed by injection over a sizing column pre-equilibrated in the SPR running buffer. This procedure allowed us to isolate the monomeric fraction as well as desalt the sample into the SPR running buffer to minimize buffer mismatch artifacts. Global fitting of the binding curves using a 1:1 Langmuir binding model yielded a K<sub>D</sub> of 4.4±0.7µM which is within the order of magnitude of the dissociation constant calculated by dilution (1.2±0.1uM) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>). The kinetic rates were k<sub>on</sub> = 7.88×10<sup>4</sup> M<sup>-1</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> and k<sub>off</sub> = 3.5×10<sup>-1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). The maximum response during binding was approximately 8 RU which was close to the theoretical maximum response of 11 RU for a 1:1 interaction. The slow association rate showed that binding was not diffusion limited. This slower rate may be due to Orf9b undergoing conformational changes prior to dimerization on the surface.</p>
<p>Next we immobilized Tom70 to the chip surface, as in the Orf9b peptide experiments, and injected apo-Orf9b. Our experimental measurement of the Orf9b homodimer dissociation constant was in the low single digit micromolar, therefore, under the concentrations that we tested for the Tom70-immobilized SPR experiment, the oligomeric state of apo-Orf9b should be largely monomeric. When we performed global fitting of our Orf9b-Tom70 sensograms, we found that a 1:1 interaction showed a good fit, yielding a K<sub>D</sub> for Orf9b:Tom70 of 190±1nM. The dissociation rate was approximately 10-fold slower than the peptide and the association rate was also approximately 3 times slower than estimated for the Orf9b peptide (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>). To explain these altered kinetics, we considered whether Orf9b can bind to more than one copy of Tom70 via the MTS motif. This idea was motivated by AlphaFold predictions of monomeric WT Orf9, which show two helices: the first encompassing residues 11-28 and the second encompassing residues 44-70 (Figure 4 - figure supplement 2A). While the 44-70aa helix is resolved in both crystal and cryo-EM structures as bound to Tom70, the 11-28aa helix could form an MTS that may be recognized by a second copy of Tom70. To test this idea, we generated a peptide for 11-28aa, but did not observe any signal for binding by the FP assay or SPR (Figure 4 - figure supplemental 2B and C). With only single site binding, we speculate that the difference between the Orf9b peptide and full-length kinetics is due to the Orf9b peptide truncating several residues that are responsible for binding to Tom70 that influence both the association and dissociation pathways.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2h">
<title>Incorporating conformational change into the kinetic model of Orf9b oligomerization and Tom70 binding</title>
<p>Our Initial models, which incorporated only a simple intermediate as Orf9b monomers and Orf9b homodimers interconvert (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>), did not accurately capture the behavior observed in the FP assay (Figure 4 - figure supplement 3). We revised our model to now explicitly include model parameters that describe the rate of interconversion and conformational change between β-sheet and LJ-helical monomers (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref>). The differential equations for the model were the following:
<list list-type="order">
<list-item><p>d[Orf9b-FITC]/dt = -k1[Orf9b-FITC][Tom70]+k2[Orf9b-FITC:Tom70]</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>d[Orf9b β-monomer]/dt = 2(-k3[Orf9b β-monomer]^2+k4[Orf9b dimer])-kα[Orf9b β- monomer]^2+kβ[Orf9b α-monomer]</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>d[Orf9b dimer]/dt = k3[Orf9b β-monomer]^2-k4[Orf9b dimer]</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>d[Tom70]/dt = -k1[Orf9b-FITC][Tom70]-k5[Orf9b α-monomer][T]+k6[Orf9b α-monomer:Tom70]+k2[PT]</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>d[Orf9b α-monomer:Tom70]/dt = k5[Orf9b α-monomer][Tom70]-k6[Orf9b α-monomer:Tom70]</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>d[Orf9b α-monomer]/dt = -k5[Orf9b α monomer][Tom70]-kβ[Orf9b α-monomer]+k6[Orf9b α-monomer:Tom70]+kα[Orf9b β-monomer]^2</p></list-item>
</list>
The model parameters k<sub>a</sub> and k<sub>B</sub> describe the rate of interchange between the β-sheet and α-helix monomer conformations. These parameters must be estimated by modeling because our assays do not allow us to directly measure the folding rates between these conformations. To identify these values, we performed a scan of ka and kB values that yielded the best agreement between the model and the experimental conditions (Figure 4 - figure supplemental 4). We tested different models that incorporated the interconversion between β-sheet to α-helix conformations by considering models that described a conformational change in the homodimer leading to Tom70 binding rather than monomers. None of these models adequately described our experimental results, therefore we continued developing our model as outlined in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref>. We found that this model adequately described the changes in kinetic behavior for different concentrations of Orf9b assuming the conversion of helix to β-sheet depended linearly on the concentration of Orf9b α-monomer with a first order rate constant k<sub>B</sub>.</p>
<p>We initially tested keeping the rate constant ka first order just like kB which did yield the sigmoidal behavior we observed in the 5uM apo-homodimer condition but extending this analysis to additional concentrations tested resulted in substantial overestimation compared to our experimental results when holding kB at a constant value throughout. We found that when the β-sheet to α-helix rate (ka) was made a second order rate constant, we were able to hold the rate constant across all concentrations tested suggesting a non-linearity in the monomer β-sheet concentration. One potential biophysical explanation for the order of these rate constants is that in the monomeric form, Orf9b is more likely to adopt either a disordered or helical conformation than the β-sheet conformation we see in the homodimer. The formation of the helical conformation may either pattern neighboring monomers to adopt the α-helical conformation and produce helix:helix dimers or the formation of monomers may destabilize the homodimer through multivalent interactions. While we did not directly test for this, we note examples of proteins exhibiting high structural plasticity that are capable of adopting different conformations mediated by cooperative mechanisms have been reported previously such as in the case of RfaH and Lymphotactic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c43">Tuinstra et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c52">Zuber et al. 2022</xref>) This revised model also allows us to use all of our measured rate constants and only requires the introduction of two unknown rate constants (k<sub>a</sub> and k<sub>B</sub>) that can be determined by fitting.</p>
<p>We began by modeling the apo-Orf9b homodimer competition experiments (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4Aii</xref>). We used the SPR derived rate constants for both Orf9b-FITC:Tom70, refolded Orf9b:Tom70, and Orf9b dimerization as our model parameters. Given that k<sub>a</sub> and k<sub>B</sub> were not experimentally determined, we used our model to identify values that achieved the closest agreement between our model and experimental results when modeling the lowest concentration and then held those values fixed for subsequent concentrations. We found that modeling the initial population of Orf9b as entirely homodimeric achieved a good agreement with our experimental results. Our model was sensitive to the change in kinetic profile as the concentration of Orf9b decreased, resulting in the sigmoidal kinetic profile observed in the 5uM condition and suggesting the the dominant behavior of apo-Orf9b is as the homodimer rather than a mix between homodimer and monomers. We feel this decision is justified both by the model’s correspondence with the experimental data and the fact that the concentrations of apo-homodimer used are several fold higher than the experimentally derived range of K<sub>D</sub> values. Further, we repeated the sensitivity analysis described previously for the peptide model and also considered the sensitivity of model parameters by inspecting each individually (Figure 4-figure supplemental 5). Inspection of the residuals from the 5uM apo-Orf9b homodimer time course showed clear patterns when individual model parameters were subjected to a 10% increase or decrease from the reported values. While our proposed model qualitatively describes the concentration dependent change in kinetic behavior, the residual plots may suggest that additional binding reactions may also be occurring that are not captured by our model. We found that when examining the RMSD’s of the lowest concentration of 5uM, the model was most sensitive to changes in three parameters: the rate of homodimer association and dissociation and the conversion from β to α-monomers. However at the highest concentrations (50uM) the model was no longer sensitive to these parameters as it was most sensitive to the rate of Orf9b-FITC dissociation from Tom70, which was the rate limiting step. Therefore, under low concentrations of Orf9b homodimer, binding to Tom70 is limited by the rate of homodimer association and dissociation as well as the conversion of Orf9b monomers to the α-helical conformation. Under high homodimer conditions, the limiting step becomes the rate at which Orf9b-FITC dissociates from Tom70.</p>
<p>Next we modeled the lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer data (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4Ai</xref>). We modeled the initial conditions prior to the addition of the fluorescent complex as entirely Orf9b homodimer with no monomeric species present just like with the refolded apo-homodimer. To simplify our model for lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer, we did not explicitly include the lipid binding kinetics into our model and hypothesized that the model parameter that would be most sensitive to lipid binding would be the rate of homodimer dissociation into monomers. We used our previously implemented model parameters for the refolded homodimer datasets and initially modeled one experimental condition and then used those optimal parameter values to compare against the remaining data sets. We observed that the model was sensitive to the parameters describing the conversion from β-monomer to α-monomer and the homodimer dissociation rate, as we saw for the apo-homodimer dataset. We assumed that lipid-binding to the homodimer would have no effect on the rate of conversion from β to α-monomer and we hypothesized that the model parameter that would be sensitized to lipid-binding would be the rate of homodimer dissociation. We found that in order for the model to pick up the correct behavior exhibited by the experimental data required an approximately 100-fold decrease to the rate of homodimer dissociation over all concentrations tested. Further, we also note that we observed sensitivity in the rate of Orf9b-FITC dissociation under high concentration of homodimer. Therefore, both model parameters are essential to the model across all concentration series with the rate of homodimer dissociation being the most sensitive parameter for the lipid-bound data.</p>
<p>We found that the lipid-bound homodimer dataset could be modeled by lowering the homodimer dissociation rate to 1.0×10<sup>-3</sup> s<sup>-1</sup>, which is nearly 2 orders of magnitude from the SPR derived value for refolded Orf9b of 3.5×10<sup>-1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4E</xref>). This brought the model into close alignment with the experimental data while all other parameters remained the same as those used in the refolded homodimer model. These model parameters resulted in a good agreement with the experimental data over different concentrations of lipid-bound homodimer. Importantly, this change in dissociation rate also explains the initial slow rate of binding to Tom70 at lower concentrations of Orf9b homodimer and the long equilibration time. Based on the fitted association and dissociation rates for the lipid-bound homodimer, our model suggests that the lipid-bound dissociation constant for the Orf9b homodimer drops to ∼13nM, which is ∼100-fold stronger than the experimentally determined dissociation constant of 1.2-4.4uM for the refolded homodimer (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4E</xref>). Further, our model shows that lipid-binding only acts on the rate of homodimer dissociation but does not affect the microscopic rate constant of Orf9b binding to Tom70 in our assay.</p>
<p>To explore the consequences of altering the different microscopic steps fit by our model in cellular contexts, we were next interested in testing mutations that biased the equilibrium towards either the Orf9b monomer or homodimer. We investigated the homodimer interface and observed that residues 91-97 of the C-terminal tail on chain A form backbone backbone hydrogen bonds with residues 50-56 of chain B (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>). Our choice to truncate the 7 C-terminal amino acids was driven by the structure of the Orf9b homodimer which indicated that the 7 C-terminal residues form ⅔ of the homodimer interface, therefore, truncating them would compromise the ability for Orf9b to form stable homodimers and impede lipid binding. Due to the homodimer being symmetric, truncating residues on one chain would be mirrored on the opposite chain. We purified truncated Orf9b and observed a peak that eluted at 70mL (the same retention volume as the homodimer) followed by a large peak near the end of the columns volume which we attribute to the monomeric species (Figure 5 - figure supplement 1A). We isolated the peak that corresponded to the homodimer and used it in the FP kinetic assay. We observed fast binding kinetics that resembled our results using the Orf9b peptide, which is an obligate monomer (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E</xref>) and suggested that the truncation destabilizes the Orf9b homodimer.</p>
<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 5:</label>
<caption><title>Truncated and fused Orf9b constructs can destabilize or stabilize the homodimer to modulate Tom70 binding</title>
<p>A. Model of Orf9b homodimer illustrating the Δ91-97 truncation (cyan). Residues 91-97 form 7 hydrogen bonds (7 mediated by backbone backbone interactions) between chains A and B (black dashes) of the homodimer and represent ⅔ of the homodimer binding interface.</p><p>B. Berkeley Madonna model (solid lines) overlaid experimental data points (circles) for the FP competition kinetic assay using Orf9b Δ91-97.</p><p>C. AlphaFold model of Orf9b homodimer with a 4xSGG linker (green) fusing the C-terminus of chain A (gray) to the N-terminus of chain B (magenta).</p><p>D. Fitted model (solid lines) overlaid with experimental data points (circles) for the FP competition kinetic assay using Orf9b 4xSGG fusion construct.</p><p>E. Model parameters used for solving ODE in Berkeley Madonna for both Δ91-97 and 4xSGG constructs.</p><p>F. Co-immunoprecipitation between Flag-Tom70 and Strep-Orf9b mutants from HEK293T cells and immunoprecipitation was performed using anti-flag magnetic beads. Representative western blots of whole-cell lysates (WCLs) and eluates after IP are shown. Actin was used as a loading control in WCLs.</p><p>G. Fold induction of ISRE-reporter activated by 3p-hpRNA upon expression of empty vector, Orf9b WT, Orf9b fused, Orf9b, truncated, and Orf9b S50/53E in HEK293T cells. Fold induction was calculated relative to unstimulated cells.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="638509v2_fig5.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>We next applied our kinetic model to describe how the truncation drives the equilibrium towards Tom70 binding relative to WT Orf9b. As with the apo and lipid-bound homodimer results, we initially focused on modeling our FP results by focusing on the dissociation rate as the model parameter most sensitive while keeping all other model parameters unchanged. The fast kinetics observed suggested to us that the truncation resulted in the Orf9b homodimer readily dissociating into monomers prior to the addition of the fluorescent complex. We believed that this was reasonable given that monomeric species formed a major peak in our SEC chromatogram (Figure 5 - figure supplement 1A). When we ran the model assuming that the truncated Orf9b was entirely homodimeric to begin with (while increasing the homodimer dissociation rate), we saw poor agreement with our experimental results. We resorted to using the same model that we used for fitting the Orf9b peptide data (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E</xref>), which treats the system as a simple equilibrium between Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 and Orf9b monomers and produced good agreement between the model and experimental results (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>). We interpreted this to mean that the truncation to Orf9b results in a homodimer that is substantially less stable than the WT homodimer and that our experimental results are capturing a largely monomeric binding behavior to Tom70 without influence of the homodimer. Therefore, we interpret these results to indicate that truncating the 7 C-terminal amino acids compromises Orf9b ability to remain a stable homodimer and drives the equilibrium strongly towards monomeric Orf9b, rendering it a good reagent for investigating the role of the monomer in cellular models. Importantly, this data showed no influence of the lipid to the observed kinetics with Tom70 which lends further support to our conclusion that the truncated Orf9b is acting like an “obligate” monomer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2i">
<title>A single chain fusion Orf9b homodimer indirectly reduces binding to Tom70</title>
<p>To create an “obligate” homodimer, we wanted to fuse two copies of Orf9b together in a single polypeptide chain using a flexible linker. We hypothesized that such a fusion protein should reduce monomer population by promoting rapid reassociation. By examining structures of Orf9b homodimer, we observed that the N-terminus of each chain is approximately 28Å from the C-terminus of the opposite chain (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref>). We designed several constructs that fused the C-terminus of one Orf9b sequence to the N-terminus of a second Orf9b sequence through a Serine-Glycine-Glycine linker of variable repeats. We purified an Orf9b fusion with 4 repeats of the SGG linker (referred to as “fusion”) and observed a retention volume that aligned with the WT homodimer (centered at 70mL) (Figure 5 - figure supplement 1B). SDS-PAGE showed the expected band for the fusion product at ∼25kDa (Figure 5 - figure supplement 1B). We attempted to refold the fusion homodimer to eliminate the co-purification of lipids however we were unable to recover the fusion homodimer. Therefore, we used the natively purified Orf9b fusion homodimer which is, presumably, lipid-bound.</p>
<p>We performed our FP kinetic assay as previously described and observed a slight decrease in signal at the highest concentrations of fusion homodimer but little to no decrease at the lower concentrations. Our experimental results showed that the 60uM and 30uM conditions resulted in some binding to Tom70, however, the initial decrease in signal occurred slowly over the course of approximately 2-4 hours (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D</xref>). Unlike our lipid-bound and apo-Orf9b homodimer results, the fusion construct did not saturate Tom70 at the highest concentrations as judged by the elevated Tom70:Orf9b-FITC concentration at equilibrium.</p>
<p>Although our model explicitly describes homodimer dissociation into monomers as a requisite step for Orf9b binding to Tom70, we adapted it for the fusion experimental data. In this case, all model parameters other than the association and dissociation kinetics of the fluorescent probe and Tom70 were adjusted to achieve the best agreement with the experimental data. When applied to the fusion homodimer, the parameters describing homodimer dissociation into separate monomers could instead describe the dissociation of the two β-sheet domains away from each other in the tertiary structure but remaining physically linked through the linker region. We observe that the Orf9b monomer:Tom70 association rate is altered approximately 10-fold to 7.0×10<sup>3</sup> M<sup>-1</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> while the dissociation rate remains unchanged compared to WT (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5E</xref>). Further, the interconversion rates between LJ-helix and β-sheet conformations increases 2-fold and 10-fold which we interpret as the fusion construct driving the formation of the β-sheet conformation over the LJ-helical conformation. Additionally, the fused homodimer association rate (which can be viewed as a rate of tertiary complex formation) is reduced 160-fold compared to WT. Taken together, these values would suggest that when two copies of Orf9b are fused together into a single chain, the interconversion between secondary structures increases with the β-sheet conformation forming quickly at the expense of a slowed LJ-helical formation. Given that the LJ-helical conformation is what drives Orf9b binding to Tom70, this reduces the rate of Orf9b association to Tom70. At the same time, the increase in secondary structure interconversion comes at the cost of reducing the tertiary complex formation. Interestingly, the homodimer dissociation rate (or the tertiary unfolding rate) is also approximately 1000-fold slower than even the WT lipid-bound rate. Taken together, these parameters may suggest a model for the homodimer fusion where upon the unfolding of the tertiary homodimer structure, the fusion construct readily adopts β-sheet conformations that do not lead the correct tertiary fold. As a result, the LJ-helical fold is compromised and slower to form which in turn slows binding to Tom70.</p>
<p>The fusion construct is particularly useful as a comparison to Orf9b S53E mutants for impacting Tom70 binding directly or indirectly because the S53E mutation mimics the phosphorylation that directly blocks binding to Tom70 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">Thorne et al. 2022</xref>). Collectively, the truncated, fused, and S53E full length Orf9b constructs position us to ask about the consequences perturbing different steps of these coupled equilibria on cellular Tom70 interactions and signalling.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2j">
<title>Co-Immunoprecipitation and IFN assays show continued inhibition for both truncated and fused constructs</title>
<p>To connect our in vitro observations to cellular signalling, we tested the truncated, fused, and phosphomimetic constructs for Tom70 binding and IFN suppression. We co-transfected flag-tagged Tom70 and strep-tagged Orf9b in HEK293T cells and performed flag-pull downs (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5F</xref>). While both WT and truncated Orf9b co-immunoprecipitatedwith Tom70, Orf9b S50/53E showed no interaction, as expected (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5F</xref>). Surprisingly, we observed that the Orf9b fusion also interacted with Tom70. This suggests that even though only a small amount of the Orf9b fusion dimer showed binding to Tom70 at the highest concentrations, this may be sufficient to drive interactions in a cellular context. To test whether these interactions were sufficient for IFN signalling suppression, we turned to an ISRE reporter cell line. We transfected cells with the same Orf9b plasmids and stimulated the cells with 3p-hpRNA, which is a RIG-I agonist and activates the RIG-I mediated type 1 interferon response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c15">Hornung et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c35">Rehwinkel et al. 2010</xref>). For both WT and truncated Orf9b, we observed a decrease in the fold induction of IFN (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5G</xref>). Again, as expected, the S50/53E construct showed comparable levels of IFN induction to the empty vector control. Surprisingly, the fusion construct showed a decrease in IFN response that was comparable to both WT and truncated Orf9b (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5G</xref>).</p>
<p>We speculate that there may be two distinct possibilities for these unexpected results. First, from our in vitro kinetic assay, we can see that although the fusion construct does not saturate Tom70 like we see with the WT experiments, we still observe some binding at the highest concentrations used. Unlike the S50/53E mutant which directly alters the microscopic rate constant between Orf9b and Tom70, our model of the fusion construct suggests that the microscopic affinity of Orf9b for Tom70 is also manipulated by rate constants that describe the interconversion between both secondary structures and tertiary structures but does not fully inhibit binding. Therefore, it is possible that even a residual interaction between Orf9b and Tom70 may be sufficient to drive a suppression of IFN without necessarily saturating Tom70.</p>
<p>Second, our results with the lipid-bound homodimer have shown that lipid binding alters the observed rate of Orf9b binding to Tom70 without altering the microscopic rate constants whereas apo-homodimer produces fast binding kinetics and rapidly reaches equilibrium with Tom70. While our in vitro kinetic results working with purified protein allow us to study how full occupancy of the homodimer by lipids biases the equilibrium, we cannot control for this in cells. One possibility that emerges is that while lipid binding to the Orf9b homodimer does occur in cells (as supported by our mass spectrometry results), not all copies of the homodimer are bound to lipids. This would leave free copies of either monomeric Orf9b or apo-Orf9b homodimer available to bind to Tom70 and result in suppressed IFN signalling. Further, our SPR results with the refolded Orf9b and Tom70 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>) suggest that the interaction between Orf9b and Tom70 is fairly tight which may result in Orf9b becoming kinetically trapped to Tom70 once it binds.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2k">
<title>Mutations in VOC modulate Orf9b homodimer stability</title>
<p>We next applied our model to study Orf9b mutations present in variants of concern (VOC). While the Delta variant possesses a T60A mutation, which is within the region of Orf9b that folds into the helix to bind Tom70, the Lambda and Omicron variants have mutations outside the Tom70 binding region. They share a P10S mutation, with Omicron also having a truncation of Δ27-29 within a disordered loop of the homodimer (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A</xref>). We used our assays to determine if any of these mutations altered the homodimer stability or the affinity of Orf9b for Tom70. We purified all three variants and subjected them to denaturation and refolding as previously described. All three refolded variants purified as homodimers based on their retention volumes by SEC relative to WT (Figure 6 - figure supplement 1A). We then performed the same kinetic FP assay as previously described.</p>
<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 6:</label>
<caption><title>Orf9b mutations in variants of concern modulate equilibrium kinetics with Tom70</title>
<p>A. An AlphaFold model of the full Orf9b homodimer with mutations found in variants of concern shown as red spheres. Resides that fold into the Tom70-binding L-helix are highlighted in magenta on one protomer and residues that form the dimer interface are highlighted in pink.</p><p>B. Berkeley Madonna model (black lines) overlaid on experimental data points (circles) for the FP competition kinetic assay using Lambda, Omicron, and Delta Orf9b variants.</p><p>C. Table of model parameters used to model experimental data in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig 6B</xref> using Berkeley Madonna.</p><p>D. Location of point mutations in variants of concern modeled in Pymol: (Left) T60 forms a hydrogen bond with the backbone carbonyl between A68 and F69 of the same chain that is lost in T60A. (Right) Point mutation P10S (red) introduces a serine that forms several hydrogen bonds with R13 and the backbone carbonyl of A11 and L48 within the same chain. Both mutations are mirrored on the opposite protomer. Hydrogen bonds are shown as black dashes. Mutations are modeled in Pymol using point mutation.</p><p>E. Co-immunoprecipitation of endogenous Tom70 with Strep-tagged of Orf9b from variants of concern in HEK293T cells.</p><p>F. Fold induction of ISRE-reporter activated by 3p-hpRNA in HEK293T cells expressing empty vector, Orf9b WT, Orf9b from VOC (Delta, Lambda, and Omicron).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="638509v2_fig6.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>We hypothesized that the most noticeable effect these mutations would have is on the dissociation rate of the homodimer into monomers. With that in mind, to minimize overfitting, we kept all model parameters that we used for the apo-WT homodimer the same and only modulated the homodimer k<sub>off</sub> rate to estimate the effect these mutations have on Orf9b homodimer stability. From our model, we observed that Omicron (P10S, Δ27-29) could be modeled with a homodimer dissociation rate of 2.5×10<sup>-1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> which yielded a modeled K<sub>D</sub> of 3.1uM which is close to the experimentally determined K<sub>D</sub> of the refolded WT dimer suggesting that the P10S, Δ27-29 mutations may have a minor effect on homodimer stability (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B</xref>). For Lambda and Delta variants, we observed that our experimental data required either lowering the homodimer dissociation rate or increasing it to best explain our experimental data. Lambda (P10S) exhibited the most stable behavior as judged by the modeled homodimer dissociation rate of 2.0×10<sup>-2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> (modeled K<sub>D</sub> = 0.25uM) which is approximately 10-fold tighter than both WT and Omicron datasets (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6C</xref>). The Delta variant (T60A) showed a kinetic behavior resembling a single exponential decay like the Orf9b peptide suggesting that the homodimer was much weaker. Our first attempts at fitting the Delta variant FP data was performed assuming that Orf9b T60A was completely homodimeric to begin with which yielded poor fits. We then revised our initial model to include that starting solution as a mix of monomers and homodimers at equilibrium which we determined algebraically using the modeled dimer dissociation constant that yielded the closest agreement to our FP data. We found that a dissociation constant of 12uM (calculated by increasing homodimer k<sub>off</sub> to 0.9 s<sup>-1</sup>) with a solution that is at equilibrium between homodimer and monomers prior to chasing with the fluorescent complex yielded the closest fit (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B</xref>). This result suggests that the T60A mutation may be destabilizing the Orf9b homodimer.</p>
<p>Given that the T60A mutation is also present within the β-sheet to LJ-helix folding region that binds to Tom70 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6D</xref>), we sought to confirm if this mutation also affected the microscopic affinity of Orf9b for Tom70. We generated a T60A peptide based on our previously described peptide and performed SPR. We hypothesized that if the T60A mutation resulted in a weaker affinity for Tom70, then that would be reflected in the SPR compared to the WT peptide. We repeated the SPR experiment as previously for WT (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>) and did not observe a decrease in the affinity between Orf9b T60A and Tom70. We interpret this to mean that T60A mutation does not reduce the affinity between Orf9b and Tom70 (Figure 6 - figure supplement 1B), which was concordant with our model parameters where we left the Orf9b monomer:Tom70 dissociation rate unchanged (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6C</xref>). Inspecting the location of these mutations in the Orf9b homodimer led to several structural hypotheses for the observed and modeled kinetics. For Delta, the T60A mutation is present within the β-strand that is responsible for refolding into the LJ-helix and binding to Tom70 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6D</xref>). T60 makes a hydrogen bond with the backbone carbonyl between A68 and F69 of the same chain which may contribute to the local stability of the β-strand. For Lambda and Omicron, the P10S mutation results in the serine being positioned to form several hydrogen bonds between R13 and the backbone carbonyl of A11 and L48 within the same chain which may contribute to local stability. The Omicron variant additionally has a truncation of residues 27-29 within a disordered loop. Although the modeled homodimer dissociation rate was close to WT, the modeled K<sub>D</sub> was slightly lower which was consistent between biological replicates suggesting that the P10S mutation is stabilizing the homodimer like the Lambda variant, but the truncation of residues 27-29 may counteract this effect by destabilizing the homodimer. We repeated this experiment with biological replicates for all variants of Orf9b described and observed consistent behavior (Figure 6 - figure supplemental 2)</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2l">
<title>Mutations in VOC do not affect binding to Tom70 or IFN suppression in cell-based assays relative to WT</title>
<p>Our in vitro kinetic model results showed that while mutations to Orf9b present in VOC can alter the stability of the Orf9b homodimer as modeled by the homodimer dissociation rate, they did not alter the association rate of the Orf9b:Tom70 complex (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6C</xref>). We returned to our co-IP experiments to validate if variants of Orf9b retain their interaction with Tom70 in a cellular context. We performed Co-IP of the three variants as previously described and observed no noticeable differences in Tom70 binding across different VOCs confirming that these mutations do not directly alter the affinity between Orf9b and Tom70 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6E</xref>). These results were concordant with the predicted behavior that we modeled in our FP results, therefore, we hypothesized that Orf9b variants should have similar effects on IFN suppression compared to WT in our IFN assay. We performed the IFN assay as previously described and saw that compared to WT, all variants had a comparable decrease in the fold-induction of IFN which was approximately 50% reduction compared to the empty vector control (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6F</xref>). These results lead us to conclude that the mutations present in variants of concern may alter the Orf9b homodimerization kinetics but they do not noticeably affect the interaction between Orf9b and Tom70 or Orf9b-mediated suppression of type 1 interferon response.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The SARS-CoV and 2 accessory protein Orf9b is an antagonist of the type 1 interferon response through its interactions with the mitochondrial receptor Tom70 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c12">Gordon et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">Thorne et al. 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c16">Jiang et al. 2020</xref>) When bound to Tom70, Orf9b adopts an amphipathic LJ-helical fold, however, it is also capable of binding to a second copy of Orf9b to form a β-sheet rich homodimer. In the homodimer conformation, Orf9b can bind to lipids such as 1-palmitolyl-sn-glycerol, a precursor to palmitate which is a metabolite that is known to be involved in innate immune activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c32">Meier et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Jin et al. 2022</xref>). These two different Orf9b conformations suggest that an equilibrium exists between homodimeric and monomeric conformations, with only the monomeric conformation capable of binding to Tom70. How this equilibrium is established and regulated may be of interest for both developing therapeutics as well as learning how the virus hijacks the host cell processes during infection.</p>
<p>We observed that the Orf9b equilibrium is heavily biased towards the Orf9b homodimer upon binding of lipids, which Orf9b co-purifies with from both mammalian cells and E.coli. By determining the microscopic rate constants of the Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium using SPR, we were able to fit ODE’s describing the coupled equilibrium between Orf9b conformations and Tom70 to quantify the contribution of lipid binding to the Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium. Specifically, we have shown that lipid binding to the Orf9b homodimer slows the observed rate of binding to Tom70 without changing the microscopic rate constant of Orf9b binding to Tom70. Rather it does so by reducing the rate of Orf9b homodimer dissociation approximately 100-fold relative to apo-homodimer. When analyzing our structural data of the refolded Orf9b homodimer, we see that lipid-binding does not drive Orf9b homodimerization as we are able to recover the homodimer conformation observed in lipid-bound structures without the lipid present. The apo-Orf9b homodimer retains the same conformation as the lipid-bound structure but we also observed an increased level of disorder as judged by the high B-factors and lower resolution of our structure when compared to published structures with lipids bound. We speculate that this lends further evidence to our argument that the lipid is not responsible for homodimerization but tightly stabilizes the homodimer conformation when compared to existing structures of the lipid-bound SARS CoV 2 Orf9b homodimer.</p>
<p>We also found that the Orf9b equilibrium could be driven towards either the monomer or homodimer by truncating 7 amino acids or by fusing two copies of Orf9b together producing behaviors that were either entirely monomeric or largely homodimeric in the context of Tom70-binding. Unlike with lipid-bound WT homodimer, the lipid-bound homodimer fusion construct did not saturate Tom70 in our kinetic assay which suggested that the fusion construct was acting as an obligate homodimer. However, when we tested the fusion homodimer construct in both Co-IP’s and IFN signaling assays, we observed that the homodimer fusion construct continued to bind to Tom70 leading to a suppressed IFN induction like WT. We had anticipated that if the Orf9b was an obligate homodimer, we would observe results resembling the phosphomimetic S53E construct, which does not bind Tom70 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">Thorne et al. 2022</xref>) but does retain the ability to homodimerize. This result was unexpected as we had anticipated the obligate homodimer results to resemble the phosphomimetic. We hypothesize that this may be explained by two possible factors. First, we can’t exclude the introduction of an increased avidity between Orf9b and Tom70 when using the fused homodimer. Although our modeled decrease in the association rate of Orf9b:Tom70 (which increases the K<sub>D</sub> of the complex) suggests that fusing two copies of Orf9b decreases the affinity to Tom70, one copy of the fusion construct could also be capable of either binding to two copies of Tom70, or, one copy of the fusion could undergo rapid rebinding to Tom70. These effects would lead to a much tighter interaction in cellular assays than we modeled in vitro. A second possible explanation is that our assumptions about high lipid binding are not valid for cell based assays.</p>
<p>As we have shown with both WT and fusion constructs, recombinantly expressed and purified Orf9b is lipid-bound and this can stabilize the homodimer to slow or inhibit the binding to Tom70. For the Orf9b fusion construct, we attempted to isolate the lipid-free species through protein refolding as previously described to compare the effect of lipid-binding on the homodimer fusion (similar to our WT experiments), however, we could not recover the stably folded homodimer. We hypothesize that the discrepancy between our kinetic results and Co-IP/IFN results could be due to subsaturation of the Orf9b fusion homodimers by lipids in cell based assays. While we have shown that lipid-binding occurs in recombinant expression systems, it is possible that in our cell based signaling assays that lipid-binding only affects a minor population of Orf9b. Given that we were unable to isolate the apo-fusion homodimer, we could not directly compare whether there are differences in fusion homodimer stability in the presence or absence of lipid-binding. Therefore, it is possible that the apo-fusion homodimer undergoes unfolding and refolding into alpha helices that lead to Tom70 binding similar to the WT construct.. A possible future experimental direction could be attempting to pre-incubate cells with excess palmitate prior to transfection with Tom70 and Orf9b to increase the concentration of the lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer and observe its effect on Tom70 pull down and IFN signaling.</p>
<p>We have also shown how mutations in VOC can perturb different steps in the Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium. Orf9b is encoded through an alternative open reading frame within the N gene of SARS CoV 1 and 2 which results in coding mutations to N being picked up by the coding region of Orf9b. These mutations include Omicron (N: P13L; Orf9b: P10S), Delta (N: D63G; Of9b: T60A), and Lambda (N:Δ30-32, P13L; Orf9b:Δ27-29, P10S) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c42">Thorne et al. 2022</xref>). Our model and FP results suggest that in the absence of lipid-binding, Orf9b VOCs still achieve rapid equilibration with Tom70 with no change in overall affinity, which is concordant with our cell based assay results. We have shown that mutations present in Lambda and Delta can be stabilizing or destabilizing to the Orf9b homodimer and shift the time it takes to reach equilibrium with Tom70 in our kinetic assay. Omicron possesses both a truncation of residues 27-29 as well as the P10S point mutation that is present in Lambda, but shows a kinetic behavior that more closely resembles WT homodimer than Lambda homodimer. These mutations may cancel their effects out where the proposed stabilizing effect of the P10S mutation observed in Lambda is countered by a destabilizing effect due to the truncation of residues 27-29. Although none of the mutations in Delta, Lambda, and Omicron variants are found at the homodimer binding interface, we speculate that their effect on Orf9b homodimer stability is exercised through local stabilizing or destabilizing forces on the overall homodimer conformation. We cannot exclude the possibility that these mutations may primarily be tuned to affect nucleocapsid function rather than Orf9b. At this time, the effect of these specific mutations on nucleocapsid function have not been assayed, therefore, we cannot conclude whether they produce a noticeable effect on viral RNA packaging.</p>
<p>When considering our results together, we propose the following expanded model for Orf9b mediated suppression of IFN through Tom70 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>). During viral infection, Orf9b can either bind to Tom70 as a monomer or homodimerize with a second copy of Orf9b. In the absence of lipid-binding, Orf9b homodimers rapidly equilibrate into monomers which can subsequently bind to Tom70, creating two pathways for freshly translated Orf9b to engage Tom70: 1) Orf9b monomers immediately bind to Tom70 after translation or 2) they homodimerize with a second copy of Orf9b, which then can undergo dissociation into monomers and bind Tom70. The binding kinetics of Orf9b:Tom70 and Orf9b:Orf9b (as determined by SPR) suggest that copies of Orf9b bound to Tom70 remain tightly associated whereas the homodimers can quickly collapse into monomers in the absence of lipid-binding. Upon lipid binding, the Orf9b homodimer is stabilized, however, they can still undergo dissociation into monomers but on a much longer time scale. Therefore, if lipid-binding occurs either at a later stage of infection or is sub-saturating the Orf9b homodimer population, it may not noticeably affect IFN signaling as the copies of Orf9b bound to Tom70 remain tightly associated. This is supported in two ways: First, our VOC data shows that modulating the homodimer stability does not drive a noticeable increase or decrease in the amount of Orf9b that binds to Tom70 nor subsequent IFN signaling levels relative to WT. Second, our truncated Orf9b (obligate monomer) does not form a stable homodimer but still achieves comparable levels of IFN suppression as WT, which can homodimerize. Given that the nature of lipid-binding to the Orf9b homodimer remains unknown, we cannot precisely place when lipid-binding becomes relevant to the Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium in the context of IFN signaling. If lipid-binding is a later event during infection, then it might not be fully captured in our assays which occur over the course of either minutes or hours. Further, the tight affinity between Orf9b and Tom70 may suggest that upon binding, Orf9b becomes kinetically trapped to Tom70 and does not fully revert to the homodimer conformation resulting in the immediate suppression of IFN.</p>
<fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure">
<label>Figure 7:</label>
<caption><title>Proposed model of the Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium</title>
<p>Orf9b transcripts are translated to produce monomeric Orf9b proteins that can bind to Tom70 leading to a suppression of IFN. Monomeric Orf9b can also undergo a conformational change and bind to a second copy of Orf9b to form the homodimer. The Orf9b homodimer is in equilibrium between free Orf9b monomers and Orf9b monomers bound to Tom70. Upon lipid binding, the homodimer is tightly stabilized and slowly releases monomeric Orf9b.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="638509v2_fig7.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/>
</fig>
<p>Although we have not directly tested for the role the homodimer conformation plays during infection, we have demonstrated that lipid-binding to the homodimer can bias the equilibrium away from Tom70.. Lipids including palmitate have been shown to act as both a signaling molecule as well as a post-translational modification during antiviral innate immune signaling (S <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c39">Mesquita et al. 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">Wen et al. 2022</xref>; S. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c50">Yang et al. 2019</xref>). As a post-translational modification (referred to as S-acylation), MAVS, a mitochondrial type 1 IFN signaling protein that associates with Tom70 (X.-Y. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c26">Liu et al. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c31">McWhirter, Tenoever, and Maniatis 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c37">Seth et al. 2005</xref>), has been shown to be post-translationally palmitoylated which affects its ability to localize to the mitochondrial outer membrane during viral infection and is a known target of Orf9b (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">Bu et al. 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c23">Lee et al. 2024</xref>). When this is impaired (either by mutation or by depletion of the palmitoylation enzyme ZDHHC24), IFN activation is impaired (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">Bu et al. 2024</xref>). Therefore, future investigations should consider if the homodimer conformation of Orf9b is capable of antagonizing other IFN signaling factors such as MAVS by binding to palmitoyl groups. Indeed, Orf9b has already been shown to be capable of binding to MAVS by Co-IP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c14">Han et al. 2021</xref>), however, whether or not this occurs through the palmitoyl modification remains unknown. Collectively, our work points to the importance of this lipid-binding role of Orf9b in modulating its coupled equilibria and likely its influence on IFN signaling in the context of viral infection.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4">
<title>Methods and Materials</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Expression and purification of mammalian expressed WT Orf9b</title>
<p>WT Orf9b was transiently transfected into Expi293 cells seeded to a density of 3×10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL and expressed for 3 days. Harvested cells were centrifuged and resuspended in a lysis buffer of 150mM NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 1.5mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1mM EDTA, and 0.5mM TCEP, lysed by sonication, and then centrifuged. Supernatant was transferred to a column of Streptactin 4-flow and allowed to bind at 4C for 1-2 hours. The column was washed with a buffer of 150mM NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCl pH 8, and 0.5mM TCEP followed by elution of the strep-tagged protein with BXT buffer. Eluted strep-tagged Orf9b was ion exchanged on an CaptoQ column equilibrated with 20mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 50mM NaCl, and 0.5mM TCEP with a salt gradient up to 1mM NaCl. Ion exchanged Orf9b was then sized on a Superdex 75 10/300 GL column equilibrated with 150mM Tris pH 8, 50mM NaCl, and 0.5mM TCEP.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4b">
<title>Purification of Native WT Orf9b</title>
<p>The WT Orf9b gene was cloned into a pET-29a backbone with an N-terminal 6xHis tag and TEV protease cleavage site. BL21 E. coli cells from NEB were transformed and grown in a starter culture of Luria Broth at 37C overnight. 1L cultures were inoculated with 10mL of the starter culture and grown in Terrific Broth media supplemented with Kanamycin (100ug/mL) at 37C until an optical density of 0.6-0.8 was reached. Cultures were chilled at 4C for 15 minutes and then induced with 1mM IPTG and grown at 16C overnight. Frozen cell pellets were resuspended in a lysis buffer of 300mM NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, and 0.5mM TCEP and a cOMPLETE EDTA free protease inhibitor tablet added per liter followed by sonication. Lysate was clarified by centrifugation and loaded onto a 5mL Ni-NTA column pre-equilibrated with the lysis buffer supplemented with 10mM Imidazole. The tagged protein was eluted off the column with a buffer of 300mM NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 300mM imidazole, and 0.5mM TCEP. The 6xHis tag was cleaved by TEV protease protease added in a ratio of 1:20 by mass and dialyzed into a buffer of 150mM NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCL pH 7.5, 5% glycerol, and 0.5mM TCEP overnight. The cleaved protein was separated by rerunning the cleaving reaction over a Ni-NTA column and collecting the flow through. The cleaved protein was then concentrated with a 3kDa Amicon centrifugal filter and purified by size exclusion chromatography using an Superdex 75 16/600 column equilibrated with 100mM NaCl, 20mM HEPES pH 7.5, and 5% glycerol. Eluted fractions were pooled, filtered and flash frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at -80C.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4c">
<title>Purification of Refolded Orf9b</title>
<p>Orf9b (WT, Delta, Lambda, Omicron) was cloned into a pET-29a backbone with an N-terminal 6xHis tag and TEV protease cleavage site. BL21 E. coli cells from NEB were transformed and grown in a starter culture of Luria Broth at 37C overnight. 1L cultures were inoculated with 10mL of the starter culture and grown in Terrific Broth media supplemented with Kanamycin (100ug/mL) at 37C until an optical density of 0.6-0.8 was reached. Cultures were then induced with 1mM IPTG and grown at 16C overnight. Frozen cell pellets were resuspended in a lysis buffer of 300mM NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, and a cOMPLETE EDTA free protease inhibitor tablet added per liter followed by sonication. Lysate was clarified by centrifugation and loaded onto a 5mL HisTrap HP Ni-NTA column pre-equilibrated with the lysis buffer supplemented with 10mM Imidazole. 10 column volumes of buffer (6M Guanidine HCl, 300mM NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, and 0.1%Triton X-1000, 0.5mm TCEP) was flowed and the tagged protein was eluted with 6M Guanidine HCl, 300mM NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 300mM imidazole, and 0.5mM TCEP. The denatured tagged Orf9b was diluted to less than 65ug/mL in a refolding buffer composed of 550mM Guanidine HCl, 55mM Tris, 21mM NaCl, 0.88mM KCl at pH 8.2 overnight at 4C and allowed to refold. The refolded 6xHis tag was cleaved by TEV protease, added in a ratio of 1:20 by mass and dialyzed into a buffer of 150mM NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCL pH 7.5, and 0.5mM TCEP overnight. The cleaved protein was separated by rerunning the cleaving reaction over a Ni-NTA column and collecting the flow through. The cleaved protein was then concentrated with a 3kDa Amicon centrifugal filter and purified by size exclusion chromatography using an Superdex 75 16/600 column equilibrated with 100mM NaCl and 20mM HEPES pH 7.5 and 5% glycerol.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4d">
<title>Purification of hTom70</title>
<p>hTom70 (109-600) lacking the transmembrane domain was cloned into a pET-29b(+) backbone with an N-terminal 6xHis tag and SUMO tag. Transformation and growing conditions were the same as WT Orf9b other than the media being supplemented with Carbanicillin (100ug/mL). Ni-NTA column purification conditions and buffers were also the same as native Orf9b except for the cleavage of the 6x-His and SUMO tag which was performed with Ulp1 protease at a ratio of 1:20 by mass. All other conditions were the same except for size exclusion chromatography which was performed with a Superdex 200 16/600 column.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4e">
<title>Generating biotinylated Tom70</title>
<p>The Tom70 (109-600) plasmid was used for generating biotinylated Tom70 for SPR experiments. An AVI-tag was introduced to the N-terminus using a Q5 Site-Directed Mutagenesis kit (NEB: E0544S) and confirmed by sequencing. BL21 cells were cotransfected with the AVI-tagged plasmid and BirA biotin ligase plasmid in equal quantities by mass. Tom70 AVI-tagged plasmid was carbenicillin resistant and BirA was chloramphenicol resistant for double selection. Starter cultures were grown ON at 37C in LB media. 1L cultures were inoculated with 10mL of the starter culture and grown in Terrific Broth media supplemented with both chloramphenicol and carbenicillin (100ug/mL) and grown at 37C until an optical density of 0.6-0.8 was reached. 1L cultures were then induced with 1mM IPTG and 100uM biotin and grown overnight at 16C. Purification proceeded as previously described with the modification of not including a TEV cleavage reaction.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4f">
<title>Generation and Purification of Orf9b Mutants</title>
<p>Orf9b mutants (Δ91-97 and 4xSGG) were generated by mutagenesis using the WT Orf9b plasmid. Mutations were introduced by primers using a Q5 Site-Directed Mutagenesis kit (NEB: E0544S). Mutants were transformed into NEB 5-alpha cells and colonies grown in 10mL of LB overnight at 37C. Mutants were subjected to miniprep and submitted for sequencing to confirm the mutation’s presence. Growth and purification conditions of all constructs were the same as WT Orf9b.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4g">
<title>FP kinetic experiments</title>
<p>Orf9b-FITC was synthesized by Biomatik comprising residues 44-70 of Orf9b with a C-terminal fluorescein fluorophore. Orf9b-FITC was resuspended from lyophilized powder in a 3:1 ratio of 100mM NaCl, 20mM HEPES pH 7.5 and DMSO and filtered. 2uM of Orf9b-FITC was mixed with 25uM Tom70 in a buffer of 100mM NaCl, 20mM HEPES pH 7.5, 0.5mM TCEP to generate the 10x fluorescent Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 complex in black eppendorf tubes and equilibrated for 1hr. 90uL of Orf9b (peptide, refolded or native) was added to black 96 well plates with a non binding surface (Greiner: 655900). 10uL of the 10x Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 complex was then added to initiate the kinetic experiment. A solution of 200nM Orf9b-FITC in buffer was used to determine the minimal FP signal. We chased the pre-equilibrated Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 fluorescent complex with either unlabeled Orf9b peptides or Orf9b homodimer (WT, VOC, and fusion) and monitored the decrease in polarization until equilibrium was reached. Measurements were performed on a Tecan Spark running Magellan with a monochromator (excitation: 485nm, emission: 535nm). Measurements were taken in 15 second intervals between measurements with 7 seconds of shaking between intervals. Biological replicates of the kinetic assay were performed by repurifying all Orf9b variants presented following the denaturing and refolding.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4h">
<title>Refolded and Lipid-bound Orf9b Homodimer Crystallization and Refinement</title>
<p>TEV cleaved refolded Orf9b was concentrated to 10mg/ml and crystallized by sitting drop diffusion with a reservoir buffer of 1.2M Sodium Phosphate, 0.8M Potassium Phosphate, 0.2M Lithium Sulfate, and 0.1M Glycine pH 10.5 at 20C. Crystallization drops were set up with 200nL of Orf9b mixed with 200nL of the mother liquor in SWISSCI 2-well plates. TEV cleaved natively folded Orf9b was concentrated to 10mg/ml and crystallized by sitting drop diffusion with a reservoir buffer of 10% PEG 3350, 10% PEG 1000, 10% MPD, 100mM Imidazole pH 6.5, 100M MES pH 6.5, and 150mM Ethylene glycol at 20C. Crystallization drops were set up with 200nL of Orf9b mixed with 200nL of the mother liquor in SWISSCI 2-well plates. Crystals appeared 1 day after plating and grew to a maximum size in 7 days. All crystals appeared 1 day after plating and grew to a maximum size in 7 days. Crystals were looped and flash frozen without added cryogen. X-ray diffraction data was collected at the Advanced Light Source beamline 8.3.1. Diffraction data was indexed in XDS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">Kabsch 2010</xref>) and merged and scaled in XSCALE. Molecular replacement was performed in phenix.phaser (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c47">Winn et al. 2011</xref>) using PDB 6Z4U as a reference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">Echols et al. 2012</xref>) with 5 macrocycles of refinement and was deposited under PDB 9MZB and 9N55. Polder maps were generated in phenix.polder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c24">Liebschner et al. 2017</xref>)</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4i">
<title>Surface Plasmon Resonance</title>
<p>For studying Orf9b peptide/Orf9b:Tom70 kinetics, biotinylated Tom70 was immobilized to a CMD500M chip (Xantec: SPSMCMD500M). 250nM biotin-Tom70 was immobilized for 60s at 25uL/s to either spots B or C on a neutravidin coated surface followed by 120s of dissociation. Spot A on the chip was used as a reference surface and had no Tom70 immobilized to it. Analytes used for studying Tom70 binding were exchanged into the SPR running buffer using Pierce 7k MWCO Desalting Spin columns (Thermo: 89862). Blank injections of the running buffer were regularly interspersed between analyte injections. Binding kinetics were performed using a Bruker SPR-24 Pro. All SPR experiments were performed using a running buffer of 100mM NaCl, 20mM HEPES pH 7.5, 0.5mM TCEP, and 0.05% Tween20. All binding sensorgrams were double reference subtracted from the reference surface and the running buffer blank injections. Sensorgram fitting to determine kinetic rates and K<sub>D</sub> were performed using Sierra Analyser 3 provided by Bruker.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4j">
<title>Kinetic Modeling</title>
<p>Modeling of the FP binding data was performed in Berkeley Madonna v10.6.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c28">Marcoline et al. 2022</xref>) using the Rosenbrock stiff ordinary differential equations (ODE) solver with a 10<sup>-2</sup> relative tolerance and a maximum time step of 1 second. All data fitting used the Nelder-Mead simplex method and a root mean squared error function between the model solution and the experimental data points. Converting from fluorescent polarization values to concentration of Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 complex was accomplished using the following equation:</p>
<p><italic>(Signal(t) - Background Signal)/Max FP signal * Conc. Fluorescent Complex = Conc. Fluorescent Complex (t)</italic></p>
<p>where max FP signal at time <italic>t</italic> is the FP signal produced in the absence of unlabeled competitor and the concentration of the fluorescent complex is the maximum concentration achieved based on the concentration of Orf9b-FITC and Tom70 and the dissociation constant for the complex. The model was initially populated with experimental values taken directly from surface plasmon resonance experiments. We then performed optimizations fitting the kinetic curves for the lowest concentrations (individually) and with additional minor adjustments to derive the best agreement with the experimental data. We used these model parameters to show the correct behavior as the concentration of Orf9b homodimer changed between conditions. For scenarios involving an initial equilibrium between monomer and dimer populations prior to the start of the experiment (Orf9b T60A variant), we solved for the steady state equilibrium concentrations algebraically and then estimated their initial starting concentrations for each condition in the ODE solver.</p>
<p>For sensitivity analysis to the peptide model in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>, we inspected each model parameter by applying a +/-10% change to the reported values to observe their effect on the models performance. Only the rate of Orf9b-FITC dissociation showed sensitivity to change producing the most notable differences in model performance relative to the experimental data. For the homodimer model outlined in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4Ai</xref> and Aii, the model was most sensitive to the rate of β to α-monomer conversion and the rate of homodimer association and dissociation. For the apo-homodimer dataset, we investigated both parameters for each concentration series and observed that both parameters were sensitive to change at the lowest concentration of 5uM but became insensitive to change at the highest concentration of 50uM suggesting that the model parameter describing the rate of β to α-monomer conversion is not essential at the highest concentrations but remains essential at the lowest concentrations. Further, we repeated this analysis for the lipid-bound dataset across all concentration series which revealed that the model was sensitive to perturbation of both parameters at all concentrations. These three parameters show similar sensitivity because they exist as sequential steps in the rate limiting part of the reaction and are sensitive to the perturbations we introduce.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4k">
<title>Co-immunoprecipitation assay</title>
<p>HEK293T cells were transfected with the indicated mammalian expression plasmids using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). After 24 hours, the cells were harvested and lysed in NP-40 lysis buffer (0.5% Nonidet P-40 Substitute (NP-40; Fluka Analytical), 50LJmM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4 at 4LJ°C), 150LJmM NaCl, and 1LJmM EDTA) supplemented with cOmplete Mini EDTA-free protease inhibitor and PhosSTOP phosphatase inhibitor cocktails (Roche). The clarified lysates were incubated with anti-DYKDDDDK magnetic agarose (Pierce) or Strep-Tactin Sepharose beads (IBA) for 2 hours or overnight (for endogenous pull-downs) at 4LJ°C, followed by five washes with NP-40 lysis buffer. Bound protein complexes were eluted in SDS loading buffer or using 3X flag peptide (Sigma) and analyzed by western blotting using the indicated antibodies. Antibodies used: rabbit anti–Strep-tag II (Abcam, ab232586); rabbit anti-β-actin (Cell Signaling Technology, 4967); monoclonal mouse anti-Flag M2 (Sigma Aldrich, F1804); monoclonal mouse anti-Tom70 (Santa Cruz, sc-390545); and polyclonal rabbit anti-Flag (Sigma Aldrich, F7425).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4l">
<title>IFN-signaling assay</title>
<p>Each viral protein was overexpressed in HEK293T cells containing a Lucia reporter under the control of the IFN-β/ISG56 promoter, alongside a vector control. For viral protein expression, cells were transfected with 250 ng of either an empty vector or a vector encoding Orf9b WT or mutants using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). Twenty-four hours after plasmid transfection, cells were stimulated with 3p-hpRNA (InvivoGen), a RIG-I agonist. After an additional 24 hours, 20 µL of cell media (supernatant) from each well was transferred into a 96-well white (opaque) plate and mixed with 50 µL of QUANTI-Luc™ 4 Lucia/Gaussia “Glow” solution (InvivoGen). Lucia activity was measured by reading luminescence on a SpectraMax iD3 system, and fold activation was calculated relative to unstimulated cells.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4m">
<title>Native Mass Spectrometry</title>
<p>For native mass spectrometry analysis, protein samples were desalted into 200 mM ammonium acetate using a 7 kDa MWCO spin centrifugal column (Thermo Fisher Scientific) to eliminate non-volatile buffer components. The desalted protein was diluted to a final concentration of 0.5 µM in ammonium acetate and loaded into a metal-coated borosilicate nanoelectrospray emitter (Thermo Scientific) and infused into a Q Exactive Extended Mass Range (EMR) Orbitrap mass spectrometer (Thermo Scientific) in negative polarity mode. The instrument was operated with the following parameters: capillary voltage 0.9–1.5 kV, capillary temperature 200 °C, and resolving power set to 17,500 (at m/z 200). Ion optics were tuned to preserve macromolecular complexes using a source DC offset of -15 V, injection flatapole DC of -10 V, inter-flatapole lens DC of -5 V, bent flatapole DC of -5 V, and transfer multipole DC of 0 V. Additional settings included 5 microscans, an automatic gain control (AGC) target of 3e<sup>6</sup>, S-lens RF level of 200, and trapping gas pressure of 1.0 (arbitrary units) to minimize collisional activation. Raw mass spectra were acquired across a m/z range of 900–7,000 and deconvoluted using UniDec software (v5.0.2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c30">Marty et al. 2015</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4n">
<title>Mass Spectrometry</title>
<p>Lipid isolation was performed using a protocol derived from the Folch method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c10">Folch, Lees, and Sloane Stanley 1957</xref>). Purified protein (10 μL) was combined with a 2:1 (v/v) methanol-chloroform mixture (500 μL) and vortexed thoroughly to ensure homogeneity. The mixture was incubated at ambient temperature for 10 min to solubilize the lipids. Phase separation was induced by adding ultrapure water to adjust the solvent ratio to 1:1:0.9 (methanol:chloroform:water), followed by centrifugation at 2,000 × g for 10 min. The lower chloroform-rich phase, enriched in lipids, was isolated, evaporated to dryness, and redissolved in 500 μL of 50:50 (v/v) acetonitrile:water supplemented with 0.1% formic acid. For mass spectrometric analysis, the reconstituted sample was directly infused into a Thermo Scientific Q Exactive Plus mass spectrometer via a syringe pump at 3 μL/min flow rate. Electrospray ionization was employed with a spray voltage of 2 kV and a capillary temperature of 320°C in the positive polarity mode. High-resolution full-scan spectra were acquired at 140,000 resolution (m/z 200) across a range of m/z 150–1000. Targeted lipid ions were subjected to tandem MS (MS/MS) fragmentation for structural elucidation. Data was processed using Freestyle 1.8 SP2 software. Lipid identification was performed by matching acquired spectra to theoretical isotopic distributions and fragmentation patterns using the LIPID MAPS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c7">Conroy et al. 2024</xref>), Human Metabolome Dase (HMDB) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c48">Wishart et al. 2022</xref>), and PubChem databases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c21">Kim et al. 2025</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>

</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>We acknowledge helpful comments from Jason Gestwicki and John Gross. This work was funded by NIH U19AI171110 and GM145238 (to JSF) and R01GM137109 (to MG). Native mass spectrometric experiments were conducted on the Thermo Scientific Exactive Plus EMR, funded by the UCSF Research Resource Program and NIH P41GM103481, at the Mass Spectrometry Resource at UCSF (A.L. Burlingame, Director), supported by the Dr. Miriam and Sheldon G. Adelson Medical Research Foundation (AMRF) and the NIH-NIGMS. The diffraction data of structures reported in this work was collected at beamline 8.3.1. of the Advanced Light Source (ALS). The ALS, a U.S. DOE Office of Science User Facility under contract no. DE-AC02-05CH11231, is supported in part by the ALS-ENABLE program funded by the NIH, National Institute of General Medical Sciences, grant P30GM124169.</p>
</ack>
<sec id="suppd1e1808" sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Additional files</title>
<supplementary-material id="d1e1799">
<label>Supplementary Files</label>
<media xlink:href="supplements/638509_file02.docx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="c1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Backes</surname>, <given-names>Sandra</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yury S.</given-names> <surname>Bykov</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Tamara</given-names> <surname>Flohr</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Markus</given-names> <surname>Räschle</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jialin</given-names> <surname>Zhou</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Svenja</given-names> <surname>Lenhard</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Lena</given-names> <surname>Krämer</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2021</year>. “<article-title>The Chaperone-Binding Activity of the Mitochondrial Surface Receptor Tom70 Protects the Cytosol against Mitoprotein-Induced Stress</article-title>.” <source>Cell Reports</source> <volume>35</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>108936</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Backes</surname>, <given-names>Sandra</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Steffen</given-names> <surname>Hess</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Felix</given-names> <surname>Boos</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Michael W.</given-names> <surname>Woellhaf</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Sabrina</given-names> <surname>Gödel</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Martin</given-names> <surname>Jung</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Timo</given-names> <surname>Mühlhaus</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Johannes M.</given-names> <surname>Herrmann</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. “<article-title>Tom70 Enhances Mitochondrial Preprotein Import Efficiency by Binding to Internal Targeting Sequences</article-title>.” <source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source> <volume>217</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1369</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Blanco-Melo</surname>, <given-names>Daniel</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Benjamin E.</given-names> <surname>Nilsson-Payant</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Wen-Chun</given-names> <surname>Liu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Skyler</given-names> <surname>Uhl</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Daisy</given-names> <surname>Hoagland</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Rasmus</given-names> <surname>Møller</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Tristan X.</given-names> <surname>Jordan</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2020</year>. “<article-title>Imbalanced Host Response to SARS-CoV-2 Drives Development of COVID-19</article-title>.” <source>Cell</source> <volume>181</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1036</fpage>–<lpage>45.e9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bouhaddou</surname>, <given-names>Mehdi</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Danish</given-names> <surname>Memon</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Bjoern</given-names> <surname>Meyer</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Kris M.</given-names> <surname>White</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Veronica V.</given-names> <surname>Rezelj</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Miguel Correa</given-names> <surname>Marrero</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Benjamin J.</given-names> <surname>Polacco</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2020</year>. “<article-title>The Global Phosphorylation Landscape of SARS-CoV-2 Infection</article-title>.” <source>Cell</source> <volume>182</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>712.e19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bouhaddou</surname>, <given-names>Mehdi</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ann-Kathrin</given-names> <surname>Reuschl</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Benjamin J.</given-names> <surname>Polacco</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Lucy G.</given-names> <surname>Thorne</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Manisha R.</given-names> <surname>Ummadi</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Chengjin</given-names> <surname>Ye</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Romel</given-names> <surname>Rosales</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2023</year>. “<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Variants Evolve Convergent Strategies to Remodel the Host Response</article-title>.” <source>Cell</source> <volume>186</volume> (<issue>21</issue>): <fpage>4597</fpage>–<lpage>4614.e26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bu</surname>, <given-names>Lang</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Huan</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Shuishen</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yi</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Miaowen</given-names> <surname>Liu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Zhengkun</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Xueji</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2024</year>. “<article-title>Targeting APT2 Improves MAVS Palmitoylation and Antiviral Innate Immunity</article-title>.” <source>Molecular Cell</source> <volume>84</volume> (<issue>18</issue>): <fpage>3513</fpage>–<lpage>29.e5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Conroy</surname>, <given-names>Matthew J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Robert M.</given-names> <surname>Andrews</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Simon</given-names> <surname>Andrews</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Lauren</given-names> <surname>Cockayne</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Edward A.</given-names> <surname>Dennis</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Eoin</given-names> <surname>Fahy</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Caroline</given-names> <surname>Gaud</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2024</year>. “<article-title>LIPID MAPS: Update to Databases and Tools for the Lipidomics Community</article-title>.” <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source> <volume>52</volume> (<issue>D1</issue>): <fpage>D1677</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Echols</surname>, <given-names>Nathaniel</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ralf W.</given-names> <surname>Grosse-Kunstleve</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Pavel V.</given-names> <surname>Afonine</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Gábor</given-names> <surname>Bunkóczi</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Vincent B.</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jeffrey J.</given-names> <surname>Headd</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Airlie J.</given-names> <surname>McCoy</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2012</year>. “<article-title>Graphical Tools for Macromolecular Crystallography in PHENIX</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Applied Crystallography</source> <volume>45</volume> (<issue>Pt 3</issue>): <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Felgenhauer</surname>, <given-names>Ulrike</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Andreas</given-names> <surname>Schoen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Hans Henrik</given-names> <surname>Gad</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Rune</given-names> <surname>Hartmann</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Andreas R.</given-names> <surname>Schaubmar</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Klaus</given-names> <surname>Failing</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Christian</given-names> <surname>Drosten</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Friedemann</given-names> <surname>Weber</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. “<article-title>Inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 by Type I and Type III Interferons</article-title>.” <source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source> <volume>295</volume> (<issue>41</issue>): <fpage>13958</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Folch</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Lees</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>G. H.</given-names> <surname>Sloane Stanley</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>1957</year>. “<article-title>A Simple Method for the Isolation and Purification of Total Lipides from Animal Tissues</article-title>.” <source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source> <volume>226</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>, <given-names>Xiaopan</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Kaixiang</given-names> <surname>Zhu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Bo</given-names> <surname>Qin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Vincent</given-names> <surname>Olieric</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Meitian</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Sheng</given-names> <surname>Cui</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. “<article-title>Crystal Structure of SARS-CoV-2 Orf9b in Complex with Human TOM70 Suggests Unusual Virus-Host Interactions</article-title>.” <source>Nature Communications</source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>2843</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gordon</surname>, <given-names>David E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Joseph</given-names> <surname>Hiatt</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Mehdi</given-names> <surname>Bouhaddou</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Veronica V.</given-names> <surname>Rezelj</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Svenja</given-names> <surname>Ulferts</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Hannes</given-names> <surname>Braberg</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Alexander S.</given-names> <surname>Jureka</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2020</year>. “<article-title>Comparative Host-Coronavirus Protein Interaction Networks Reveal Pan-Viral Disease Mechanisms</article-title>.” <source>Science</source> <volume>370</volume> (<issue>6521</issue>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abe9403</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Han</surname>, <given-names>Lulu</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yi</given-names> <surname>Zheng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jian</given-names> <surname>Deng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Mei-Ling</given-names> <surname>Nan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yang</given-names> <surname>Xiao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Meng-Wei</given-names> <surname>Zhuang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jing</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Wei</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Chengjiang</given-names> <surname>Gao</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Pei-Hui</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. “<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 ORF10 Antagonizes STING-Dependent Interferon Activation and Autophagy</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Medical Virology</source> <volume>94</volume> (<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>5174</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Han</surname>, <given-names>Lulu</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Meng-Wei</given-names> <surname>Zhuang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jian</given-names> <surname>Deng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yi</given-names> <surname>Zheng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jing</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Mei-Ling</given-names> <surname>Nan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Xue-Jing</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Chengjiang</given-names> <surname>Gao</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Pei-Hui</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. “<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 ORF9b Antagonizes Type I and III Interferons by Targeting Multiple Components of the RIG-I/MDA-5-MAVS, TLR3-TRIF, and cGAS-STING Signaling Pathways</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Medical Virology</source> <volume>93</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>5376</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hornung</surname>, <given-names>Veit</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jana</given-names> <surname>Ellegast</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Sarah</given-names> <surname>Kim</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Krzysztof</given-names> <surname>Brzózka</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Andreas</given-names> <surname>Jung</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Hiroki</given-names> <surname>Kato</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Hendrik</given-names> <surname>Poeck</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2006</year>. <article-title>5’-Triphosphate RNA Is the Ligand for RIG-I</article-title>, <source>Science</source>, <volume>314</volume> (<issue>5801</issue>): <fpage>994</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>He-Wei</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Hai-Nan</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Qing-Feng</given-names> <surname>Meng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jia</given-names> <surname>Xie</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yang</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Hong</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yun-Xiao</given-names> <surname>Zheng</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2020</year>. “<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Orf9b Suppresses Type I Interferon Responses by Targeting TOM70</article-title>.” <source>Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology</source> <volume>17</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>998</fpage>–<lpage>1000</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jin</surname>, <given-names>Xiyue</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Xue</given-names> <surname>Sun</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yan</given-names> <surname>Chai</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yu</given-names> <surname>Bai</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ying</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Tianjiao</given-names> <surname>Hao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jianxun</given-names> <surname>Qi</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Hao</given-names> <surname>Song</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Catherine C. L.</given-names> <surname>Wong</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>George F.</given-names> <surname>Gao</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. “<article-title>Structural Characterization of SARS-CoV-2 Dimeric ORF9b Reveals Potential Fold-Switching Trigger Mechanism</article-title>.” <source>Science China Life Sciences</source> <volume>66</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Joshi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Seidel-Morgenstern</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Kremling</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Exploiting the Bootstrap Method for Quantifying Parameter Confidence Intervals in Dynamical Systems</article-title>.” <source>Metabolic Engineering</source> <volume>8</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kabsch</surname>, <given-names>Wolfgang</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>XDS</article-title>.” <source>Acta Crystallographica. Section D, Biological Crystallography</source> <volume>66</volume> (<issue>Pt 2</issue>): <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kang</surname>, <given-names>Dong-Chul</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Rahul V.</given-names> <surname>Gopalkrishnan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Qingping</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Eckhard</given-names> <surname>Jankowsky</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Anna Marie</given-names> <surname>Pyle</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Paul B.</given-names> <surname>Fisher</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2002</year>. “<article-title>Mda-5: An Interferon-Inducible Putative RNA Helicase with Double-Stranded RNA-Dependent ATPase Activity and Melanoma Growth-Suppressive Properties</article-title>.” <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>99</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>, <given-names>Sunghwan</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jie</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Tiejun</given-names> <surname>Cheng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Asta</given-names> <surname>Gindulyte</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jia</given-names> <surname>He</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Siqian</given-names> <surname>He</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Qingliang</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2025</year>. “<article-title>PubChem 2025 Update</article-title>.” <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source> <volume>53</volume> (<issue>D1</issue>): <fpage>D1516</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kreutz</surname>, <given-names>Clemens</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Andreas</given-names> <surname>Raue</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Jens</given-names> <surname>Timmer</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. “<article-title>Likelihood Based Observability Analysis and Confidence Intervals for Predictions of Dynamic Models</article-title>.” <source>BMC Systems Biology</source> <volume>6</volume> (<month>September</month>):<fpage>120</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>Jae Seung</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Mark</given-names> <surname>Dittmar</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jesse</given-names> <surname>Miller</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Minghua</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Kasirajan</given-names> <surname>Ayyanathan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Max</given-names> <surname>Ferretti</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jesse</given-names> <surname>Hulahan</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2024</year>. “<article-title>Pressure to Evade Cell-Autonomous Innate Sensing Reveals Interplay between Mitophagy, IFN Signaling, and SARS-CoV-2 Evolution</article-title>.” <source>Cell Reports</source> <volume>44</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>115115</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liebschner</surname>, <given-names>Dorothee</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Pavel V.</given-names> <surname>Afonine</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Nigel W.</given-names> <surname>Moriarty</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Billy K.</given-names> <surname>Poon</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Oleg V.</given-names> <surname>Sobolev</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Thomas C.</given-names> <surname>Terwilliger</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Paul D.</given-names> <surname>Adams</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Polder Maps: Improving OMIT Maps by Excluding Bulk Solvent</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallographica. Section D, Structural Biology</source> <volume>73</volume> (<issue>Pt 2</issue>): <fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>, <given-names>Rongtuan</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Suzanne</given-names> <surname>Paz</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>John</given-names> <surname>Hiscott</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>Tom70 Imports Antiviral Immunity to the Mitochondria</article-title>.” <source>Cell Research</source> <volume>20</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>971</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>Xin-Yi</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Bo</given-names> <surname>Wei</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>He-Xin</given-names> <surname>Shi</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yu-Fei</given-names> <surname>Shan</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Chen</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>Tom70 Mediates Activation of Interferon Regulatory Factor 3 on Mitochondria</article-title>.” <source>Cell Research</source> <volume>20</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>994</fpage>–<lpage>1011</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>Yongzhen</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Chao</given-names> <surname>Qin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Youliang</given-names> <surname>Rao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Chau</given-names> <surname>Ngo</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Joshua J.</given-names> <surname>Feng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jun</given-names> <surname>Zhao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Shu</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2021</year>. “<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Nsp5 Demonstrates Two Distinct Mechanisms Targeting RIG-I and MAVS To Evade the Innate Immune Response</article-title>.” <source>mBio</source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>e0233521</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marcoline</surname>, <given-names>Frank V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>John</given-names> <surname>Furth</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Smita</given-names> <surname>Nayak</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Michael</given-names> <surname>Grabe</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Robert I.</given-names> <surname>Macey</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. “<article-title>Berkeley Madonna Version 10-A Simulation Package for Solving Mathematical Models</article-title>.” <source>CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology</source> <volume>11</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>290</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marra</surname>, <given-names>Marco A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Steven J. M.</given-names> <surname>Jones</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Caroline R.</given-names> <surname>Astell</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Robert A.</given-names> <surname>Holt</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Angela</given-names> <surname>Brooks-Wilson</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yaron S. N.</given-names> <surname>Butterfield</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jaswinder</given-names> <surname>Khattra</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2003</year>. <article-title>The Genome Sequence of the SARS-Associated Coronavirus</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>300</volume> (<issue>5624</issue>): <fpage>1399</fpage>–<lpage>1404</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marty</surname>, <given-names>Michael T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Andrew J.</given-names> <surname>Baldwin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Erik G.</given-names> <surname>Marklund</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Georg K. A.</given-names> <surname>Hochberg</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Justin L. P.</given-names> <surname>Benesch</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Carol V.</given-names> <surname>Robinson</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. “<article-title>Bayesian Deconvolution of Mass and Ion Mobility Spectra: From Binary Interactions to Polydisperse Ensembles</article-title>.” <source>Analytical Chemistry</source> <volume>87</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>4370</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McWhirter</surname>, <given-names>Sarah M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Benjamin R.</given-names> <surname>Tenoever</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Tom</given-names> <surname>Maniatis</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>Connecting Mitochondria and Innate Immunity</article-title>.” <source>Cell</source> <volume>122</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>645</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Meier</surname>, <given-names>Christoph</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Radu Aricescu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Rene</given-names> <surname>Assenberg</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Robin T.</given-names> <surname>Aplin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Robert J. C.</given-names> <surname>Gilbert</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jonathan M.</given-names> <surname>Grimes</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>David I.</given-names> <surname>Stuart</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>The Crystal Structure of ORF-9b, a Lipid Binding Protein from the SARS Coronavirus</article-title>.” <source>Structure</source> <volume>14</volume> (<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1157</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mills</surname>, <given-names>Ryan D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jill</given-names> <surname>Trewhella</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Theresa Wenli</given-names> <surname>Qiu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Thomas</given-names> <surname>Welte</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Timothy M.</given-names> <surname>Ryan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Tracey</given-names> <surname>Hanley</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Robert B.</given-names> <surname>Knott</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Trevor</given-names> <surname>Lithgow</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Terrence D.</given-names> <surname>Mulhern</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>Domain Organization of the Monomeric Form of the Tom70 Mitochondrial Import Receptor</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source> <volume>388</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1043</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pichlmair</surname>, <given-names>Andreas</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Oliver</given-names> <surname>Schulz</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Choon Ping</given-names> <surname>Tan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Tanja I.</given-names> <surname>Näslund</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Peter</given-names> <surname>Liljeström</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Friedemann</given-names> <surname>Weber</surname></string-name>, and <collab>Caetano Reis e Sousa</collab></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>IG-I-Mediated Antiviral Responses to Single-Stranded RNA Bearing 5’-Phosphates</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>314</volume> (<issue>5801</issue>): <fpage>997</fpage>–<lpage>1001</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rehwinkel</surname>, <given-names>Jan</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Choon Ping</given-names> <surname>Tan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Delphine</given-names> <surname>Goubau</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Oliver</given-names> <surname>Schulz</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Andreas</given-names> <surname>Pichlmair</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Katja</given-names> <surname>Bier</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Nicole</given-names> <surname>Robb</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>RIG-I Detects Viral Genomic RNA during Negative-Strand RNA Virus Infection</article-title>.” <source>Cell</source> <volume>140</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rota</surname>, <given-names>Paul A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Steven Oberste</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Stephan S.</given-names> <surname>Monroe</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>W.</given-names> <surname>Allan Nix</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ray</given-names> <surname>Campagnoli</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Joseph P.</given-names> <surname>Icenogle</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Silvia</given-names> <surname>Peñaranda</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2003</year>. <article-title>Characterization of a Novel Coronavirus Associated with Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>300</volume> (<issue>5624</issue>): <fpage>1394</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Seth</surname>, <given-names>Rashu B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Lijun</given-names> <surname>Sun</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Chee-Kwee</given-names> <surname>Ea</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Zhijian J.</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>Identification and Characterization of MAVS, a Mitochondrial Antiviral Signaling Protein That Activates NF-kappaB and IRF 3</article-title>.” <source>Cell</source> <volume>122</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shemesh</surname>, <given-names>Maya</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Turgut E.</given-names> <surname>Aktepe</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Joshua M.</given-names> <surname>Deerain</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Julie L.</given-names> <surname>McAuley</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Michelle D.</given-names> <surname>Audsley</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Cassandra T.</given-names> <surname>David</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Damian F. J.</given-names> <surname>Purcell</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2021</year>. “<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Suppresses IFNβ Production Mediated by NSP1, 5, 6, 15, ORF6 and ORF7b but Does Not Suppress the Effects of Added Interferon</article-title>.” <source>PLOS Pathogens</source> <volume>17</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>e1009800</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>S</given-names> <surname>Mesquita</surname></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Francisco</surname>, <given-names>Laurence Abrami</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Maurine E.</given-names> <surname>Linder</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Shernaz X.</given-names> <surname>Bamji</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Bryan C.</given-names> <surname>Dickinson</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>F.</given-names> <surname>Gisou van der Goot</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2024</year>. “<article-title>Mechanisms and Functions of Protein S-Acylation</article-title>.” <source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source> <volume>25</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>488</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stetson</surname>, <given-names>Daniel B.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Ruslan</given-names> <surname>Medzhitov</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Type I Interferons in Host Defense</article-title>.” <source>Immunity</source> <volume>25</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Takeuchi</surname>, <given-names>Osamu</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Shizuo</given-names> <surname>Akira</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>Innate Immunity to Virus Infection</article-title>.” <source>Immunological Reviews</source> <volume>227</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Thorne</surname>, <given-names>Lucy G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Mehdi</given-names> <surname>Bouhaddou</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ann-Kathrin</given-names> <surname>Reuschl</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Lorena</given-names> <surname>Zuliani-Alvarez</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ben</given-names> <surname>Polacco</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Adrian</given-names> <surname>Pelin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jyoti</given-names> <surname>Batra</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2022</year>. “<article-title>Evolution of Enhanced Innate Immune Evasion by SARS-CoV-2</article-title>.” <source>Nature</source> <volume>602</volume> (<issue>7897</issue>): <fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tuinstra</surname>, <given-names>Robbyn L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Francis C.</given-names> <surname>Peterson</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Snjezana</given-names> <surname>Kutlesa</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>E.</given-names> <surname>Sonay Elgin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Michael A.</given-names> <surname>Kron</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Brian F.</given-names> <surname>Volkman</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Interconversion between Two Unrelated Protein Folds in the Lymphotactin Native State</article-title>.” <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>105</volume> (<issue>13</issue>): <fpage>5057</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>Wenjing</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Zhuo</given-names> <surname>Zhou</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Xia</given-names> <surname>Xiao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Zhongqin</given-names> <surname>Tian</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Xiaojing</given-names> <surname>Dong</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Conghui</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Li</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2021</year>. “<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 nsp12 Attenuates Type I Interferon Production by Inhibiting IRF3 Nuclear Translocation</article-title>.” <source>Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology</source> <volume>18</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>945</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wei</surname>, <given-names>Bo</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ye</given-names> <surname>Cui</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yuefeng</given-names> <surname>Huang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Heng</given-names> <surname>Liu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Lin</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Mi</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Kang-Cheng</given-names> <surname>Ruan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Qin</given-names> <surname>Zhou</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Chen</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. “<article-title>Tom70 Mediates Sendai Virus-Induced Apoptosis on Mitochondria</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Virology</source> <volume>89</volume> (<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>3804</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wen</surname>, <given-names>Shubo</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yang</given-names> <surname>Song</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Chang</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ningyi</given-names> <surname>Jin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jingbo</given-names> <surname>Zhai</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Huijun</given-names> <surname>Lu</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. “<article-title>Positive Regulation of the Antiviral Activity of Interferon-Induced Transmembrane Protein 3 by S-Palmitoylation</article-title>.” <source>Frontiers in Immunology</source> <volume>13</volume> (<issue>June</issue>):<fpage>919477</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Winn</surname>, <given-names>Martyn D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Charles C.</given-names> <surname>Ballard</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Kevin D.</given-names> <surname>Cowtan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Eleanor J.</given-names> <surname>Dodson</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Paul</given-names> <surname>Emsley</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Phil R.</given-names> <surname>Evans</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ronan M.</given-names> <surname>Keegan</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2011</year>. “<article-title>Overview of the CCP4 Suite and Current Developments</article-title>.” <source>Acta Crystallographica. Section D, Biological Crystallography</source> <volume>67</volume> (<issue>Pt 4</issue>): <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wishart</surname>, <given-names>David S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Anchi</given-names> <surname>Guo</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Eponine</given-names> <surname>Oler</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Fei</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Afia</given-names> <surname>Anjum</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Harrison</given-names> <surname>Peters</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Raynard</given-names> <surname>Dizon</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2022</year>. “<article-title>HMDB 5.0: The Human Metabolome Database for 2022</article-title>.” <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source> <volume>50</volume> (<issue>D1</issue>): <fpage>D622</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>Jianing</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Yingmin</given-names> <surname>Cui</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Dalang</given-names> <surname>Yu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Guoqing</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ruifang</given-names> <surname>Cao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Zhili</given-names> <surname>Gu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Guangyi</given-names> <surname>Dai</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2023</year>. “<article-title>A Noncoding A-to-U Kozak Site Change Related to the High Transmissibility of Alpha, Delta, and Omicron VOCs</article-title>.” <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source> <volume>40</volume> (<issue>6</issue>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msad142</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>Shigao</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Alfred T.</given-names> <surname>Harding</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Catherine</given-names> <surname>Sweeney</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>David</given-names> <surname>Miao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Gregory</given-names> <surname>Swan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Connie</given-names> <surname>Zhou</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Zhaozhao</given-names> <surname>Jiang</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> <year>2019</year>. “<article-title>Control of Antiviral Innate Immune Response by Protein Geranylgeranylation</article-title>.” <source>Science Advances</source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <elocation-id>eaav7999</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Young</surname>, <given-names>Jason C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Nicholas J.</given-names> <surname>Hoogenraad</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>F.</given-names> <surname>Ulrich Hartl</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2003</year>. “<article-title>Molecular Chaperones Hsp90 and Hsp70 Deliver Preproteins to the Mitochondrial Import Receptor Tom70</article-title>.” <source>Cell</source> <volume>112</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="c52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zuber</surname>, <given-names>Philipp K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Tina</given-names> <surname>Daviter</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ramona</given-names> <surname>Heißmann</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ulrike</given-names> <surname>Persau</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Kristian</given-names> <surname>Schweimer</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Stefan H.</given-names> <surname>Knauer</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. “<article-title>Structural and Thermodynamic Analyses of the β-to-α Transformation in RfaH Reveal Principles of Fold-Switching Proteins</article-title>,” <source>October</source>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.76630</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<sub-article id="sa0" article-type="editor-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106484.2.sa3</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>eLife Assessment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sohn</surname>
<given-names>Jungsan</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role>
<aff>
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</institution>
</institution-wrap>
<city>Baltimore</city>
<country>United States of America</country>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="evidence-strength">
<kwd>Compelling</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="claim-importance">
<kwd>Fundamental</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>This <bold>fundamental</bold> study demonstrates that lipid binding can regulate the dimerization state of the SARS-CoV2 Orf9b protein. The data from biophysical and cellular experiments along with mathematical modeling are <bold>compelling</bold>. This paper is broadly relevant to those studying coupled equilibria across all aspects of biology.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa1" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106484.2.sa2</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #1 (Public review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>Felipe and colleagues try to answer an important question in Sarbecovirus Orf9b-mediated interferon signaling suppression, given that this small viral protein adopts two distinct conformations, a dimeric β-sheet-rich fold and a helix-rich monomeric fold when bound by Tom70 protein. Two Orf9b structures determined by X-ray crystallography and Cryo-EM suggest an equilibrium between the two Orf9b conformations, and it is important to understand how this equilibrium relates to its functions. To answer these questions, the authors developed a series of ordinary differential equations (ODE) describing the Orf9b conformation equilibrium between homodimers and monomers binding to Tom70. They used SPR and a fluorescent polarization (FP) peptide displacement assay to identify parameters for the equilibrium and create a theoretical model. They then used the model to characterize the effect of lipid-binding and the effects of Orf9b mutations in homodimer stability, lipid binding, and dimer-monomer equilibrium. They used their model to further analyze dimerization, lipid binding, and Orf9b-Tom70 interactions for truncated Orf9b, Orf9b fusion mutant S53E (blocking Tom70 binding), and Orf9b from a set of Sars-CoV-2 VOCs. They evaluated the ability of different Orf9b variants for binding Tom70 using Co-IP experiments and assessed their activity in suppressing IFN signaling in cells.</p>
<p>Overall, this work is well designed, the results are of high quality and well-presented; the results support their conclusions.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>(1) They developed a working biophysical model for analyzing Orf9b monomer-dimer equilibrium and Tom70 binding based on SPR and FP experiments; this is an important tool for future investigation.</p>
<p>(2) They prepared lipid-free Orf9b homodimer and determined its crystal structure.</p>
<p>(3) They designed and purified obligate Orf9b monomer, fused-dimer, etc., a very important Orf9b variant for further investigations.</p>
<p>(4) They identified the lipid bound by Orf9b homodimer using mass spectra data.</p>
<p>(5) They proposed a working model of Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>(1) It is difficult to understand why the obligate Orf9b dimer has similar IFN inhibition activity as the WT protein and obligate Orf9b monomer truncations.</p>
<p>(2) The role of Orf9b homodimer and the role of Orf9b-bound lipid in virus infection, remains unknown.</p>
<p>Comments on revisions:</p>
<p>In the revised manuscript, the authors have addressed my concerns.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa2" article-type="referee-report">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106484.2.sa1</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviewer #2 (Public review):</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<anonymous/>
<role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>This study focuses on Orf9b, a SARS-COV1/2 protein that regulates innate signaling through interaction with Tom70. San Felipe et al use a combination of biophysical methods to characterize the coupling between lipid-binding, dimerization, conformational change, and protein-protein-interaction equilibria for the Orf9b-Tom70 system. Their analysis provides a detailed explanation for previous observations of Orf9b function. In a cellular context, they find other factors may also be important for the biological functioning of Orf9b.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>San Felipe et al elegantly combine structural biology, biophysics, kinetic modelling, and cellular assays, allowing detailed analysis of the Orf9b-Tom70 system. Such complex systems involving coupled equilibria are prevalent in various aspects of biology, and a quantitative description of them, while challenging, provides a detailed understanding and prediction of biological outcomes. Using SPR to guide initial estimates of the rate constants for solution measurements is an interesting approach.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>This study would benefit from a more quantitative description of uncertainties in the numerous rate constants of the models, either through a detailed presentation of the sensitivity analysis or another approach such as MCMC. Quantitative uncertainty analysis, such as MCMC is not trivial for ODEs, particularly when they involve many parameters and are to be fitted to numerous data points, as is the case for this study. The authors use sensitivity analysis as an alternative, however, the results of the sensitivity analysis are not presented in detail, and I believe the authors should consider whether there is a way to present this analysis more quantitatively. For example, could the residuals for each +/-10% parameter change for the peptide model be presented as a supplementary figure, and similarly for the more complex models? Further details of the range of rate constants tested would be useful, particularly for the ka and kB parameters.</p>
<p>The authors build a model that incorporates an α-helix-β-sheet conformational change, but the rate constant for the conversion to the α-helix conformation is required to be second order. Although the authors provide some rationale, I do not find this satisfactorily convincing given the large number of adjustable parameters in the model and the use of manual model fitting. The authors should discuss whether there is any precedence for second-order rate constants for conformational changes in the literature. On page 14, the authors state this rate constant &quot;had to be non-linear in the monomer β-sheet concentration&quot; - how many other models did the authors explore? For example, would αT↔α↔αα↔ββ (i.e., conformational change before dimer dissociation) or α↔βαT↔ββ (i.e., Tom70 binding driving dimer dissociation) be other plausible models for the conformational change that do not require assumptions of second-order rate constants for the conformational change?</p>
<p>Overall, this study progresses the analysis of coupled equilibria and provides insights into Orf9b function.</p>
<p>Comments on revisions:</p>
<p>The authors have done a satisfactory job addressing my concerns.</p>
<p>Regarding my recommendations to the authors - point 7: &quot;Orf9b-FITC:Tom70&quot; and &quot;PT&quot;, representing the same species, are still both used in the equations on page 14, which is confusing for anyone who may wish to re-use the model. I appreciate this is quite a subtle point but given the importance of the model for the manuscript I feel the authors should do their due diligence to ensure it is presented as clearly as possible.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
<sub-article id="sa3" article-type="author-comment">
<front-stub>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.106484.2.sa0</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Author response:</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>San Felipe</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2695-5951</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Batra</surname>
<given-names>Jyoti</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Muralidharan</surname>
<given-names>Monita</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9401-0397</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Malpotra</surname>
<given-names>Shivali</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Anand</surname>
<given-names>Durga</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bauer</surname>
<given-names>Rachel</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Verba</surname>
<given-names>Kliment A</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2238-8590</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Swaney</surname>
<given-names>Danielle L</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6119-6084</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krogan</surname>
<given-names>Nevan J</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4902-337X</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grabe</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3509-5997</contrib-id></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fraser</surname>
<given-names>James S</given-names>
</name>
<role specific-use="author">Author</role>
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5080-2859</contrib-id></contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>The following is the authors’ response to the original reviews.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p><bold>Reviewer #1 (Public review):</bold></p>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>Felipe and colleagues try to answer an important question in Sarbecovirus Orf9b-mediated interferon signaling suppression, given that this small viral protein adopts two distinct conformations, a dimeric β-sheet-rich fold and a helix-rich monomeric fold when bound by Tom70 protein. Two Orf9b structures determined by X-ray crystallography and Cryo-EM suggest an equilibrium between the two Orf9b conformations, and it is important to understand how this equilibrium relates to its functions. To answer these questions, the authors developed a series of ordinary differential equations (ODE) describing the Orf9b conformation equilibrium between homodimers and monomers binding to Tom70. They used SPR and a fluorescent polarization (FP) peptide displacement assay to identify parameters for the equilibrium and create a theoretical model. They then used the model to characterize the effect of lipid-binding and the effects of Orf9b mutations in homodimer stability, lipid binding, and dimer-monomer equilibrium. They used their model to further analyze dimerization, lipid binding, and Orf9b-Tom70 interactions for truncated Orf9b, Orf9b fusion mutant S53E (blocking Tom70 binding), and Orf9b from a set of Sars-CoV-2 VOCs. They evaluated the ability of different Orf9b variants for binding Tom70 using Co-IP experiments and assessed their activity in suppressing IFN signaling in cells.</p>
<p>Overall, this work is well designed, the results are of high quality and well-presented; the results support their conclusions.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We thank reviewer #1 for their thoughtful assessment of our work and their constructive feedback.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>(1) They developed a working biophysical model for analyzing Orf9b monomer-dimer equilibrium and Tom70 binding based on SPR and FP experiments; this is an important tool for future investigation.</p>
<p>(2) They prepared lipid-free Orf9b homodimer and determined its crystal structure.</p>
<p>(3) They designed and purified obligate Orf9b monomer, fused-dimer, etc., a very important Orf9b variant for further investigations.</p>
<p>(4) They identified the lipid bound by Orf9b homodimer using mass spectra data.</p>
<p>(5) They proposed a working model of Orf9b-Tom70 equilibrium.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>(1) It is difficult to understand why the obligate Orf9b dimer has similar IFN inhibition activity as the WT protein and obligate Orf9b monomer truncations.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We thank the reviewer for their observation and agree that the obligate homodimer IFN results were not what we expected to observe given our FP kinetic results with the purified obligate homodimer and noted our surprise in the discussion. We also note that we have two possible hypotheses for why this is the case.</p>
<p>In our discussion, we noted the possible introduction of an increased avidity effect with fused homodimer and have improved it as follows with additions in red:</p>
<p>“This result was unexpected as we had anticipated the obligate homodimer results to resemble the phosphomimetic. We hypothesize that this may be explained by two possible factors. First, we can’t exclude the introduction of an increased avidity between Orf9b and Tom70 when using the fused homodimer. Although our modeled decrease in the association rate of Orf9b:Tom70 (which increases the K<sub>D</sub> of the complex) suggests that fusing two copies of Orf9b decreases the affinity to Tom70, one copy of the fusion construct could also be capable of either binding to two copies of Tom70, or, one copy of the fusion could undergo rapid rebinding to Tom70. These effects would lead to a much tighter interaction in cellular assays than we modeled in vitro. A second possible explanation is that our assumptions about high lipid binding are not valid for cell based assays.”</p>
<p>We also noted that a second possible explanation is due to our limitations in isolating the apo-fused homodimer to compare to the lipid-bound fused homodimer and possible differences this could have on our assays and briefly expanded upon this. Again, we improved this with additions in red:</p>
<p>“As we have shown with both WT and fusion constructs, recombinantly expressed and purified Orf9b is lipid-bound and this can stabilize the homodimer to slow or inhibit the binding to Tom70. For the Orf9b fusion construct, we attempted to isolate the lipid-free species through protein refolding as previously described to compare the effect of lipid-binding on the homodimer fusion (similar to our WT experiments); however, we could not recover the stably folded homodimer. We hypothesize that the discrepancy between our kinetic results and Co-IP/IFN results could be due to subsaturation of the Orf9b fusion homodimers by lipids in cell based assays. While we have shown that lipid-binding occurs in recombinant expression systems, it is possible that in our cell based signaling assays that lipid-binding only affects a minor population of Orf9b. Given that we were unable to isolate the apo-fusion homodimer, we could not directly compare whether there are differences in fusion homodimer stability in the presence or absence of lipid-binding. Therefore, it is possible that the apo-fusion homodimer undergoes unfolding and refolding into alpha helices that lead to Tom70 binding similar to the WT construct.”</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(2) The role of Orf9b homodimer and the role of Orf9b-bound lipid in virus infection, remains unknown.</p>
<p>We agree that we did not try to directly test for the role of the homodimer during infection and this remains an open area of exploration for future studies. We have included this caveat in our discussion but suggested possible experiments and future directions that could help shed light on this:</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>“Although we have not directly tested for the role the homodimer conformation plays during infection, we have demonstrated that lipid-binding to the homodimer can bias the equilibrium away from Tom70. Lipids including palmitate have been shown to act as both a signaling molecule as well as a post-translational modification during antiviral innate immune signaling (S Mesquita et al. 2024; Wen et al. 2022; S. Yang et al. 2019). As a post-translational modification (referred to as S-acylation), MAVS, a mitochondrial type 1 IFN signaling protein that associates with Tom70 (X.-Y. Liu et al. 2010; McWhirter, Tenoever, and Maniatis 2005; Seth et al. 2005), has been shown to be post-translationally palmitoylated which affects its ability to localize to the mitochondrial outer membrane during viral infection and is a known target of Orf9b (Bu et al. 2024; Lee et al. 2024). When this is impaired (either by mutation or by depletion of the palmitoylation enzyme ZDHHC24), IFN activation is impaired (Bu et al. 2024). Therefore, future investigations should consider if the homodimer conformation of Orf9b is capable of antagonizing other IFN signaling factors such as MAVS by binding to palmitoyl groups. Indeed, Orf9b has already been shown to be capable of binding to MAVS by Co-IP (Han et al. 2021), however, whether or not this occurs through the palmitoyl modification remains unknown.”</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p><bold>Reviewer #2 (Public review):</bold></p>
<p>Summary:</p>
<p>This study focuses on Orf9b, a SARS-COV1/2 protein that regulates innate signaling through interaction with Tom70. San Felipe et al use a combination of biophysical methods to characterize the coupling between lipid-binding, dimerization, conformational change, and protein-protein-interaction equilibria for the Orf9b-Tom70 system. Their analysis provides a detailed explanation for previous observations of Orf9b function. In a cellular context, they find other factors may also be important for the biological functioning of Orf9b.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>San Felipe et al elegantly combine structural biology, biophysics, kinetic modelling, and cellular assays, allowing detailed analysis of the Orf9b-Tom70 system. Such complex systems involving coupled equilibria are prevalent in various aspects of biology, and a quantitative description of them, while challenging, provides a detailed understanding and prediction of biological outcomes. Using SPR to guide initial estimates of the rate constants for solution measurements is an interesting approach.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>This study would benefit from a more quantitative description of uncertainties in the numerous rate constants of the models, either through a detailed presentation of the sensitivity analysis or another approach such as MCMC. Quantitative uncertainty analysis, such as MCMC is not trivial for ODEs, particularly when they involve many parameters and are to be fitted to numerous data points, as is the case for this study. The authors use sensitivity analysis as an alternative, however, the results of the sensitivity analysis are not presented in detail, and I believe the authors should consider whether there is a way to present this analysis more quantitatively. For example, could the residuals for each +/-10% parameter change for the peptide model be presented as a supplementary figure, and similarly for the more complex models? Further details of the range of rate constants tested would be useful, particularly for the ka and kB parameters.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We thank the reviewer for their constructive feedback and have generated supplemental figures providing a deeper analysis of the residuals for each model parameter adjusted +/- 10% from the reported values which we have added to our supplemental figures as Figure 1 - Supplemental 3 and Figure 4 - Supplemental 5  .</p>
<p>We note that there are modest improvements in residual plots where model parameters are individually lowered by 10% from their reported value when considering this single dataset, however, our choice of using the reported values was driven by finding values that were suitable for improving model behavior across multiple concentration series in different datasets. Specifically, we have also included the RMSD values for each model parameter subjected to a +/-10% change from a single concentration time course as well as the percent change in RMSD relative to the RMSD generated by our reported model parameters to illustrate this. We have also included text that makes note of the observed pattern in the residuals from Figure 4 - Supplement 5 and provided some explanations for why this may occur.</p>
<p>“Inspection of the residuals from the 5uM apo-Orf9b homodimer time course showed clear patterns when individual model parameters were subjected to a 10% increase or decrease from the reported values. While our proposed model qualitatively describes the concentration dependent change in kinetic behavior, the residual plots may suggest that additional binding reactions may also be occurring that are not captured by our model.”</p>
<p>Figure 1 - Supplemental 3. Plots of residuals from Orf9b peptide model showing effect of an increase or decrease by 10% on each model parameter. All residuals and reporting are with respect to the100uM of unlabeled Orf9b peptide condition. Blue dots: reported value. Red dots: 10% increase in reported value. Green dots: 10% decrease in reported value. Table reporting of RMSD values for model fitsafter +/-10% change to model parameter (Left column) and percent change in RMSD relative to reported model RMSD (Right column).</p>
<p>“As an alternative to attempting to place CIs on the parameters, we performed sensitivity analysis to determine which parameters the model was most sensitive to (see methods and Figure 1 - Supplemental 3). Additionally, we note that the model parameters were derived from the fit of only one concentration (100uM), but fit the other concentrations equally well. We observed that the model parameter that was most sensitive to change was the rate of Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 ([PT]) dissociation when subjected to a 10% increase or decrease whereas all other model parameters showed no sensitivity to change (Figure 1 - Supplemental 3).”</p>
<p>Figure 4 - Supplemental 5: Plot of residuals showing the effect of increasing or decreasing individual model parameters 10% compared to the reported values. All residual plots are with respect to the 5uM apo-Orf9b homodimer condition. Blue dots: reported value. Red dot: 10% increase in reported value. Green dot: 10% decrease in reported value. (Left columns) Table of RMSD values calculated from model fits showing the effect of both +/-10% change to individual model parameters. (Right columns) Percent change in RMSD values subjected to +/-10% change for individual model parameters relative to the RMSD of the reported model.</p>
<p>We have also included the following revised text to accompany this figure.</p>
<p>“Further, we repeated the sensitivity analysis described previously for the peptide model and also considered the sensitivity of model parameters by inspecting each individually (Figure 4- figure supplemental 5). We found that when examining the residuals of the lowest concentration of 5uM, the model was most sensitive to changes in three parameters: the rate of homodimer association and dissociation and the conversion from β to α-monomers.”</p>
<p>“Therefore, under low concentrations of Orf9b homodimer, binding to Tom70 is limited by the rate of homodimer association and dissociation as well as the conversion of Orf9b monomers to the α-helical conformation.”</p>
<p>We have also included a supplemental figure showing how changes in the model parameters ka and kB affect the models behavior to help illustrate the range of values tested as Figure 4 - Supplemental 4.</p>
<p>Figure 4 - Supplemental 4: Plots of model behavior showing the effect of changes to alpha-beta and beta-alpha monomer  interconversion rates compared to experimental values. Data is modeled with respect to the apo-Orf9b homodimer 5uM condition. Black line represents reported model fit and values used.</p>
<p>We have also incorporated the following revised text.</p>
<p>“The model parameters k<sub>a</sub> and k<sub>B</sub> describe the rate of interchange between the β-sheet and α-helix monomer conformations. These parameters must be estimated by modeling because our assays do not allow us to directly measure the folding rates between these conformations. To identify these values, we performed a scan of k<sub>a</sub> and k<sub>B</sub> values that yielded the best agreement between the model and the experimental conditions (Figure 4 - figure supplemental 4).”</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>The authors build a model that incorporates an α-helix-β-sheet conformational change, but the rate constant for the conversion to the α-helix conformation is required to be second order. Although the authors provide some rationale, I do not find this satisfactorily convincing given the large number of adjustable parameters in the model and the use of manual model fitting. The authors should discuss whether there is any precedence for second-order rate constants for conformational changes in the literature. On page 14, the authors state this rate constant &quot;had to be non-linear in the monomer β-sheet concentration&quot; - how many other models did the authors explore? For example, would αT↔α↔αα↔ββ (i.e., conformational change before dimer dissociation) or α↔βαT↔ββ (i.e., Tom70 binding driving dimer dissociation) be other plausible models for the conformational change that do not require assumptions of second-order rate constants for the conformational change?</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We thank the reviewer for their feedback. During our studies, we tested several models prior to the final one presented in Figure 4A. The first model that we tested as described in Figure 4 - Supplemental 3 described ββ↔α↔αT with no conformational change. We tested several models that integrated the existing structural data for both Orf9b and Tom70 and found that while these models could fit individual time series, they did not explain the concentration dependent changes in subsequent time series nor did they explain changes induced by lipid-binding and mutations in VOC.</p>
<p>With respect to the possibilities of αT↔α↔αα↔ββ and α↔βαT↔ββ models, we have revised our manuscript to mention that we did test additional models before we settled on the model that we presented.</p>
<p>“We tested different reaction schemes that incorporated the interconversion between β-sheet to α-helix conformations by considering models that described a conformational change in the homodimer leading to Tom70 binding rather than monomers. None of these models adequately described our experimental results, therefore we continued developing our model as outlined in Figure 4D”</p>
<p>With respect to the second-order rate describing the fold change from β to α, we have added the revised text to the manuscript:</p>
<p>“We initially tested the impact of keeping the rate constant k<sub>a</sub> first order, just like k<sub>B</sub> which did yield the sigmoidal behavior we observed in the 5uM apo-homodimer condition. However, this assumption failed to describe the data at other concentrations resulting in a substantial overestimation compared to our experimental results when holding k<sub>B</sub> at a constant value throughout. We found that when the β-sheet to α-helix rate (k<sub>a</sub> ) was made a second order rate constant, we were able to hold the rate constant across all concentrations tested suggesting a non-linearity in the monomer β-sheet concentration.”</p>
<p>While this was surprising to us, we reasoned that a biological explanation for why the conversion from β to α was second order was that the β-monomers may transiently self-associate to cooperatively fold into the α-helical conformation. We did acknowledge this choice to make the β to α parameter non-linear (unlike the α to β conversion which was single order).</p>
<p>We concede that we could not find specific examples describing non-linear kinetics comparable to the system we described in literature, however, such systems have been reported for proteins that exhibit high structural plasticity where transient interactions with another copy of the protein or another protein altogether drive folding changes and we have revised this manuscript to include some additional citations to papers that describe such systems (Zuber et al. 2022; Tuinstra et al. 2008).</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>Overall, this study progresses the analysis of coupled equilibria and provides insights into Orf9b function.</p>
<p><bold>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations for the authors):</bold></p>
<p>(1) What was the unlabeled Orf9b peptide is added to the pre-equilibrated Orf9b-FITC:Tom70 solution as a competitor? Figure 1D illustrates that the competitor was full-length Orf9b.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We have revised the figure to illustrate that in this experiment, the competitor is the unlabeled FITC peptide and not the full length Orf9b sequence</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(2) Figure 2B, what is the higher Mw peak from refolded Orf9b homodimer.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We have added the following revised text (highlighted in red) to the manuscript to clarify Figure 2B.</p>
<p>“The SEC elution profile and retention volume of refolded Orf9b directly overlapped with natively folded homodimeric Orf9b and suggested a high recovery of the refolded homodimer with the early eluting peaks corresponding to either a chaperone-bound species (natively folded) or misfolded protein (refolded) as judged by SDS-PAGE (Figure 2B). Together, the overlap in elution peaks corresponding to the folded homodimer suggested a high recovery of the homodimer from the refolding conditions.”</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(3) Figure 2C, in the main text, the authors state that &quot;...observed that the refolded homodimer structure closely aligned with the lipid-bound reference structure, which shows that the homodimer fold can be recovered after denaturing&quot;. Please provide structural comparison details here, software used? Rmsd and Dali Z-score.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We have added the following revised text (highlighted in red) to the manuscript to clarify Figure 2C.</p>
<p>“Aligning the structure of the Orf9b homodimer (PDB 6Z4U) with our structure of the refolded Orf9b homodimer (9N55) in Pymol resulted in an RMSD of 1.1Å. Further, we also searched our structures of the refolded Orf9b homodimer on the Dali server against the existing structures of the lipid-bound Orf9b homodimer which yielded a Z-score of 2.2 which shows good correspondence between the structures.”</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(4) To prove the refolded Orf9b homodimer did not contain lipid, could the authors provide mass spectra data for the refolded Orf9b sample and compare it with the results in Figure 2 - Supplemental 1.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We do not have complete mass spectra data for the refolded homodimer samples, however, we feel that the native mass spectrometry data provides a good orthogonal comparison between natively folded and refolded samples for the presence or absence of lipids. We concede that we only used mass spectrometry to characterize the four peaks that were unique to the natively folded deconvoluted spectra which confirmed that shift in mass relative to the expected homodimer molecular weight corresponded to the two lipids we presented. However, we would expect that performing mass spectrometry on the refolded sample would only further confirm our observations from the crystal structures and the native mass spectrometry.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(5) Have the authors tried to use analytical ultracentrifugation to analyze the Orf9b dimer-monomer equilibrium, given that AUC provides a much more accurate measurement of molecular mass?</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We thank the reviewer for this suggestion and agree that AUC could be an additional useful strategy for monitoring the dimer-monomer equilibrium and provide additional validation of the molecule weights of both the monomer and homodimer.</p>
<p>While we have not performed AUC, we have revised our manuscript to include more discussion about the determination of molecular weights by SEC.</p>
<p>“For the Orf9b homodimer, the retention volume was consistent with molecular weight standards based on the expected molecular weight of the homodimer (~21kDa) and the standard (~29kDa). In the case of the Orf9b monomer, although we would expect the retention volume of the monomer (~10.6kDA) to be between the molecular weight standards of 13.4kDa and 6.5kDa, the greater retention volume could be explained by non-specific hydrophobic interactions between the monomeric Orf9b and the column.”</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(6) The authors used truncation of 7 C-terminal amino acids to generate an obligate Orf9b monomer for their assays. It would be interesting to mutate residues at the homodimer interface to generate Orf9b monomers rather than deleting residues. For example, mutate 91-96aa (FVVVTV) to negatively charged residues, which will not only disrupt the dimerization interface, but also impair lipid binding. The dimer interface mutant should then be tested in their SPR, FP assays, as well as IFN inhibition assays.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We thank the reviewer for their suggestion and agree that mutation of the 7 C-terminal amino acids into negatively charged residues could be an interesting alternative strategy to generating an obligate Orf9b monomer without the need for truncating the residues. Our choice of using the truncated construct we proposed was driven by our analysis of the structure of the homodimer which reveals that a significant portion of the dimer interface is composed of backbone-backbone hydrogen bonding between the two chains of Orf9b. We reasoned that truncating these residues would be the most effective way to compromise the interface between the two chains and drive a predominantly monomeric behavior, however, compromising the interface with multiple mutations is an intriguing alternative.</p>
<p><bold>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</bold></p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(1) The authors could comment on the slow monomer-dimer exchange observed by SEC and how it fits with their other analysis.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We thank the reviewer for their comment and concede that the slow exchange may be a limitation of this experimental setup. Our observations from our SPR experiments and modeling showed us that the homodimer may be fast to dissociate into monomer given the off rate which would suggest a half-life for the homodimer to be on the order of seconds, however, we still observe a noticeable dimer species on the chromatograms. We initially allowed the diluted samples to reach equilibrium prior to injection onto the analytical sizing column, however, it is possible that the system is still in a pre-equilibrium prior to injection onto the column. This could be driven by interactions between the protein and the column that prevents full dissociation of the homodimer. While this is a limitation, we note that we did not use the Kd value that we determined by non-linear regression fitting to the equilibrium observed on the chromatograms for downstream experiments but instead used the value to get a ballpark estimate for the homodimer Kd which is on the same order as the Kd determined by SPR.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(2) It might be useful to include the rate constants on the reaction arrows of the schematic representation of the models</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>.</p>
<p>We have revised Figure 4D to include the rates for both Orf9b monomer binding to Tom70 and Orf9b binding to Orf9b as derived from the SPR experiments as well as the modeled values for the interconversion between α and β monomers. We also revised Figure 7 to include these values as well as the modeled dissociation rate for homodimer when lipid-bound.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(3) I couldn't find how the sensitivity analysis was performed for the more complex models. Was this the same +/- 10% as per the peptide model?</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We used the same +/- 10% sensitivity analysis for the peptide model in the more complex equilibrium model and have revised our manuscript to clearly reflect that.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(4) Further clarification of &quot;inspection of residuals suggested that the fits were accurate&quot;. In Figure 1B, the residues look to have systematic errors, perhaps indicating other processes occurring.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We agree that in the SPR kinetic fitting results for the Orf9b peptide binding to Tom70 in Figure 1B that there are some regions where the fit over or under estimates the experimental results. This is partially the result of limitations in the number of different binding models that we can fit in the analysis software which is why we reported using a 1:1 langmuir binding model. It is certainly possible that there may be some additional binding reactions that occur, however, we limited our use of these specific kinetic results to the peptide model that we proposed in Figure 1D. We did note in the manuscript text that it was necessary for us to change the model parameter values to some extent in order to fit our experimental results which may be partially explained by the SPR fitting errors.</p>
<p>“With the parameter set obtained from the 100µM condition, we then held all parameters fixed and simply changed the peptide concentrations in the model to fit the remaining conditions by hand. We note that this process saw the model parameter values change between 3% at the lowest end up to 70% at the highest end from the experimentally derived values but remained within an order of magnitude of the experimental SPR values. We speculate that this arises due to the differences in experimental setup between SPR and FP-based methods of measuring kinetics.”</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(5) The manuscript builds logically, but given the sophisticated nature of the system and the modelling could benefit from more clarity/streamlining in the descriptions/illustrations.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We have revised our manuscript in response to both reviewers comments and hope that the clarity of the work is improved as a result.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(6) Figure 4 Supplement 3 - where did the rate constants for Model 1 come from? Was there any attempt to alter them to fit the data better?</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>We have clarified in the figure description that the rate constants used in Model 1 were the same values used in Figure 4B (but without the interconversion between beta and alpha rates).</p>
<p>“Comparison of kinetic model 1 and 2 in describing experimental results from the kinetic binding assay. Experimental results using 10uM of refolded Orf9b homodimer are shown as rings with the predicted behavior of model 1 (equilibrium exchange) shown as a dark blue line. The predicted behavior of model 2 (equilibrium exchange with a conformational change between β-sheet and ɑ-helical monomers) is shown as the light blue line. Model parameter values were the same as described in Figure 4D and kept constant in both model comparisons.”</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(7) What are and [PT] in the second set of equations (page 13)?</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>[‘PT] refers to the concentration of “fluorescent probe” (Orf9b-FITC) and Tom70.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(8) &quot;Additionally, the fused homodimer association rate (which can be viewed as a rate of tertiary complex formation)&quot; - can the authors provide a mathematical proof for this?</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>In the case of the fused homodimer kinetic data, we did not develop a separate model to explicitly take into account the differences between using a fused construct versus the WT construct that can dissociate into monomers. We have clarified our interpretation of this in the manuscript.</p>
<p>“Although our model explicitly describes homodimer dissociation into monomers as a requisite step for Orf9b binding to Tom70, we adapted it for the fusion experimental data. In this case, all model parameters other than the association and dissociation kinetics of the fluorescent probe and Tom70 were adjusted to achieve the best agreement with the experimental data. When applied to the fusion homodimer, the parameters describing homodimer dissociation into separate monomers could instead describe the dissociation of the two β-sheet domains away from each other in the tertiary structure but remaining physically linked through the linker region.”</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(9) &quot;For Lambda and Omicron, the P10S mutation results in the serine being positioned to form several hydrogen bonds between R13 and the backbone carbonyl of A11 and L48 within the same chain...&quot; is this taken from AlphaFold predicted structures of the mutants? If so, it should be made clear that this is derived from predicted structures. And even so, AlphaFold can be poor at determining structures of mutants, and so there is greater uncertainty in the prediction of the bonds.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>For Lambda, Omicron, and Delta mutations, we used Pymol to examine how the placement of mutations could structurally explain the kinetic differences we observed in our model. We have gone back and clarified in the figure description that these predictions are not derived from AlphaFold.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(10) &quot;biological replicates&quot; - is this different protein purifications?</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>Yes, in this case biological replicates refer to different protein purifications for all variants described and tested.</p>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
<p>(11) Are any of the authors involved in the Berkeley Madonna commercial software used in the manuscript? If so, should this be in the conflict of interest statement?</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>Yes, Michael Grabe is an owner of Berkeley Madonna, and we have updated our conflicts of interest statement to reflect this.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
</article>