<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">60710</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.60710</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cell Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Generation of stress fibers through myosin-driven reorganization of the actin cortex</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-197149"><name><surname>Lehtimäki</surname><given-names>Jaakko I</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0002-0242</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-197150"><name><surname>Rajakylä</surname><given-names>Eeva Kaisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-23272"><name><surname>Tojkander</surname><given-names>Sari</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-19580"><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname><given-names>Pekka</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6227-0354</contrib-id><email>pekka.lappalainen@helsinki.fi</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>HiLIFE Institute of Biotechnology, University of Helsinki</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Helsinki</named-content></addr-line><country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Section of Pathology, Department of Veterinary Biosciences, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Helsinki</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Helsinki</named-content></addr-line><country>Finland</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Fässler</surname><given-names>Reinhard</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Max Planck Institute of Biochemistry</institution><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Akhmanova</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>Utrecht University</institution><country>Netherlands</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>28</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e60710</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2020-07-03"><day>03</day><month>07</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2021-01-27"><day>27</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021, Lehtimäki et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lehtimäki et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-60710-v3.pdf"/><abstract><p>Contractile actomyosin bundles, stress fibers, govern key cellular processes including migration, adhesion, and mechanosensing. Stress fibers are thus critical for developmental morphogenesis. The most prominent actomyosin bundles, ventral stress fibers, are generated through coalescence of pre-existing stress fiber precursors. However, whether stress fibers can assemble through other mechanisms has remained elusive. We report that stress fibers can also form without requirement of pre-existing actomyosin bundles. These structures, which we named cortical stress fibers, are embedded in the cell cortex and assemble preferentially underneath the nucleus. In this process, non-muscle myosin II pulses orchestrate the reorganization of cortical actin meshwork into regular bundles, which promote reinforcement of nascent focal adhesions, and subsequent stabilization of the cortical stress fibers. These results identify a new mechanism by which stress fibers can be generated <italic>de novo</italic> from the actin cortex and establish role for stochastic myosin pulses in the assembly of functional actomyosin bundles.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>actin</kwd><kwd>myosin</kwd><kwd>stress fiber</kwd><kwd>mechanosensing</kwd><kwd>cell adhesion</kwd><kwd>cell cortex</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>None</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Sigrid Juselius Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>4708344</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname><given-names>Pekka</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Aatos Erkko Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>4704407</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname><given-names>Pekka</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002341</institution-id><institution>Academy of Finland</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>294174</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Tojkander</surname><given-names>Sari</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Live-cell microscopy studies revealed that stress fibers can be generated de novo from the actin cortex without the involvement of stress fiber precursors.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cell migration, morphogenesis, and adhesion depend on contractile networks composed of actin and non-muscle myosin II (NMII) filaments. The forces in these structures are generated through sliding of bipolar NMII filaments along actin. Depending on the type of NMII isoform as well as on the organization and dynamics of actin filaments, different types of functional contractile actomyosin arrays can be generated in eukaryotic cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Lehtimäki et al., 2017a</xref>). Assembly and contractility of these actomyosin arrays are controlled by upstream signals including Rho-family GTPases, kinase-phosphatase pathways, and Ca<sup>2+</sup> influxes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Vicente-Manzanares et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Prager-Khoutorsky et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tojkander et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Tojkander et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Burridge and Guilluy, 2016</xref>).</p><p>Beneath the plasma membrane of animal cells lies a thin meshwork that is composed of actin filaments, NMII filaments, and associated proteins. This structure, the actin cortex, contributes to morphogenesis of interphase cells, and drives cell rounding during cytokinesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bray and White, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chugh and Paluch, 2018</xref>). In human cells, the assembly of actin cortex depends on both formins and the Arp2/3 complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bovellan et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Lu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Cao et al., 2020</xref>). Ezrin, radixin, moesin (ERM)-family proteins link the cortical actin meshwork to the plasma membrane in interphase cells and during mitosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bretscher et al., 2002</xref>). Cortical actin meshwork is constantly under isotropic tension due to intracellular hydrostatic pressure and NMII-generated contractile forces to the actin cortex, and this can lead to formation of membrane blebs through local detachment of the actin cortex from the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Charras and Paluch, 2008</xref>). In a three-dimensional environment, some cell types can polarize and persistently migrate by stabilizing the bleb expansion through rearward cortical flows and modulating the cortical tension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Logue et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Ruprecht et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>Whereas the actin cortex is composed of an irregular meshwork of actin filaments, animal cells also harbor highly ordered actomyosin structures. In many interphase cells, the most prominent actomyosin structures are called stress fibers. These thick, contractile actin bundles often connect to focal adhesions at their ends, and they are especially prominent in cells plated on stiff matrix or when external force is applied to the cells. Thus, stress fibers, together with focal adhesions, constitute a major mechanosensitive machinery in cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Tojkander et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Livne and Geiger, 2016</xref>). Apart from adhesion and mechanosensing, stress fibers contribute to cell morphogenesis and tail retraction during migration. Stress fibers also serve as precursors for sarcomeres during cardiomyocyte myofibrillogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Fenix et al., 2018</xref>), and stress fiber-like actomyosin bundles contribute to interactions of epithelial cells with their neighbors and with basal lamina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">Yamada and Nelson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Munjal et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">López-Gay et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Rajakylä et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Stress fibers can be classified into different sub-types based on their protein compositions and association with focal adhesions. <italic>Ventral stress fibers</italic> are thick actomyosin bundles that are connected from their both ends to focal adhesions at the bottom of the cell. Despite their name, the central regions of ventral stress fibers often rise toward the dorsal surface of cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Naumanen et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Burnette et al., 2014</xref>). In many cell types, ventral stress fibers associate with each other to form a complex, mechanically interconnected network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">Xu et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kassianidou et al., 2017</xref>). <italic>Dorsal stress fibers</italic> (also known as radial fibers) are non-contractile actin filament bundles that are generated at the cell front through formin- and VASP-mediated actin filament assembly at focal adhesions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hotulainen and Lappalainen, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Tee et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tojkander et al., 2015</xref>). <italic>Transverse arcs</italic>, on the other hand, are thin, contractile actomyosin bundles, arising through NMII-promoted condensing of the lamellipodial actin network at the cell edge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hotulainen and Lappalainen, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Burnette et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Tojkander et al., 2011</xref>). Following their appearance, transverse arcs undergo retrograde flow toward the cell center, fuse with each other into thicker bundles, and become more contractile due to concatenation and persistent expansion of NMII filaments into stacks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tojkander et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Fenix et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Beach et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Jiu et al., 2019</xref>). Although transverse arcs are not directly linked to focal adhesions, they associate with focal adhesion-connected dorsal stress fibers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Burnette et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Senger et al., 2019</xref>). Ventral stress fibers can be generated from the transverse arc and dorsal stress fiber network through a complex process that involves both mechanosensitive regulation of actin filament assembly at focal adhesions, as well as inhibition of actin disassembly within the stress fiber network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hayakawa et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tojkander et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Tojkander et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lee and Kumar, 2020</xref>). Moreover, pre-existing ventral stress fibers can undergo ‘splitting’ to generate new, adjacent ventral stress fibers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Young and Higgs, 2018</xref>). However, whether stress fibers can also be generated through other mechanisms has remained elusive.</p><p>Here we show that different cell types also exhibit, at their ventral actin cortex, thin stress fibers that are connected to focal adhesions at both ends. These actomyosin bundles form predominantly underneath the nucleus, and are less contractile and more dynamic compared to the ventral stress fibers, which are derived through fusion of transverse arcs at the lamella of migrating cells. Importantly, we demonstrate that assembly of these thin actomyosin bundles does not involve transverse arcs or any other stress fiber precursor. Instead, they are generated <italic>de novo</italic> from the actin cortex through NMIIA-driven reorganization of the actin filament meshwork, and hence we call them as cortical stress fibers.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>The actin cortex harbors cortical stress fibers of various size and orientation</title><p>Ventral stress fibers were originally defined as contractile actomyosin bundles, which attach to focal adhesions at their both ends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Small et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hotulainen and Lappalainen, 2006</xref>). However, migrating mesenchymal cells harbor ventral stress fibers of various length, orientation, and thickness, and these can either locate entirely at the ventral surface of cells or rise toward the dorsal surface from their central regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Prager-Khoutorsky et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Burnette et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Elkhatib et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Schulze et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Baird et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Lehtimäki et al., 2017b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Kumari et al., 2020</xref>). To uncover the possible molecular differences between these diverse stress fibers, we utilized the 3D-structured illumination microscopy (SIM) on human osteosarcoma (U2OS) and mouse embryonic fibroblast (MEF) cells migrating on fibronectin. Consistent with previous literature, NMIIA containing, focal adhesion-attached stress fibers of varying thickness and length were visible in both cell lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>, white and red arrows). In addition to thick ventral stress fibers that connect focal adhesions located at the opposite sides of the cell, both cell types exhibited thin and relatively short actomyosin bundles that were connected to small focal adhesions at their both ends. As illustrated by the temporal-color coded 3D-SIM projections of F-actin, these thin actomyosin bundles reside at the immediate vicinity of the ventral cortex of the cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>, white arrows), whereas typical ventral stress fibers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Burnette et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tojkander et al., 2015</xref>) rise toward the dorsal surface from the middle of the bundle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>; red arrows). We named these thin, actin cortex-associated actomyosin bundles as <italic>cortical stress fibers</italic>.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Stress fiber architecture of migrating cells.</title><p>3D-structured illumination microscopy (SIM) maximum intensity projections (MIPs) of the actomyosin networks in cells migrating on fibronectin. (<bold>A</bold>) Human osteosarcoma (U2OS) and mouse embryonic fibroblast (MEF) cells, where the panels on the left display complete MIPs. The panels in the middle show only the filament structures close to the ventral plane (‘ventral MIP’), and the panels on the right are magnifications of the boxed regions from the middle panels. Red arrows highlight ventral stress fibers, and white arrows indicate examples of thin cortical stress fibers that are embedded at the cell cortex. DAPI (blue) and phalloidin (gray) were applied to mark the F-actin and nucleus, respectively. Vinculin (magenta) and non-muscle myosin II (NMII)A tails (green) were detected with respective specific antibodies. (<bold>B</bold>) 3D-SIM MIP projection from the ventral plane of a U2OS cell transfected with mApple-NMIIA construct (motor, green) and stained with NMIIA-tail specific antibody (magenta, tail) and phalloidin to visualize F-actin. 4× and 10× magnifications (orange box and yellow dotted box, respectively) show the bipolar NMIIA filaments in cortical stress fibers. (<bold>C</bold>) Traction force microscopy (TFM) analysis of the forces exerted by ventral stress fibers (red arrows) and cortical stress fibers (white arrows) to the underlying substrate. On the left, exemplary image of a LifeAct-mKate1.31-expressing U2OS cell and the obtained force map with root mean square tractions (RMS). Quantification of the RMS forces between the two stress fiber subtypes (n = 41 for ventral stress fibers [SF] and 45 for cortical stress fibers) is shown on right as half-violin plot including binned individual data points and mean with ±1 standard deviation (SD). p = 1.56 × 10<sup>−12</sup> (Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test, including outliers). Scale bars 10 µm and 5 µm for whole cell images and magnifications, respectively.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata1"><label>Figure 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Combined data of RMS traction forces.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig1-data1-v3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Cortical stress fibers display periodic non-muscle myosin II (NMII) — α-actinin pattern and assemble on different ECMs.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Human osteosarcoma (U2OS) and mouse embryonic fibroblast (MEF) cells (related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>), where vinculin and NMII were detected by specific antibodies, and F-actin and nucleus by fluorescent phalloidin and DAPI, respectively. Two panels on the left show temporal color-coded projection from the phalloidin staining, where red and white arrows highlight ventral stress fibers and cortical stress fibers, respectively. At the middle, ventral plane of the cells show the localizations of vinculin and NMIIA tail. On the right, magnification of the boxed regions form the middle panels demonstrating the presence of thin cortical stress fibers (white arrows) at the back of the cell and in the vicinity of the nucleus. (<bold>B</bold>) α-actinin-1 and NMIIA localization in ventral stress fibers and cortical stress fibers in a U2OS cell. 3D-structured illumination microscopy (SIM) maximum intensity projection (MIP) with 4× magnifications of ventral stress fibers (orange box) display the periodic localization of the α−actinin1-TagRFP-T and NMIIA in the ventral stress fibers (red arrows), whereas cortical stress fibers (4× mag., yellow box) display less regular pattern of α-actinin. (<bold>C</bold>) 3D-SIM MIPs of U2OS and MEF cells cultured either on laminin or collagen coated dishes. F-actin was visualized by fluorescent phalloidin, focal adhesions by vinculin antibody, and nuclei by DAPI. Endogenous NMIIA tail domain was visualized by specific antibody. White arrows indicate examples of cortical stress fibers. Scale bars 10 µm and 5 µm for whole cell images and magnified areas, respectively.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig1-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Cortical stress fibers are not linked to fibrillar adhesions.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) 3D-structured illumination microscopy (SIM) maximum intensity projections (MIPs) of human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cells and mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) cultured on uncoated high precision glass coverslips. An antibody detecting fibronectin was applied to visualize fibronectin deposits under the cells. 4× magnifications on the right (from yellow boxes) display cortical stress fibers (white arrows) in both cell types and demonstrate that in U2OS cells they do not co-localize with the fibronectin. For MEFs, some cortical stress fibers were associated with the fibronectin deposits (red asterisks). Nuclei were detected by DAPI. (<bold>B</bold>) An antibody detecting the Y118-phosphorylated version of the paxillin was applied to discern the focal adhesions from fibrillar adhesions, which were reported to be devoid of paxillin phosphorylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">Zaidel-Bar et al., 2007</xref>). 3D-SIM MIPs from both U2OS and MEF cells on fibronectin-coated high precision coverslips were stained with phalloidin (F-actin) and an antibody to detect vinculin. 4× magnification of marked areas (yellow boxes) illustrate pY118-paxillin co-localization with vinculin at the focal adhesions in the ends of cortical stress fibers (white arrows). Scale bars 10 μm and 5 μm for the whole cell images and magnified images, respectively.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig1-figsupp2-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Similar to the ventral stress fibers, NMII filaments displayed a bipolar arrangement in the small, basally located cortical stress fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). However, NMII did not appear to assemble into stacks, and the periodic pattern of actin filament cross-linking protein α-actinin was less regular in cortical stress fibers compared to transverse arcs and ventral stress fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Moreover, the forces exerted by cortical stress fibers to the ECM were much smaller compared to typical ventral stress fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). Although cortical stress fibers were able to form also on laminin and collagen, they were most prevalently observed in cells migrating on fibronectin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1C</xref>). Due to their apparent fibronectin preference, we investigated the cortical stress fibers for fibrillar fibronectin deposits and Y118-phospho(p)-paxillin, two markers that are typical to fibrillar and focal adhesions, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">Zaidel-Bar et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Geiger and Yamada, 2011</xref>). Apart from few adhesions in MEFs, cortical stress fibers did not associate with fibronectin deposits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>). Moreover, the adhesions at the ends of cortical stress fibers contained Y118-phospho(p)-paxillin, indicating that they were not associated with fibrillar adhesions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref>). Taken together, the molecular composition of cortical stress fibers closely resembles the one of ventral stress fibers, but they are typically much smaller, localize consistently at the ventral actin cortex, and exert only weak traction forces.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Cortical stress fibers are generated <italic>de novo</italic> from the ventral actin cortex</title><p>Ventral stress fibers are generated from a network of pre-existing transverse arcs and focal adhesion-attached dorsal stress fibers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tojkander et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Tojkander et al., 2018</xref>). Thus, we examined if the thin cortical stress fibers are generated by the same or a different mechanism. To this end, we imaged the ventral cortex of migrating U2OS cells and MEFs expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (to detect F-actin) and vinculin-mApple (to visualize focal adhesions) by time-lapse total internal reflection microscopy (TIRFM). Surprisingly, these experiments revealed that cortical stress fibers emerged <italic>de novo</italic> from the ventral actin cortex, without involvement of any pre-existing stress fiber precursors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A and B</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video1">Videos 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video2">2</xref>). In this process, actin filaments of the cell cortex reorganized into thicker bundles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A and B</xref>, blue arrows) and this was followed by growth of nascent, initially barely visible, vinculin-positive adhesions at the both ends of the bundle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A and B</xref>, orange arrows). This eventually led to the formation of an actin filament bundle that was connected to focal adhesions at its both ends.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Cortical stress fibers assemble <italic>de novo</italic> from the actin cortex.</title><p>TIRF time-lapse imaging of a migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) (<bold>A</bold>) and mouse embryonic fibroblast (MEF) cell (<bold>B</bold>) expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray) and vinculin-mApple (magenta). Selected time-lapse frames from the magnified areas (yellow box) are shown on the right as separate channels and merged frames. These demonstrate the <italic>de novo</italic> emergence of a cortical stress fiber from the ventral actin cortex. Blue arrows illustrate F-actin bundling and orange arrows point the maturation of the vinculin-positive focal adhesions. See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video1">Videos 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video2">2</xref>. Scale bars 10 µm and 2 µm for whole cell images and time-lapse zoom-ins, respectively. Imaging interval 30 s.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig2-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Cortical stress fibers emerge from the ventral actin cortex through different intermediate assembly states.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Photoactivation of PA-GFP-actin (gray) at both cortical and dorsal stress fibers in human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cells that additionally expressed Lifeact-mKate1.31 (red) and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta). PA-GFP-actin was always activated adjacent to a paxillin positive adhesion. The images of entire cells after photoactivation are shown on the left. Kymographs of PA-GFP-actin dynamics from the selected stress fibers indicated in the whole cell images illustrate that, unlike dorsal stress fibers (4), cortical stress fibers do not elongate through actin polymerization from the adhesion (1,2), and can occasionally even exhibit slow actin flow towards the adhesion (3). All kymographs were oriented in a way that the adhesion is facing to the top. Black arrows on the kymographs indicate the activation time-point, preceded by three time-lapse frames, and the dashed lines movement of activated stress fiber segments. Imaging interval was 10 s, and scale bars are 10 µm in whole cell images. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of the actin polymerization rates from focal adhesions. Actin polymerization rates (µm/min) are shown as half-violin plot, displaying binned individual data points and mean with ±1 SD. p = 5.22 × 10<sup>−15</sup> (two-sample <italic>t</italic>-test). Polymerization rates for individual data points/kymographs were obtained through plot profiles, subtracting the distance of the peak intensities at time points 10 s and 300 s after photoactivation. N (cortical SF) = 13 cells; 33 foci and N (dorsal SF) = 6 cells; seven foci. (<bold>C</bold>) Cortical stress fiber assembly in a migrating U2OS cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (F-actin, magenta) and vinculin-mApple (focal adhesions, green) imaged by TIRF microscopy. Blue arrows exemplify the <italic>de novo</italic> generation of a cortical stress fiber, and the orange arrow highlights a vinculin positive adhesion that was used by several cortical stress fibers over the time. Imaging interval 30 s. See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video3">Video 3</xref>. Scale bars 10 μm and 5 μm for the whole cell images and magnified images, respectively.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2s1sdata1"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>PA-actin intensity profiles from photoactivated foci.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig2-figsupp1-data1-v3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig2-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group><media id="video1" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video1.mp4"><label>Video 1.</label><caption><title>Cortical stress fiber formation at the ventral actin cortex of a migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell.</title><p>Zoom in of a U2OS cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray) and mApple-vinculin (magenta), migrating on a fibronectin (10 µg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 30 s imaging interval. Playback rate 10 frames/s. Scale bar 2 µm.</p></caption></media><media id="video2" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video2.mp4"><label>Video 2.</label><caption><title>Cortical stress fiber formation at the ventral actin cortex of a migrating mouse embryonic fibroblast (MEF) cell.</title><p>Zoom in of a MEF cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray) and mApple-vinculin (magenta), migrating on a fibronectin (10 µg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 30 s imaging interval. Playback rate 10 frames/s. Scale bar 2 µm.</p></caption></media><p>Because dorsal stress fibers elongate through actin polymerization at focal adhesions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hotulainen and Lappalainen, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Tee et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tojkander et al., 2015</xref>), we also examined the possible role of actin filament assembly at adhesions in the formation of cortical stress fibers. For this purpose, we photoactivated small regions of stress fibers adjacent to adhesions in U2OS cells expressing photoactivatable (PA) actin, and subsequently followed the movement of the photoactivated actin foci. Whereas the photoactivated regions in dorsal stress fibers displayed a centripetal movement with a typical rate of ~0.3 µm/min, the photoactivated regions in cortical stress fibers were nearly immobile. This provides evidence that, unlike dorsal stress fibers, cortical stress fibers do not elongate from adhesions at their ends (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A and B</xref>).</p><p>Live-cell imaging experiments also demonstrated that cortical stress fibers are typically very dynamic with relatively short half-life (~25 min). However, it is important to note that the half-life of cortical stress fibers was highly variable from few minutes to more than 1.5 hr. Moreover, cortical stress fibers often associated dynamically with each other, and they could also arise via various intermediate assembly states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video3">Video 3</xref>). Collectively, these data reveal that cortical stress fibers are relatively dynamic actomyosin bundles, which assemble through a novel mechanism from the actin cortex, without involvement of stress fiber precursors or actin polymerization at focal adhesions.</p><media id="video3" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video3.mp4"><label>Video 3.</label><caption><title>Cortical stress fiber assembly at the trailing edge of a migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell.</title><p>Zoom in of a U2OS cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (magenta) and mApple-vinculin (green), migrating on a fibronectin (10 µg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1C</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 30 s imaging interval. Playback rate 20 frames/s; Scale bar 5 µm.</p></caption></media></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Cortical stress fibers preferably emerge underneath the nucleus in migrating cells</title><p>Cortical stress fibers were enriched at the rear of migrating cells and were typically located either underneath or close to the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). Nucleus is a relatively bulky organelle, localized behind the lamella at the cell rear in polarized mesenchymal cells, and it undergoes NMII-dependent translocation as the cell moves forward (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Wu et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Thomas et al., 2015</xref>). Thus, we examined possible connection between the nucleus and generation of cortical stress fibers. Live-imaging of U2OS cells expressing Histone-H2B-mCherry to mark the nucleus, as well as LifeAct-TagGFP2 and focal adhesion marker miRFP670-paxillin, revealed that the assembly of cortical stress fibers occurred typically under the nucleus during cell locomotion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video4">Video 4</xref>). Similar results were obtained when nuclei were visualized together with miRFP670-paxillin and mApple-NMIIA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video5">Video 5</xref>). Quantification of the emergence of cortical stress fibers from 19 time-lapse videos revealed that ~80% of the cortical stress fibers assembled underneath the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). By considering that the nucleus typically consists of &lt;30% of the cell area, the assembly of cortical stress fibers occurs predominantly underneath the nucleus.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Non-muscle myosin II (NMII)A pulse-mediated cortical stress fibers assembly occurs predominantly underneath the nucleus in migrating cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) TIRF time-lapse imaging of a migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell. The selected time-lapse frames (from the yellow boxed area) illustrate the assembly of a cortical stress fiber (exemplified by white arrows) below the moving nucleus. Histone H2B-mCherry was applied to detect the nucleus (blue, EPI-TIRF) and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta) and LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray) to visualize focal adhesions and F-actin, respectively. See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video4">Video 4</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of the position of <italic>de novo</italic> formation of cortical stress fibers from TIRF-time-lapse videos of U2OS cells expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2, Histone-H2B-mCherry, and miRFP670-paxillin. Data are presented as %-distribution of cortical stress fibers assembled under the nucleus versus outside the nucleus perimeter ± SEM. n = 101 cortical stress fibers analyzed from 19 cells. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of NMIIA pulse location at the ventral cortex of U2OS cells expressing Histone H2B-eGFP and mApple-NMIIA. Data are presented as pulse frequency (number of individual pulses) under the nucleus vs. outside the nucleus perimeter (rest of the ventral cortex). Each data point is normalized to the area of nucleus. Half-violin plot displays binned individual data points and mean with ±1 standard deviation (SD), n = 19 cells. Significance (p = 0.00012) tested with a paired <italic>t</italic>-test. (<bold>D</bold>) TIRF time-lapse imaging of a migrating U2OS cell expressing eGFP-NMIIA (green) and vinculin-mApple (magenta). Selected time-lapse frames from the magnified area (yellow box) demonstrate that NMIIA pulses (yellow arrows) are associated with the assembly of a cortical stress fiber and enforcement of vinculin positive focal adhesions (orange arrows). See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video7">Video 7</xref>. For (<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>D</bold>), scale bars 10 µm and 5 µm for whole cell images and time-lapse zoom-ins, respectively. Imaging interval 30 s.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata1"><label>Figure 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Analysis of <italic>de novo</italic> forming cortical SFs.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig3-data1-v3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata2"><label>Figure 3—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Analysis of NMIIA pulse dynamics.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig3-data2-v3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig3-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Myosin pulses are associated with cortical stress fibers assembly underneath the nucleus, and morphologically similar adhesion-attached actin filament bundles also exist in cells migrating in 3D matrix.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) TIRF time-lapse imaging of a migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell expressing histone H2B-eGFP (gray), mApple-NMIIA (green), and miRFP670-paxillin (focal adhesions, magenta). Selected time-lapse frames from the magnified area (yellow box) show examples of myosin pulses that assemble into cortical stress fibers underneath the nucleus, with concurrent maturation of paxillin-positive focal adhesions. Orange arrow illustrates how a single focal adhesion is used by two different cortical stress fibers assembling over the time (original imaging interval 30 s). Scale bars 10 µm and 5 µm for the whole cell image and magnified time-lapse frames, respectively. See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video5">Video 5</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Stress fibers in three eGFP-paxillin (green) expressing U2OS cells migrating in 3D fibrin matrix. Magnifications of selected regions (1. to 3.) from a 3D-reconstruction of representative confocal stack display examples of stress fibers (orange arrows) that based on their small size (length &lt;10 µm), presence of small adhesions at each end, and vicinity to nucleus resemble the cortical stress fibers of cells migrating on 2D matrix. Also thicker and longer ‘ventral- stress fiber’ – like actomyosin bundles (blue arrows) – were frequently observed. However, it is important to note that as such, there is no ventral nor dorsal side in cells migrating in 3D matrix. DAPI (blue) and phalloidin (magenta) were applied to visualize the F-actin and nucleus, respectively. Scale bars 10 µm. See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video6">Video 6</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig3-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group><media id="video4" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video4.mp4"><label>Video 4.</label><caption><title>Cortical stress fiber assembly under the nucleus of migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell.</title><p>Zoom in of a U2OS cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray), histone-H2B-mCherry (blue), and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta), migrating on a fibronectin (10 µg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 30 s imaging interval. Playback rate 20 frames/s. Scale bar 5 µm.</p></caption></media><media id="video5" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video5.mp4"><label>Video 5.</label><caption><title>Non-muscle myosin II (NMII)A pulses assemble into cortical stress fibers under the nucleus of migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell.</title><p>Zoom in of a U2OS cell expressing histone H2B-eGFP (gray), mApple-NMIIA (green), and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta), migrating on a fibronectin (10 µg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1A</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 20 s imaging interval. Playback rate 20 frames/s. Scale bar 5 µm.</p></caption></media><p>To elucidate if actin filament bundles resembling cortical stress fibers also exist in cells migrating in three-dimensional (3D) environment, we examined the distributions of adhesions, actin filaments, and nuclei in U2OS cells migrating in 3D fibrin network. In addition to thick, long actin filament bundles, which resemble ‘ventral stress fibers’ observed in cells migrating on 2D matrix, U2OS cells in 3D fibrin matrix also exhibited relatively short and thinner actin filament bundles, which terminated to paxillin-rich adhesions at their both ends (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video6">Video 6</xref>). These filament bundles were prominent in the vicinity of the nuclei, suggesting that they may be related to cortical stress fibers.</p><media id="video6" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video6.mp4"><label>Video 6.</label><caption><title>3D-reconstruction of human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cells migrating in a 3D fibrin matrix.</title><p>U2OS cells expressing eGFP-paxillin (green), stained further with phalloidin for F-actin (magenta) and DAPI (blue) for visualization of the nuclei. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1B</xref>. Confocal stacks were acquired and deconvolved with Andor Dragonfly 505; 3D-reconstruction performed with Imaris 9.2.1. Scale bar size (µm) is proportional to the degree of zoom in the video and is indicated at the lower left corner.</p></caption></media></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Myosin pulses direct cortical stress fiber assembly and maturation</title><p>Pulsatile behavior of NMII at the actin cortex has been documented in epithelial and mesenchymal cells, and reported to induce transient accumulation of cortical actin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim and Davidson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Munjal et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Baird et al., 2017</xref>). Our analysis indicated that NMIIA pulses at the ventral cortex of U2OS cells are slightly more prevalent underneath the nucleus, where cortical stress fibers also principally assembled, compared to the region outside the nucleus perimeter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). To reveal the possible role of NMII pulses in generation of the cortical stress fibers, we performed TIRFM imaging of U2OS cells expressing eGFP-NMIIA and vinculin-mApple. Interestingly, assembly of cortical stress fibers and enforcement of focal adhesions at their ends were associated with NMIIA pulses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video7">Video 7</xref>). To examine this in more detail, we performed three-color TIRFM on U2OS cells expressing mApple-NMIIA, LifeAct-TagGFP2, and miRFP670-paxillin. These experiments revealed that NMIIA pulses frequently coincided with F-actin bundling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video8">Video 8</xref>). In majority of cases the NMIIA pulses were transient and ‘non-productive’, and the actin filament bundles collapsed back to the ventral cortex along with the cessation of the pulse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). However, in some cases the NMIIA pulses were more persistent and ‘productive’, and led to the formation of more stable actomyosin bundles. These actomyosin bundles engaged paxillin positive focal adhesions, causing them to align to the direction of the pull and to increase in size, thus leading to stabilization and maturation of the cortical stress fiber (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A and C</xref>). Importantly, focal adhesions associating with the new cortical stress fiber could either emerge <italic>de novo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>, orange arrow, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video9">Video 9</xref>) or be pre-existing adhesions that were connected to other, discrete contractile bundles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref>, orange arrow and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video8">Videos 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video10">10</xref>). Moreover, we occasionally observed assembly of cortical stress fibers, where one end of the contractile bundle was connected to the mesh of pre-existing actomyosin bundles instead of a focal adhesion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>, yellow arrow, and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video9">Video 9</xref>). Thus, generation of cortical stress fibers is both very dynamic and plastic process, and it can involve either <italic>de novo</italic> formation of focal adhesions or ‘recycling’ of pre-existing focal adhesions or higher-order actomyosin structures to connect the nascent cortical stress fiber to the cell cortex.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Cortical non-muscle myosin II (NMII) pulses orchestrate F-actin bundling for the assembly of cortical stress fibers.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Formation of a cortical stress fiber from the ventral cortex of a migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell as studied by time-lapse TIRF microscopy. The entire cell is shown on the right, and the selected time-lapse frames (from the region indicated by yellow box) display how F-actin (gray, LifeAct-mKate1.31; blue arrows) and NMIIA (green, eGFP-NMIIA; yellow arrows) organize into an actomyosin bundle, which promotes the enlargement of pre-existing paxillin-positive focal adhesions (FA) (magenta, miRFP670-paxillin). Note that prior to bundle assembly, the pre-existing focal adhesions were connected to different actomyosin bundles. Original imaging interval 30 s. See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video8">Video 8</xref>. Scale bars 10 µm and 2 µm for whole cell image and magnified time-lapse frames, respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) Two representative kymographs of transient NMIIA pulses occurring at the ventral cortex of U2OS cells expressing eGFP-NMIIA, LifeAct-mKate 1.31 and miRFP670-paxillin. The ‘non-productive’ NMIIA pulses are accompanied by transient accumulation of F-actin, but without emergence of paxillin-positive nascent adhesions and stabilization of the actomyosin bundle. Kymographs were obtained from TIRF time-lapse videos with imaging interval of 10 s. (<bold>C</bold>) Two representative kymographs (obtained from <xref ref-type="video" rid="video7">Video 7</xref>) illustrating how emergence of a NMIIA pulse (green) leads to enforcement of adhesions (magenta) and maturation of a cortical stress fiber. White dashed lines in the kymographs indicate the onsets of NMIIA pulses. See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>. (<bold>D</bold>) Percentual distribution of cortical stress fiber numbers in U2OS cells and mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) after different pharmacological perturbations. Cortical stress fiber number and length measurements were obtained through blind analysis of the tile-scan TIRF data. n = DMSO 157 and 247, CK-666, 166, and 182, Blebbistatin 195 and 198 cells for U2OS cells and MEFs, respectively. See also respective <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>A and C.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata1"><label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Cortical SF number quantification after pharmacological inhibitions.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig4-data1-v3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig4-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Different ways to assemble cortical stress fibers from the ventral actomyosin cortex.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Example of a formation of cortical stress fiber in a migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell, where one end of the stress fiber connects to a focal adhesion and the other one to a cortical actomyosin patch. Blue arrows in the selected, magnified time-lapse frames (from the yellow-boxed area) illustrate F-actin bundling, orange arrows highlight the maturing paxillin-positive focal adhesion (magenta, miRFP670-paxillin), and yellow arrows highlight the non-muscle myosin II (NMII) patch where the stress fiber is connected from its other end. NMIIA (green) and F-actin (gray) were visualized by expressing eGFP-NMIIA and LifeAct-mKate1.31, respectively. See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video9">Video 9</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Example of a focal adhesion exchanging from one cortical stress fiber to another one in a migrating U2OS cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (F-actin, gray), eGFP-NM-IIA (green), and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta). Selected time-lapse frames (magnified from the yellow boxed area) show that after disassembly of the preceding cortical stress fiber (white arrow), the newly forming cortical stress fiber (illustrated with blue arrows) engages itself to the pre-existing paxillin-positive focal adhesion (orange arrow). See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video10">Video 10</xref>. For both (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>), scale bars 10 µm and 2 µm for whole cell images and magnified time-lapse frames, respectively. Original imaging interval 10 s. (<bold>C</bold>) Depletion of Dia1 or Dia2 by siRNAs from U2OS cells as detected by western blot. GAPDH was probed to assess equal sample loading. (<bold>D</bold>) Effects of formin inhibitor SMIFH2 (left) and Dia1 and Dia2 depletions (right) on cortical stress fibers as examined by blind analysis of cortical stress fiber numbers (percentual distribution of indicated categories) from tile-scan TIRF data sets. For SMIFH2 experiments, the ‘WT’ represents control cells treated only with DMSO, whereas for siRNA experiments the ‘Ctrl’ cells were transfected with negative control siRNA. Please note that because SMIFH2 was recently shown to inhibit also NMII activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Nishimura et al., 2020</xref>), it was used at low (12.5 µM) concentration for 1 hr prior fixation to minimize unspecific effects. N = WT 209, Ctrl siRNA 232, mDia1 163, mDia2 138, and SMIFH2 229 U2OS cells analyzed.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s1sdata1"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Cortical SF number quantification after formin inhibitions.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig4-figsupp1-data1-v3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig4-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Cortical stress fiber assembly is dependent on functional non-muscle myosin II (NMII) and integrin-based adhesions.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) TIRF time-lapse images of a human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell expressing mApple-NMIIA (green), miRFP670-paxillin (magenta), and LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray), after 1 hr incubation with 50 µM para-amino Blebbistatin. Blebbistatin does not cease myosin pulses highlighted with yellow arrows (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Baird et al., 2017</xref>), but abolishes cortical stress fiber formation. Magnified time-lapse frames (from yellow boxed area) and display NMIIA pulses (yellow arrows) that are unable to bundle F-actin. See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video11">Video 11B</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) TIRF time-lapse imaging of U2OS cells plated onto poly-D-lysine coated dishes 24 hr prior imaging. Only cells that displayed partial integrin-mediated adhesion (based on miRFP670-paxillin, magenta) from their edges were imaged. Exemplary time-lapse images from the magnified region (yellow box) illustrate NMIIA pulses (mApple-NMIIA, green) that are unable to stabilize F-actin bundles. Note the blue arrows pointing out the transient accumulation of cortical actin (LifeAct-TagGFP2, gray), coinciding with the NMIIA pulses (yellow arrows). See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video12">Video 12</xref>. (<bold>C</bold>) Cortical stress fiber formation in a U2OS cell transfected with miRFP670-paxillin and LifeAct-TagGFP2, and subjected to CK-666 for 4 hr prior onset of TIRF-imaging. Selected time-lapse frames from the magnified regions show an example of cortical stress fiber formation (blue arrows) and reinforcement of focal adhesions (orange arrows). See also <xref ref-type="video" rid="video13">Video 13</xref>. Scale bars 10 µm and 5 µm for the whole cell images and magnifications, respectively. Time-lapse imaging interval 30 s for (<bold>A and C</bold>) and 20 s for (<bold>B</bold>), respectively.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig4-figsupp2-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group><media id="video7" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video7.mp4"><label>Video 7.</label><caption><title>Non-muscle myosin II (NMII)A pulses at the trailing edge of a migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cells.</title><p>Zoom in of a U2OS cell expressing eGFP-NMIIA (green) and mApple-vinculin (magenta) migrating on a fibronectin (10 µg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 30 s imaging interval. Playback rate 20 frames/s. Scale bar 5 µm.</p></caption></media><media id="video8" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video8.mp4"><label>Video 8.</label><caption><title>Non-muscle myosin II (NMII)A pulses coordinate the cortical stress fiber assembly in a migrating human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell.</title><p>Zoom in of a U2OS cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray), mApple-NMIIA (green), and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta), migrating on a fibronectin (10 µg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 30 s imaging interval. Playback rate 10 frames/s. Scale bar 2 µm.</p></caption></media><media id="video9" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video9.mp4"><label>Video 9.</label><caption><title>NMIIA pulse-coordinated cortical stress fiber assembly in a migrating U2OS cell, where one end of the fiber connects to actomyosin mesh.</title><p>Zoom in of a U2OS cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray), mApple-NMIIA (green), and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta), migrating on a fibronectin (10 μg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>A. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 10s imaging interval. Playback rate 20 frames/s. Scale bar 2 μm.</p></caption></media><media id="video10" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video10.mp4"><label>Video 10.</label><caption><title>NMIIA pulse-coordinated cortical stress fiber assembly in a migrating U2OS cell, where one end of the fiber connects to a pre-existing adhesion.</title><p>Zoom in of a U2OS cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray), mApple-NMIIA (green), and miRFP670-paxillin, migrating on a fibronectin (10 μg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>B. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 10s imaging interval. Playback rate 20 frames/s. Scale bar 2 μm.</p></caption></media><p>To examine the role of NMII in the assembly of cortical stress fibers more closely, we applied NMII inhibitor para-amino-Blebbistatin. As reported earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Baird et al., 2017</xref>), Blebbistatin did not cease the NMII pulsatile behavior in U2OS cells. Thus, myosin pulses do not depend on the catalytic activity of NMII, but can occur also if the motor domain of myosin is brought to low actin-affinity state by Blebbistatin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kovács et al., 2004</xref>). Interestingly, the cortical stress fiber formation was almost completely abolished in Blebbistatin-treated cells, providing evidence that NMII activity is critical for the assembly of cortical stress fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video11">Video 11</xref>). We also cultured U2OS cells on poly-D-lysine coated imaging dishes to examine the importance of integrin-based adhesions in this process. By imaging cells that had managed to adhere to the dish only from their edges, but were devoid of adhesions inside cell margins, we revealed that while NMII pulses still drove transient cortical F-actin enrichment, they could not engage F-actin bundling to the assembly of cortical stress fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video12">Video 12</xref>).</p><media id="video11" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video11.mp4"><label>Video 11.</label><caption><title>Inhibiting non-muscle myosin II (NMII) activity abolishes cortical stress fiber assembly.</title><p>Zoom in of a human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray), mApple-NMIIA (green), and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta, not shown in the zoom in) migrating on a fibronectin (10 µg/ml)-coated high precision imaging dish after 1 hr treatment with 50 µM p-amino-Blebbistatin. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2A</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 30 s imaging interval. Playback rate 20 frames/s. Scale bar 5 µm.</p></caption></media><media id="video12" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video12.mp4"><label>Video 12.</label><caption><title>Inhibiting integrin-based ECM adhesion obstructs cortical stress fiber formation.</title><p>Zoom in of a human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray), mApple-NMIIA (green), and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta, not shown in the zoom in) on a poly-D-lysine (10 µg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish. Imaging started 24 hr post plating. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2B</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 20 s imaging interval. Playback rate 20 frames/s. Scale bar 5 µm.</p></caption></media><p>We also applied the Arp2/3 inhibitor CK-666 to elucidate the possible role of Arp2/3 complex mediated actin filament assembly in the generation of cortical stress fibers. Even after 4 hr post drug administration, de novo cortical stress fiber assembly was frequently observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2C</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video13">Video 13</xref>). Quantification of cortical stress fibers from control (DMSO-treated), para-amino-Blebbistatin, and CK-666 treated U2OS cells and MEFs confirmed that NMII inhibition led to an almost complete loss of cortical stress fibers, whereas Arp2/3 inhibition resulted in only a moderate decrease in the amount of these actomyosin bundles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>).</p><media id="video13" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60710-video13.mp4"><label>Video 13.</label><caption><title>CK-666 mediated Arp2/3 inhibition does not prevent cortical stress fiber assembly.</title><p>Zoom in of a human osteosarcoma (U2OS) cell expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 (gray) and miRFP670-paxillin (magenta) migrating on a fibronectin (10 µg/ml)-coated high-precision imaging dish after 4 hr treatment with 100 µM CK-666. Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2C</xref>. Time-lapse ring-TIRFM video was recorded with Deltavision OMX SR with 30 s imaging interval. Playback rate 20 frames/s. Scale bar 5 µm.</p></caption></media><p>Because formins were shown to contribute to assembly of dorsal stress fibers and to nucleation of actin filaments in the actin cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hotulainen and Lappalainen, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Tojkander et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bovellan et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Cao et al., 2020</xref>), we examined the effects of formins on cortical stress fibers. We first used the SMIFH2 compound, which inhibits formins, but at higher concentration also increasingly affects the activities of various myosins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Rizvi et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Nishimura et al., 2020</xref>). Treatment of U2OS cells for 1 hr with 12.5 µM SMIFH2 decreased the amount of cortical stress fibers, suggesting that formins contribute, either directly or indirectly, to the assembly of cortical stress fibers. However, subsequent siRNA experiments on Dia1 and Dia2, which are two formins that were linked to assembly of dorsal stress fibers and transverse arcs, did not result in significant reduction in the number of cortical stress fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1C and D</xref>). These results suggest that Dia1 and Dia2 are either not critical for generation of cortical stress fibers or that they are functionally redundant with each other or with some other formins expressed in U2OS cells.</p><p>Collectively, these results demonstrate that generation of cortical stress fibers is driven by NMII-catalyzed reorganization of the cortical actin filament network and dependent on integrin-based cell-matrix adhesions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Here we discovered a new mechanism by which focal adhesion-attached stress fibers assemble in cells. We show that unlike ventral stress fibers, which are generated from the pre-exiting network of dorsal stress fibers and transverse arcs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tojkander et al., 2015</xref>), cortical stress fibers located at the ventral cortex of 2D-migrating cells assemble <italic>de novo</italic> through NMII-dependent reorganization of the actin cortex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A and B</xref>). It is important to note that although generation of cortical stress fibers below the nucleus and transverse arcs at the lamellipodium–lamellum interface display some parallels, transverse arc formation does not involve prominent myosin pulses, but they are rather assembled through condensation of the lamellipodial actin filament network during the retraction phase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Burnette et al., 2011</xref>). Cortical stress fibers bear close resemblance to the ventral stress fibers because they terminate to focal adhesions at both ends, do not elongate through actin polymerization at focal adhesions, and are composed of bipolar NMII filaments and α-actinin decorated actin filaments. However, they are thinner, more dynamic, devoid of NMII stacks, and less contractile compared to ventral stress fibers.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Two different mechanisms for generation of contractile stress fibers.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of the <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of a cortical stress fiber from the ventral actomyosin cortex. 1. Non-muscle myosin II (NMII) pulses occur frequently at the ventral actin cortex. 2. These pulses can cause transient accumulation and bundling of the cortical actin filaments via myosin-mediated actin filament crosslinking and reorganization. This triggers the enlargement of nascent focal adhesions at the ends of the bundle. 3. The transient actomyosin bundle can mature to a cortical SF through recruitment of more actin filaments and NMII. (<bold>B</bold>) Ventral stress fibers assemble from pre-existing stress fiber precursors at the lamellum of a migrating cell. 1. Dorsal stress fibers elongate through actin filament polymerization at focal adhesions, whereas transverse arcs are generated from NMII filaments and actin filaments at the lamellipodium–lamella interface. Assembly of transverse arcs does not involve prominent myosin pulses, but they are formed during retraction phase of lamellipodium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Burnette et al., 2011</xref>). The network of dorsal stress fibers and transverse arcs flows toward the cell center, and the arcs fuse with each other to form thicker actomyosin bundles. 2. The dorsal stress fibers in parallel to the transverse arcs are under strongest tension and begin to align with the fusing transverse arc network. On the other hand, the dorsal stress fibers arranged perpendicularly to the fusing transverse arcs sense lower tension and are disassembled by ADF/cofilins. 3. This leads to the formation of a thick stress fiber that is attached to focal adhesions at both ends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tojkander et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Tojkander et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-fig5-v3.tif"/></fig><p>The assembly of cortical stress fibers is intimately linked to the actin cortex, where stochastic, NMII-mediated contractions of the cortical actin meshwork can lead to the formation of cortical actomyosin bundles. These are initially transient by nature and can either form a cortical stress fiber or collapse back into the ventral cortex. Although NMII-pulses have not been previously linked to assembly of contractile actomyosin bundles, transient NMII pulse-driven cortical actin condensations were reported to occur in epithelial tissues of developing organisms where they drive tissue morphogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Munro et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Solon et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Rauzi et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Munjal et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Michaux et al., 2018</xref>) and in cells of mesenchymal origin migrating in 2D environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim and Davidson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Nie et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Baird et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Graessl et al., 2017</xref>). In <italic>Drosophila</italic> epithelia, the NMII/actin foci were also reported to undergo E-cadherin-mediated stabilization into medioapical filaments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Mason et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Vasquez et al., 2014</xref>). Thus, myosin II pulse-driven F-actin bundling may have a more general role in the formation of different types of contractile actomyosin bundles in cells.</p><p>Also during cytokinesis, small actomyosin nodes can coalescence and form highly ordered contractile bundles at the cleavage furrow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Laplante et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Reymann et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Henson et al., 2017</xref>). Thus, initially very similar cortical actomyosin foci appear drive the formation of various different contractile structures. Similarly, the nascent cortical stress fibers come in many intermediate shapes that reflect the initially random formation of NMII/F-actin clusters. These intermediate structures can become momentarily engaged by more than two focal adhesions, but during subsequent tug-of-war-type process usually two focal adhesions become dominant at the ends of the cortical stress fiber. Moreover, a recent study reported emergence of new actomyosin bundles from the actin cortex close to a pre-existing stress fiber, and demonstrated that these actomyosin bundles exhibit a mechanical continuum with the actomyosin cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Vignaud et al., 2020</xref>). The degree of cortical F-actin network bundling may be dependent on both the mesh gap-size and thickness of the actin meshwork that vary between different cell types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bovellan et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Svitkina, 2020</xref>). Interestingly, the actin cortex appears to be more dense and under higher tension at the back of the 2D-migrating cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chugh and Paluch, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bisaria et al., 2020</xref>), where we observe the most prominent cortical stress fiber assembly.</p><p>What could be the reason underlying the assembly of cortical stress fibers under the nucleus in migrating mesenchymal cells? Transportation of the relatively rigid nucleus in cells migrating in tissue environment poses mechanical challenges, especially when facing narrow passages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Petrie et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Denais et al., 2016</xref>). This results in accumulation of contractile F-actin bundles around the nucleus to mediate movement of the nucleus through the constriction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Thomas et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Davidson et al., 2020</xref>). Similarly, when subjecting MEF or U2OS cells to adhere and migrate along narrow ECM-coated tracks, directional F-actin bundles are observed under the nucleus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Doyle et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lee et al., 2018</xref>). The stress fibers underneath the nucleus appear to be largely independent of linker of nucleus and cytoskeleton (LINC)-complex, which is known to mediate contacts between the nuclear envelope and perinuclear cap fibers at the dorsal surface of the nucleus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Luxton et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kim et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Calero-Cuenca et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lee et al., 2018</xref>). Interestingly, RhoA pulses upstream of NMII were also found to localize mainly near the cell center (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Graessl et al., 2017</xref>). Although the mechanisms by which these actomyosin bundles protecting the nucleus are assembled is still unknown, we envision that it would be difficult to generate such fibers from the transverse arc network, which to our knowledge is not generally present in cells migrating in a 3D environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Doyle et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Thomas et al., 2015</xref>). Thus, the <italic>de novo</italic> mechanism to generate contractile cortical stress fibers reported here is well suited for generation of stress fibers in 3D environment to protect the nucleus during migration. In line with this hypothesis, cells in 3D environment utilizing mesenchymal migration mode exhibit multiple focal adhesion-mediated ECM attachments around their dorso-ventral and antero-posterior axis, and impose greater challenges with protecting the integrity of the nucleus than cells in 2D (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Yamada and Sixt, 2019</xref>). We indeed observed short, adhesion-attached actomyosin bundles close to nuclei in U2OS cells migrating in 3D fibrin network. However, whether these structures correspond to cortical stress fibers and are generated from the actomyosin cortex through the same mechanism remain important questions for future research.</p><p>Taken together, we demonstrate that the myosin II pulse-induced actin contractions are linked to maturation of nascent focal adhesions at the cell cortex, and this can lead to an assembly of a contractile stress fiber that is attached to focal adhesions at its both ends. This new mechanism expands the toolbox that cells can apply for generation of stress fibers, thus allowing assembly of stress fibers also in conditions where the pre-existing stress fiber precursors (transverse arcs and dorsal stress fibers) are not present. In the future, it will be important to examine the functional relevance of cortical stress fibers especially in 3D environment, where transverse arcs are not present and focal adhesion formation is not restricted to the ventral plane.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Reagent type (species) or resource</th><th valign="top">Designation</th><th valign="top">Source or reference</th><th valign="top">Identifiers</th><th valign="top">Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">Human osteosarcoma cells (U2OS)</td><td valign="top">ATCC</td><td valign="top">Cat# HTB-96, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:CVCL_0042">CVCL_0042</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Authenticated through STR profiling</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (<italic>Mus musculus)</italic></td><td valign="top">Mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs)</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jiu et al., 2015</xref></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">A gift from John Eriksson (University of Turku, Finland)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">eGFP-NMIIA (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">Addgene, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jacobelli et al., 2009</xref></td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:Addgene_38297">Addgene_38297</ext-link></td><td valign="top">A gift from Mathew Krummel (University of California, San Francisco)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">PA-GFP-Actin (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">Addgene</td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:Addgene_57121">Addgene_57121</ext-link></td><td valign="top">A gift from Michael Davidson</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">LifeAct-mKate1.31 (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">Addgene, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Shcherbo et al., 2009</xref></td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:Addgene_54668">Addgene_54668</ext-link></td><td valign="top">A gift from Michael Davidson</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">mApple-NMIIA (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">Addgene, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Burnette et al., 2014</xref></td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:Addgene_54929">Addgene_54929</ext-link></td><td valign="top">A gift from Michael Davidson</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">Vinculin-mApple (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">Addgene</td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:Addgene_54962">Addgene_54962</ext-link></td><td valign="top">A gift from Michael Davidson</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">α-actinin1-TagRFP-T (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">Addgene</td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:Addgene_58033">Addgene_58033</ext-link></td><td valign="top">A gift from Michael Davidson</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">LifeAct-TagGFP2 (plasmid)</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Stefani et al., 2017</xref></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">A gift from Emmanuel Lemichez (Pasteur Institute, France)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">Histone H2B-eGFP (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">A gift from Maria Vartiainen (University of Helsinki, Finland)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">Histone H2B-mCherry (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">A gift from Maria Vartiainen (University of Helsinki, Finland)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">eGFP-Paxillin (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"><italic>Gallus gallus</italic> paxillin ORF with T132S and M133L unattended mutations (pPL1277)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">miRFP670-Paxillin (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">eGFP in eGFP-Paxillin replaced with miRFP670-N1 (pPL1514)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent</td><td valign="top">miRFP670-N1 (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">Addgene, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Shcherbakova et al., 2016</xref></td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:Addgene_79987">Addgene_79987</ext-link></td><td valign="top">A gift from Vladislav Verkusha (Albet Einstein College of Medicine, NY)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Transfected construct (human)</td><td valign="top">SMARTpoolON-TARGETplus siRNA to mDia1</td><td valign="top">Dharmacon</td><td valign="top">Cat# L-010347-00-0005</td><td valign="top">Transfected using GeneSilencer</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Transfected construct (human)</td><td valign="top">SMARTpoolON-TARGETplus siRNA to mDia2</td><td valign="top">Dharmacon</td><td valign="top">Cat# L-012029-00-0005</td><td valign="top">Transfected using GeneSilencer</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Transfected construct (human)</td><td valign="top">negative (non-targeting) control siRNA</td><td valign="top">Qiagen</td><td valign="top">Cat# 1027281</td><td valign="top">Transfected using GeneSilencer</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">anti-vinculin (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# V9131, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_477629">AB_477629</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:400 (IF)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">anti-NMIIA (C-termini) (rabbit polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 909801, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2565100">AB_2565100</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:800 (IF)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">anti-fibronectin (rabbit polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# F3648, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_476976">AB_476976</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:400 (IF) a gift from Johanna Ivaska (University of Turku, Finland)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">anti-Y118-paxillin (rabbit monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Cell Signaling Technology</td><td valign="top">Cat# 2541, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2174466">AB_2174466</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:50 (IF) a gift from Johanna Ivaska (University of Turku, Finland)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">anti-human mDia1 (rabbit monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Abcam</td><td valign="top">Cat# ab129167, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_11143749">AB_11143749</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:1000 (WB)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">anti-human mDia2 (rabbit polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# HPA005647, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_1078657">AB_1078657</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:1000 (WB)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">anti-GAPDH (rabbit polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# G9545, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_796208">AB_796208</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:10,000 (WB)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-mouse Alexa Fluor 488 (goat polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# A-11001, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2534069">AB_2534069</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:200 (IF)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-mouse Alexa Fluor 568 (goat polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# A-11031, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_144696">AB_144696</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:200 (IF)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor Plus 647 (goat polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# A32733, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2633282">AB_2633282</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:400 (IF)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">HRP-conjugated anti–rabbit (goat polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# 32460, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_1185567">AB_1185567</ext-link></td><td valign="top">1:1000 (WB)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">Lipofectamine 2000</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# 11668019</td><td valign="top">Plasmid transfection (3.5:1 DNA: Lipofectamine ratio)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">GeneSilencer</td><td valign="top">Genlantis</td><td valign="top">Cat# T500750</td><td valign="top">siRNA transfection</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">jetPRIME</td><td valign="top">Polyplus transfection</td><td valign="top">Cat# 114–01</td><td valign="top">Plasmid transfection (TFM)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">NEBuilder</td><td valign="top">New England Biolabs</td><td valign="top">Cat# E5520S</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Para-amino Blebbistatin</td><td valign="top">Optopharma</td><td valign="top">Cat# DR-Am-89</td><td valign="top">50 µM working concentration</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">SMIFH2</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# S4826</td><td valign="top">12.5 µM working concentration</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">CK-666</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# SML0006</td><td valign="top">100 µM working concentration</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">DMSO</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# D2650</td><td valign="top">Diluent/negative control</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="top">Fiji</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Schindelin et al., 2012</xref></td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:SCR_002285">SCR_002285</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="top">OriginPro</td><td valign="top">OriginLab Corp.</td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:SCR_014212">SCR_014212</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="top">NMII pulse quantification (macro)</td><td valign="top">This paper. Modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim and Davidson, 2011</xref></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/UH-LMU/lmu-users/tree/master/jaakko/NMIIA_pulses">https://github.com/UH-LMU/lmu-users/tree/master/jaakko/NMIIA_pulses</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">Fibrinogen (from human plasma)</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# 341578</td><td valign="top">2.25 mg/ml working concentration</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">Thrombin (from human plasma)</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# T6884</td><td valign="top">1 U/ml working concentration</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">Fibronectin (human plasma)</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# FIBRP-RO</td><td valign="top">10 µg/ml working concentration</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">Laminin</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# L2020</td><td valign="top">25 µg/ml working concentration</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">Collagen</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# C4243</td><td valign="top">500 µg/ml working concentration</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">poly-D-lysine</td><td valign="top">Sigma Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# P0899</td><td valign="top">10 µg/ml working concentration</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">DAPI stain</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# D1306</td><td valign="top">0.2 µM working concentration (IF)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">Alexa Fluor 488-Phalloidin</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# A12379</td><td valign="top">1:200 (IF)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">Alexa Fluor 568-Phalloidin</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# 12380</td><td valign="top">1:200 (IF)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">Fluorescent microspheres. 0.2 µm diameter</td><td valign="top">Invitrogen</td><td valign="top">Cat# F8848</td><td valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Cell culture and transfections</title><p>Wild-type MEFs (a gift from J.Eriksson’s lab) and U2OS (ATCC HTB-96, verified through STR profiling) cells were cultured in high-glucose DMEM (Lonza, BE12-119F), supplemented with 10% FBS (Gibco, 10500–064), 10 U/ml penicillin, 10 µg/ml streptomycin, and 20 mM L-glutamine (Gibco, 10378–016) (from here on referred as complete DMEM) and kept at +37°C in a humidified atmosphere with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Regular mycoplasma testing has been conducted with Lonza MycoAlert plus (LT07-710). For live-cell imaging experiments, Fluorobrite DMEM (Gibco, A1896701), supplemented with 25 mM HEPES and 10% FBS was used. Transient transfections were performed with Lipofectamine 2000 (Thermo Fisher Scientific) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. 24 hr after transfection, cells were either fixed with 4% PFA in PBS for 10 min at +37°C (3D-SIM/tile-scan TIRF) or detached with 0.05% Trypsin-EDTA (Gibco, 15400054) and plated onto high-precision (#1.5H) 35 mm imaging dishes (Ibidi µ-dish high, 81158), coated with 10 µg/ml fibronectin (Sigma Aldrich, FIBRP-RO) for 1 hr RT (live-cell TIRF imaging experiments). To prevent integrin-mediated adhesion, 10 µg/ml poly-D-lysine (Sigma Aldrich, P0899) was applied onto the 35 mm imaging dishes at RT for 10 min, washed, and allowed to dry prior plating the cells. Cells were allowed to attach for 24 hr prior onset of imaging. For 3D-SIM or tile-scan TIRF, cells were plated onto #1.5H coverslips coated with 10 µg/ml fibronectin (Sigma Aldrich, FIBRP-RO), 25 µg/ml laminin (Sigma Aldrich, L2020), or 500 µg/ml collagen (Sigma Aldrich, C4243).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Plasmids</title><p>eGFP-NMIIA was a gift from Mathew Krummel (Addgene plasmid #38297; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jacobelli et al., 2009</xref>). PA-GFP-Actin, LifeAct-mKate1.31, mApple-NMIIA, Vinculin-mApple, and α-actinin1-TagRFP-T were all gifts from Michael Davidson (Addgene plasmids #57121, #54668, #54929, #54962, #58033, respectively; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Burnette et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Shcherbo et al., 2009</xref>). LifeAct-TagGFP2 was kindly provided by the Emmanuel Lemichez lab. Histone H2B-eGFP (in peGFP-N3 backbone) and Histone H2B-mCherry (in pmCherry-N3 backbone) were gifts from Maria Vartiainen lab. miRFP670-Paxillin (pPL1514) was constructed by replacing the eGFP in eGFP-paxillin (pPL1277) (containing <italic>Gallus gallus</italic> paxillin ORF with T132S and M133L unattended mutations in an eGFP-C1 backbone) with miRFP670 originated from miRFP670-N1 (a gift from Vladislav Verkhusha, Addgene plasmid #79987; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Shcherbakova et al., 2016</xref>) via restriction free cloning using NEBuilder (New England Biolabs). All inserts have been sequence verified prior the respective plasmid usage.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Reagents</title><p>Mouse monoclonal antibody (ab) for vinculin (Sigma Aldrich, V9131), rabbit polyclonal ab recognizing the C-terminal tail of the NMIIA heavy chain (Biolegend, 909801), rabbit polyclonal anti-fibronectin (F3648, Sigma Aldrich), and monoclonal rabbit ab against Y118-phosphorylated paxillin (#2541, Cell Signaling Technology) were employed in this study. 4’,6’-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) (Thermo Fisher Scientific, D1306) was utilized to detect the nuclei, whereas Alexa Fluor 488- and 568-Phalloidin (Thermo Fisher Scientific, A12379/12380) were applied to visualize F-actin. Alexa Fluor 488- and 568-conjugated goat anti-mouse (Thermo Fisher Scientific, A-11001 and A-11031, respectively) and Alexa Fluor Plus 647-conjugated goat anti-rabbit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, A32733) were used as secondary antibodies. 5% BSA-TBS-Tween20 (0.02%) was used as a blocking buffer for the cells prior staining as well as a diluent for the abovementioned reagents. Monoclonal rabbit ab against human mDia1 (Abcam, ab129167) and polyclonal rabbit ab raised against human mDia2 (Sigma Aldrich, HPA005647) were used in 1:1000 dilution in 5% milk TBS-Tween20 (0.05%) to detect siRNA depletion efficiency. Polyclonal rabbit ab against GAPDH (Sigma-Aldrich, G9545) was used in 1:10,000 dilution to probe equal loading in WB. 50 µM of para-amino-Blebbistatin (Optopharma, DR-Am-89) was applied for 1 hr to inhibit NMII activity, 100 µM CK-666 (Sigma Aldrich, SML0006) for 4 hr to inhibit the Arp2/3 complex, and 12.5 µM of SMIFH2 (Sigma Aldrich, S4826) was added for 1 hr to inhibit formin activity. Inhibitor stocks were made to dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) (Sigma Aldrich, D2650) that was also used as control in the corresponding experiments. To study the role of mDia1 and mDia2 formins in the process, we treated U2OS cells for 72 hr with specific siRNAs (20 µM of SMARTpool ON-TARGETplus, L-010347-00-0005, and L-012029-00-0005, respectively, Dharmacon) or with 20 µM of negative control siRNA (Qiagen, 1027281). For 3D-SIM experiments, samples were mounted using either non-hardening Vectashield (Vector laboratories, H-1000) or Prolong Glass (Thermo Fisher Scientific, P36980). Fibrinogen (Sigma-Aldrich, 341578) and Thrombin (Sigma-Aldrich, T6884) were used to prepare the 3D-fibrin gels.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>3D-SIM</title><p>All 3D-SIM images were obtained at RT, using Deltavision OMX SR (Cytiva) with 60×/1.42NA PlanApo N oil objective with 1.516 RI immersion oil, a laser module with 405-, 488-, 568-, and 640 nm diode laser lines and three sCMOS cameras, operated through Acquire SR 4.4 acquisition software. SI reconstruction and image alignment were performed with SoftWoRx 7.0. Imaging arrays of 1024 × 1024 or 512 × 512 were used, both with pixel size of 0.08 µm and 0.125 µm (x/y and z). Samples for 3D-SIM were prepared according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kraus et al., 2017</xref> with exceptions of using 5% BSA-PBST as blocking reagent, and omitting the pre-incubation with mounting reagent when using the Prolong Glass as a mountant.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>TIRF microscopy</title><p>For live-cell TIRF experiments, the Ring-TIRF module from the Deltavision OMX SR (Cytiva) with 60×/1.49NA Apo N oil objective (Olympus), 1.522 RI immersion oil and imaging chamber with controlled humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and 37°C was utilized. Sample illumination with 488, 568, and 640 nm diode lasers was detected and recorded with three respective sCMOS cameras and controlled through Acquire SR 4.4 acquisition software. The captured 1024 × 1024 time-lapse videos had a pixel size of 0.08 µm (x/y). Photoactivation experiments were also performed with Deltavision OMX SR. There, 4% laser power (405 nm) in EPI mode with 1 ms exposure was applied to activate PA-GFP-Actin on a cortical stress fiber visualized by mKate1.31-LifeAct adjacent to a miRFP670-paxillin positive adhesion. The time-lapse imaging with 10 s interval for a total of 5 min was conducted in TIRF (cortical stress fiber) or in Highly Inclined and Laminated Optical sheet (HILO, dorsal stress fiber) mode by recording also three frames prior to photoactivation. Obtained time-lapse series were deconvolved and channels aligned with SoftWoRx 7.0. Prior the onset of live-cell imaging, cells were allowed to settle within the imaging chamber for 1 hr.</p><p>‘Tile-scan’ TIRF of fixed specimens on 35 mm imaging dishes (Ibidi µ-dish high) in 1× PBS was performed with Eclipse Ti-E N-STOM/TIRF microscope (Nikon Instruments) using 100×/1.49NA Apo TIRF oil objective. Illumination was provided by 405 nm (100 mW), 488 nm (Argon), and 561 nm (150 mW) laser lines and LU4A laser unit (Nikon Instruments), controlled via NIS-Elements (NIS-AR version 4.5). Images were captured using iXon+ 885 EMCCD camera (Andor Technology) with imaging array of 1004 × 1002 pixels, and final pixel size of 0.08 µm (x/y). In order to acquire the data set from the specimen in unbiased manner, focus was set, followed by capturing 5 × 5 field of view (FOV) tile-scan with 10% overlap. After this, the next tile-scan was acquired from a new area, six times the FOV to another direction.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Traction force microscopy (TFM)</title><p>For the TFM experiments, U2OS cells on a 35 mm imaging dishes (Mat-Tek, P35G-1.5–14C) were transfected with mKate1.31-LifeAct using JetPRIME transfection reagent (Polyplus transfection, 114–01) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Next day, cells were re-plated on polyacrylamide (PAA) gels of known stiffness (Young’s Modulus/elastic modulus = 26 kPa) coated with mixture of collagen and fibronectin and incubated for 2–4 hr prior to imaging. PAA substrates were surface-coated with sulfate fluorescent microspheres of 0.2 µm diameter (Invitrogen, F8848) before coating with the ECM proteins. Cells and the underlying microspheres were imaged with 3I-Marianas imaging setup containing a heated sample chamber (+37°C) and controlled 5% CO<sub>2</sub> (3I intelligent Imaging Innovations, Germany). 63×/1.2 W C-Apochromat Corr WD = 0.28 M27 objective was used. After first round of images, the cells were removed from the substrates with 10× Trypsin (Lonza, BE02-007E) and a second set of images were obtained of the microspheres in a cell-free configuration. Microsphere displacement maps were achieved by comparing the first and second set of microsphere images. By knowing the spatial displacement field, substrate stiffness (26 kPa), and tracing manually cell boundaries and single adhesions in the ends of stress fibers, we could compute the traction fields by using Fourier Transform Traction Cytometry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Tolić-Nørrelykke et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Krishnan et al., 2009</xref>). From the traction fields, root mean squared (RMS) magnitudes were computed. Importantly, several of the cortical stress fibers relayed forces so low that they were undetectable by the microsphere displacement assay, and thus the actual RMS values for this stress fiber subtype are likely to be even lower. Distinct stress fiber types for the measurements were chosen based on their appearance, location, and connections to FAs: Ventral stress fibers were defined as thick, straight bundles, usually behind an arc network and connected to focal adhesions from both ends; Cortical stress fibers were defined as thin and short bundles, usually located under the nucleus and associated with focal adhesions from both ends.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Fibrin gel preparation and imaging</title><p>For the visualization of the actomyosin cytoskeleton in 3D environment, U2OS cells transfected with eGFP-Paxillin were embedded into a fibrin matrix according to protocol by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Owen et al., 2017</xref> with small modifications. Briefly 15 mg/ml fibrinogen stocks were mixed with HBSS (Gibco, 14175095) to total volume of 800 µl. Subsequently, 100 µl of 9× DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS and 100 µl of 2.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml in complete DMEM were added, and mixed thoroughly, avoiding air bubble formation to obtain final fibrinogen concentration of 2.25 mg/ml. One unit of Thrombin was added, the suspension was mixed by pipetting three times, and 300 µl aliquots were immediately transferred onto the 35 mm imaging dishes (Ibidi µ-dish high). Dishes were inverted and kept 15 min at +37°C to allow fibrin polymerization. After polymerization, 3 ml complete DMEM was added and cells were allowed to spread for 48 hr prior fixation and staining.</p><p>The eGFP-paxillin expressing cells in fibrin gels were further stained with phalloidin and DAPI. The samples were imaged in 1× PBS with Andor Dragonfly 505 (Oxford Instruments) spinning disk confocal, using 60×/1.2NA Plan APO VC water immersion objective with 0.29 mm working distance. Samples were illuminated with 404 (100 mW), 488 (150 mW), and 561 nm (100 mW) direct modulation lasers, using 40 µm pinhole diameter and 1× camera magnification. 3D stacks using 190 nm step size, 2047 × 2047 resolution, and 0.1 µm pixel size (x/y) were captured with Andor Zyla 4.2 sCMOS camera controlled through Fusion 2.0 acquisition program. Acquired 3D stacks were further deconvoluted with the ClearVieW-GPU (Oxford Instruments). 3D-rendered images and videos were constructed using Bitplane Imaris 9.2.1 (Oxford Instruments).</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>NMIIA pulse quantification</title><p>A Fiji/ImageJ macro originally used to quantify F-actin dynamics was obtained from Lance Davidson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim and Davidson, 2011</xref>), and used here to detect and track the frequency of NMIIA pulses. The macro was adapted to current file type and modified to save intermediate results which were further processed with a Python script. Pulses were tracked at the ventral cortex from TIRF time-lapse series of U2OS cells expressing mApple-NMIIA and H2B-eGFP, and analyzed similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Baird et al., 2017</xref> with exceptions of defining the initial regions of interest (ROIs) so that pulses were recorded first from the ventral cortex excluding nucleus (‘outside’) and then only within the nucleus perimeter (‘within’). Also more stringent 1.3 threshold of NMIIA signal over the background intensity was used and number of connected hexagons smaller than 3 (in individual x–y frames) were filtered out to improve the analysis by excluding single bright myosin puncta. Furthermore, the ‘outside’ ROI excluded edges of the cell as well as the early lamella, to prevent the NMII signal from these locations to bias the analysis. To minimize the effect of photobleaching, pulse frequency was determined by registering all pulses within the first 30 min of TIRFM time-lapse videos that persisted more than three frames. The frequency of each ‘outside’ data point was further normalized to the smaller ventral cortex area covered by the nucleus as calculated from the drawn ROIs with Fiji/ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Schindelin et al., 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Image processing and statistical analyses</title><p>All TIRFM data, excluding the LifeAct channel, was processed with the rolling ball background subtraction plug-in using a 50-pixel ball radius in Fiji/ImageJ. Temporal color-coded hyperstacks (3D-SIM) and kymographs (TIRF time-lapse data, KymographBuilder plugin) were also created with Fiji. The statistical analysis for TFM data, NMII pulse frequency, and cortical stress fiber localization, as well as bar graph generation, were performed with Excel (Microsoft). Half-violin plots were constructed with OriginPro 2020 (OriginLab Corp.). Statistical significance for myosin pulse frequency was calculated with paired <italic>t</italic>-test as respective ‘inside’ vs. ‘outside’ pulses were quantified within the same cell, preceded by examining data normality with quantile–quantile plot. To assess statistical difference for the TFM data, nonparametric Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test was applied. In quantification of cortical stress fiber formation from the TIRFM time-lapse data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>), cortical stress fibers of maximum 10 µm diameter, persisting for 2 min or longer, having focal adhesion at both ends with possibility of sharing a common focal adhesion, were included in the analysis. To be categorized as forming under the nucleus, at least one focal adhesion had to reside below the nucleus. Number of cells analyzed for each quantification are listed in the respective figure legends. The cortical stress fibers' number from TIRF images of fixed cells depleted of mDia1/2 or treated with SMIFH2, Blebbistatin, CK-666, or DMSO alone were quantified by manual blind analysis. Here, the cortical stress fibers were defined as focal adhesion attached (from both ends) actin bundles located at least partially underneath the nucleus and with a length smaller than the diameter of nucleus.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the Biomedicum Imaging Unit of the University of Helsinki, sponsored by HiLIFE and Biocenter Finland, for support with imaging. Maria Vartiainen (University of Helsinki) and Johanna Ivaska (University of Turku) are acknowledged for providing reagents. We thank Lance Davidson (University of Pittsburgh) for providing the macro and Harri Jäälinoja (LMU imaging unit, Institute of Biotechnology, University of Helsinki) for help with modifying the macro for pulse quantification. This work was supported by grants from Sigrid Juselius Foundation (to PL), Jane and Aatos Erkko Foundation (to PL and ST), and Academy of Finland (to ST).</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf2"><p>Reviewing editor, <italic>eLife</italic></p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing, JL conducted all experiments and analyzed the data, expect for the TFM experiments</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Investigation, Methodology, Conducted the TFM experiments</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Investigation, Methodology, Writing - review and editing, Conducted the TFM experiments</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Conceptualization, Funding acquisition, Writing - original draft, Project administration, Writing - review and editing</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60710-transrepform-v3.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files. Source data files for pulse quantification are provided in GitHub (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/UH-LMU/lmu-users/tree/master/jaakko/NMIIA_pulses">https://github.com/UH-LMU/lmu-users/tree/master/jaakko/NMIIA_pulses</ext-link>).</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baird</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Billington</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelstein</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellers</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterman</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Local pulsatile contractions are an intrinsic property of the myosin 2A motor in the cortical cytoskeleton of adherent cells</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.e16-05-0335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27881665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beach</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruun</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Swider</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Remmert</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelstein</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusan</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Betzig</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Actin dynamics and competition for myosin monomer govern the sequential amplification of myosin filaments</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb3463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28114272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bisaria</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayer</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garbett</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Membrane-proximal F-actin restricts local membrane protrusions and directs cell migration</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>368</volume><fpage>1205</fpage><lpage>1210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aay7794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32527825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bovellan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Romeo</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Biro</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boden</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chugh</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaghela</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritzsche</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulding</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorogate</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jégou</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thrasher</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Romet-Lemonne</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Paluch</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Charras</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Cellular control of cortical actin nucleation</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1628</fpage><lpage>1635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.05.069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25017211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year><article-title>Cortical flow in animal cells</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>239</volume><fpage>883</fpage><lpage>888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.3277283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3277283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bretscher</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fehon</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>ERM proteins and Merlin: integrators at the cell cortex</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12154370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burnette</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Manley</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sengupta</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sougrat</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kachar</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippincott-Schwartz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>A role for actin arcs in the leading-edge advance of migrating cells</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21423177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burnette</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasapera</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Baird</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Der Loughian</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Delanoe-Ayari</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Paszek</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Betzig</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippincott-Schwartz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A contractile and counterbalancing adhesion system controls the 3D shape of crawling cells</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>205</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201311104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burridge</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Guilluy</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><source>Focal Adhesions, Stress Fibers and Mechanical Tension, Experimental Cell Research</source><publisher-name>Academic Press Inc</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexcr.2015.10.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calero-Cuenca</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Janota</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><source>Dealing with the Nucleus During Cell Migration, Current Opinion in Cell Biology</source><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2018.01.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaghela</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barriga</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chugh</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Maufront</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavoie</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Méant</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferber</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bovellan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberts</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayor</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Paluch</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jégou</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Romet-Lemonne</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Charras</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>SPIN90 associates with mDia1 and the Arp2/3 complex to regulate cortical actin organization</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41556-020-0531-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32572169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charras</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Paluch</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Blebs lead the way: how to migrate without lamellipodia</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18628785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chugh</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Paluch</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>The actin cortex at a glance</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>131</volume><elocation-id>jcs186254</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.186254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30026344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Battistella</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Déjardin</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Betz</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Plastino</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Borghi</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadot</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sykes</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Nesprin-2 accumulates at the front of the nucleus during confined cell migration</article-title><source>EMBO Reports</source><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>e49910</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embr.201949910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32419336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denais</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Isermann</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McGregor</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>te Lindert</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigelin</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedl</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lammerding</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Nuclear envelope rupture and repair during Cancer cell migration</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>352</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aad7297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27013428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doyle</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutys</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelstein</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Micro-environmental control of cell migration--myosin IIA is required for efficient migration in fibrillar environments through control of cell adhesion dynamics</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>125</volume><fpage>2244</fpage><lpage>2256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.098806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22328520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doyle</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvajal</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Local 3D matrix microenvironment regulates cell migration through spatiotemporal dynamics of contractility-dependent adhesions</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>8720</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms9720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26548801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elkhatib</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Neu</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zensen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmoller</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Louvard</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bausch</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Betz</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vignjevic</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Fascin plays a role in stress fiber organization and focal adhesion disassembly</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1492</fpage><lpage>1499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.05.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24930964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenix</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Taneja</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Buttler</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Engelenburg</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohi</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnette</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Expansion and concatenation of nonmuscle myosin IIA filaments drive cellular contractile system formation during interphase and mitosis</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>1465</fpage><lpage>1478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E15-10-0725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenix</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Neininger</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Taneja</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Visetsouk</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Garde</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nixon</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Manalo</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawley</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bader</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyska</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutzman</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnette</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Muscle-specific stress fibers give rise to sarcomeres in cardiomyocytes</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e42144</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30540249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geiger</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Molecular architecture and function of matrix adhesions</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>a005033</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a005033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21441590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graessl</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Calderon</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamps</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazel</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jungkurth</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Patwardhan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Solouk</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hampe</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehmelt</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nalbant</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>An excitable rho GTPase signaling network generates dynamic subcellular contraction patterns</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>216</volume><fpage>4271</fpage><lpage>4285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201706052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsumi</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokabe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Actin filaments function as a tension sensor by tension-dependent binding of cofilin to the filament</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>195</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201102039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henson</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ditzler</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Germain</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwin</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogt</surname> <given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuster</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>The ultrastructural organization of actin and myosin II filaments in the contractile ring: new support for an old model of cytokinesis</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.e16-06-0466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28057763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotulainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Stress fibers are generated by two distinct actin assembly mechanisms in motile cells</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>173</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200511093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dasbiswas</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tee</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiagarajan</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hersen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chew</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Safran</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaidel-Bar</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bershadsky</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Long-range self-organization of cytoskeletal myosin II filament stacks</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb3466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28114270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobelli</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname> <given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandurangi</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tooley</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Krummel</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Myosin-IIA and ICAM-1 regulate the interchange between two distinct modes of T cell migration</article-title><source>The Journal of Immunology</source><volume>182</volume><fpage>2041</fpage><lpage>2050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.0803267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19201857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehtimäki</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tojkander</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jäälinoja</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Varjosalo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Bidirectional interplay between vimentin intermediate filaments and contractile actin stress fibers</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2015.05.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26027931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenix</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaible</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Varjosalo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnette</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Myosin-18B promotes the assembly of myosin II stacks for maturation of contractile actomyosin bundles</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2018.11.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30581023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kassianidou</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname> <given-names>US</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Geometry and network connectivity govern the mechanics of stress fibers</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>114</volume><fpage>2622</fpage><lpage>2627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1606649114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28213499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>D-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatau</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Walcott</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>SX</given-names></name><name><surname>Longmore</surname> <given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Actin cap associated focal adhesions and their distinct role in cellular mechanosensing</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep00555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Tight coupling between nucleus and cell migration through the perinuclear actin cap</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>2528</fpage><lpage>2541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.144345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24639463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Punctuated actin contractions during convergent extension and their permissive regulation by the non-canonical Wnt-signaling pathway</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.067579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21266466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovács</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tóth</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hetényi</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Málnási-Csizmadia</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellers</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Mechanism of blebbistatin inhibition of myosin II</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>35557</fpage><lpage>35563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M405319200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kraus</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Miron</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Demmerle</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitiashvili</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Budco</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alle</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonhardt</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schermelleh</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Markaki</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Quantitative 3D structured illumination microscopy of nuclear structures</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1011</fpage><lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2017.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28406495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krishnan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mead</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaspers</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Trepat</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenormand</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tambe</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolensky</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoll</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredberg</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Reinforcement versus fluidization in cytoskeletal mechanoresponsiveness</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e5486</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0005486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19424501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumari</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Carman</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tojkander</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kogan</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Varjosalo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunning</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominguez</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Tropomodulins control the balance between protrusive and contractile structures by stabilizing Actin-Tropomyosin filaments</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>767</fpage><lpage>778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2019.12.049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laplante</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tebbs</surname> <given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bewersdorf</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Molecular organization of cytokinesis nodes and contractile rings by super-resolution fluorescence microscopy of live fission yeast</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>E5876</fpage><lpage>E5885</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1608252113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27647921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassianidou</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Actomyosin stress fiber subtypes have unique viscoelastic properties and roles in tension generation</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>1992</fpage><lpage>2004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E18-02-0106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29927349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Cofilin is required for polarization of tension in stress fiber networks during migration</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>133</volume><elocation-id>jcs243873</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.243873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32501289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehtimäki</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakala</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017a</year><chapter-title>Actin filament structures in migrating cells</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jockusch</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Handbook of Experimental Pharmacology</source><volume>235</volume><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/164_2016_28</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehtimäki</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenix</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotila</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Balistreri</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Paavolainen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Varjosalo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnette</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017b</year><article-title>UNC-45a promotes myosin folding and stress fiber assembly</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>216</volume><fpage>4053</fpage><lpage>4072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201703107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livne</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiger</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>The inner workings of stress fibers - from contractile machinery to focal adhesions and back</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>129</volume><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>1304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.180927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27037413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Logue</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartagena-Rivera</surname> <given-names>AX</given-names></name><name><surname>Baird</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chadwick</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterman</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Erk regulation of actin capping and bundling by Eps8 promotes cortex tension and leader bleb-based migration</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e08314</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.08314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26163656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>López-Gay</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunley</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>di Pietro</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Guirao</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosveld</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Markova</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaugue</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubensky</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellaïche</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Apical stress fibers enable a scaling between cell mechanical response and area in epithelial tissue</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>370</volume><elocation-id>eabb2169</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb2169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33060329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname> <given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Daam1 regulates fascin for actin assembly in mouse oocyte meiosis</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1350</fpage><lpage>1356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15384101.2017.1325045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28682694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luxton</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Folker</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Vintinner</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gundersen</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Linear arrays of nuclear envelope proteins harness retrograde actin flow for nuclear movement</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>329</volume><fpage>956</fpage><lpage>959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1189072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20724637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mason</surname> <given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tworoger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Apical domain polarization localizes actin-myosin activity to drive ratchet-like apical constriction</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>926</fpage><lpage>936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaux</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Robin</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>McFadden</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Munro</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Excitable RhoA dynamics drive pulsed contractions in the early <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryo</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>217</volume><fpage>4230</fpage><lpage>4252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201806161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munjal</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippe</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Munro</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecuit</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A self-organized biomechanical network drives shape changes during tissue morphogenesis</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>524</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26214737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munro</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nance</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Priess</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Cortical flows powered by asymmetrical contraction transport PAR proteins to establish and maintain anterior-posterior polarity in the <italic>early C. elegans</italic> embryo</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2004.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15363415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naumanen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotulainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Mechanisms of actin stress fibre assembly</article-title><source>Journal of Microscopy</source><volume>231</volume><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2818.2008.02057.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18755000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nie</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname> <given-names>M-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ou-Yang</surname> <given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jedlicka</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vavylonis</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Formation of contractile networks and fibers in the medial cell cortex through myosin-II turnover, contraction, and stress-stabilization</article-title><source>Cytoskeleton</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cm.21207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="preprint"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishimura</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bershadsky</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Viasnoff</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellers</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>The formin inhibitor, SMIFH2, inhibits members of the myosin superfamily</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.08.30.274613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owen</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikari</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimmer</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leijnse</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Notbohm</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Franck</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>A cytoskeletal clutch mediates cellular force transmission in a soft, three-dimensional extracellular matrix</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>1959</fpage><lpage>1974</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.e17-02-0102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28592635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrie</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Generation of compartmentalized pressure by a nuclear piston governs cell motility in a 3D matrix</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>345</volume><fpage>1062</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1256965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25170155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prager-Khoutorsky</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajendran</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayo</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kam</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiger</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bershadsky</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Fibroblast polarization is a matrix-rigidity-dependent process controlled by focal adhesion mechanosensing</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1457</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22081092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajakylä</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehtimäki</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Acheva</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaible</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tojkander</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Assembly of peripheral actomyosin bundles in epithelial cells is dependent on the CaMKK2/AMPK pathway</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>4266</fpage><lpage>4280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2020.02.096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32209483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rauzi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenne</surname> <given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecuit</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Planar polarized actomyosin contractile flows control epithelial junction remodelling</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>468</volume><fpage>1110</fpage><lpage>1114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21068726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reymann</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Staniscia</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Erzberger</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salbreux</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Grill</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Cortical flow aligns actin filaments to form a furrow</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e17807</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.17807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27719759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizvi</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidt</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Feiger</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Skau</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardel</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozmin</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovar</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Identification and characterization of a small molecule inhibitor of formin-mediated actin assembly</article-title><source>Chemistry &amp; Biology</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1158</fpage><lpage>1168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chembiol.2009.10.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19942139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruprecht</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieser</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Callan-Jones</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smutny</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sako</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barone</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritsch-Marte</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sixt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Voituriez</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heisenberg</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Cortical contractility triggers a stochastic switch to fast amoeboid cell motility</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>160</volume><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.01.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25679761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schindelin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arganda-Carreras</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Frise</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaynig</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Longair</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietzsch</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Preibisch</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rueden</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saalfeld</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinevez</surname> <given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartenstein</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliceiri</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomancak</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardona</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Fiji: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulze</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Graessl</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blancke Soares</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehmelt</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nalbant</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>FHOD1 regulates stress fiber organization by controlling the dynamics of transverse arcs and dorsal fibers</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>1379</fpage><lpage>1393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.134627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24481812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senger</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitaval</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ennomani</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurzawa</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchoin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Théry</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Spatial integration of mechanical forces by α-actinin establishes actin network symmetry</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>132</volume><elocation-id>jcs236604</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.236604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31615968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shcherbakova</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baloban</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Emelyanov</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenowitz</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Verkhusha</surname> <given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Bright monomeric near-infrared fluorescent proteins as tags and biosensors for multiscale imaging</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms12405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shcherbo</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ermakova</surname> <given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Solovieva</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chepurnykh</surname> <given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Shcheglov</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Verkhusha</surname> <given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Pletnev</surname> <given-names>VZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazelwood</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roche</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukyanov</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaraisky</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chudakov</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Far-red fluorescent tags for protein imaging in living tissues</article-title><source>Biochemical Journal</source><volume>418</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20081949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Small</surname> <given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Rottner</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaverina</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>KI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Assembling an actin cytoskeleton for cell attachment and movement</article-title><source>Biochimica Et Biophysica Acta</source><volume>1404</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-4889(98)00080-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9739149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solon</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya-Copur</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombelli</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Pulsed forces timed by a ratchet-like mechanism drive directed tissue movement during dorsal closure</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>137</volume><fpage>1331</fpage><lpage>1342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2009.03.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19563762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stefani</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Rodriguez</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Senju</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Doye</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Efimova</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Janel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipuma</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamaoui</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddugoda</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochet-Escartin</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Prévost</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafont</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Svitkina</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassereau</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemichez</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Ezrin enhances line tension along transcellular tunnel edges via NMIIa driven actomyosin cable formation</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>15839</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms15839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28643776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svitkina</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Actin cell cortex: structure and molecular organization</article-title><source>Trends in Cell Biology</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcb.2020.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32278656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tee</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shemesh</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiagarajan</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hariadi</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Volkmann</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanein</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivaramakrishnan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozlov</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bershadsky</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Cellular chirality arising from the self-organization of the actin cytoskeleton</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb3137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25799062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yenepalli</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Denais</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rape</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beach</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y-li</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiemann</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Baskaran</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lammerding</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Egelhoff</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Non-muscle myosin IIB is critical for nuclear translocation during 3D invasion</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>210</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201502039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tojkander</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gateva</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schevzov</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotulainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Naumanen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunning</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>A molecular pathway for myosin II recruitment to stress fibers</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2011.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21458264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tojkander</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gateva</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Actin stress fibers--assembly, dynamics and biological roles</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>125</volume><fpage>1855</fpage><lpage>1864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.098087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22544950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tojkander</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gateva</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Husain</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Generation of contractile actomyosin bundles depends on mechanosensitive actin filament assembly and disassembly</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e06126</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.06126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26652273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tojkander</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciuba</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>CaMKK2 regulates mechanosensitive assembly of contractile actin stress fibers</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.06.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29972773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tolić-Nørrelykke</surname> <given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Spatial and temporal traction response in human airway smooth muscle cells</article-title><source>American Journal of Physiology-Cell Physiology</source><volume>283</volume><fpage>C1254</fpage><lpage>C1266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpcell.00169.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12225988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasquez</surname> <given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tworoger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Dynamic myosin phosphorylation regulates contractile pulses and tissue integrity during epithelial morphogenesis</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>206</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201402004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vicente-Manzanares</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelstein</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Horwitz</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Non-muscle myosin II takes centre stage in cell adhesion and migration</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>778</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19851336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vignaud</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Copos</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leterrier</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Toro-Nahuelpan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahamid</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchoin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogilner</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Théry</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurzawa</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Stress fibres are embedded in a contractile cortical network</article-title><source>Nature Materials</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41563-020-00825-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname> <given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shekhar</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chancellor</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendonca</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lele</surname> <given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Actomyosin pulls to advance the nucleus in a migrating tissue cell</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2013.11.4489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24411232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Babcock</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Dual-objective STORM reveals three-dimensional filament organization in the actin cytoskeleton</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22231642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Localized zones of rho and rac activities drive initiation and expansion of epithelial cell–cell adhesion</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>178</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200701058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sixt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Mechanisms of 3D cell migration</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-019-0172-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31582855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgs</surname> <given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Focal adhesions undergo longitudinal splitting into Fixed-Width units</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>2033</fpage><lpage>2045</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2018.04.073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29910076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaidel-Bar</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Milo</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kam</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiger</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>A paxillin tyrosine phosphorylation switch regulates the assembly and form of cell-matrix adhesions</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.03314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17164291</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.60710.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Fässler</surname><given-names>Reinhard</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Max Planck Institute of Biochemistry</institution><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Fässler</surname><given-names>Reinhard</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>Max Planck Institute of Biochemistry</institution><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Schnorrer</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>Aix Marseille University, CNRS, IDBM</institution><country>France</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife publishes the most substantive revision requests and the accompanying author responses.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Acceptance summary:</bold></p><p>This elegant study uses cutting-edge imaging techniques to reveal the existence of cortical stress fibers that assemble in the cortex underneath the nucleus. The characterization of these cellular structures improves our understanding of the mechanisms by which cells produce and sense force.</p><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Generation of stress fibers through myosin-driven re-organization of the actin cortex&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, including Reinhard Fässler as the Reviewing Editor and Reviewer #1, and the evaluation has been overseen by Anna Akhmanova as the Senior Editor. The following individual involved in review of your submission has agreed to reveal their identity: Frank Schnorrer (Reviewer #2). The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>As the editors have judged that your manuscript is of interest, but as described below that additional experiments are required before it is published, we would like to draw your attention to changes in our revision policy that we have made in response to COVID-19 (https://elifesciences.org/articles/57162). First, because many researchers have temporarily lost access to the labs, we will give authors as much time as they need to submit revised manuscripts. We are also offering, if you choose, to post the manuscript to bioRxiv (if it is not already there) along with this decision letter and a formal designation that the manuscript is &quot;in revision at <italic>eLife</italic>&quot;. Please let us know if you would like to pursue this option. (If your work is more suitable for medRxiv, you will need to post the preprint yourself, as the mechanisms for us to do so are still in development.)</p><p>Summary:</p><p>The authors identified and characterised a novel type of stress fibre, which forms underneath the nucleus from the pre-existing cortical actin. The assembly of this new stress fibre termed cortical stress fiber is triggered by non-muscle myosin II pulses, which reorganise the cortical actin. The cortical stress fibers attach to and reinforce nascent adhesions.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) The formin mDia1 and mDia2 are involved in stress fiber formation (Hotulainen and Lappalainen, 2006; Tojkander et al., 2011), and recently, mDia1 has been involved in the nucleation of actin filaments in the actin cortex (https://doi.org/10.1038/s41556-020-0531-y). The role of formins in the assembly of the cortical stress fibers with either SMIFH2 treatments or by depleting formins using siRNA or Crispr should be tested.</p><p>2) It is not clear whether the cortical stress fibers elongate through actin polymerization. FRAP experiment on cortical stress fibers in GFP-actin expressing cells (used by the authors in previous articles) would help clarifying this issue.</p><p>3) The sentence “Blebbistatin did not cease the NMII pulsatile behavior in U2OS cells. However, the cortical stress fiber formation was almost completely abolished, providing evidence that NMII activity is critical for the assembly of cortical stress fibers” is ambiguous. It is necessary to clarify the relationship between myosin pulses and mysoin motor activity. It is also important to illustrate the spatiotemporal correlation between NMII pulses and focal adhesion reinforcement (Figure 3D) and F-actin bundling (Figure 4A). NMII pulses are not obvious in in Figures 3D and 4A. We suggest to perform two-color (NMII/vinculin and NMII/actin) kymographs of cross-sections on existing time-lapses.</p><p>4) The authors should clarify the fate of cortical stress fibers (do they transit or mature to “ventral stress fibers”, or just disappear) and determine their average half-life.</p><p>5) The investigations should be complemented with 3D migrating cells. Particularly, since the authors rightly speculate that CSFs may protect the integrity of the nucleus in 3D migrating cells. Hence, they should also exist in 3D.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.60710.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) The formin mDia1 and mDia2 are involved in stress fiber formation (Hotulainen and Lappalainen, 2006; Tojkander et al., 2011), and recently, mDia1 has been involved in the nucleation of actin filaments in the actin cortex (https://doi.org/10.1038/s41556-020-0531-y). The role of formins in the assembly of the cortical stress fibers with either SMIFH2 treatments or by depleting formins using siRNA or Crispr should be tested.</p></disp-quote><p>This is an excellent suggestion, and we have accordingly examined the involvement of formins in cortical stress fiber formation by using both SMIFH2 and siRNA. Experiments on SMIFH2 were performed with low concentration of the compound, because SMIFH2 was recently shown to also inhibit various myosins (Nishimura et al., 2020).</p><p>Nevertheless, the SMIFH2 experiments provided evidence that formins may indeed contribute to the assembly of cortical stress fibers. However, our siRNA experiments on Dia1 and Dia2 did not result in significant reduction in the number of cortical stress fibers, suggesting that these specific formins are either not critical for generation of cortical stress fibers, or that they are functionally redundant with each other or with some other formins expressed in U2OS cells. The new data are shown in Figure 4—figure supplement 1C and D, and discussed in the Results (and in the Materials and methods).</p><p>Concerning the role of formins in cortical stress fiber assembly, is important to note that, unlike dorsal stress fibers (e.g. Lappalainen and Hotulainen, 2006), cortical stress fibers do not elongate through actin polymerization at adhesions (see point #2 below). Therefore, formins most likely contribute to cortical stress fiber assembly indirectly, for example by nucleating actin filaments for the actin cortex.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) It is not clear whether the cortical stress fibers elongate through actin polymerization. FRAP experiment on cortical stress fibers in GFP-actin expressing cells (used by the authors in previous articles) would help clarifying this issue.</p></disp-quote><p>We have now performed photoactivation experiments to examine possible elongation of cortical stress fibers through actin polymerization. These experiments (shown in Figure 2—figure supplement 1A, B, and discussed in the Results, as well as in the Materials and methods) revealed that cortical stress fibers do not elongate through actin polymerization at focal adhesions. This is also consistent with their assembly mechanism, which involves reorganization of the pre-existing cortical actin filament network rather than generation of new actin filaments.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) The sentence “Blebbistatin did not cease the NMII pulsatile behavior in U2OS cells. However, the cortical stress fiber formation was almost completely abolished, providing evidence that NMII activity is critical for the assembly of cortical stress fibers” is ambiguous. It is necessary to clarify the relationship between myosin pulses and mysoin motor activity. It is also important to illustrate the spatiotemporal correlation between NMII pulses and focal adhesion reinforcement (Figure 3D) and F-actin bundling (Figure 4A). NMII pulses are not obvious in in Figures 3D and 4A. We suggest to perform two-color (NMII/vinculin and NMII/actin) kymographs of cross-sections on existing time-lapses.</p></disp-quote><p>We have now prepared kymographs of both “non-productive” and “productive” myosin pulses to illustrate the correlation between myosin pulses and adhesion reinforcement. These new data are shown in Figure 4B and C, and discussed in –the Results. We have also revised the manuscript text –Results to clarify the relationships between NMII pulses and NMII activity (i.e. that as described before by Baird et al., myosin pulses do not depend on the catalytic activity of NMII, but can occur also if the motor domain of myosin is inhibited).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) The authors should clarify the fate of cortical stress fibers (do they transit or mature to “ventral stress fibers”, or just disappear) and determine their average half-life.</p></disp-quote><p>Although we occasionally observed fusion of cortical stress fibers with each other, they do not mature to thick, long “ventral” ventral stress fibers. Instead, majority of cortical stress fibers persist only a relative short period of time. This is illustrated by an analysis of longer (120 min) videos (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="respfig1">Author response image 1</xref>), which demonstrated that the half-life of cortical stress fibers is ~25 min. It is, however, important to note that a large variation exists between the lifetimes of individual cortical stress fibers. We now discuss the fate and half-life of cortical stress fibers in the Results.</p><fig id="respfig1"><label>Author response image 1.</label><caption><title>Analysis of cortical stress fiber half-life in U2OS cells migrating on a fibronectin and expressing LifeAct-TagGFP2 and mApple-Paxillin.</title><p>120 min TIRFM time-lapse videos with 1-minute imaging interval. N = 15 cells; 77 cortical stress fibers. Please note that all stress fibers that were visible already in the beginning of videos and/or were present in the end of videos were excluded from the analysis. We only analysed cortical stress fibers of max 10 µm length arising at the cell center, approximately within the nucleus perimeter. It is also important to note that in many cases cortical stress fibers fused with each other, making it difficult to accurately measure their half-lifes.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60710-resp-fig1-v3.tif"/></fig><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) The investigations should be complemented with 3D migrating cells. Particularly, since the authors rightly speculate that CSFs may protect the integrity of the nucleus in 3D migrating cells. Hence, they should also exist in 3D.</p></disp-quote><p>This an interesting point, and we have now examined the distributions of adhesions, actin filaments, and nuclei in U2OS cells migrating in 3D fibrin network. In addition to thick, long actin filament bundles, which we assume are related to “ventral stress fibers” observed in cells on 2D matrix, these cells also exhibited close to their nuclei relatively short and thin actin filament bundles, which terminated to paxillin-rich adhesions at their both ends. These new data are shown in Figure 3—figure supplement 1B and Video 6, and discussed in the Results, Discussion, as well as in the Materials and methods.</p><p>We also acknowledge that in order to confirm that these actin filament bundles indeed correspond to “cortical stress fibers”, one should carefully examine the assembly mechanisms of these actin filament bundles in a 3D environment. However, high-resolution, high-speed live-cell imaging in 3D is extremely challenging due to technical reasons, and thus we sincerely feel that such experiments are well beyond the scope of present study.</p></body></sub-article></article>