<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">50896</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.50896</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cell Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Developmental Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Endogenous siRNAs promote proteostasis and longevity in germline-less <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-153118"><name><surname>Cohen-Berkman</surname><given-names>Moran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-32384"><name><surname>Dudkevich</surname><given-names>Reut</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-153119"><name><surname>Ben-Hamo</surname><given-names>Shani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-153120"><name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>Alla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-114953"><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>Yehuda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-153122"><name><surname>Waldman Ben-Asher</surname><given-names>Hiba</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-153121"><name><surname>Lamm</surname><given-names>Ayelet T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-32111"><name><surname>Henis-Korenblit</surname><given-names>Sivan</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8023-6336</contrib-id><email>sivan.korenblit@biu.ac.il</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>The Mina &amp; Everard Goodman Faculty of Life Sciences, Bar-Ilan University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Ramat-Gan</named-content></addr-line><country>Israel</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Faculty of Biology, Technion-Israel Institute of Technology, Technion City</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Haifa</named-content></addr-line><country>Israel</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Neurobiology, Weizmann Institute of Science</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Rehovot</named-content></addr-line><country>Israel</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kaeberlein</surname><given-names>Matt</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Washington</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Cambridge</institution><country>United Kingdom</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>26</day><month>03</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e50896</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2019-08-06"><day>06</day><month>08</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2020-03-26"><day>26</day><month>03</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020, Cohen-Berkman et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cohen-Berkman et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-50896-v2.pdf"/><abstract><p>How lifespan and the rate of aging are set is a key problem in biology. Small RNAs are conserved molecules that impact diverse biological processes through the control of gene expression. However, in contrast to miRNAs, the role of endo-siRNAs in aging remains unexplored. Here, by combining deep sequencing and genomic and genetic approaches in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, we reveal an unprecedented role for endo-siRNA molecules in the maintenance of proteostasis and lifespan extension in germline-less animals. Furthermore, we identify an endo-siRNA-regulated tyrosine phosphatase, which limits the longevity of germline-less animals by restricting the activity of the heat shock transcription factor HSF-1. Altogether, our findings point to endo-siRNAs as a link between germline removal and the HSF-1 proteostasis and longevity-promoting somatic pathway. This establishes a role for endo siRNAs in the aging process and identifies downstream genes and physiological processes that are regulated by the endo siRNAs to affect longevity.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>endogenous siRNAs</kwd><kwd>aging</kwd><kwd>proteostasis</kwd><kwd>HSF1</kwd><kwd>germline</kwd><kwd>longevity</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd><italic>C. elegans</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003977</institution-id><institution>Israel Science Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>689/19</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Henis-Korenblit</surname><given-names>Sivan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003977</institution-id><institution>Israel Science Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>927/18</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lamm</surname><given-names>Ayelet T</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100010423</institution-id><institution>Israel Ministry of Science, Technology and Sports</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>3-12066</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Henis-Korenblit</surname><given-names>Sivan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund4"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100005386</institution-id><institution>Israeli Centers for Research Excellence</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>1796/12</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lamm</surname><given-names>Ayelet T</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Endo-siRNAs slow down the rate of aging and enable the maintenance of a responsive heat shock response in aging germline-less <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Aging is a major risk factor for chronic age-related diseases, which have become a major cause of death in the elderly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Matus et al., 2011</xref>). Such pathologies and aging share a common set of basic biological mechanisms, including a failure to maintain the homeostasis of the proteome (proteostasis) with age. Given the high conservation of the aging and proteostasis-promoting pathways between low and high organisms, analysis of these pathways in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> has proven to be valuable for the understanding of aging and proteostasis in all animals, including mammals.</p><p>Dedicated signaling pathways, which coordinate cellular processes that maintain protein homeostasis, have evolved to prevent the grave consequences associated with the accumulation of misfolded proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Taylor et al., 2014</xref>). These pathways are triggered by the accumulation of misfolded proteins in different cell compartments and initiate processes that maintain a functional protein-folding environment by controlling translation rate, increasing expression of chaperones, and enhancing the protein degradation machinery.</p><p>In the cytoplasm, the proteostasis stress response pathway is governed by the transcription factor HSF1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Akerfelt et al., 2010</xref>). In <italic>C. elegans</italic>, HSF-1 overexpression is sufficient for extending lifespan and is important for lifespan extension by most longevity pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hsu et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Baird et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Morley and Morimoto, 2004</xref>). Although the proteostasis stress response pathways assure proteome homeostasis in young animals during development, they lose responsiveness and fail to protect the proteome of aging animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Shemesh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Labbadia and Morimoto, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Taylor and Dillin, 2011</xref>). This may increase the risk for protein conformational diseases, such as Alzheimer’s disease, Huntington’s disease, Parkinson’s disease <italic>etc</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Matus et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">López-Otín et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Consistent with the importance of proteostasis maintenance for proper health and function, mutations and treatments that extend lifespan and healthspan maintain proteostasis in aging animals. Improved proteostasis can be achieved by boosting protein degradation pathways in the soma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Safra et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Henis-Korenblit et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Vilchez et al., 2012</xref>), or by postponing the age-dependent decline in the responsiveness of the stress responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Shemesh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Labbadia and Morimoto, 2015</xref>).</p><p>In <italic>C. elegans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</xref>) and <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Flatt and Schmidt, 2009</xref>), germline depletion extends lifespan. Likewise, lifespan extension can result from ovarian transplantation experiments in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mason et al., 2009</xref>) and castration in men (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Min et al., 2012</xref>). These suggest that reproductive control on lifespan might be conserved in mammals as well. In addition to extending lifespan, germline depletion also promotes proteostasis. The improved proteostasis of germline-less <italic>C. elegans</italic> is achieved by reducing the repressive chromatin marks at HSF1-regulated stress-responsive genes. In turn, the removal of repressive chromatin marks delays the age-dependent collapse of the proteostasis promoting pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Shemesh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Labbadia and Morimoto, 2015</xref>).</p><p>Studies of the last decade identified about a dozen genes that function in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> reproductive-longevity pathway. Many of these genes encode or regulate transcription factors, which are activated in the intestine upon germline removal. Little is known about how depletion of germline stem cells regulates these transcription factors, with the exception of DAF-16 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Antebi, 2013</xref>). The germline-regulated transcription factors remodel the transcriptional landscape in germline-less animals. Germline-regulated genes are enriched in proteostasis, innate immunity, and metabolism-related genes, altering the physiology of the animals and promoting longevity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">McCormick et al., 2012</xref>). Accordingly, germline depletion enhances oxidative stress resistance and immunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Alper et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Libina et al., 2003</xref>), modulates fat metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Wang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Ratnappan et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Steinbaugh et al., 2015</xref>), induces autophagy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lapierre et al., 2013</xref>), and boosts proteostasis-related stress responses in aging animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Shemesh et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Small RNAs and their Argonaute cofactors are conserved components of eukaryotic organisms. Along with transcription factors and transcription regulators, the small RNA silencing pathways impose a layer of gene regulation, which affects diverse biological processes. This is achieved by the generation of short antisense RNAs that act in the cytoplasm, where they interfere with gene expression by inhibiting translation, by degrading cytoplasmic mRNA, or by altering mRNA storage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Grishok, 2013</xref>). Short antisense RNAs also target chromatin modifications in the nucleus, generating epigenetic changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Burton et al., 2011</xref>). In <italic>C. elegans</italic>, small RNAs can move between tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Winston et al., 2002</xref>) and be passed along several generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Rechavi and Lev, 2017</xref>).</p><p>The three main endogenous small RNA pathways in <italic>C. elegans</italic> include miRNAs, endogenous small interfering RNAs (endo-siRNAs), and PIWI (P-element-induced wimpy testis) interacting RNAs (piRNAs). Each of these pathways uses RNAs with different characteristics and involves both distinct and overlapping enzymes and Argonautes. Although small noncoding RNAs impact many biological processes, in the context of aging, studies mainly focused on miRNAs. Multiple studies followed the age-associated changes in expression of miRNAs in <italic>C. elegans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kato et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">de Lencastre et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aalto et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Ibáñez-Ventoso, 2006</xref>). Furthermore, life-extending and life-shortening properties have been attributed to specific miRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Shen et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Boulias and Horvitz, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Boehm and Slack, 2005</xref>) and miRNA-dedicated Argonautes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aalto et al., 2018</xref>). These include several miRNAs that facilitate the localization and transcriptional activity of DAF-16 in the intestine of germline-less animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Shen et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Boulias and Horvitz, 2012</xref>).</p><p>In contrast to miRNAs, much less is known about the physiological roles of naturally-produced endogenous siRNAs that align and complement multiple coding and non-coding loci across the genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Blumenfeld and Jose, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gu et al., 2009</xref>). Thus far, endo-siRNAs in <italic>C. elegans</italic> have been primarily implicated in immune surveillance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Fischer, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Rechavi et al., 2011</xref>) and the transfer of stress resistance between generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Rechavi et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Kishimoto et al., 2017</xref>). Nevertheless, the functional role of endo siRNAs in the regulation of aging remains largely unexplored. This is in spite of the fact that a study of global small RNA profiling over the course of <italic>C. elegans</italic> aging identified an age-dependent increase in the expression of different endo-siRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kato et al., 2011</xref>). Furthermore, another study reported that endo-siRNAs regulate the lifespan of the fly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Lim et al., 2011</xref>). Here, by combining deep sequencing and genomic and genetic approaches in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, we have established a role of endo-siRNAs in lifespan extension and the regulation of the proteostasis-promoting transcription factor HSF-1 in germline-less animals and have also identified direct and indirect aging-related targets of this silencing pathway.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Endo-siRNAs contribute to the longevity of germline-less animals</title><p>To examine if endo-siRNAs are implicated in the longevity of germline-less animals, we made use of the well-characterized <italic>dcr-1(mg375) C. elegans</italic> mutant strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Welker et al., 2010</xref>). Dicer is a member of the RNase III family of nucleases that degrade double-stranded RNA (dsRNA). Dicer processes exogenous dsRNA as well as endogenous dsRNA of which miRNAs and endo-siRNAs are produced. Unlike most <italic>dcr-1</italic> alleles that interfere with the processing of a variety of small RNAs, <italic>dcr-1(mg375)</italic> mutants have a point mutation in the helicase domain of the dicer enzyme. This point mutation disrupts the processing of a subset of endo-siRNAs, without affecting the processing of other small RNA molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Welker et al., 2010</xref>). To limit germline proliferation, we made use of <italic>glp-1(e2144)</italic> mutants, which carry a temperature-sensitive notch receptor required for germline stem cells (GSC) proliferation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Priess et al., 1987</xref>). For simplicity, we will refer henceforth to germline-less <italic>glp-1</italic> animals raised at the restrictive temperature as GSC(-) animals.</p><p>First, we generated <italic>dcr-1(mg375) glp-1</italic> double mutants and followed their lifespan when raised from eggs to adulthood at restrictive temperature. As expected, <italic>glp-1</italic> GSC(-) animals exhibited extended lifespan compared to wild-type animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). However, we found that the <italic>dcr-1(mg375)</italic> mutation shortened the lifespan of GSC(-) animals to a greater extent than in animals with an intact germline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Similarly, limiting germline expansion by dietary supplementation of dihomo-γ-linolenic acid (DGLA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Watts and Browse, 2006</xref>) extended the lifespan of wild-type animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Shemesh et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">O'Rourke et al., 2013</xref>), but failed to extend the lifespan of <italic>dcr-1(mg375)</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Together, these findings imply that endo-siRNAs that depend on the helicase activity of dicer may be implicated in longevity induced by germline removal.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Endo-siRNAs are required for the longevity of GSC(-) animals.</title><p>(<bold>A,C–E</bold>) Impairment of the endo-siRNA pathway by <italic>dcr-1(mg375), rrf-3(pk1426), ergo-1(gg98)</italic>, or <italic>nrde-3(gg66)</italic> compromises the longevity of <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants. (<bold>B</bold>) The longevity conferred by germline depletion via DGLA supplementation is perturbed by the <italic>mg375</italic> mutation in the <italic>dcr-1</italic> helicase domain. (<bold>F</bold>) Impairment of the dsRNA channel <italic>sid-1(pk3321)</italic> does not compromise the longevity of <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants. Breslow (Generalized Wilcoxon) P-values between endo-siRNA mutants and corresponding animals with intact endo-siRNA are indicated between GSC(+) animals (in orange) or between GSC(-) animals (in red). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>. Note that the <italic>dcr-1</italic> and <italic>nrde-3</italic> mutants have not been outcrossed. This may affect their lifespan phenotypes.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-50896-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><p>We then examined if mutations in additional components, which are specifically required for the processing of endo-siRNA but not directly implicated in the processing of other small RNAs, affected the lifespan of GSC(-) animals. To this end, we generated <italic>glp-1</italic> double mutants with mutations in the <italic>rrf-3, ergo-1,</italic> and <italic>nrde-3</italic> genes. <italic>rrf-3</italic> encodes an RNA-directed RNA polymerase (RdRP), which uses single-stranded RNA as template for second-strand synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Gent et al., 2010</xref>). <italic>ergo-1</italic> encodes an endo-siRNA-specific Argonaute, which stabilizes the initial class of 26G endo-siRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Vasale et al., 2010</xref>). NRDE-3 is an Argonaute that functions in nuclear RNA interference (RNAi) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Guang et al., 2008</xref>). In all cases, the lifespan extension conferred by germline removal was significantly curtailed by mutations that perturbed different steps in the processing of endo-siRNAs, with less of an effect on the lifespan of animals with an intact reproductive system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C–E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). The finding of similar shortening of the lifespan of GSC(-) animals by multiple mutations that affect endo-siRNA processing strongly implicates endo-siRNAs in the lifespan extension of GSC(-) animals. Furthermore, this reduces the likelihood that the observed differences in lifespan are due to background mutations in non-outcrossed strains <italic>dcr-1(mg375)</italic> and <italic>nrde-3(gg66)</italic>. Thus, we conclude that the processing of a subset of siRNAs, whose processing is <italic>dcr-1</italic> helicase<italic>, rrf-3, ergo-1</italic>, and <italic>nrde-3</italic>-dependent, contributes to the lifespan extension of GSC(-) animals.</p><p>In <italic>C. elegans</italic>, small RNA molecules spread between cells via SID-1 dsRNA channels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Shih and Hunter, 2011</xref>). To explore if endo-siRNAs act in a hormonal-like fashion to promote longevity, we examined whether the longevity of GSC(-) animals is dependent upon SID-1 channels. We found that GSC(-) <italic>glp-1; sid-1</italic> double mutants were long-lived similarly to GSC(-) <italic>glp-1</italic> single mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Thus, there was no need for SID-1-dependent uptake of the endo-siRNA molecules by neighboring cells for the longevity of <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants. This could be either because the silencing takes place in the same cells that produce the lifespan-regulatory small RNA molecules, or because an alternative RNA channel mediates the spread of the endo-siRNAs between tissues.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Endo-siRNAs promote chaperone expression in GSC(-) animals</title><p>Germ cell depletion results in significant remodeling of the animal’s transcriptome, promoting the expression of genes that drive proteostasis, autophagy, innate immunity, lipid metabolism and more (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Antebi, 2013</xref>). In order to identify which downstream physiological processes are hindered by the depletion of endo-siRNA in GSC(-) animals, we compared the mRNA transcriptomes of GSC(-) animals and wild-type animals upon interference with the processing of endo-siRNA. Even though mutations in several endo-siRNA related genes affected the lifespan of GSC(-) animals, we performed this analysis using the <italic>dcr-1(mg375)</italic> point mutation, due to its relative focused effect on only a subset of endo-siRNAs molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Welker et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>We first focused on a group of 72 genes whose mRNA levels consistently decreased by more than 1.5 fold (p-value&lt;0.05) in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> single mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref>). Since siRNAs downregulate gene expression (i.e., lack of siRNA results in upregulation of their target genes), these genes cannot be direct targets of the siRNA pathway. However, their altered expression upon siRNA inactivation may point out downstream processes affected by the siRNA activity. A protein-protein interaction network of these 72 genes using STRING (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Szklarczyk et al., 2019</xref>) highlighted a group of 10 interacting genes, composed mostly of chaperone-encoding genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>). GO enrichment analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Ashburner et al., 2000</xref>) of the 72 genes identified enrichment in genes related to cellular response to unfolded proteins as relatively down-regulated in the <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants (p-value&lt;1*10<sup>−4</sup>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp3">Supplementary file 3</xref>). Interestingly, out of the group of 72 genes, 15 genes are known to be upregulated in an <italic>hsf-1</italic>-dependent manner upon heat shock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Brunquell et al., 2016</xref>). This is a significant enrichment in the amount of HSF-1-regulated genes, more than expected by chance (chi-square with yates correction p-value&lt;1*10<sup>−4</sup>). We confirmed the downregulation of three of these genes in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants by qRT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). We hypothesize that the growth conditions of the animals at 25 degrees from eggs to adulthood, after prior cultivation in 20 degrees, resulted in a mild heat shock response, allowing the detection of heat-induced genes. Together, these results suggest that in the absence of some endo-siRNAs, expression of a set of cytosolic chaperones and additional HSF-1-regulated genes is compromised in GSC(-) animals.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Endo-siRNAs are required for HSF-1 activation in GSC(-) animals.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) qRT-PCR of the indicated genes on day 1 of adulthood. Asterisks mark Student’s t-test values of p value&lt;0.05 (N = 4). Note that the <italic>dcr-1</italic> mutation reduced the transcript levels of all three chaperone genes in GSC(-) animals, consistent with the possibility that the activity of their upstream transcription factor HSF-1 has been compromised. Interestingly, the <italic>dcr-1</italic> mutation also affected the levels of the <italic>f44e5.5</italic> transcript in GSC(+) animals. Nevertheless, it did not significantly affect the transcript levels of the <italic>hsp-16.2</italic> and <italic>hsp-12.6</italic> chaperones in GSC(+) animals. Given that HSF-1 and some of its targets are expressed also in the germline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Ooi and Prahlad, 2017</xref>), to avoid biases due to the presence/absence of the germline tissue, comparisons should be made within GSC(-) animals or within GSC(+) animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">McCormick et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Steinbaugh et al., 2015</xref>). See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp3">Supplementary file 3</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative western blot of endogenous HSF-1 in day one animals (upper panel) compared to loading control (lower panel). Boxplots represent the distribution of normalized HSF-1 levels per strain. Different shapes represent independent experiments (N = 7). P-values of One-Sample Test and One-Way ANOVA followed by Tukey's post hoc analysis across all seven experiments are indicated. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp8">Supplementary file 8</xref> for statistic details. (<bold>C</bold>) Bars represent mean of means of the number of HSF-1::GFP nuclear foci per hypodermal cell. Dots represent mean number of HSF-1 foci per cell with different shapes representing independent experiments. At least 140 cells per genotype were scored in a total of 3 independent experiments. P-values determined by One-Way ANOVA followed by Tukey's post hoc analysis are indicated. Data are presented as mean ± SEM. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp8">Supplementary file 8</xref> for statistic details. (<bold>D</bold>) Representative fluorescent micrographs of hypodermal cell nuclei in day three adults, harboring a single copy of the <italic>Phsf-1::hsf-1::gfp</italic> transgene upon heat shock stress. Exposures and contrast were adjusted for each picture independently to best emphasize foci amount. Nucleus boundaries are circled.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-50896-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>String analysis of 72 genes whose levels decreased by more than 1.5 fold in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> mutant.</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-50896-fig2-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Endo-siRNAs are required for activation of the heat shock response in GSC(-) animals</title><p>Our data indicate that endo-siRNAs are important for the expression of a set of HSF-1 target genes in adult GSC(-) animals. Hence, we first checked if there was a decrease in HSF-1 protein levels in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> animals compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> animals. Analysis of the levels of endogenous HSF-1 protein in these mutants demonstrated that HSF-1 levels were higher in GSC(-) animals compared to wild-type animals (p=0.004, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Furthermore, HSF-1 levels were not reduced upon dicer inactivation in GSC(-) animals (in fact HSF-1 levels were higher in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> single mutants in 5/7 experiments, p=0.054, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). These results demonstrate that endo-siRNAs are not required for HSF-1 expression in GSC(-) animals.</p><p>We next checked whether the endo-siRNA pathway affected HSF-1 activation. One hallmark of HSF-1 activation upon heat-shock is its rapid redistribution into sub-nuclear structures, which share many properties with human nuclear stress granules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Morton and Lamitina, 2013</xref>). The formation of these foci is dependent upon the DNA binding domain of HSF-1 and they co-localize with markers of active transcription. We used the same single copy HSF-1::GFP translational fusion strain to follow its organization into foci in different genetic backgrounds. As reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Morton and Lamitina, 2013</xref>), under non-stress conditions, HSF-1::GFP was found primarily in the nucleus but not in foci. Following a 10 min heat shock, day three wild-type animals had on average two foci per hypodermal cell. In long-lived <italic>glp-1</italic> animals, we observed increased levels of these foci under heat shock conditions (on average 3.6 foci per hypodermal cell). In contrast, GSC(-) animals impaired in their endo-siRNA pathway had only 1.4 foci on average per hypodermal cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C–D</xref>). These results demonstrate that <italic>dcr-1</italic>-dependent endo-siRNA molecules are required for HSF-1 foci formation upon heat shock in GSC(-) animals.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Endo-siRNAs are required for proteostasis maintenance in GSC(-) animals</title><p>A low amount of chaperones and reduced ability of HSF-1 to form foci may render <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> animals sensitive to proteostasis challenges. To test this, we exposed late day two animals to a prolonged heat shock and followed their survival after a recovery period. As reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Shemesh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Libina et al., 2003</xref>), <italic>glp-1</italic> animals were more resistant to heat shock than were wild-type animals. While 71% of the <italic>glp-1</italic> animals survived the heat shock, only 38% of the wild-type animals survived the same stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A,P</xref>-value&lt;0.001). Strikingly, the <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> mutants were sensitive to the heat shock, similar to the wild-type animals, with only 39% survival (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A,P</xref>-value=0.99). Similar sensitivity to heat shock was observed upon perturbation of the endo-siRNA pathway in <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants by a mutation in the <italic>rrf-3</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). The finding of similar sensitivity of GSC(-) animals to heat stress by two independent mutations that affect endo-siRNA processing strongly implicates endo-siRNAs in the heat shock resistance of GSC(-) animals. Furthermore, this reduces the likelihood that the observed differences in heat sensitivity are due to background mutations in the non-outcrossed <italic>dcr-1(mg375) </italic> strain.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Endo-siRNAs are required for proteostasis maintenance in GSC(-) animals.</title><p>(<bold>A–B</bold>) Thermo-resistance was examined in age-synchronized animals subjected to heat shock (37°C, 9 hr) on day 2 of adulthood. Survival was assayed after 5 hr of recovery at 25°C (120 animals per treatment, <italic>N</italic> = 3). Asterisks mark Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel Test values of p&lt;0.001. (<bold>C</bold>) Bars represent mean of the percentage of motile animals scored in age-synchronized day 5 <italic>Q35m</italic> or <italic>glp-1;Q35m</italic> animals (more than 45 animals per treatment, N = 3). Different shapes represent mean motility in independent experiments. Asterisks mark p-values&lt;0.001 determined by One-Way ANOVA followed by Tukey's post hoc analysis. (<bold>D</bold>) Bars represent mean of means of the number of body bends per minute in age-synchronized day four <italic>unc-52(ts)</italic> animals. Animals were raised at 25°C till day 1 of adulthood, and shifted to the permissive temperature (15°C) thereafter. A total of 180 animals per strain were scored in three independent experiments. Different shapes represent mean motility in independent experiments. Asterisks mark Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test values of p&lt;0.001. Data are presented as mean ± SEM. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp8">Supplementary file 8</xref> for statistic details.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-50896-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig><p>Expression of toxic aggregating proteins such as Poly-Q rich proteins perturbs proteostasis. Specifically, the expression of these toxic proteins in the muscle cells causes the animals to undergo age-dependent loss of motility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Morley et al., 2002</xref>). Hence, we examined the motility of wild-type and GSC(-) animals, expressing toxic poly Q35 fused to YFP in their muscles in the presence or absence of an intact endo-siRNA pathway. The motility of the animals was determined by the number of swimming strokes they performed when placed in liquid on day 5 of adulthood. As reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Shemesh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Labbadia and Morimoto, 2015</xref>), wild-type Q35 animals showed reduced motility compared to their GSC(-) Q35 counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). Perturbation of the endo-siRNA pathway by a point mutation in the <italic>dcr-1</italic> gene reduced the motility of <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants to the level of wild-type animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). Altogether, these experiments suggest that endo-siRNA molecules contribute to the superior proteostasis state of GSC(-) animals.</p><p>Finally, we also asked whether endo-siRNAs contributed to proper protein folding. For this purpose, we used the <italic>unc-52(e669su250)</italic> allele, harboring a temperature-sensitive point mutation in the <italic>unc-52</italic> gene. This strain is an established folding reporter reflecting an age-dependent decline in motility under permissive temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Ben-Zvi et al., 2009</xref>). We monitored <italic>unc-52(ts)</italic>-dependent paralysis on day 4 of adulthood in different genetic backgrounds. At this time-point, only 20% of the <italic>unc-52(ts)</italic> animals were motile, whereas the <italic>glp-1</italic> mutation rescued <italic>unc-52(ts)</italic>-dependent paralysis in 80% of the animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D,P</xref>-value&lt;0.001). Perturbation of the endo-siRNA pathway by a mutation in the <italic>dcr-1</italic> gene partially reduced the motility of <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D,P</xref>-value&lt;0.001). This suggests that endo-siRNAs are required for some aspects of correct protein folding in adult GSC(-) animals.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Identification of endo siRNA-regulated genes in GSC(-) animals</title><p>We next set out to identify potential direct and indirect targets affected by endo-siRNA in GSC(-) animals. To this end, we compared both the mRNA transcriptomes and the siRNAs of GSC(-) animals in the presence or absence of the <italic>dcr-1(mg375)</italic> point mutation.</p><p>We predicted that direct mRNA targets of the endo-siRNA would be present at low levels in GSC(-) animals but stabilized when dicer activity is disrupted. We identified a group of 132 genes whose levels consistently and significantly increased by more than 1.5 fold (p-value&lt;0.05) in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to that of <italic>glp-1</italic> animals with wild-type dicer activity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp4">Supplementary file 4</xref>). 84 of these genes were previously reported as regulated by endo-siRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Asikainen et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp4">Supplementary file 4</xref>), attesting to the validity of our data. A protein-protein interaction network of these 132 genes using STRING (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Szklarczyk et al., 2019</xref>) highlighted a group of 64 interacting genes whose interaction was based primarily on co-expression rather than on physical, genetic, or physiological interactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). Strikingly, 49 out of these 64 genes overlapped with the list of 84 <italic>rrf-1</italic>-regulated genes.</p><p>This group of 132 genes, whose transcripts are down-regulated (directly or indirectly) by endogenous siRNAs in <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants, are likely to include putative direct targets of the siRNA pathway in these animals. These direct targets are predicted to have increased levels of siRNA directed towards them in <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants compared to that of the dicer-defective double mutant. To identify these putative direct endo-siRNA targets, we generated small RNA libraries using a method that mainly captures secondary endo-siRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Fishman et al., 2018</xref>) from <italic>glp-1</italic> and <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> GSC(-) mutant animals, synchronized to day 1 of adulthood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). As expected, <italic>glp-1</italic> and <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> mutants lacked 21u-RNAs, which are specifically expressed in the germ cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Wang and Reinke, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp5">Supplementary file 5</xref>). We identified 138 genes whose endo-siRNA levels were ten-fold higher in <italic>glp-1</italic> compared to <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp5">Supplementary file 5</xref>). This defines a group of endo-siRNAs whose production in GSC(-) animals relied on the integrity of the helicase domain of dicer. Among the list of genes targeted by these endo-siRNAs, the mRNA levels of five genes (ZK380.5, W04B5.1, ZK402.2, ZK402.3, F55C9.3) were decreased in a <italic>dcr-1</italic>-dependent manner in <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants. Thus, we considered these five genes as potential direct endo-siRNA targets in GSC(-) animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp5">Supplementary file 5</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Inactivation of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> restores longevity in GSC(-) animals with perturbed endogenous siRNA.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Scatter plot depicts comparisons of gene-by-gene siRNA counts from three paired <italic>glp-1</italic> mutant and <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutant samples. Gray- all genes. Orange- 132 genes whose levels increased by more than 1.5 folds in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> single mutants at the transcriptome analysis. Purple- five overlapping genes between the transcriptome analysis and siRNA seq, which are candidate direct targets of endo-siRNA. Blue- <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> (<italic>c24d10.1</italic>). See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp4">Supplementary files 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp6">6,</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp7">7</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) qRT-PCR of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcript on day 1 of adulthood. Asterisks mark Student’s t-test values of p value&lt;0.05 of 4 independent experiments. Data are presented as mean ± SEM. The low levels of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcript in GSC(-) animals is consistent with the interpretation that in GSC(+) animals, most of the transcript is expressed in the germline. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative fluorescent images of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> transgenic animals expressing an extrachromosomal array of a translational reporter fused to the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> gene, driven by <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> upstream sequences. Note that the reporter is only detected in a fraction of the animals. Animals that expressed the reporter displayed a clear fluorescent signal specifically in two adjacent cells in the mid-intestine (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2B</xref>). A similar expression pattern of the transgene was observed in all genetic backgrounds (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>). Bars represent mean of the percentage of animals expressing the <italic>ptp-5.1::gfp</italic> transgene in the intestine. At least 250 animals per strain were scored in four independent experiments. Different colors represent independent experiments. Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test P-values are indicated. Asterisks mark p&lt;0.001. Somatic expression of the transgene was detected in all backgrounds in a fraction of the animals. Inactivation of the endo-siRNA pathway by the <italic>dcr-1</italic> mutation increased the fraction of the animals expressing the reporter in their mid-intestine. (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>ptp-5.1(tm6122)</italic> extended the lifespan of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants. Breslow (Generalized Wilcoxon) P-values for each mutant vs. the mutant; <italic>ptp-5.1(tm6122)</italic> double mutant are indicated. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref> for additional lifespan data.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-50896-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>String analysis of 132 genes whose levels increased by more than 1.5 fold in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> mutant.</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-50896-fig4-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>The <italic>ptp-5.1::gfp</italic> transgene is expressed in the intestine of a fraction of the animals.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Only a fraction of the transgenic animals of the indicated genotypes express the transgene. However, all animals that express the transgene express it to a similar extent and almost always in two adjacent intestinal cells in the mid-body of the animal. The reporter is expressed both in the cytoplasm and in the nucleus. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative X200 images of Day one <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> transgenic animal stained with the nuclear dye DAPI while maintaining the fluorescence of the GFP. DAPI staining and GFP fluorescence were individually captured and overlaid in the merged image, to demonstrate the localization of the GFP-expressing cells relative to the intestinal nuclei. Anterior part of the animals is to te left. Arrows indicate DAPI-stained intestinal nuclei.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-50896-fig4-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Identification of endo-siRNA regulated genes that affect lifespan</title><p>Next, we set out to identify <italic>dcr-1</italic>-regulated genes whose silencing is required for the longevity of GSC(-) animals. Silencing of these genes in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants, by means other than endo-siRNA, should restore the extended lifespan and improve proteostasis to the typical levels as in GSC(-) animals. As the <italic>dcr-1(mg375)</italic> mutation does not compromise the exogenous RNAi pathway, we examined the effect of RNAi silencing of a select group of these genes on the lifespan of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants. Specifically, we focused on the five genes that may be directly targeted by endo-siRNA (identified by the overlap between their expression levels and the levels of their corresponding endo-siRNAs) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp5">Supplementary file 5</xref>). In addition, we examined the requirement of 18 cellular protein modification-related genes, identified as significantly enriched within the group of 132 endo-siRNA repressed genes by DAVID enrichment analysis (p-value&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp6">Supplementary file 6</xref>).</p><p>We treated <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants with RNAi against each of these genes, and qualitatively examined the number of live animals in the plates on days 8–11. At these time-points, the survival of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants was significantly reduced compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants. We found seven RNAi clones that improved the survival of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> mutants in the screen (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp7">Supplementary file 7</xref>). These included ZK402.2, ZK402.3 and W04B5.1, which might be direct endo-siRNA targets, and five modification-related genes (F26E4.5, F26A1.3, C24D10.1, C03C10.2, M05B5.1), which were probably indirectly regulated by endo-siRNAs. ZK402.2, and ZK402.3 are homologous 12.4 and 5.4 kDa proteins of unknown function. W04B5.1 is a pseudogene, whose expression is up-regulated in <italic>rrf-3</italic> and <italic>eri-1</italic> mutants, in which endo-siRNA production is disrupted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Gent et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Pavelec et al., 2009</xref>). The group of modification-related genes included a protein tyrosine phosphatase gene (<italic>c24d10.1),</italic> whose expression is up-regulated in <italic>rrf-3(pk1426)</italic> and <italic>eri-1(mg366)</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Asikainen et al., 2007</xref>). Given this established connection between the tyrosine phosphatase <italic>c24d10.1</italic> and the endo-siRNAs pathway, we further examined the role of its silencing in the longevity of <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants. For simplicity, we named <italic>c24d10.1</italic> as <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> (protein tyrosine phosphatase 5.1), based on its putative protein tyrosine phosphatase activity.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title><italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcript levels are indirectly regulated by endo-siRNAs in GSC(-) animals</title><p>First, we used qRT-PCR to follow the transcript levels of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> in the different genetic backgrounds. As previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Asikainen et al., 2007</xref>), we found that <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcript levels increase upon interference with endo-siRNA processing in wild-type animals. In addition, <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcripts were almost absent in GSC(-) animals compared to wild-type controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). This is consistent with previous work indicating that <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> may be a sperm-specific gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Ortiz et al., 2014</xref>). Interestingly, we did detect a low level of the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcript in germline-less <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref> inset), implying that the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcript is expressed to an extent in the soma of these animals (and perhaps also in the wild-type animals), and that the low levels of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcript in the soma are regulated in an endo-siRNA dependent manner, at least in GSC(-) mutants.</p><p>To further analyze the somatic expression of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic>, we generated transgenic animals expressing an extra-chromosomal translational reporter of the PTP-5.1 protein fused to GFP, driven by the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> promoter. Interestingly, whereas no detectable expression of the transgene was observed in the majority of the wild-type transgenic animals, we did detect clear expression of the transgene in 15% of the animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>). In most of these animals, the reporter was expressed in two adjacent cells in the middle of the intestine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>). In very few cases, we detected expression of the transgene in the animals’ nerve system, in lieu of the intestine. Interference with endo-siRNA processing, by the <italic>mg375</italic> mutation in the <italic>dcr-1</italic> helicase domain, increased the fraction of animals with the intestinal expression of the reporter. Interestingly, removal of the germline did not further alter the somatic expression of the reporter (i.e. 15% of the germline-less animals expressed the transgene in two of their intestinal cells, and twice as many germline-less animals expressed the transgene upon interference with the endo-siRNA pathway, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). Altogether, these findings support the notion that <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> expression in the soma is suppressed in an endo siRNA-dependent manner in wild-type animals and in GSC(-) animals. We assume that this expression corresponds to the product of a very small fraction of the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcripts, the majority of which are expressed in the germline rather than in the soma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). Nevertheless, since we did not detect a change in the amount of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> endo-siRNAs between the <italic>glp-1</italic> and the <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> samples (fold change = 1, P-adj = 0.278, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>), we conclude that the regulation of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcript levels by endo-siRNAs in <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants is indirect.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Inactivation of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> restores longevity and improves proteostasis in GSC(-) animals with perturbed endo-siRNA</title><p>Our limited RNAi screen, described above, suggested that more <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants were alive upon treatment with <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> RNAi. Hence, we examined how a deletion mutation in the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> gene affected the lifespan of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> mutants, in a detailed lifespan experiment. We found that a mutation in <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> extended the lifespan of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants to the level of that of long-lived GSC(-) <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). In contrast, the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> mutation did not significantly change the lifespan of wild-type animals, <italic>dcr-1</italic> single mutants or <italic>glp-1</italic> single mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Thus, <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> seems to specifically limit the lifespan of GSC(-) animals when the endo-siRNA pathway is compromised.</p><p>Since we found that endo-siRNAs were required for HSF-1’s activity in GSC(-) animals, we also examined the effect of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> inactivation on the compromised heat shock response of GSC(-) <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants. We found that mutation in <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> fully restored the heat shock resistance of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants to the same survival level as that of <italic>glp-1</italic> single mutants. In contrast, introduction of a mutation in <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> into wild-type or <italic>dcr-1</italic> animals did not alter their survival after heat shock (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Inactivation of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> improves proteostasis in GSC(-) animals with perturbed endogenous siRNA.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Thermo-resistance of age-synchronized animals subjected to heat shock (37°C, 9 hr) on day 2 of adulthood upon 5 hr of recovery at 25°C (120 animals per treatment, <italic>N</italic> = 3). Asterisks mark Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test values of p&lt;0.001. (<bold>B</bold>) Bars represent mean of mean number of HSF-1::GFP nuclear foci per hypodermal cell. At least 140 cells per genotype were scored in a total of 3 independent experiments. Dots represent mean number of HSF-1 foci per cell with different shapes representing independent experiments. Asterisk marks p-value&lt;0.05 determined by One-Way ANOVA followed by Tukey's post hoc analysis. Data are presented as mean ± SEM. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp8">Supplementary file 8</xref> for statistic details. (<bold>C</bold>) Fluorescence micrographs of representative hypodermal cells in day three adults, harboring a single copy of the <italic>Phsf-1::hsf-1::gfp</italic> transgene upon exposure to heat shock. Nuclear boundaries are circled. Exposures and contrast were adjusted for each picture independently to best emphasize foci amount.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-50896-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig><p>In addition to their sensitivity to heat shock, <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants were less capable of forming HSF-1 foci within the nuclei in response to heat shock compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). Hence, we examined the ability of HSF-1 to form intra-nuclear foci upon heat shock in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> animals in the presence of the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> mutation. We observed a significant increase in the average number of HSF-1-labeled foci per hypodermal cell in heat-shocked <italic>dcr-1 glp-1; ptp-5.1</italic> triple mutants compared to <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants. This increase in the number of foci upon <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> inactivation was unique to <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> mutants, as its inactivation did not increase the number of foci in wild-type, <italic>dcr-1</italic> mutants or <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B–C</xref>). Altogether, these experiments suggest that <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> downregulation is sufficient for restoration of the longevity and the improved heat shock response, which were compromised by the endo-siRNA-deficiency in GSC(-) animals.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Although the idea that the rate of aging can be slowed down and the existence of longevity-promoting genes and pathways are well established, we are still deciphering the underlying mechanism whereby longevity pathways extend lifespan. At the molecular level, most life-span extension pathways involve extensive remodeling of the transcriptome. Accordingly, genes involved in chromatin modifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Maures et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Greer et al., 2011</xref>), RNA modifying pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Heintz et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Tabrez et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Son et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Masse et al., 2008</xref>), a long list of transcription factors, as well as several miRNAs are all required for the longevity of animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Denzel et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Besides microRNAs, <italic>C. elegans</italic> produces additional small RNAs as well as long noncoding RNAs, targeting coding genes, pseudogenes, and transposons. These, too, could potentially alter gene expression landscape and affect basic biological processes such as lifespan. Although advances in sequencing technologies have led to the identification of thousands of endo-siRNAs, their biological impact is not fully understood. In this study, we demonstrate that endo-siRNAs are implicated in longevity regulation in animals reprogrammed to slow down aging due to the depletion of their germline.</p><p>The processing of endo-siRNAs and the silencing of their target genes are complex. Endo-siRNA processing in <italic>C. elegans</italic> requires multiple proteins, including dicer, several RdRPs, and different Argonaute proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Yigit et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Duchaine et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Fischer et al., 2011</xref>). We found that impairment of primary siRNA production (via <italic>dcr-1</italic> and <italic>rrf-3</italic> mutations), impairment of secondary siRNA production and target silencing in the cytoplasm (via <italic>ergo-1</italic> mutation), and impairment of target silencing in the nucleus (via <italic>nrde-3</italic> mutation), all compromise longevity associated with germline depletion. Interestingly, impairment of the endo-siRNA machinery did not consistently affect the lifespan of wild-type animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A–E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). This suggests that the silencing by endo-siRNAs affects target genes that specifically limit longevity, at least in GSC(-) animals, rather than normal lifespan. Furthermore, given the lack of germline in these animals, this establishes an important somatic role for endo siRNAs, which have been mostly associated with germline inheritance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Rechavi and Lev, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Rechavi et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Kishimoto et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Ni et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>Depending on the mutated endo siRNA-related gene, different extents of lifespan shortening were observed in <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants. The strongest effect on lifespan was observed with the <italic>nrde-3</italic> mutant. This suggests that the silencing event that controls the longevity of GSC(-) animals is mediated via nuclear silencing. We attribute the weaker effects of the other endo-siRNA related mutations to partial inactivation of the endo-siRNA processing, due to possible redundancies (for example in the case of mutation in the <italic>rrf-3</italic> RdRP, which is one of four RdRPs in <italic>C. elegans</italic>), or due to mis-regulation of only a subset of endo siRNAs (as in the case of the point mutation in the helicase domain of dicer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Welker et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>To identify longevity-related endo siRNA regulated genes and pathways in GSC(-) animals, we undertook a functional genomic approach, monitoring both the abundance of all endo siRNAs as well as the transcriptomic changes in the same animals. This genomic approach was then complemented by functional studies leading to the identification of direct and indirect endo siRNA-regulated genes, whose endo siRNA-dependent silencing is critical for the longevity of GSC(-) animals.</p><p>Among the identified genes were putative direct endo siRNA targets genes as well as the indirect target <italic>ptp-5.1.</italic> In addition, the transcriptome analysis pointed out a set of HSF-1 regulated genes, primarily but not exclusively chaperone genes, whose levels were reduced in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> mutants, suggesting that the endo siRNA protects the cytosolic heat shock response in <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). The impairment in HSF-1 activity in endo siRNA defective <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants could in turn account for the compromised longevity and proteostasis in these animals, as both the longevity and the superior proteostasis of <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants are dependent on HSF-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Shemesh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hansen et al., 2005</xref>). These findings suggest that endo siRNAs are required to remove an activity restraint on the proteostasis-related transcription factor HSF-1 in <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants. Interestingly, the requirement to counteract restraining pathways to promote HSF-1 activity is also observed in animals with reduced insulin/IGF-1 signaling, in which HSF-1 must dissociate from inhibitory factors, such as DDL-1, to gain activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Chiang et al., 2012</xref>). These mechanisms are consistent with the multi-step nature of HSF-1 activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Sarge et al., 1993</xref>).</p><p>Of the different endo-siRNA regulated genes identified in this study, we focused on tyrosine phosphatase <italic>ptp-5.1</italic>. We found that endo siRNA indirect repression of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> in the soma is critical for HSF-1 activation in GSC(-) animals. This places <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> as an upstream inhibitor of HSF-1 in GSC(-) animals. Interestingly, expression data analysis indicates that <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> is primarily expressed in the sperm and is normally absent from the soma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Ortiz et al., 2014</xref>). Our data confirm that the majority of the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcripts reflect germline expression rather than somatic expression. Nevertheless, we did detect PTP-5.1 expression in the soma in a subset of the transgenic animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). Hence, the removal of this low amount of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> in the soma is critical for the proteostasis maintenance and the longevity of GSC(-) animals.</p><p>Inactivation of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> completely restored both longevity and the superior proteostasis of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> mutants to the level of <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants, implying that it is a proteostasis and longevity-limiting factor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). Nevertheless, <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> mutants, which do not express <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> in the soma, are not long-lived or heat shock resistant as are GSC(-) animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). This suggests that in addition to the removal of the proteostasis/lifespan limiting gene <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> from the soma, additional proteostasis/lifespan promoting events must take place to obtain these benefits. For example, in GSC(-) animals, <italic>jmjd-3.1</italic> relaxes the chromatin and allows more efficient binding of HSF-1 to the DNA in mature GSC(-) animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Labbadia and Morimoto, 2015</xref>). Thus, a combination of HSF-1 activating pathways along with the removal of HSF-1 inhibitory pathways is concomitantly required to activate HSF-1 to promote proteostasis and longevity (see model in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Endo-siRNAs improve proteostasis and promote longevity of GSC(-) animals by enabling HSF-1 activation.</title><p>Model: Germline-less animals extensively remodel their transcriptome to promote longevity and proteostasis. HSF-1 is one of the central transcription factors that transcribe proteostasis and longevity-promoting genes. We find that endo-siRNAs are critical for HSF-1 activity in GSC(-) animals, and consequently for their longevity and improved proteostasis. These endo-siRNAs are important because they indirectly limit the level of the tyrosine phosphatase <italic>ptp-5.1.</italic> The inhibition of this tyrosine phosphatase is critical for HSF-1 activation in proteostasis challenging settings such as heat-shock and aging. Whereas the release of HSF-1 from <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> inhibition is required for the proteostasis and longevity benefits in GSC(-) animals, it is not sufficient. To achieve effective remodeling of the proteostasis and longevity promoting networks, germline removal must coordinate between the removal of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic>-dependent inhibition of HSF-1 and additional cellular events that promote HSF-1 activity such as reducing the repressive chromatin marks at HSF1-regulated stress-responsive genes.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-50896-fig6-v2.tif"/></fig><p>In summary, this study provides insight into the molecular mechanisms that enable enhanced proteostasis and longevity in GSC(-) animals. Specifically, this study identified a set of endo siRNA-regulated longevity-limiting genes, whose expression must be repressed in the context of the longevity treatment to enable the activation of the heat shock transcription factor HSF-1. This establishes a role for endo siRNAs in the regulation of proteostasis and aging in long-lived germline-less animals. We propose that such longevity-limiting genes and pathways may provide new targets for interventions that, along with pro-longevity treatments, may more effectively attenuate or reverse systemic dysfunction associated with age, and therefore have the potential to reduce overall disease risk for chronic and proteostasis-related diseases in the elderly.</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>Materials and correspondence</title><p>Correspondence and material requests should be addressed to Sivan Henis-Korenblit.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Reagent type <break/>(species) or resource</th><th>Designation</th><th>Source or reference</th><th>Identifiers</th><th>Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>N2</td><td valign="bottom">Caenorhabditis Genetics Center</td><td valign="bottom">Wild Type</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>CF1903</td><td valign="bottom">Caenorhabditis Genetics Center</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>glp-1(e2144)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">outcrossed three times in C Kenyon's lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>YY470</td><td valign="bottom">Caenorhabditis Genetics Center</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>dcr-1(mg375)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">an outcrossed version of YY11 <italic>dcr-1(m9375)</italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK77</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>dcr-1(mg375) glp-1(e2144)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>CF3152</td><td valign="bottom">Cynthia Kenyon lab</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>rrf-3(pk1426)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">outcrossed three times in C Kenyon's lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK55</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>rrf-3(pk1426);glp-1(e2144)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK80</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>ergo-1(gg98)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain outcrossed two times in S Henis-Korenblit lab. Total eight outcrosses</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK87</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>glp-1(e2144);ergo-1(gg98)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>YY158</td><td valign="bottom">Caenorhabditis Genetics Center</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>nrde-3(gg66)</italic></td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK328</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>glp-1(e2144); nrde-3(gg66)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK53</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>sid-1(pk3321)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain outcrossed four times in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK56</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>glp-1(e2144);sid-1(pk3321)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>OG497</td><td valign="bottom">Caenorhabditis Genetics Center</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-119(ed3);drSi13[hsf-1p::hsf-1::GFP::unc-54utr;Cb-unc-119+]</italic></td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK299</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-119(ed3);drSi13[hsf-1p::hsf-1::GFP::unc-54utr;Cb-unc-119+];glp-1(e2144)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK300</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-119(ed3);drSi13[hsf-1p::hsf-1::GFP::unc-54utr;Cb-unc-119+];dcr-1(mg375)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK301</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-119(ed3);drSi13[hsf-1p::hsf-1::GFP::unc-54utr;Cb-unc-119+];dcr-1(mg375) glp-1(e2144)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>AM140</td><td valign="bottom">Caenorhabditis Genetics Center</td><td valign="bottom"> <italic>rmIs132 [unc-54p::Q35::YFP]</italic></td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK409</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>rmIs132 [unc-54p::Q35::YFP];glp-1(e2144)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK412</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>rmIs132 [unc-54p::Q35::YFP];dcr-1 (mg375)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK410</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>rmIs132 [unc-54p::Q35::YFP];dcr-1 (mg375) glp-1(e2144)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>HE250</td><td valign="bottom">Caenorhabditis Genetics Center</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-52(e669su250)</italic></td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK574</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-52(e669su250);glp-1(e2144)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK575</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-52(e669su250);dcr-1(mg375)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK576</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-52(e669su250);dcr-1(mg375) glp-1(e2144)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK415</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>ptp-5.1(tm6122)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain outcrossed three times in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK470</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>glp-1(e2144);ptp-5.1(tm6122)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK469</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>dcr-1(mg375);ptp-5.1(tm6122)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK471</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>dcr-1(mg375) glp-1(e2144);ptp-5.1(tm6122)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK405</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-119(ed3);drSi13[hsf-1p::hsf-1::GFP::unc-54utr;Cb-unc-119+];glp-1(e2144);ptp-5.1(tm6122)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK406</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-119(ed3);drSi13[hsf-1p::hsf-1::GFP::unc-54utr;Cb-unc-119+];dcr-1(mg375);ptp-5.1(tm6122)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK407</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>unc-119(ed3);drSi13[hsf-1p::hsf-1::GFP::unc-54utr;Cb-unc-119+];dcr-1(mg375) glp-1(e2144);ptp-5.1(tm6122)</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK619</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>biuEx63[Pptp-5.1::genomic ptp-5.1::gfp+rol-6]</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK622</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>dcr-1(mg375); biuEx63[Pptp-5.1::genomic ptp-5.1::gfp+rol-6]</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK623</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td><italic>glp-1(e2144); biuEx63[Pptp-5.1::genomic ptp-5.1::gfp+rol-6]</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK624</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td><italic>glp-1(e2144); biuEx63[Pptp-5.1::genomic ptp-5.1::gfp+rol-6]</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK620</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td><italic>dcr-1(mg375) glp-1(e2144); biuEx63[Pptp-5.1::genomic ptp-5.1::gfp+rol-6]</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td>SHK621</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td><italic>dcr-1(mg375) glp-1(e2144); biuEx63[Pptp-5.1::genomic ptp-5.1::gfp+rol-6]</italic></td><td valign="bottom">Strain created in S Henis-Korenblit lab</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>act-1</italic> FW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">CCAATCCAAGAGAGGTATCCTTAC</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>act-1</italic> BW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">CATTGTAGAAGGTGTGATGCCAG</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>F44E5.5</italic> FW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">CAGAATGGAAAGGTTGAGATCCTCGCC</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>F44E5.5</italic> BW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">ACTGTATTCTCTGGATTACGAGCTGCTTGA</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>hsp-16.2</italic> BW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">CTCTCCATCTGAGTCTTCTGAGATTGTTAACA</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>hsp-16.2</italic> FW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">CAATTCTTGTTCTCCTTGGATTGATAGCGT</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>hsp-12.6</italic> BW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">GATGGAGTTGTCAATGTCCTCGACGAC</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>hsp-12.6</italic> FW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">TTGTGCTCCATATGGATTTCAAGAAGTTCTCC</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>ptp-5.1</italic> FW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">AAGGCTCCGTCTCCTGCACT</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>ptp-5.1</italic> BW</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">qPCR primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">TCCAGAGACACTTGTTGCTATCGGAG</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>bw_kpni_ptp-5.1_cds</italic></td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">cloning primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">GACAATGGTACCTTTCCAGGTCCCATCATACT</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td><italic>fw_PstI_ptp-5.1_Prom</italic></td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">cloning primers</td><td valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="sequence">ATGCCTGCAGCACC TACATTACGCCTGCGC</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td valign="bottom">anti-HSF-1, rabbit polyclonal Antibody</td><td valign="bottom">Abcam</td><td valign="bottom">ABE1044</td><td valign="bottom">WB(1:1,000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td valign="bottom">anti-Tubulin mouse monoclonal ascites fluid B-5-1-2</td><td valign="bottom">SIGMA-ALDRICH</td><td valign="bottom">T5168</td><td valign="bottom">WB(1:6000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td valign="bottom">anti-Tubulin, mouse monoclonal</td><td valign="bottom">DHSB</td><td valign="bottom">AA4.3</td><td valign="bottom">WB(1:2,000), RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_579793">AB_579793</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Commercial kit</td><td valign="bottom">RNA spike-in kit</td><td valign="bottom">Agilent</td><td valign="bottom">5188–5279</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Commercial kit</td><td valign="bottom">miRVana miRNA isolation kit (w/phenol)</td><td valign="bottom">Ambion</td><td valign="bottom">AM1560</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Commercial assay</td><td valign="bottom"><italic>C. elegans</italic> microarray 4 × 23,000</td><td valign="bottom">Agilent</td><td valign="bottom">G2519F-020186</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Chemical compound</td><td valign="bottom">TRIzol</td><td valign="bottom">Ambion</td><td valign="bottom">15596026</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Chemical compound</td><td valign="bottom">Linoleic acid sodium salt</td><td valign="bottom">Sigma</td><td valign="bottom">L8134</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Chemical compound</td><td valign="bottom">Maxima SYBR GREEN</td><td valign="bottom">Thermo Scientific</td><td valign="bottom">K0221</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Instrument</td><td valign="bottom">microarray scanner</td><td valign="bottom">Agilent</td><td valign="bottom">G2565BA</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Instrument</td><td valign="bottom">CFX-96 real time system</td><td valign="bottom">BioRad</td><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="bottom">Agilent Feature Extraction software</td><td valign="bottom">Agilent</td><td valign="bottom">version 9.5.1.1</td><td valign="bottom">Agilent Technologies, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_014963">SCR_014963</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="bottom">Partek Genomics Suite software</td><td valign="bottom">Partek</td><td valign="bottom">version 6.6</td><td valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_011860">SCR_011860</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="bottom">DAVID</td><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_001881">SCR_001881</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="bottom">STRING</td><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_005223">SCR_005223</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="bottom">SPSS</td><td valign="bottom">SPSS</td><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_002865">SCR_002865</ext-link></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Molecular cloning and generation of transgenic animals</title><p>The genomic fragment of <italic>ptp-5.1,</italic> including the coding region and 2 kb upstream sequence, was amplified from the corresponding cosmid and cloned into the <italic>PstII</italic> and <italic>KpnI</italic> sites in the L3691 plasmid, in frame with the GFP coding sequence. Germline transformations were performed by injection of 40 ng/μl plasmid and 60 ng/μl of <italic>rol-6(su1006)</italic> as a co-transformation marker into wild-type animals. Transgenic animals were allowed to lay eggs for 4 hrs. Eggs were raised at 25 degrees until day 1 of adulthood. On day 1 of adulthood, the animals were anesthetized on 2% agarose pads containing 2 mM levamisol. Number of GFP-expressing animals was scored with 100X magnification. At least 250 animals per strain were scored in four independent experiments. For localization analysis, DAPI staining was performed using an acetone-based protocol, which preserves the GFP signal, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Liang et al., 2018</xref>). Images were taken with a CCD digital camera using a Nikon 90i fluorescence microscope and merged using ImageJ.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>RNA interference</title><p>Bacteria expressing dsRNA were cultured overnight in LB containing 10 μg/mL tetracycline and 100 μg/mL ampicillin. Bacteria were seeded on NGM plates containing 2 mM IPTG and 0.05 mg/ml carbenicillin. RNAi clone identity was verified by sequencing. Eggs were placed on plates and synchronized at day 0 (L4).</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Lifespan and paralysis assay</title><p>Eggs were placed on standard NGM media with OP50 bacteria. Lifespan was scored every 1–2 days. Animals were raised at 25 degrees from eggs until day 1, and transferred to 20 degrees henceforth, except for the DGLA related lifespans. Related lifespans experiments were performed concurrently to minimize variability. In all experiments, lifespan was scored as of the L4 stage, which was set as t = 0. Animals that ruptured or crawled off the plates were included in the lifespan analysis as censored worms. For DGLA-supplemented lifespans, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sigmaaldrich.com/catalog/product/sigma/l8134?lang=en&amp;region=US">linoleic acid sodium salt (Sigma L8134)</ext-link> was dissolved in water and added to 0.1% NP-40-containing plates to a final concentration of 150 μM. Plates containing the detergent NP-40 (0.1%) were used as control. DGLA related lifespans were performed at 20 degrees from egg stage. SPSS program was used to determine the means and the P-values. P-values were calculated using the Breslow (Generalized Wilcoxon) method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gehan, 1965</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Microarray analysis</title><p>Total RNA was extracted with TRIzol reagent (Ambion, 15596026) from wild type, <italic>dcr-1(mg375), glp-1(e2144), and dcr-1(mg375) glp-1(e2144)</italic> animals. RNA concentrations were measured using a NanoDrop spectrophotometer (ND-1000), and sample quality was checked using a bioanalyzer (Agilent). 200 ng of total RNA of each sample, in the presence of control RNAs (RNA spike-in kit, Agilent), was labeled with either Cy-3 or Cy-5 using the low-input quick amp labeling kit, two-color (Agilent) following the manufacturer’s protocol. Each strain had four biological replicates. Equal amounts of labeled RNA were hybridized overnight to Agilent’s <italic>C. elegans</italic> microarray 4 × 23,000 at 60°C. Hybridization mixes were prepared using the gene expression hybridization kit of Agilent following the manufacturer’s protocol. Following hybridization, the each slide was first washed with Gene Expression Wash Buffer 1 (Agilent) and then with Gene Expression Wash Buffer 2 (Agilent). This was followed by an acetonitrile wash. Finally, the slides were placed in stabilization and drying solution (Agilent). The washed slides were scanned on an Agilent G2565BA microarray scanner. The data of all the arrays were first subjected to background correction and LOESS within-array normalization using Agilent Feature Extraction software (version 9.5.1.1, Agilent Technologies). The remaining analyses were performed in Partek Genomics Suite software (version 6.6, Partek, Inc). The log expression ratios were produced during the normalization step. Data from the four biological replicates were used to perform two-way ANOVA analysis. Genes with significantly up- or downregulated expression (p-value 0.05) were identified, with a cut-off of at least a 1.5-fold change. We then focused on expressed genes or pathways enriched as indicated by DAVID enrichment analysis program [22] and the gene ontology (GO) classification analysis. The DAVID GO fold change is defined as the ratio between the proportions of the submitted list and the proportion of the background one. Raw and processed data were deposited under the Gene Expression Omnibus, with accession number GSE122457.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR</title><p>Animals were raised at 25 degrees until day 1. On day 1 of adulthood, total RNA was extracted with TRIzol reagent (Ambion, 15596026). RNA extraction, purification, and reverse transcription were carried out using standard protocol. Real-time PCR was done using Maxima SYBR GREEN (Thermo Scientific, K0221) in Step one plus instrument. Purified DNA templates were amplified in a BioRad CFX-96 real-time system. mRNA levels of <italic>act-1</italic> were used for normalization. P-values were calculated using Student’s T-test.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Small RNA sequencing and analysis</title><p>Animals were raised at 25 degrees until day 1 of adulthood. Low molecular RNA fraction was extracted using miRVana miRNA isolation kit (Ambion). Library preparation was done using QsRNA-seq protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Fishman et al., 2018</xref>). To allow ligation of secondary siRNA to adapter, two out of three phosphates were enzymatically removed from the 5’-termini, resulting in secondary siRNA enriched libraries. Sequences were processed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Fishman et al., 2018</xref>). This included demuxing, trimming, and collapsing the sequences. Only sequences longer than 14nt long were processed. The sequences were aligned to WS220 annotated genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org">www.wormbase.org</ext-link>) using Bowite aligner (with parameters -v 0 -e 120 -a --<monospace>strata</monospace> –best) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Langmead et al., 2009</xref>). DEseq (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Anders and Huber, 2010</xref>) package in R (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>, with pooled-CR parameter) was used to evaluate siRNA expression. Genes with significant changes in DEseq normalized siRNA counts between <italic>glp-1</italic> mutant and <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> mutant were considered if there was at least 10 fold difference with adjusted p-value after Benjamini–Hochberg correction (P-adj) &lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp5">Supplementary file 5</xref>). Raw and processed data were deposited under the Gene Expression Omnibus, with accession number GSE128935.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Western blot</title><p>100 animals were boiled in protein sample buffer containing 2% SDS. Proteins were separated using standard PAGE separation, transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane, and detected by western-blotting using the following antibodies: anti-HSF-1 (ABE1004), anti-Tubulin (DHSB, 1:5000).</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>HSF-1::GFP foci</title><p>HSF-1::GFP foci were scored as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Morton and Lamitina, 2013</xref>). Specifically, eggs of animals containing HSF-1::GFP were placed on standard NGM media with OP50 bacteria and raised at 25 degrees until day 3 of adulthood. On day 3 of adulthood, the animals were moved to pre-warmed plates and exposed to heat shock (37°C for 10 min). Animals were anesthetized on 2% agarose pads containing 2 mM levamisol. Number of foci were scored immediately in posterior hypodermal cells (per experiment - seven nuclei assessed per worm, seven worms per strain) with 630X magnification. Foci scoring was done in the plane that showed the maximal number of foci per hypodermal cell. Images were taken with a CCD digital camera using a Nikon 90i fluorescence microscope. For each trial, exposure time was calibrated to minimize the number of saturated pixels and kept constant through the experiment. Exposures and contrast were adjusted for each picture independently to best emphasize foci amount. At least 140 cells per genotype were scored in a total of 3 independent experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Thermo‐resistance assay</title><p>Age-synchronized animals (n &gt; 40) were grown at 25°C until day 2 of adulthood. On day 2 of adulthood, animals were subjected to 37°C heat shock for 9 hr and recovered at 25°C for 5 hr. Animals that failed to move in response to a gentle touch with a metal pick were scored as dead.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Motility assay</title><p>Age-synchronized animals (n &gt; 30) that express <italic>Punc-54::Q35::YFP (Q35)</italic> were grown at 25°C until day 5 of adulthood. On day 5 of adulthood, animals were placed in 96 wells containing M9 buffer. Each animal was monitored visually over 15 s for trashing. Values are presented as bends per minute.</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Stiff body paralysis assay</title><p>Age-synchronized (n &gt; 30) <italic>unc-52(ts)</italic> mutant animals were grown at 25°C until day 1 of adulthood. Animals were then shifted to 15°C, and paralysis was scored on day 4 of adulthood.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>RNAi screen</title><p><italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> eggs were treated with RNAi against the listed genes until day 1. Viability of the animals in the plates was qualitatively scored at days 9–11 as improved or not improved. RNAi identity was verified by sequencing. Genes whose RNAi identity was not supported by sequencing were noted as no RNAi. Genes whose RNAi interfered with animal development were indicated as lethal.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Error bars represent the standard error of the mean (SEM), unless noted otherwise. For qRT-PCR, P-values were calculated using the unpaired Student’s t test. For lifespan experiments, P-values were calculated using the Breslow (Generalized Wilcoxon) method. For thermo‐resistance assay and <italic>unc-52(ts)</italic> paralysis, P-values were calculated using the Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test. For Q35 motility assay and HSF-1 foci formation assay, P-values were calculated using one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's post hoc analysis. For Western Blot analysis, One sample Test and One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's post hoc analysis were applied. For fraction of animals expressing the <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transgene, P-values were calculated using the Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr. Jennifer Israel Cohen Benichou for statistical analysis and data presentation and Ms. Yael Laure for English editing. We thank members of the Henis-Korenblit laboratory for helpful discussions. We thank Dr. Shohei Mitani (National Bioresource Project for the nematode, Tokyo Women's Medical University School of Medicine, Japan) and the Caenorhabditis Genetics Center for providing nematode strains. This work was supported by funds from ISF grants no. 1571/15 and 689/19 to S.H.K. and no. 927/18 to ATL, by grant no. 3–12066 from the Israeli Ministry of Science, Technology and Space to S.H.K, and by the Israeli Centers of Research Excellence (I-CORE) program (Center No. 1796/12 to ATL).</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - original draft</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conducted some of the lifespan experiments and some of the western blot experiments</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Conducted some of the lifespan experiments and generated the dcr-1 glp-1 double mutant</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Supervision, Methodology, Writing - review and editing, Contributed to the acquisition of the small RNA data</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Generated the transgenic animals</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Formal analysis, H.W.B-A analyzed and interpreted the genomic data</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>Formal analysis, Supervision, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - review and editing, A.T.L. analyzed and interpreted the small RNA data</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Project administration, Writing - review and editing</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Lifespan analysis of mutants with defective processing of endo-siRNA and inactivation of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-50896-supp1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp2"><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>72 genes whose levels decreased by more than 1.5 fold in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> single mutants (p-value&lt;0.05).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-50896-supp2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp3"><label>Supplementary file 3.</label><caption><title>GO analysis of 72 genes whose levels decreased by more than 1.5 fold in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants (p-value&lt;0.05).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-50896-supp3-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp4"><label>Supplementary file 4.</label><caption><title>132 genes whose levels increased by more than 1.5 fold in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> single mutants (p-value&lt;0.05).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-50896-supp4-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp5"><label>Supplementary file 5.</label><caption><title>Expression of secondary siRNAs of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> vs. <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants (Padj &lt;0.05).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-50896-supp5-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp6"><label>Supplementary file 6.</label><caption><title>DAVID analysis of 132 genes whose levels increased by more than 1.5 fold in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants compared to <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants (p-value&lt;0.05).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-50896-supp6-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp7"><label>Supplementary file 7.</label><caption><title>RNAi lifespan screen of <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutant.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-50896-supp7-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp8"><label>Supplementary file 8.</label><caption><title>Statistical data.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-50896-supp8-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-50896-transrepform-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Raw and processed high-throughput sequencing data and microarray data generated and/or analyzed during this study were deposited under the Gene Expression Omnibus, with accession number GSE122457 and GSE128935. All other data generated or analysed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files.</p><p>The following datasets were generated:</p><p><element-citation id="dataset1" publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Hemo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldman</surname><given-names>B-AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamm</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Henis-Korenblit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><data-title>endo-siRNA induced inactivation of a neddylation suppresor promotes longevity and HSF-1 activation in germline-less animals</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id assigning-authority="NCBI" pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE122457">GSE122457</pub-id></element-citation></p><p><element-citation id="dataset2" publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemo</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldman</surname><given-names>B-AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamm</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Henis-Korenblit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><data-title>Endogenous siRNAs promote proteostasis and longevity in germline-less Caenorhabditis elegans</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id assigning-authority="NCBI" pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE128935">GSE128935</pub-id></element-citation></p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aalto</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicastro</surname> <given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Broughton</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chipman</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiner</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquinelli</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Opposing roles of microRNA argonautes during <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> aging</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1007379</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1007379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29927939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akerfelt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Sistonen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Heat shock factors: integrators of cell stress, development and lifespan</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20628411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alper</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwee</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Apfeld</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lackford</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Freedman</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> germ line regulates distinct signaling pathways to control lifespan and innate immunity</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>285</volume><fpage>1822</fpage><lpage>1828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.057323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19923212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>R106</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antebi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Regulation of longevity by the reproductive system</article-title><source>Experimental Gerontology</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2012.09.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23063987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolinski</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwight</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eppig</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Issel-Tarver</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasarskis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matese</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringwald</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherlock</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. the gene ontology consortium</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/75556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asikainen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Storvik</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakso</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Whole genome microarray analysis of <italic>C. elegans</italic> rrf-3 and <italic>eri-1</italic> mutants</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><volume>581</volume><fpage>5050</fpage><lpage>5054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2007.09.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17919598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baird</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Simic</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moresco</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>HSF-1-mediated cytoskeletal integrity determines thermotolerance and life span</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>346</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1253168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25324391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ben-Zvi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Collapse of proteostasis represents an early molecular event in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> aging</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>14914</fpage><lpage>14919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0902882106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19706382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blumenfeld</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jose</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Reproducible features of small RNAs in <italic>C. elegans</italic> reveal NU RNAs and provide insights into 22G RNAs and 26G RNAs</article-title><source>RNA</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.054551.115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26647462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boehm</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Slack</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>A developmental timing microRNA and its target regulate life span in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><volume>310</volume><fpage>1954</fpage><lpage>1957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1115596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16373574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulias</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvitz</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>The <italic>C.</italic> elegans microRNA mir-71 acts in neurons to promote germline-mediated longevity through regulation of DAF-16/FOXO</article-title><source>Cell Metabolism</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2012.02.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22482727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunquell</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerheide</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>The genome-wide role of HSF-1 in the regulation of gene expression in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>559</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-2837-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27496166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burton</surname> <given-names>NO</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkhart</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Nuclear RNAi maintains heritable gene silencing in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>19683</fpage><lpage>19688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1113310108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22106253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ching</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mousigian</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>HSF-1 regulators DDL-1/2 link insulin-like signaling to heat-shock responses and modulation of longevity</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>148</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2011.12.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22265419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Lencastre</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pincus</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Slack</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>MicroRNAs both promote and antagonize longevity in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>2159</fpage><lpage>2168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2010.11.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21129974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denzel</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapierre</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mack</surname> <given-names>HID</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Emerging topics in <italic>C. elegans</italic> aging research: transcriptional regulation, stress response and epigenetics</article-title><source>Mechanisms of Ageing and Development</source><volume>177</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mad.2018.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30134144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duchaine</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wohlschlegel</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bei</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownell</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Harding</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Functional proteomics reveals the biochemical niche of <italic>C. elegans</italic> DCR-1 in multiple small-RNA-mediated pathways</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2005.11.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Small RNA-mediated gene silencing pathways in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>The International Journal of Biochemistry &amp; Cell Biology</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>1306</fpage><lpage>1315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocel.2010.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20227516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahlgren</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Breen</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>The ERI-6/7 helicase acts at the first stage of an siRNA amplification pathway that targets recent gene duplications</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e1002369</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22102828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fishman</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Light</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamm</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>QsRNA-seq: a method for high-throughput profiling and quantifying small RNAs</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>113</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-018-1495-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30107842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flatt</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Integrating evolutionary and molecular genetics of aging</article-title><source>Biochimica Et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - General Subjects</source><volume>1790</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2009.07.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gehan</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1965">1965</year><article-title>A generalized two-sample Wilcoxon test for doubly censored data</article-title><source>Biometrika</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>650</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biomet/52.3-4.650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gent</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamm</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavelec</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniar</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Parameswaran</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fire</surname> <given-names>AZ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Distinct phases of siRNA synthesis in an endogenous RNAi pathway in <italic>C. elegans</italic> soma</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2010.01.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20116306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greer</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Maures</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ucar</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauswirth</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancini</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Benayoun</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Transgenerational epigenetic inheritance of longevity in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>479</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grishok</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Biology and mechanisms of short RNAs in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Advances in Genetics</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-407675-4.00001-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23890211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirayama</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasale</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Batista</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Claycomb</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moresco</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Youngman</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Keys</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoltz</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasschau</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahlgren</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Distinct argonaute-mediated 22G-RNA pathways direct genome surveillance in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> germline</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2009.09.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19800275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bochner</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavelec</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkhart</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Harding</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lachowiec</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>An argonaute transports siRNAs from the cytoplasm to the nucleus</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>321</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1157647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18653886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>A-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>New genes tied to endocrine, metabolic, and dietary regulation of lifespan from a <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> genomic RNAi screen</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>e17</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0010017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heintz</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Doktor</surname> <given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanjuin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Escoubas</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Weir</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutta</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva-García</surname> <given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruun</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morantte</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoxhaj</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Andresen</surname> <given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mair</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Splicing factor 1 modulates dietary restriction and TORC1 pathway longevity in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>541</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature20789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27919065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henis-Korenblit</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormick</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cary</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Insulin/IGF-1 signaling mutants reprogram ER stress response regulators to promote longevity</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>9730</fpage><lpage>9735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1002575107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20460307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsin</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Signals from the reproductive system regulate the lifespan of <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>399</volume><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/20694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Regulation of aging and age-related disease by DAF-16 and heat-shock factor</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>300</volume><fpage>1142</fpage><lpage>1145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1083701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12750521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibáñez-Ventoso</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Modulated microRNA expression during adult lifespan in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1474-9726.2006.00210.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Inukai</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Slack</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Age-associated changes in expression of small, noncoding RNAs, including microRNAs, in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>RNA</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>1804</fpage><lpage>1820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.2714411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kishimoto</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Uno</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okabe</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nono</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Environmental stresses induce transgenerationally inheritable survival advantages via germline-to-soma communication in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>14031</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms14031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labbadia</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Repression of the Heat Shock Response Is a Programmed Event at the Onset of Reproduction</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2015.06.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>R25</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2009-10-3-r25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19261174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lapierre</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>De Magalhaes Filho</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>McQuary</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Visvikis</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelino</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Irazoqui</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The TFEB orthologue HLH-30 regulates autophagy and modulates longevity in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>2267</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms3267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23925298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Castro</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Detecting protein subcellular localization by green fluorescence protein tagging and 4',6-Diamidino-2-phenylindole staining in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Visualized Experiments : JoVE</source><volume>30</volume><elocation-id>57914</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/57914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libina</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Tissue-specific activities of <italic>C. elegans</italic> DAF-16 in the regulation of lifespan</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00889-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14622602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Noh</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>The endogenous siRNA pathway in <italic>Drosophila</italic> impacts stress resistance and lifespan by regulating metabolic homeostasis</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><volume>585</volume><fpage>3079</fpage><lpage>3085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2011.08.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21889502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>López-Otín</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blasco</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Partridge</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrano</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroemer</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The hallmarks of aging</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>153</volume><fpage>1194</fpage><lpage>1217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.05.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23746838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mason</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cargill</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Transplantation of young ovaries to old mice increased life span in transplant recipients</article-title><source>The Journals of Gerontology</source><volume>64A</volume><fpage>1207</fpage><lpage>1211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/glp134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masse</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Molin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouchiroud</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanhems</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Palladino</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Billaud</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Solari</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>A novel role for the SMG-1 kinase in lifespan and oxidative stress resistance in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e3354</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18836529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matus</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Glimcher</surname> <given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hetz</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Protein folding stress in neurodegenerative diseases: a glimpse into the ER</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Cell Biology</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2011.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21288706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maures</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Greer</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauswirth</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>The H3K27 demethylase UTX-1 regulates <italic>C. elegans</italic> lifespan in a germline-independent, insulin-dependent manner</article-title><source>Aging Cell</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1474-9726.2011.00738.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21834846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCormick</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>New genes that extend <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>' lifespan in response to reproductive signals</article-title><source>Aging Cell</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1474-9726.2011.00768.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22081913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Min</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>The lifespan of korean eunuchs</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>R792</fpage><lpage>R793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2012.06.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23017989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morley</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brignull</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Weyers</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>The threshold for polyglutamine-expansion protein aggregation and cellular toxicity is dynamic and influenced by aging in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>10417</fpage><lpage>10422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.152161099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12122205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morley</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Regulation of longevity in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> by heat shock factor and molecular chaperones</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.e03-07-0532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14668486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morton</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamitina</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title><italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> HSF-1 is an essential nuclear protein that forms stress granule-like structures following heat shock</article-title><source>Aging Cell</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acel.12024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname> <given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalinava</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trinh</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>A transgenerational role of the germline nuclear RNAi pathway in repressing heat stress-induced transcriptional activation in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Epigenetics &amp; Chromatin</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>3</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13072-016-0052-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Rourke</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuballa</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xavier</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>ω-6 polyunsaturated fatty acids extend life span through the activation of autophagy</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.205294.112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23392608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ooi</surname> <given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Prahlad</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Olfactory experience primes the heat shock transcription factor HSF-1 to enhance the expression of molecular chaperones in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Science Signaling</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>eaan4893</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.aan4893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29042483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ortiz</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Noble</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorokin</surname> <given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimble</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A new dataset of spermatogenic vs. oogenic transcriptomes in the <italic>nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>G3: Genes|Genomes|Genetics</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>1765</fpage><lpage>1772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.114.012351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavelec</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lachowiec</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duchaine</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Requirement for the ERI/DICER complex in endogenous RNA interference and sperm development in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>183</volume><fpage>1283</fpage><lpage>1295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.109.108134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19797044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Priess</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnabel</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnabel</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1987">1987</year><article-title>The glp-1 locus and cellular interactions in early <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(87)90129-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ratnappan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrit</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghazi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Germline signals deploy NHR-49 to modulate fatty-acid β-oxidation and desaturation in somatic tissues of <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e1004829</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25474470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rechavi</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Minevich</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobert</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Transgenerational inheritance of an acquired small RNA-Based antiviral response in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>147</volume><fpage>1248</fpage><lpage>1256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2011.10.042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rechavi</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Houri-Ze'evi</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Anava</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goh</surname> <given-names>WSS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerk</surname> <given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobert</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Starvation-induced transgenerational inheritance of small RNAs in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>158</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.06.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25018105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rechavi</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lev</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Principles of transgenerational small RNA inheritance in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>R720</fpage><lpage>R730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2017.05.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28743023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Safra</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fickentscher</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi-Ferber</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Danino</surname> <given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Haviv-Chesner</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Juven-Gershon</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Henis-Korenblit</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>The FOXO transcription factor DAF-16 bypasses ire-1 requirement to promote endoplasmic reticulum homeostasis</article-title><source>Cell Metabolism</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>870</fpage><lpage>881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2014.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25448701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarge</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>Activation of heat shock gene transcription by heat shock factor 1 involves oligomerization, acquisition of DNA-binding activity, and nuclear localization and can occur in the absence of stress</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1392</fpage><lpage>1407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.13.3.1392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8441385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shemesh</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shai</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Zvi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Germline stem cell arrest inhibits the collapse of somatic proteostasis early in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> adulthood</article-title><source>Aging Cell</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>814</fpage><lpage>822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acel.12110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shemesh</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Meshnik</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shpigel</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Zvi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Dietary-Induced signals that activate the gonadal longevity pathway during development regulate a proteostasis switch in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> Adulthood</article-title><source>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>254</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnmol.2017.00254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28848390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollam</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Magner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Karalay</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Antebi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>A steroid receptor-microRNA switch regulates life span in response to signals from the gonad</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>338</volume><fpage>1472</fpage><lpage>1476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1228967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23239738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shih</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>SID-1 is a dsRNA-selective dsRNA-gated channel</article-title><source>RNA</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>1057</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.2596511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21474576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Son</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ham</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Artan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaletsky</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arey</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Roh</surname> <given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>RNA surveillance via nonsense-mediated mRNA decay is crucial for longevity in daf-2/insulin/IGF-1 mutant <italic>C</italic>. elegans</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>14749</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms14749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28276441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinbaugh</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Narasimhan</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Robida-Stubbs</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moronetti Mazzeo</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreyfuss</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hourihan</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghavan</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Operaña</surname> <given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Esmaillie</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackwell</surname> <given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Lipid-mediated regulation of SKN-1/Nrf in response to germ cell absence</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e07836</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.07836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szklarczyk</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gable</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Junge</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyder</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonovic</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Doncheva</surname> <given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mering</surname> <given-names>CV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>STRING v11: protein-protein association networks with increased coverage, supporting functional discovery in genome-wide experimental datasets</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>D607</fpage><lpage>D613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30476243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabrez</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Differential alternative splicing coupled to nonsense-mediated decay of mRNA ensures dietary restriction-induced longevity</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>306</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-00370-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28824175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Berendzen</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Systemic stress signalling: understanding the cell non-autonomous control of proteostasis</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm3752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24556842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Aging as an event of proteostasis collapse</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>a004440</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a004440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21441594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasale</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Thivierge</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Batista</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Claycomb</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Youngman</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Duchaine</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Sequential rounds of RNA-dependent RNA transcription drive endogenous small-RNA biogenesis in the ERGO-1/Argonaute pathway</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>3582</fpage><lpage>3587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0911908107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vilchez</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Morantte</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Merkwirth</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>RPN-6 determines <italic>C. elegans</italic> longevity under proteotoxic stress conditions</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>489</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22922647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Rourke</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Fat metabolism links germline stem cells and longevity in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><volume>322</volume><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1162011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18988854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinke</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>A <italic>C. elegans</italic> piwi, PRG-1, regulates 21U-RNAs during spermatogenesis</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2008.05.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18501605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watts</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Dietary manipulation implicates lipid signaling in the regulation of germ cell maintenance in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>292</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2006.01.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16487504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welker</surname> <given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavelec</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nix</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Duchaine</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bass</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Dicer's helicase domain is required for accumulation of some, but not all, <italic>C. elegans</italic> endogenous siRNAs</article-title><source>RNA</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>893</fpage><lpage>903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.2122010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20354150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winston</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Molodowitch</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Systemic RNAi in <italic>C.</italic> Elegans requires the putative transmembrane protein SID-1</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>295</volume><fpage>2456</fpage><lpage>2459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1068836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11834782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yigit</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Batista</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bei</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolia</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshua-Tor</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Simard</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Analysis of the <italic>C. elegans</italic> argonaute family reveals that distinct argonautes act sequentially during RNAi</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.09.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110334</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.50896.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kaeberlein</surname><given-names>Matt</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Washington</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife publishes the most substantive revision requests and the accompanying author responses.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Acceptance summary:</bold></p><p>This manuscript describes a role for endogenous small interfering RNAs (siRNA) in lifespan extension. Using long-lived germ-line ablated <italic>C. elegans</italic>, the authors show that the machinery required for maturation siRNA are required for enhanced proteostasis and lifespan extension. They identify a specific siRNA target, the tyrosine phosphatase ptp-5.1, that is also required for these effects, supporting the model that siRNA regulation of ptp-5.1 mediates longevity.</p><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Endogenous siRNAs promote proteostasis and longevity in germline less <italic>C. elegans</italic>&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, one of whom is a member of our Board of Reviewing Editors, and the evaluation has been overseen by David Ron as the Senior Editor. The reviewers have opted to remain anonymous.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>This manuscript entitled &quot;Endogenous siRNAs promote proteostasis and longevity in germline-less <italic>C. elegans</italic>&quot; showed that endo-siRNAs are necessary for the long lifespan and the maintenance of proteostasis of glp-1 mutants, which do not have germline. They showed that endo-siRNA-regulating factors, including dicer, are required for the longevity of glp-1 mutants. They found that dicer was necessary for the activation of HSF-1, a master transcription factor for cytosolic chaperone expression, and proteostasis in the glp-1 mutants. Using transcriptomic analysis, they identified a tyrosine phosphatase, ptp-5.1, as an indirect target of endo-siRNA, whose genetic inhibition restored the longevity and the activation of HSF-1 in glp-1 dicer double mutants. These data suggest that down-regulation of ptp-5.1 by endo-siRNA promotes longevity and improves proteostasis in germline-deficient animals. The findings are intriguing and will provide useful information about the role of endo-siRNAs in aging regulation.</p><p>Essential Revisions:</p><p>1) It is possible that the low-level heat shock required to induce loss of GSCs could be contributing to the involvement of chaperones here. Because all of the experiments in this paper are done with the ts allele of glp-1, it is unclear whether the model proposed is general for GSC depletion or specific for ts glp-1. It is important to provide some evidence that these observations are general rather than specific for ts glp-1. This could be done by testing whether an alternative method for extending lifespan via depletion of GSCs, such as ablation, has similar requirements for lifespan extension.</p><p>2) One of the interesting and surprising findings in the paper is that ptp-5.1 mRNA level is extremely low in both glp-1 mutants and dcr-1 glp-1 mutants, despite the increase in the expression by dcr-1 mutation in glp-1 mutants. This small difference appears to exert a robust functional and physiological consequence in shown by using ptp-5.1 mutants (Figure 4C and Figure 5). Therefore, we think it is important to test whether they can detect ptp-5.1 expression in the soma of dcr-1 glp-1 mutant adult worms (in comparison to glp-1 mutants) by using transgenic animals and/or in situ hybridization.</p><p>3) The Western Blot in Figure 2B is of poor quality. This needs to be cleaned up with similar loading control levels. It seems obvious that HSF-1 is elevated in dcr-1 glp-1 animals and probably in the single mutants as well. The claim that there is no significant difference in dcr-1 and glp-1 single mutants does not pass the &quot;eye test&quot;. While it appears that this experiment was done 6 times, if this is the best looking of the Westerns, that's an additional concern. Why are only comparisons between glp-1 vs WT and glp-1 vs glp-1 dcr-1 shown? It would be good to see the data from all 6 replicates.</p><p>4) Discussion section, you need to be careful about describing changes to the &quot;shapes of lifespan curves&quot;. As far as we can tell, there is no formal analysis of mortality here, which would be necessary to statistically assess whether the shape (i.e. slope or intercept of the ln(mortality) plot) is altered. Same comment about claiming changes in maximal lifespan. What statistical test was performed to assess maximal lifespan differences?</p><p>5) There seem to be some inconsistencies between the model and the data which need to be addressed. For example, in Figure 2A, cytosolic chaperone levels are not increased in glp-1 mutants compared to wild-type but decreased by dcr-1 mutations. How can this be explained with the role of HSF-1 in the longevity of glp-1 mutants? This also does not fit the model regarding inhibition of HSF-1 by ptp-5.1, as ptp-5.1 mRNA level was drastically reduced in the glp-1 mutants, and therefore the expectation is HSF-1 up-regulation in glp-1 mutants compared to wild-type.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.50896.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>This manuscript entitled &quot;Endogenous siRNAs promote proteostasis and longevity in germline-less <italic>C. elegans</italic>&quot; showed that endo-siRNAs are necessary for the long lifespan and the maintenance of proteostasis of glp-1 mutants, which do not have germline. They showed that endo-siRNA-regulating factors, including dicer, are required for the longevity of glp-1 mutants. They found that dicer was necessary for the activation of HSF-1, a master transcription factor for cytosolic chaperone expression, and proteostasis in the glp-1 mutants. Using transcriptomic analysis, they identified a tyrosine phosphatase, ptp-5.1, as an indirect target of endo-siRNA, whose genetic inhibition restored the longevity and the activation of HSF-1 in glp-1 dicer double mutants. These data suggest that down-regulation of ptp-5.1 by endo-siRNA promotes longevity and improves proteostasis in germline-deficient animals. The findings are intriguing and will provide useful information about the role of endo-siRNAs in aging regulation.</p><p>Essential Revisions:</p><p>1) It is possible that the low-level heat shock required to induce loss of GSCs could be contributing to the involvement of chaperones here. Because all of the experiments in this paper are done with the ts allele of glp-1, it is unclear whether the model proposed is general for GSC depletion or specific for ts glp-1. It is important to provide some evidence that these observations are general rather than specific for ts glp-1. This could be done by testing whether an alternative method for extending lifespan via depletion of GSCs, such as ablation, has similar requirements for lifespan extension.</p></disp-quote><p>To avoid the temperature shift, which is required for the temperature dependent depletion of the germline by the <italic>glp-1(ts)</italic> mutation, we sought for alternative ways to deplete the germline, which do not involve a temperature shift. To this end, we have re-examined the requirement of the <italic>dcr1</italic> helicase activity for the lifespan extension conferred by preventing germline proliferation upon dietary supplementation of dihomo-γ-linolenic acid (DGLA). Previous studies have shown that this treatment interferes with germline proliferation <sup>1</sup>, extends lifespan<sup>2,3</sup> and confers superior proteostasis (similar to that observed in germline-less <italic>glp-1</italic> animals)<sup>2</sup>. We found that DGLA-mediated germline depletion extended the lifespan of wild-type animals, but failed to extend the lifespan of <italic>dcr-1(mg375)</italic> mutants. Hence, the endo-siRNA pathway appears to be required for the longevity of germline-less animals in general, and does not merely reflect a technical requirement stemming from the temperature shift of the temperature sensitive <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants. These experiments are described in subsection “Endo-siRNAs contribute to the longevity of germline-less animals”, Figure 1B and Supplementary file 1.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) One of the interesting and surprising findings in the paper is that ptp-5.1 mRNA level is extremely low in both glp-1 mutants and dcr-1 glp-1 mutants, despite the increase in the expression by dcr-1 mutation in glp-1 mutants. This small difference appears to exert a robust functional and physiological consequence in shown by using ptp-5.1 mutants (Figure 4C and Figure 5). Therefore, we think it is important to test whether they can detect ptp-5.1 expression in the soma of dcr-1 glp-1 mutant adult worms (in comparison to glp-1 mutants) by using transgenic animals and/or in situ hybridization.</p></disp-quote><p>We have generated transgenic animals expressing an extrachromosomal array of <italic>Pptp-</italic></p><p><italic>5.1::genomic ptp-5.1::gfp</italic>. As expected, we did not detect expression of the transgene in most of the transgenic animals (indicating that the transgene was either not expressed or expressed below our detection threshold). Surprisingly, we did detect somatic expression of the transgene in 15% of both wild-type and GSC(-) <italic>glp-1</italic> animals. Specifically both the wild-type and the <italic>glp-1</italic> animals that expressed the reporter displayed a clear fluorescent signal specifically in two adjacent cells in the mid-intestine. Interestingly, inactivation of the endo-siRNA pathway (by introduction of a <italic>dcr-1</italic> mutation) doubled the fraction of the animals expressing the reporter in their mid-intestine, but this was independent of the removal of the germline. Based on this we conclude that <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> is expressed in 2 intestinal cells in a fraction of the animals. We hypothesize that repression of the expression in these cells is important for HSF-1 activation in <italic>glp-1</italic> animals. These experiments are described in subsection “<italic>ptp-5.1</italic> transcript levels are indirectly regulated by endo-siRNAs in GSC(-) animals”, Figure 4C and Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) The Western Blot in Figure 2B is of poor quality. This needs to be cleaned up with similar loading control levels. It seems obvious that HSF-1 is elevated in dcr-1 glp-1 animals and probably in the single mutants as well. The claim that there is no significant difference in dcr-1 and glp-1 single mutants does not pass the &quot;eye test&quot;. While it appears that this experiment was done 6 times, if this is the best looking of the Westerns, that's an additional concern. Why are only comparisons between glp-1 vs WT and glp-1 vs glp-1 dcr-1 shown? It would be good to see the data from all 6 replicates.</p></disp-quote><p>We added an additional replicate (total of 7 replicates), re-quantitated all the data and did the statistical analysis on all 7 experiments, including comparisons between all strains. Based on the updated results, the statistical analysis indicates that HSF-1 levels significantly increase in <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants (in 6/7 repeats, P=0.004) and in <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants (in 7/7 repeats, P=0.002) compared to WT. <italic>dcr-1</italic> mutants also had more HSF-1 upon averaging across all 7 experiments compared to WT animals (in practice a clear increase was observed in 4/7 experiments), but this was not statistically significant (P=0.0559). ANOVA test between the remaining strains (dcr-1/glp-1/dcr-1 glp-1) showed no significant difference among them (P=0.0649). This includes the comparison which interested us the most – the comparison between <italic>glp-1</italic> and <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic>. In addition, we replotted the data as boxplots and added representation of each individual experiment (Figure 2B). We present a western blot of an experiment with values similar to those of the combined analysis (Figure 2B) See subsection “Endo-siRNAs are required for activation of the heat shock response in GSC(-) animals”, Figure 2B, Supplementary file 8.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) Discussion section, you need to be careful about describing changes to the &quot;shapes of lifespan curves&quot;. As far as we can tell, there is no formal analysis of mortality here, which would be necessary to statistically assess whether the shape (i.e. slope or intercept of the ln(mortality) plot) is altered. Same comment about claiming changes in maximal lifespan. What statistical test was performed to assess maximal lifespan differences?</p></disp-quote><p>The parts referring to the shape of the lifespan curves and the maximal lifespan have been removed.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) There seem to be some inconsistencies between the model and the data which need to be addressed. For example, in Figure 2A, cytosolic chaperone levels are not increased in glp-1 mutants compared to wild-type but decreased by dcr-1 mutations. How can this be explained with the role of HSF-1 in the longevity of glp-1 mutants?</p></disp-quote><p>Because the germline accounts for about two-thirds of all adult nuclei, one needs to be careful when comparing expression levels between animals that contain a germline to those that lack a germline. Hence, we were very careful throughout the manuscript to compare GSC(-) animals to GSC(-) animals (i.e. <italic>glp-1</italic> mutants and <italic>dcr-1 glp-1</italic> double mutants). This is an important point, and thus we now added this point to the text in the legend of Figure 2A. Taking this into account, the high expression of chaperones in WT animals compared to GSC(-) animals could be accounted for by expression of chaperones in the germline cells.</p><p>As for the effects of <italic>dcr-1</italic> inactivation on chaperone expression – we detected a significant reduction in the expression of all 3 chaperone transcripts examined in GSC(-) animals. In contrast, we detected a significant reduction in the expression of only one of the chaperones in the case of GSC(+) animals. Thus, this seems to be a different mode of regulation specific for this gene rather than the regulation of the upstream transcription factor HSF-1. legend of Figure 2A.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>This also does not fit the model regarding inhibition of HSF-1 by ptp-5.1, as ptp-5.1 mRNA level was drastically reduced in the glp-1 mutants, and therefore the expectation is HSF-1 up-regulation in glp-1 mutants compared to wild-type.</p></disp-quote><p>Even though we cannot compare between chaperone levels between WT (=soma+germline) and <italic>glp-1</italic> animals (=soma only) (because of the presence vs. absence of the germline), we can compare the activation of HSF-1 in the soma of these strains, by looking at HSF-1 foci formation in the soma. Indeed, consistent with the predictions of our model, in this set of experiments HSF-1 formed more foci in glp-1 mutants compared to WT animals (Figure 2C-D).</p><p>Nevertheless, we extended the model to demonstrate that removal of <italic>ptp-5.1</italic> is required, but not sufficient for activating HSF-1. See Figure 6.</p></body></sub-article></article>