<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">42687</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Tools and Resources</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Brain-wide cellular resolution imaging of Cre transgenic zebrafish lines for functional circuit-mapping</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-123555"><name><surname>Tabor</surname><given-names>Kathryn M</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3696-4584</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-123556"><name><surname>Marquart</surname><given-names>Gregory D</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9811-5372</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-123557"><name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-123558"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Trevor S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-123559"><name><surname>Geoca</surname><given-names>Alexandra K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-123560"><name><surname>Bhandiwad</surname><given-names>Ashwin A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-123561"><name><surname>Subedi</surname><given-names>Abhignya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-123562"><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>Jennifer L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="dataset1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-129894"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>Hannah M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con9"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="dataset1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-123563"><name><surname>Polys</surname><given-names>Nicholas F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con10"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-113228"><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>Harold A</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1966-7801</contrib-id><email>burgessha@mail.nih.gov</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con11"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="dataset1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Division of Developmental Biology</institution><institution>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Bethesda</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Neuroscience and Cognitive Science Program</institution><institution>University of Maryland</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">College Park</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Advanced Research Computing, Department of Computer Science</institution><institution>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Blacksburg</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="dept">Postdoctoral Research Associate Training Program</institution><institution>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Bethesda</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>Indira M</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Northwestern University</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Stainier</surname><given-names>Didier Y</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>Max Planck Institute for Heart and Lung Research</institution><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>08</day><month>02</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e42687</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-10-08"><day>08</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2019-02-07"><day>07</day><month>02</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article, free of all copyright, and may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. The work is made available under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons CC0 public domain dedication</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-42687-v2.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.001</object-id><p>Decoding the functional connectivity of the nervous system is facilitated by transgenic methods that express a genetically encoded reporter or effector in specific neurons; however, most transgenic lines show broad spatiotemporal and cell-type expression. Increased specificity can be achieved using intersectional genetic methods which restrict reporter expression to cells that co-express multiple drivers, such as Gal4 and Cre. To facilitate intersectional targeting in zebrafish, we have generated more than 50 new Cre lines, and co-registered brain expression images with the Zebrafish Brain Browser, a cellular resolution atlas of 264 transgenic lines. Lines labeling neurons of interest can be identified using a web-browser to perform a 3D spatial search (zbbrowser.com). This resource facilitates the design of intersectional genetic experiments and will advance a wide range of precision circuit-mapping studies.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>Cre</kwd><kwd>Gal4</kwd><kwd>intersectional genetics</kwd><kwd>brain atlas</kwd><kwd>registration</kwd><kwd>imaging</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Zebrafish</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100009633</institution-id><institution>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>1ZIAHD008884-04</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>Harold A</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100007263</institution-id><institution>Virginia Tech</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Advanced Research Computing</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Polys</surname><given-names>Nicholas F</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>A new resource of transgenic zebrafish lines facilitates precise targeting of neuronal cell-types within the brain, supported by online software for visualizing transgene expression patterns.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Elucidating the functional circuitry of the brain requires methods to visualize neuronal cell types and to reproducibly control and record activity from identified neurons. Genetically encoded reporters and effectors enable non-invasive manipulations in neurons but are limited by the precision with which they can be targeted. While gene regulatory elements are often exploited to direct transgene expression, very few transgenic lines strongly express reporter genes in a single cell type within a spatially restricted domain. Precise targeting of optogenetic reagents can be achieved using spatially restricted illumination in immobilized or optic-fiber implanted animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aravanis et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Arrenberg et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Wyart et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Zhu et al., 2012</xref>). However, non-invasive genetic methods that confine expression to small groups of neurons enable analysis of behavior in freely moving animals. Such methods include intersectional genetic strategies, where reporter expression is controlled by multiple independently-expressed activators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Dymecki et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Gohl et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>In zebrafish, intersectional control of transgene expression has been achieved by combining the Gal4/UAS and Cre/lox systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Förster et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Satou et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Tabor et al., 2018</xref>). Gal4-Cre intersectional systems take advantage of hundreds of existing Gal4 lines which are already widely used in zebrafish circuit neuroscience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Asakawa et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bergeron et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Scott et al., 2007</xref>), but are limited by the relatively poor repertoire of existing Cre lines, and difficulty in identifying pairs of driver lines that co-express in neurons of interest. The first version of the Zebrafish Brain Browser (ZBB) atlas provided a partial solution to these problems by co-aligning high resolution image stacks of more than 100 transgenic lines, with an accuracy approaching the limit of biological variability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Marquart et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Marquart et al., 2015</xref>). ZBB enabled users to conduct a 3D spatial search for lines with reporter expression in areas of interest and predict the area of intersection between Gal4 and Cre lines, aiding the design of intersectional genetic experiments. However, ZBB software required local installation and only included 9 Cre lines, limiting opportunities for intersectional targeting.</p><p>Here, we describe the ZBB2 atlas, which comprises whole-brain expression patterns for 264 transgenic lines, including 65 Cre lines, and 158 Gal4 lines. We generated more than 100 new enhancer trap lines that express Cre or Gal4 in diverse subsets of neurons, then registered a high resolution image of each to the original ZBB atlas. For 3D visualization of expression patterns and to facilitate spatial searches for experimentally useful lines, we now provide an online interface to the atlas. Collectively, ZBB2 labels almost all cellular regions within the brain and will facilitate the reproducible targeting of neuronal subsets for circuit-mapping studies.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>To accelerate discovery of functional circuits we generated a library of transgenic lines that express Cre in restricted patterns within the brain and built an online 3D atlas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). New Cre lines were generated through an enhancer trap screen: we injected embryos with a Cre vector containing a basal promoter that includes a neuronal-restrictive silencing element to suppress expression outside the nervous system, and tol2 transposon arms for high efficiency transgenesis (<italic>REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bergeron et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kawakami, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Marquart et al., 2015</xref>). In injected G0 embryos, the reporter randomly integrates into the genome such that Cre expression is directed by local enhancer elements. To isolate lines with robust brain expression in relatively restricted domains, we visually screened progeny of G0 adults crossed to the <italic>βactin:Switch</italic> transgenic line that expresses red fluorescent protein (RFP) in cells with Cre (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Horstick et al., 2015</xref>). We retained 52 new lines that express Cre in restricted brain regions at 6 days post-fertilization (dpf), the stage most frequently used for behavioral experiments and circuit-mapping. We then used a confocal microscope to scan brain-wide GFP and RFP fluorescence from <italic>et-Cre, βactin:Switch</italic> larvae at high resolution, aligned the merged signal to the ZBB <italic>βactin:GFP</italic> pattern and applied the resulting transformation matrix to the RFP signal alone. To obtain a representative image of Cre expression, we averaged registered brain scans from 3 to 10 larvae and masked expression outside the brain. Cre lines reported here for the first time are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, and an overview of all 65 Cre lines that can be searched using ZBB2 is summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.002</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Procedure for imaging and co-registering new Cre lines.</title><p>Inset schematics: neuronal-restrictive silencing element (NRSE) sites in the enhancer trap construct are targets for the REST protein, which suppresses Cre expression outside the brain.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42687-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.003</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Cre enhancer trap lines.</title><p>Horizontal maximum projection of 52 new Cre enhancer trap lines, with color indicating depth along the dorsal-ventral dimension (huC counter-label, grey).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42687-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig><p>We previously isolated more than 200 Gal4 lines with expression in subregions of the brain; however, the original ZBB atlas represented only those that showed expression restricted to the nervous system. The subsequent development of a synthetic untranslated region (UTR.zb3) that suppresses non-neuronal expression has mitigated issues associated with Gal4 driving effector genes in non-neuronal tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Marquart et al., 2015</xref>). We therefore imaged 45 additional Gal4 lines in which robust brain expression is accompanied by expression in non-neural tissues. We visualized Gal4 expression using the <italic>UAS:Kaede</italic> transgenic line and registered patterns to ZBB by co-imaging <italic>vglut2a:DsRed</italic> expression. New Gal4 lines reported here are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>. We also aligned 20 high resolution brain scans of Gal4 lines performed by either the Dorsky or Baier laboratories by adapting a method for multi-channel registration of the Z-Brain and ZBB atlases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Förster et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Marquart et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Otsuna et al., 2015</xref>). In total, ZBB2 includes the spatial pattern of expression for 158 Gal4 lines. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref> summarizes all Gal4 enhancer traps generated by our laboratory that can be searched in ZBB2. The relative expression of each transgenic line within 20 µm-side bins is reported in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp3">Supplementary file 3</xref>. In total, ZBB2 describes the expression pattern for 264 transgenic lines, more than doubling the number in the original atlas (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.004</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Gal4 enhancer trap lines.</title><p>Horizontal maximum projection of 45 new Gal4 enhancer trap lines (depth coded; huC counter-label, grey).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42687-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.005</object-id><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Summary of transgenic lines in ZBB2.</title><p>Total numbers of enhancer trap lines, and transgenic lines (made using promoter fragments from genes, or through BAC recombination), broken down by type: Gal4, Cre or fluorescent protein (FP). Right columns total the number of lines where genomic information driving the expression pattern is available. This information inherently exists for transgenic lines, and was derived through integration site mapping for enhancer trap lines.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top"/><th colspan="3" valign="top">All lines (n = 264)</th><th valign="top"/><th colspan="3" valign="top">Mapped (n = 171)</th></tr><tr><th valign="top"/><th valign="top">Gal4</th><th valign="top">Cre</th><th valign="top">FP</th><th valign="top"/><th valign="top">Gal4</th><th valign="top">Cre</th><th valign="top">FP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Enhancer trap</td><td valign="top">138</td><td valign="top">65</td><td valign="top">5</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">96</td><td valign="top">15</td><td valign="top">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Transgenic</td><td valign="top">20</td><td valign="top">0</td><td valign="top">36</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">20</td><td valign="top">0</td><td valign="top">36</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Total</td><td valign="top">158</td><td valign="top">65</td><td valign="top">41</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">116</td><td valign="top">15</td><td valign="top">40</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Enhancer traps randomly integrate into the genome and it is not usually possible to determine the identity of the cells labeled by their spatial pattern of expression alone. However, cell-type information for enhancer trap lines can be inferred from co-localization with reporters whose expression is directed by a defined promoter, or through integration into a bacterial artificial chromosome. ZBB2 contains expression data for 56 such transgenic lines, including reporters for most major neurotransmitters. The relative mean expression intensity for nine major cell-type markers within neuroanatomic. Additional cell-type information in enhancer trap lines may be revealed by integration site mapping, because enhancer traps often recapitulate, at least in part, the expression pattern of genes close to the site of transgene integration. We therefore developed a new method to efficiently map integration sites, using an oligonucleotide to hybridize with the enhancer trap tol2 arms and capture flanking genomic DNA fragments for sequencing (see Materials and methods for detail). We recovered the integration site for 55 Gal4 and Cre enhancer trap lines (detailed in ). Altogether 171 of the lines in ZBB2 either use a defined promoter, or have a known genomic integration site, providing molecular genetic information on cell-type identity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>To assess how useful the lines represented in ZBB2 will be for circuit-mapping studies, we calculated the selectivity of each line. For this, we first estimated the volume of the brain that includes cell bodies — using transgenic markers of cell bodies and neuropil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>) — then calculated the percent of the cell body volume labeled by each line. For Cre lines, median coverage of the cell body volume was 6% (range 0.1% to 48%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B,D</xref>). As we estimate that there are ~92,000 neurons in the six dpf brain (see Materials and methods), this equates to a median of around 5500 neurons per line. In total, 96% of the cellular volume is labeled by at least one Cre line, with an average of 6 lines per voxel. However, Cre lines provide limited access to the midbrain tegmentum, posterior tuberculum and trigeminal ganglion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). Gal4 lines tend to have more restricted expression than Cre lines, with a median coverage of 1% (range 0.02% to 29%,~900 neurons per line). Collectively Gal4 lines label 91% of the cell body volume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C,D</xref>). Salient areas that are not labeled include a rostro-dorsal domain of the optic tectum, the caudal lobe of the cerebellum, and a medial area within rhombomeres 3–4 of the medulla oblongata. Despite Gal4 lines having more restricted expression, few show tightly confined expression, highlighting the importance of intersectional approaches for precise targeting.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.006</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Spatial coverage of Cre and Gal4 enhancer trap lines.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Horizontal (left), coronal (top right), sagittal (bottom right) sections showing <italic>huC:nls-mCar</italic> (cell bodies, red) and <italic>huC:Gal4,UAS:syp-RFP</italic> (neuropil, cyan) from ZBB (huC counter-label, gray), illustrating the separation of cell bodies and neuropil in six dpf brains. (<bold>B–C</bold>) Horizontal sections (at the levels indicated in A) of heat-maps showing the number of <italic>et-Cre</italic> (<bold>B</bold>) and <italic>et-</italic>Gal4 (<bold>C</bold>) lines that label each voxel within the cellular area of the brain (scale bar, right). Voxels that lack coverage indicated in green. Coverage for Cre lines is highest in the pallium (Pa). Gal4 lines conspicuously lack coverage in the anterior optic tectum (TeO) and in a medial zone of the medulla oblongata (MO). (<bold>D</bold>) Histogram of the cellular-region coverage for <italic>et-Cre</italic> (red) and <italic>et-Gal4</italic> (green) lines.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42687-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig><p>We envisaged using Cre lines to select experimentally useful subdomains of Gal4 expression patterns. To test this, we selected pairs of Cre and Gal4 lines with overlapping expression in spatially restricted regions, then analyzed reporter expression in triple transgenic Gal4/Cre/UAS:Switch larvae. As any given brain region likely contains multiple intermingled cell types, Gal4 and Cre lines that appear to overlap, may actually label distinct neurons. Nevertheless, intersectional patterns observed closely matched predicted intersects, labeling relatively small clusters of neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). In general, intersectional expression in individual larvae is more restricted than predicted. In part, this may be because UAS transgenics are susceptible to silencing, reducing the extent of expression.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.007</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Spatially restricted reporter expression in Gal4/Cre intersectional domains.</title><p>Maximum projections for et-Gal4 and et-Cre lines predicted to show co-expression in small domains of neurons, and of the resulting pattern of expression in a triple transgenic et-Gal4, et-Cre, UAS:KillSwitch larva. Scale bar 100 µm. (<bold>A</bold>) Horizontal (top) and sagittal (bottom) maximum projections for (left to right): <italic>y318-Gal4</italic> expression, <italic>y481-Cre</italic> expression, predicted reporter distribution in cells that co-express <italic>y318</italic> and <italic>y481,</italic> actual RFP expression in an individual <italic>y318, y481, UAS:KillSwitch</italic> larva. Closed arrowhead indicates the cerebellar eminentia granularis (Eg), which is labeled in both lines and the intersect. Open arrowhead indicates descending fiber tract from Eg neurons. (<bold>B</bold>) As for (<bold>A</bold>) with <italic>y393-Gal4</italic> and <italic>y528-Cre</italic> lines. Closed arrowheads indicate the lateral habenula (black) and trigeminal ganglion (grey). Open arrowhead indicates central projections from the trigeminal ganglion.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42687-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig><p>For the first release of the ZBB atlas, we provided downloadable <italic>Brain Browser</italic> software that allowed users to conduct a 3D spatial search for transgenic lines that label neurons within a specific Z-Brain defined neuroanatomic region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Randlett et al., 2015</xref>) or selected volume. For ZBB2, we have imported all the new lines into the original <italic>Brain Browser</italic>. However, recognizing that requiring a locally installed IDL runtime platform posed a limit to accessibility, we implemented an online version that can be accessed using a web-browser (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zbbrowser.com">http://zbbrowser.com</ext-link>). The online version includes key features of the original <italic>Brain Browser</italic>, including 3D spatial search, prediction of the area of intersectional expression between selected lines, partial/maximal/3D projections, information about the neuroanatomical identity of any selected voxel and ability to load user-generated image data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>). Additionally, the online version features an integrated virtual reality viewer for Google cardboard. We used X3DOM libraries to achieve rapid volume rendering and enable users to select data resolution that best matches their connection speed, so that the browser-based implementation remains highly responsive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Arbelaiz et al., 2017b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Arbelaiz et al., 2017a</xref>). Both local and web-based versions include hyper-links to PubMed, UCSC Genome Browser and Zfin, so that users can quickly retrieve publications describing each line, its integration site, and ordering information, respectively.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.008</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Web-browser based edition of the Zebrafish Brain Browser with key functions annotated.</title><p>Panel size can be adjusted to best fit screen dimensions with the Settings menu.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42687-fig6-v2.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The ZBB2 atlas provides cellular resolution imaging data for 65 Cre lines, and 158 Gal4 lines, enabling small clusters of neurons to be genetically addressed through intersectional targeting. To aid in the design of such experiments, we have implemented a web-based interface that allows users to perform a spatial search for lines that express Cre or Gal4 in any selected 3D volume, and thereby identify transgenic lines for intersectional visualization or manipulation of selected neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Tabor et al., 2018</xref>). We anticipate that the ZBB2 lines will also facilitate structural mapping of the zebrafish brain because many strongly label discrete neuroanatomical entities.</p><p>In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, intersectional genetic targeting is often achieved using 'split' systems (Gal4, lexA and Q) in which the DNA-binding domain and transactivation domain of a transcription factor are separately expressed ensuring that activity is reconstituted only in neurons that express both protein domains during the same time interval (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Pfeiffer et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Ting et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Wei et al., 2012</xref>). We did not pursue this approach because of the investment needed to create and maintain numerous 'half' lines which can not be used alone. In contrast, Gal4 and Cre lines are independently useful and Cre lines can be used intersectionally with hundreds of existing zebrafish Gal4 lines. Several intersectional reporter lines have already been generated to visualize cells that co-express Cre and Gal4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Förster et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Satou et al., 2013</xref>). In addition, the <italic>UAS:KillSwitch</italic> line enables selective ablation of neurons that co-express Gal4 and Cre, and the <italic>UAS:DoubleSwitch</italic> line sparsely labels neurons within a Gal4/Cre co-expression domain for morphological reconstruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Tabor et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>New Gal4 and Cre lines described here were generated through enhancer trap screening, a high throughput method that facilitates the isolation of strongly expressing transgenic reporters in diverse anatomical regions and cell types. An alternative is to use CRISPR or TALEN based methods to insert transgenes into genes known to mark useful cell types or anatomical regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Auer et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Kimura et al., 2014</xref>). These methods are moderate throughput, and have the advantage of providing more reliable cell type information on the resulting transgene expression patterns. Limitations are that expression from an endogenous locus may not be sufficient to drive experimentally useful levels of Gal4 or Cre, and that an insertion may depress expression of the endogenous protein from the targeted allele. Given that many neurological disorders are associated with haploinsufficiency, reporter lines generated in this way may therefore perturb brain development or function. BAC transgenesis is a third method that has been widely used to make new Gal4 and Cre lines, that also exploits known gene expression patterns, while avoiding potentially disruptive insertions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Förster et al., 2017</xref>). However BAC transgenesis is low throughput, and as for targeted insertions, can not guarantee robust reporter expression. Thus future efforts at generating new transgenic reporters will likely be best served through enhancer traps and CRISPR-mediated transgene insertion.</p><p>A limitation of the Cre system is that insufficient expression may lead to stochastic activity at target loxP sites and consequent mosaic reporter expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Förster et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Schmidt-Supprian and Rajewsky, 2007</xref>). We therefore only retained lines with strong expression across multiple animals. Conversely Cre is toxic at high levels — in some cases, mosaic expression may be due to the death of a subset of cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bersell et al., 2013</xref>). While we cannot readily assess the toxicity of our lines, confounding effects can be experimentally addressed with the proper controls. Our enhancer trap Cre lines tend to have broader expression than Gal4 lines, likely because (1) Cre expression in progenitor cells labels all offspring, expanding the domain of expression, and (2) switch reporters remain active after transient Cre expression, whereas Gal4 must be continually expressed to drive UAS reporters. Occasionally we have observed UAS:Switch expression in neurons outside the domain of Cre expression in the ZBB2 atlas. This may be because the 14xUAS-E1b promoter is stronger than the β-actin promoter present in the switch reporter used to build the atlas. Additionally, most brain regions contain multiple cell types with biological variability in their precise position. Thus predicted overlapping expression based on co-registered brain scans must be experimentally verified.</p><p>The ZBB2 atlas advances mapping of the zebrafish brain at single cell resolution by comprehensively describing the cellular-resolution pattern of brain expression for 264 transgenic lines and providing a user-friendly web-browser based interface for searching and visualizing the expression in each. New Cre and Gal4 enhancer trap lines are freely available and we anticipate will advance circuit-mapping studies by providing essential reagents for intersectional targeting of neurons. We expect that this database and the associated transgenic lines will drive exploration of structure/function relations in the vertebrate brain.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Reagent type <break/>(species) or <break/>resource</th><th valign="bottom">Designation</th><th valign="bottom">Source or <break/>reference</th><th valign="bottom">Identifiers</th><th valign="bottom">Additional <break/>information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y234</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:23100441</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-121114–10</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y234Et; Et(SCP1:Gal4ff)y234</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y236</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:23293587</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-130214–2</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y236Et; Et(REx2-cfos:kGal4ff)y236</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y237</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:23293587</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-130214–3</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y237Et; Et(REx2-cfos:kGal4ff)y237</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y241</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:24203884</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-131007–1</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y241Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:kGal4ff)y241</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y242</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-130214–5</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y242Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:Gal4)y242</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y244</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:23293587</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-130214–7</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y244Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:kGal4ff)y244</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y252</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:25224259</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-151117–1</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y252Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:kGal4ff)y252</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y264</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:24848468</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-141111–2</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y264Et; Et(SCP1:Gal4ff)y264</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y265</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–10</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y265Et; Et(SCP1:Gal4ff)y265</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y269</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:24848468</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-141111–3</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y269Et; Et(REx2-cfos:kGal4ff)y269</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y270</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:24848468</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-141111–4</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y270Et; Et(REx2-cfos:kGal4ff)y270</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y271</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:25628360</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-150721–4</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y271Et; Et(SCP1:kGal4ff)y271</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y274</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–11</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y274Et; Et(SCP1:Gal4ff)y274</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y348</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–12</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y348Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:kGal4ff)y348</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y387</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–14</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y387Et; Et(tph2:Gal4ff)y387</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y394</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–16</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y394Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y394</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y396</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:26635538</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-170320–13</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y396Et; Et(SCP1:Gal4ff)y396</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y412</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–20</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y412Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y412</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y416</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–21</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y416Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y416</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y420</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:26635538</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–23</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y420Et; Et(REx2-cfos:Gal4ff)y420</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y421</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–24</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y421Et; Et(REx2-cfos:Gal4)y421</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y433</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-151125–10</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y433Et; Et(cfos:kGal4ff)y433</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y436</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-151125–13</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y436Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y436</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y441</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–27</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y441Et; <break/>Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y441</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y444</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–28</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y444Et; Et(SCP1:Gal4ff)y444</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y445</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–29</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y445Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y445</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y456</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–30</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y456Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y456</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y457</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–31</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y457Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y457</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y458</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–32</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y458Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y458</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y459</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–33</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y459Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y459</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y465</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–34</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y465Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer)y465</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y467</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–35</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y467Et; Et(tph2:Gal4ff)y467</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y468</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–36</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y468Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y468</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y469</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–37</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y469Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y469</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y470</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–38</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y470Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:Gal4ff)y470</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y471</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–39</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y471Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:Gal4ff)y471</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y472</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–40</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y472Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:Gal4ff)y472</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y473</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–41</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y473Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y473</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y477</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–43</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y477Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y477</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y478</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–44</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y478Et; Et(attP-REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer-attP)y478</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y479</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–45</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y479Et; Et(attP-REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer-attP)y479</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y480</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–46</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y480Et; Et(attP-REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer-attP)y480</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y481</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–47</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y481Et; Et(attP-REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer-attP)y481</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>) <break/></td><td valign="bottom">y483</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–48</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y483Et; Et(attP-REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer-attP)y483</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y484</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–49</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y484Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer)y484</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y485</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–50</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y485Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y485</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y486</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–51</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y486Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y486</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y487</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–52</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y487Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y487</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y488</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–53</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y488Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y488</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>) <break/></td><td valign="bottom">y489</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–54</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y489Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y489</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y490</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–55</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y490Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y490</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y492</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB- <break/>ALT-180717–56</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y492Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y492</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y493</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–57</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y493Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y493</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y494</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–58</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y494Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y494</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y495</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–59</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y495Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y495</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y511</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–60</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y511Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y511</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y512</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–61</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y512Et; Et(SCP1:Gal4)y512</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y514</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–63</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y514Et; Et(REx2-cfos:kGal4ff)y514</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y515</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–64</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y515Et; Et(REx2-cfos:kGal4ff)y515</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y519</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–65</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y519Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer)y519</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y520</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–66</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y520Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer)y520</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y521</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–67</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y521Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y521</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y523</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–68</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y523Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y523</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y524</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–69</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y524Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer)y524</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y526</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–70</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y526Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y526</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y528</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–71</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y528Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y528</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y532</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–72</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y532Et; Et(cfos:Gal4ff)y532</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y533</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–73</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y533Et; Et(SCP1:Gal4ff)y533</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y541</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–74</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y541Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y541</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y542</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–75</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y542Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y542</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y543</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–76</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y543Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y543</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y544</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–77</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y544Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y544</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y545</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–78</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y545Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y545</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y546</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–79</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y546Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y546</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y547</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–80</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y547Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y547</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y548</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–81</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y548Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y548</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y549</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–82</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y549Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y549</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y550</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–83</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y550Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y550</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y551</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–84</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y551Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y551</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y552</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–85</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y552Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y552</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y554</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–87</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y554Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y554</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y555</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–88</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y555Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y555</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y556</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–89</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y556Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y556</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y557</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–90</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y557Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y557</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y558</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–91</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y558Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y558</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y559</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–92</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y559Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y559</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y564</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–93</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y564Et; Et(SCP1:Gal4ff)y564</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y565</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–94</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y565Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:Gal4ff)y565</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y566</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–95</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y566Et; Et(REx2-cfos:Gal4ff)y566</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y567</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–96</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y567Et; Et(REx2-cfos:Gal4ff)y567</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y568</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–97</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y568Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3)y568</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y569</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–98</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y569Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y569</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y570</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–99</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y570Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y570</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y571</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–100</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y571Et; Et(R2R6-hoxa2-CNE-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer)y571</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y574</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–101</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y574Et; Et(REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre)y574</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y575</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–102</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y575Et; Et(cfos:Gal4)y575</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">y576</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-180717–103</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN symbol:y576Et; Et(cfos:Gal4)y576</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">βactin:Switch; y272</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:25628360</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-150721–8</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">vglut2a:DsRed; nns14</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:22302816</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-110413–5</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">UAS:KillSwitch; y518</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:30078569</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-181218–5</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">UAS:Kaede; s1999t</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:17335798</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-070314–1</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td valign="bottom">elavl3:h2b-GCaMP6; jf5</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:25068735</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ALT-141023–2</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td>Recombinant <break/>DNA reagent</td><td>REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer (plasmid)</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:26635538</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ETCONSTRCT-151102–1</td><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td>Recombinant <break/>DNA reagent</td><td valign="bottom">REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ETCONSTRCT-180514–2</td><td valign="bottom">Progenitors:REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer (plasmid)</td></tr><tr><td>Recombinant <break/>DNA reagent</td><td valign="bottom">REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer.zf3 (plasmid)</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ETCONSTRCT-180518–1</td><td valign="bottom">Progenitors:REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer (plasmid)</td></tr><tr><td>Recombinant <break/>DNA reagent</td><td valign="bottom">attP-REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer-attP</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ETCONSTRCT-151102–2</td><td valign="bottom">Progenitors:REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer (plasmid)</td></tr><tr><td>Recombinant <break/>DNA reagent</td><td valign="bottom">R2R6-hoxa2-CNE-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">ZFIN:ZDB-ETCONSTRCT-180514–1</td><td valign="bottom">Progenitors:REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer (plasmid)</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td valign="bottom">tol2-arrm pulldown oligonucleotide</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom">5-<named-content content-type="sequence">CTCAAGTGAAAGTACAAGTACTTAGGGAAAATTTTACTCAATTAAAAGTAAAAGTATCTGGCTAGAATCTTACTTGAGTAAAAGTAAAAAAGTACTCCATTAAAATTGTACTTGAGTATT</named-content></td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td valign="bottom">tol2-arrm pulldown oligonucleotide</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom">5-<named-content content-type="sequence">TGTAATTAAGTAAAAGTAAAAGTATTGATTTTTAATTGTACTCAAGTAAAGTAAAAATCCCCAAAAATAATACTTAAGTACAGTAATCAAGTAAAATTACTCAAGTACTTTACACCTCTG</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Software</td><td valign="bottom">Advanced Normalization Tools</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:17659998</td><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Software</td><td valign="bottom">Zebrafish Brain Browser (desktop)</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:26635538</td><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom">Download at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://science.nichd.nih.gov/confluence/display/burgess/Brain+Browser">https://science.nichd.nih.gov/confluence/display/burgess/Brain+Browser</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Software</td><td valign="bottom">Zebrafish Brain Browser (online)</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">GitHub:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/BurgessLab/ZebrafishBrainBrowser">BurgessLab/ZebrafishBrainBrowser</ext-link></td><td valign="bottom">zbbrowser.com; Githhub hosts javascript code using X3DOM to render image files</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Software</td><td valign="bottom">ImageJ</td><td valign="bottom">PMID:22930834</td><td valign="bottom"/><td valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td valign="bottom">Other</td><td valign="bottom">Confocal images for ZBB2 lines</td><td valign="bottom">This paper</td><td valign="bottom">Dryad:doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.tk467n8">10.5061/dryad.tk467n8</ext-link></td><td valign="bottom">Compressed archives containing 16-bit NIFTI format scans of individual larvae</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Husbandry</title><p>Zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) were maintained on a Tubingen long fin strain background. Larval zebrafish were raised on 14/10 hr light/dark cycle at 28°C in E3h medium (5 mM NaCl, 0.17 mM KCl, 0.33 mM CaCl2, 0.33 mM MgSO4, 1.5 mM HEPES, pH 7.3) with 300 µM N-Phenylthiourea (PTU, Sigma) to suppress melanogenesis for imaging. Experiments were conducted with larvae at 6 days post fertilization (dpf), before sex differentiation. Experimental procedures were approved by the NICHD animal care and use committee.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Zebrafish lines</title><p>Enhancer trap lines that express Cre (<italic>et-Cre</italic> lines) were initially isolated through enhancer trap screening using a tol2 vector containing a REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre-2a-Cer cassette (286 adult fish screened) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Marquart et al., 2015</xref>). Although the fluorescent protein Cerulean is co-expressed with Cre in this vector, it was rarely strong enough to visualize directly, and we instead screened using the <italic>βactin:Switch</italic> transgenic line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Horstick et al., 2015</xref>). Thus subsequently, we removed the 2a-Cer cassette from the enhancer trap vector for generating new lines and injected a vector with a REx2-SCP1:BGi-Cre cassette (75 adult fish screened). At least 50 (usually over 100) offspring of injected fish were visually screened for RFP fluorescence from the <italic>βactin:Switch (Tg(actb2:loxP-eGFP-loxP-ly-TagRFPT)y272)</italic> reporter line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Horstick et al., 2015</xref>). As around 10% of injected animals transmitted more than a single expression pattern, likely reflecting several integration loci, we bred each line for multiple generations to isolate a single heritable transgene. Gal4 lines newly described here have been maintained for at least seven generations, in all cases with the UAS:Kaede reporter for visualizing expression. New Cre lines have been maintained for at least three generations, with the <italic>βactin:Switch</italic> reporter. Because we only retained lines with restricted areas of brain expression, we ultimately kept lines from around 20% of injected fish. For maintenance, Cre lines were crossed to fish heterozygous for the <italic>βactin:Switch</italic> transgene. Outcrossing to <italic>βactin:Switch</italic> was necessary because, as in other systems, leaky Cre expression recombines lox sites that are transmitted through the same gamete (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Schmidt-Supprian and Rajewsky, 2007</xref>). Consequently, in clutches from <italic>et-Cre;βactin:Switch</italic> crossed to <italic>βactin:Switch</italic>, we discarded ~25% of embryos that showed ubiquitous RFP expression due to complete recombination of the Switch reporter in gametes also containing the Cre transgene. We also imaged previously described Cre lines with rhombomere-specific expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Tabor et al., 2018</xref>). Gal4 enhancer trap lines were isolated as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bergeron et al., 2012</xref>). UAS reporter transgenes are susceptible to silencing leading to variegated expression. To minimize silencing, we raise single insertion UAS reporters with a broadly expressed Gal4 transgene. In each generation, we outcross to wildtype stock, and raise only double transgenic individuals with the brightest and most complete expression (typically around 20% of fluorescent protein positive embryos).</p><p>Other zebrafish lines in this study were: <italic>UAS:Kaede (Tg(UAS-E1b:Kaede)s1999t</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Davison et al., 2007</xref>)<italic>, UAS:KillSwitch (Tg(14xUAS-E1b:BGi-lox-GFP-sv40-loxepNTR-TagRFPT)y518)</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Tabor et al., 2018</xref>), <italic>y379-Cre</italic> and <italic>y484-Cre</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Marquart et al., 2017</xref>)<italic>, vglut2a:DsRed (TgBAC(slc17a6b:loxP-DsRed-loxP-GFP)nns9) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Satou et al., 2013</xref>)</italic>, <italic>Tg(gata1:dsRed)sd2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Traver et al., 2003</xref>), <italic>Tg(−4.9sox10:EGFP)ba2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Wada et al., 2005</xref>), <italic>Tg(−8.4neurog1:GFP)sb1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Blader et al., 2003</xref>), <italic>Tg(kctd15a:GFP)y534</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Heffer et al., 2017</xref>), <italic>Tg(pou4f3:gap43-GFP)s356t</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Xiao et al., 2005</xref>)<italic>, Et(−1.5hsp70l:Gal4-VP16)s1156t</italic> and <italic>Et(fos:Gal4-VP16)s1181t</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Scott and Baier, 2009</xref>), <italic>TgBAC(neurod:EGFP)nl1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Obholzer et al., 2008</xref>)<italic>, Tg(mnx1:GFP)ml2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Flanagan-Steet et al., 2005</xref>), and <italic>y271-Gal4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Horstick et al., 2015</xref>)</italic>. For counting neurons in the brain, we used <italic>huC:h2b-GCaMP6</italic> (<italic>Tg(elavl3:h2b-GCaMP6)jf5</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Vladimirov et al., 2014</xref>), which has multiple transgene integrations, minimizing effects of variable expression and silencing.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Brain imaging and processing</title><p>For imaging, six dpf larvae were embedded in 1.5–3.5% agarose in E3h and oriented dorsal to the objective. Each larval brain was scanned in two image stacks (anterior and posterior halves, 1 × 1×2 µm resolution) with an inverted Leica TCS-SP5 II confocal with a 25X, 0.95 NA objective, while adjusting laser power during scans to compensate for intensity loss with depth. Gal4 expression was visualized using <italic>UAS:Kaede</italic> and Cre expression using RFP expression from <italic>βactin:Switch.</italic> Color channels were usually acquired simultaneously and crosstalk removed in post-processing using a Leica dye separation algorithm. Substacks were connected using the pairwise stitching plugin in ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Preibisch et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Schneider et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>Image registration was performed using affine and diffeomorphic algorithms in ANTs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Avants et al., 2011</xref>) with parameters optimized for live embryonic zebrafish brain scans that produce alignments with an accuracy of approximately one cell diameter (8 µm) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Marquart et al., 2017</xref>). For registration, each image stack required a reference image previously registered to the ZBB coordinate system. Reference channels were <italic>vglut2a:DsRed</italic> for Gal4 lines and <italic>βactin:Switch</italic> GFP for Cre lines. Other transgenic lines and patterns were registered using either <italic>vglut2a:dsRed</italic> or <italic>vglut2a:GFP</italic> where appropriate. For Cre lines, we merged the <italic>βactin:Switch</italic> GFP and RFP signals into a combined pattern to provide a channel for registration. We then applied the resulting transformation matrix to the RFP channel alone. Next, we averaged registered brain images from at least three larvae per line, using the ANTs <italic>AverageImages</italic> command, to create a representative image of each line. Mean images were masked to remove expression outside the brain, except where inner ear hair cells or neuromasts were labeled. Next, we normalized intensity to saturate the top 0.01% of pixels, and downsampled to 8-bit to reduce file size and facilitate distribution. We manually defined fluorescent intensity thresholds for each line that best distinguished cellular expression from neuropil or background to facilitate spatial search for lines that express in selected cell populations. Mean images were also aligned to Z-Brain using a previously described bridging transformation matrix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Marquart et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Because registration using the <italic>βactin:Switch</italic> bridging channel proved more accurate than our previous bridging registration with <italic>HuC:Cer</italic>, we re-imaged and registered the Cre lines recovered in our pilot screen. Gal4 lines generated and imaged by the Dorsky lab (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Otsuna et al., 2015</xref>) were registered using two channels: the nuclear counter-stain channel (TO-PRO−3) and immunolabeling for myosin heavy chain, aligned to <italic>HuC:nls-mCar</italic> and <italic>tERK</italic> in ZBB respectively. We also used multichannel registration to align brain scans performed by the Baier lab (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Förster et al., 2017</xref>), taking advantage of three expression patterns present in both datasets: v<italic>glut2a:dsRed</italic>, <italic>isl2b:GFP</italic> and <italic>gad1b:GFP</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Integration site mapping</title><p>To efficiently map enhancer trap integration sites we extracted genomic DNA from embryos from each line (Qiagen DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit) and generated a barcoded library. We hybridized the library to biotinylated 120 bp primers (IDT ultramers) designed against the tol2 sequence arms and enriched for genomic integration sites using avidin-pulldown. Enriched libraries were combined into 15 pools such that each pool contained a unique combination of five transgenic lines and each line was exclusively represented in two pools. Pooled libraries were sequenced using an Illumina MiSeq (Illumina) which produced 250 bp paired-end reads. Reads were aligned against the biotinylated primer sequence, then unique sequences within each read subsequently aligned to a zebrafish reference genome (danRer10). Sequences common to all pools were assumed to be off-target and removed from analysis. Remaining reads from each pool were cross-referenced to the combination of embryos in each pool. Regions that had high and specific enrichment in both pools containing DNA from a particular sample were assigned as candidate insertion sites for that sample. To validate this procedure, we confirmed the map position for four lines through direct PCR genotyping.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Expression analysis</title><p>To assess the selectivity of transgene expression, we manually set an intensity threshold for each line to distinguish cell body labeling from background, and calculated the proportion of voxels in the total cell body volume with a super-threshold signal. In assessing total brain coverage by the Cre library, we excluded <italic>y457-Cre</italic> which has extremely broad (possibly pan-neuronal) expression. To quantitatively describe transgene expression patterns, we created 20 × 20 × 20 µm cubic bins (total 1804 bins) that were each entirely within the left hemisphere of the brain. For each line, we measured the mean expression within each bin and its corresponding volume on the right hemisphere. The resulting 1804 element vector was re-scaled in the range 0 to 1.0 to describe the relative intensity of transgene expression in each bin. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp3">Supplementary file 3</xref> reports these values together with the location of center voxel for each bin (Horizontal: dorsal to ventral; Transverse: Anterior to Posterior; Sagittal: Left to Right). In the downloadable version of ZBB2, this position can be recalled by using View → Jump to Frame, then entering the coordinates provided in first three columns in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp3">Supplementary file 3</xref> (e.g. 230, 90, 210 to access the center position for the first volume in the Table).</p><p>To estimate the total number of cells at six dpf, we dissected brains and counted dissociated cells using a cell sorter, yielding a total of 124700 ± 2200 cells per brain (mean and standard error, N = 9), including mature and immature neurons, glia and non-neural cells (e.g. connective tissue and vasculature).</p><p>For this procedure, brains were dissected at room temperature in 1x PBS (K-D Medical), dissociated in papain (Papain Dissociation System, Worthington Biochemical) by incubation in 20 U/mL papain for 20 min then triturated and 0.005% DNAse added. The final volume was adjusted to 200 µL in DMEM fluorobrite (Gibco) and immediately counted using a BD FACSCalibur (BD Biosciences), using a custom gate to include single cells in the forward and side scattered area. To minimize cell death, the entire process was completed within 45 min per brain.</p><p>We estimated the number of differentiated neurons by manually counting fluorescently labeled post-mitotic neurons in brain images. For this, we first imaged <italic>huC:h2b-GCaMP6</italic> transgenic brains at high-resolution (0.5 × 0.5 × 0.5 μm per voxel). In this line, nuclear-localized GCaMP fluorescence provides a discrete signal that facilitates identification of single neurons even in dense regions. We assigned all voxels in the brain to five neuronal-density bins based on the ratio of <italic>huC:nls-mCar</italic> (somas), and <italic>huC:Gal4, UAS:syp-RFP</italic> (synapses; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>) and identified five representative volumes (30 × 30 × 30 μm each) for each of the five bins. We then counted neurons in <italic>huC:h2b-GCaMP6</italic> brain scans in each of the 25 volumes. Finally, we scaled the mean number of neurons in each bin by the relative fraction of the brain that each bin covers to obtain an estimate of the total neuron number. Using this procedure, we estimated that there are 92,000 ± 3000 mature neurons in the six dpf brain (N = 3 larvae).</p><p>To analyze the regional distribution of cell types based on molecular marker expression, we calculated the mean transgene expression intensity for 72 manually annotated anatomical structures (Z-Brain, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp4">Supplementary file 4</xref>) and for 168 computational defined brain regions (subset of Pajevic 180 regions, excluding narrow regions on the perimeter of the brain, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp5">Supplementary file 5</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Gupta et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Randlett et al., 2015</xref>). For each line analyzed, voxel expression values were scaled 0–1, and means thus reflect the relative intensity of expression for regions within each maker and can not be compared between markers.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Zebrafish Brain Browser software</title><p>The lines scanned and registered here were incorporated into the locally run Zebrafish Brain Browser, which requires downloading and installing the free IDL runtime environment. ZBB2 (including software and full resolution datasets) can be downloaded from our website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://science.nichd.nih.gov/confluence/display/burgess/Brain+Browser">https://science.nichd.nih.gov/confluence/display/burgess/Brain+Browser</ext-link>).</p><p>To increase accessibility we also implemented an online version of ZBB2 that does not require downloading, and runs in any javascript-enabled web-browser (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zbbrowser.com">http://zbbrowser.com</ext-link>). We used Bootstrap (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://getbootstrap.com/">http://getbootstrap.com/</ext-link>) for interface design and jQuery for event-handling (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jquery.com/">https://jquery.com/</ext-link>). For rendering of 2D slices and 3D projections, we used X3DOM, a powerful set of open-source 3D graphics libraries for web development which integrates the X3D file format into the HTML5 DOM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Behr et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Congote, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">John et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Polys and Wood, 2012</xref>). ZBB2 uses X3DOM’s built in <italic>MPRVolumeStyle</italic> and <italic>BoundaryEnhancementVolumeStyle</italic> functions to render 2D image files (texture atlases) in 3D space. The <italic>MPRVolumeStyle</italic> is used for the X, Y and Z slicer views to display a single slice from a 3D volume along a defined axis. We modified X3DOM source code for this volume style to support additional features including color selection, contrast and brightness controls, rendering of crosshairs, spatial search boxes and intersections between selected lines. The <italic>BoundaryEnhancementVolumeStyle</italic> renders the 3D projection. We also modified this function's source code, including additions of color, contrast, and brightness values. Other minor changes were made to the X3DOM libraries including a hardcoded override to allow additive blending of line colors. The online ZBB2 loads images of each line as a single 2D texture atlas. Image volumes for each line were converted to a montage, downsampling by taking every 4th plane in the z-dimension, and to 0.25, 0.5, and 0.75 their original size for low, medium, and high resolutions respectively to ensure rapid loading time. Texture atlas images were then referenced using X3DOM’s ‘ImageTextureAtlas’ node, and its ‘numberOfSlices’, ‘slicesOverX’, and ‘slicesOverY’ attributes were specified as 100, 10, and 10, respectively. These atlases were then referenced by ‘VolumeData’ nodes, along with an <italic>MPRVolumeStyle</italic> or <italic>BoundaryEnhancementVolumeStyle</italic> node, to build the volumes visible on the screen.</p><p>To implement the 3D spatial search in the online edition of ZBB2, we first binarized and 4x-downsampled the resolution of each line. The data for each line was then parsed into a single array (width, height, depth). We compressed adjacent binary values into a single byte using bit shifting operators, downsampling the data once again by eight times. While greatly downsized, the entire dataset was still much too large to quickly download. We therefore fragmented the array for each line into 8 × 8×8 blocks of 64 bytes each, and concatenated blocks for every line, creating a single array of around 17 kb for a specific sub-volume of the brain. After the user defines the search volume, relevant volume fragments are downloaded and searched. Data from each fragment file is passed to a JavaScript Web Worker, allowing each file to be searched in a separate thread. This procedure facilitates minimal search times, with the main limitation being that thousands of binary files must be regenerated whenever a new line is added to the library.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Quantification and statistical analysis</title><p>Analysis was performed with IDL (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.harrisgeospatial.com/SoftwareTechnology/IDL.aspx">http://www.harrisgeospatial.com/SoftwareTechnology/IDL.aspx</ext-link>), Gnumeric (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://projects.gnome.org/gnumeric/">http://projects.gnome.org/gnumeric/</ext-link>) and Matlab (Mathworks).</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Resource sharing</title><p>Most enhancer trap lines are available from Zebrafish International Resource Center (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://zebrafish.org">https://zebrafish.org</ext-link>), with all others available from the authors upon request. Registered individual confocal brain scans can be downloaded from Dryad (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.tk467n8">https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.tk467n8</ext-link>). Brain browser javascript code can be downloaded from GitHub (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hurt et al., 2018</xref>; copy archived at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/ZebrafishBrainBrowser">https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/ZebrafishBrainBrowser</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Steven Coon and James Iben from the NICHD Molecular Genomics Core and Lisa Williams-Simons from the NICHD FACS core for vital assistance. We are grateful to Jeremy Swan for help with interface design. This study utilized the high-performance computational capabilities of the Biowulf Linux cluster at the National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://hpc.nih.gov/">https://hpc.nih.gov/</ext-link>). The authors acknowledge Advanced Research Computing at Virginia Tech for providing computational resources and technical support that have contributed to the results reported within this paper (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arc.vt.edu">http://www.arc.vt.edu</ext-link>). This work was supported by the Intramural Research Program of the <italic>Eunice Kennedy Shriver</italic> National Institute for Child Health and Human Development.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Data curation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Software, Writing—original draft</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Data curation, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>Formal analysis, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con9"><p>Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con10"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Software, Supervision</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con11"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Software, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Validation, Investigation, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Animal experimentation: This study was performed in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. All of the animals were handled according to approved institutional animal care and use committee (IACUC) protocols (#15-039) of the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.009</object-id><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Summary of Cre lines generated by our lab, available in ZBB2.</title><p>Integration site given in zv10 coordinates, transgene orientation indicated in brackets.</p><p>Integration sites inside genes are annotated, or nearest Refseq gene within ~50 kb indicated.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-42687-supp1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.010</object-id><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>Summary of all Gal4 lines generated by our lab, available in ZBB2.</title><p>Coordinate system for mapped lines is either zv9 or zv10 as indicated.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-42687-supp2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.011</object-id><label>Supplementary file 3.</label><caption><title>Transgene expression intensity in small volumes within the brain.</title><p>First three columns provide central coordinates of 20 × 20 × 20 µm volumes in the ZBB reference volume (Horizontal plane: distance in microns from the dorsal surface of the volume; Transverse plane: distance from the anterior edge of the volume; Sagittal plane: distance from the left side of the volume). Additional columns indicate the mean expression per bin of each transgene after scaling voxels from 0 to 1.0.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-42687-supp3-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.012</object-id><label>Supplementary file 4.</label><caption><title>Cell-type expression levels in neuroanatomical regions.</title><p>Mean expression levels of transgenic markers in neuroanatomical regions defined by Z-Brain. Cell type markers: Glutamatergic (<italic>vglut2a:DsRed</italic>), GABAergic (<italic>gad1b:GFP</italic>), Glycinergic (<italic>glyt2:GFP</italic>), Catecholaminergic (<italic>vmat2:GFP</italic>), Serotonergic, (<italic>pet1:GFP</italic>), Cholinergic (<italic>chata:Gal4</italic>), Dopaminergic (<italic>th:Gal4</italic>), Hypocretin (<italic>hcrt:RFP</italic>), and glia (<italic>gfap:GFP</italic>).</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-42687-supp4-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.013</object-id><label>Supplementary file 5.</label><caption><title>Cell-type expression levels in neuroanatomical regions.</title><p>Mean expression levels of transgenic markers in computationally defined neuroanatomical regions.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-42687-supp5-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.014</object-id><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-42687-transrepform-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Registered individual confocal brain scans have been deposited in Dryad <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.tk467n8">https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.tk467n8</ext-link>. Brain browser javascript code can be downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/BurgessLab/ZebrafishBrainBrowser">https://github.com/BurgessLab/ZebrafishBrainBrowser</ext-link>; copy archived at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/ZebrafishBrainBrowser">https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/ZebrafishBrainBrowser</ext-link>.</p><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><element-citation id="dataset1" publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabor</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquart</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Geoca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhandiwad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannah</surname><given-names>M Rose</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennifer</surname><given-names>L Sinclair</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><data-title>Brain-wide cellular resolution imaging of Cre transgenic zebrafish lines for functional circuit-mapping</data-title><source>Dryad Digital Repository</source><pub-id assigning-authority="Dryad" pub-id-type="doi">10.5061/dryad.tk467n8</pub-id></element-citation></p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aravanis</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Meltzer</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogri</surname> <given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Deisseroth</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>An optical neural interface: in vivo control of rodent motor cortex with integrated fiberoptic and optogenetic technology</article-title><source>Journal of Neural Engineering</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>S143</fpage><lpage>S156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1741-2560/4/3/S02</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17873414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arbelaiz</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabongo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>García-Alonso</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017a</year><article-title>X3DOM volume rendering component for web content developers</article-title><source>Multimedia Tools and Applications</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>13425</fpage><lpage>13454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11042-016-3743-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arbelaiz</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabongo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Polys</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>García-Alonso</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017b</year><article-title><italic>Community-Driven extensions to the X3D volume rendering component</italic></article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the 22nd International Conference on 3D Web Technology</conf-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3055624.3075945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arrenberg</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Bene</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Optical control of zebrafish behavior with halorhodopsin</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>17968</fpage><lpage>17973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0906252106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asakawa</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suster</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizusawa</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagayoshi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotani</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Urasaki</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishimoto</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Genetic dissection of neural circuits by Tol2 transposon-mediated Gal4 gene and enhancer trapping in zebrafish</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>1255</fpage><lpage>1260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0704963105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18202183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Auer</surname> <given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Duroure</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>De Cian</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Concordet</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Bene</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Highly efficient CRISPR/Cas9-mediated knock-in in zebrafish by homology-independent DNA repair</article-title><source>Genome Research</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.161638.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24179142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avants</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tustison</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gee</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>A reproducible evaluation of ANTs similarity metric performance in brain image registration</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>2033</fpage><lpage>2044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.09.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20851191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behr</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eschler</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zöllner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>X3DOM - A DOM-based HTML5/ X3D integration model</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on 3D Web Technology</conf-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/1559764.1559784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergeron</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannan</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Codore</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fero</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moak</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokogawa</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Brain selective transgene expression in zebrafish using an NRSE derived motif</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neural Circuits</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>110</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncir.2012.00110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23293587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bersell</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhury</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mollova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Polizzotti</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganapathy</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadugu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arab</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kühn</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Moderate and high amounts of tamoxifen in αMHC-MerCreMer mice induce a DNA damage response, leading to heart failure and death</article-title><source>Disease Models &amp; Mechanisms</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>1469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dmm.010447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23929941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blader</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Plessy</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Strähle</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Multiple regulatory elements with spatially and temporally distinct activities control neurogenin1 expression in primary neurons of the zebrafish embryo</article-title><source>Mechanisms of Development</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0925-4773(02)00413-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12559493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Congote</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>MEDX3DOM: MEDX3D for X3DOM</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the 17th International Conference on 3D Web Technology</conf-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2338714.2338746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davison</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Akitake</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goll</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosse</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Halpern</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Leach</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Transactivation from Gal4-VP16 transgenic insertions for tissue-specific cell labeling and ablation in zebrafish</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>304</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2007.01.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17335798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dymecki</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Mapping cell fate and function using recombinase-based intersectional strategies</article-title><source>Methods in Enzymology</source><volume>477</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0076-6879(10)77011-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20699143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flanagan-Steet</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanes</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Neuromuscular synapses can form in vivo by incorporation of initially aneural postsynaptic specializations</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>4471</fpage><lpage>4481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.02044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16162647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Förster</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold-Ammer</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurell</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Finger-Baier</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Filosa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmbrecht</surname> <given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kölsch</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kühn</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Slanchev</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Genetic targeting and anatomical registration of neuronal populations in the zebrafish brain with a new set of BAC transgenic tools</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>5230</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-04657-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28701772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gohl</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silies</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname> <given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhalerao</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Luongo</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clandinin</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>A versatile in vivo system for directed dissection of gene expression patterns</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21473015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquart</surname> <given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Horstick</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabor</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pajevic</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Morphometric analysis and neuroanatomical mapping of the zebrafish brain</article-title><source>Methods</source><volume>150</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2018.06.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29936090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heffer</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquart</surname> <given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilina-Beck</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleem</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawid</surname> <given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Generation and characterization of Kctd15 mutations in zebrafish</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e0189162</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0189162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29216270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horstick</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergeron</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabor</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Serpe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Increased functional protein expression using nucleotide sequence features enriched in highly expressed genes in zebrafish</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>43</volume><elocation-id>e48</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25628360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurt</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Polys</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><data-title>https://github.com/BurgessLab/ZebrafishBrainBrowser</data-title><source>GitHub</source><version designator="26afcb4">26afcb4</version><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/BurgessLab/ZebrafishBrainBrowser">https://github.com/BurgessLab/ZebrafishBrainBrowser</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>John</surname> <given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Aratow</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Couch</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Evestedt</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Polys</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Puk</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Victor</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>MedX3D: standards enabled desktop medical 3D</article-title><source>Studies in Health Technology and Informatics</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18391284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawakami</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Tol2: a versatile gene transfer vector in vertebrates</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>S7</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2007-8-s1-s7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18047699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hisano</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawahara</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashijima</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Efficient generation of knock-in transgenic zebrafish carrying reporter/driver genes by CRISPR/Cas9-mediated genome engineering</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>6545</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep06545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25293390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquart</surname> <given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabor</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Strykowski</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Varshney</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>LaFave</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashijima</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A 3D searchable database of transgenic zebrafish Gal4 and cre lines for functional neuroanatomy studies</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neural Circuits</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>78</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncir.2015.00078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26635538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquart</surname> <given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabor</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Horstick</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Geoca</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Polys</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogare</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>High-precision registration between zebrafish brain atlases using symmetric diffeomorphic normalization</article-title><source>GigaScience</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/gix056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28873968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obholzer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfson</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapani</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nechiporuk</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch-Nentwich</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Seiler</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Söllner</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Boehland</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolson</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Vesicular glutamate transporter 3 is required for synaptic transmission in zebrafish hair cells</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>2110</fpage><lpage>2118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5230-07.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18305245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otsuna</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutcheson</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>McPherson</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Scoresby</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaynes</surname> <given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chien</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorsky</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>High-resolution analysis of central nervous system expression patterns in zebrafish Gal4 enhancer-trap lines</article-title><source>Developmental Dynamics</source><volume>244</volume><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>796</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.24260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25694140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngo</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibbard</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenett</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Truman</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Refinement of tools for targeted gene expression in Drosophila</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>186</volume><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.110.119917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20697123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polys</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>New platforms for health hypermedia</article-title><source>Issues in Information Systems</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preibisch</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saalfeld</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomancak</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Globally optimal stitching of tiled 3D microscopic image acquisitions</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>1463</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Randlett</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Wee</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Naumann</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nnaemeka</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoppik</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Portugues</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacoste</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Riegler</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Engert</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schier</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Whole-brain activity mapping onto a zebrafish brain atlas</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26778924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satou</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirata</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suster</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashijima</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Transgenic tools to characterize neuronal properties of discrete populations of zebrafish neurons</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>140</volume><fpage>3927</fpage><lpage>3931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.099531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23946442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt-Supprian</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajewsky</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Vagaries of conditional gene targeting</article-title><source>Nature Immunology</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni0707-665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17579640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasband</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliceiri</surname> <given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>NIH image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrenberg</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziv</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosse</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname> <given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Targeting neural circuitry in zebrafish using GAL4 enhancer trapping</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth1033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>The cellular architecture of the larval zebrafish tectum, as revealed by gal4 enhancer trap lines</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neural Circuits</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>13</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/neuro.04.013.2009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19862330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabor</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergeron</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggman</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Presynaptic inhibition selectively gates auditory transmission to the brainstem startle circuit</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>2527</fpage><lpage>2535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2018.06.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30078569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ting</surname> <given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guttikonda</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Focusing transgene expression in Drosophila by coupling Gal4 with a novel split-LexA expression system</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>188</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.110.126193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21368278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traver</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paw</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Poss</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Penberthy</surname> <given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zon</surname> <given-names>LI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Transplantation and in vivo imaging of multilineage engraftment in zebrafish bloodless mutants</article-title><source>Nature Immunology</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>1238</fpage><lpage>1246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni1007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14608381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vladimirov</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname> <given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Looger</surname> <given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahrens</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Light-sheet functional imaging in fictively behaving zebrafish</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>883</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25068735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wada</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Javidan</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carney</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelsh</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Hedgehog signaling is required for cranial neural crest morphogenesis and chondrogenesis at the midline in the zebrafish skull</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>3977</fpage><lpage>3988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16049113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Controlling gene expression with the Q repressible binary expression system in Caenorhabditis Elegans</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22406855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyart</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Bene</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Warp</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname> <given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Optogenetic dissection of a behavioural module in the vertebrate spinal cord</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>461</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19759620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Roeser</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Staub</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>A GFP-based genetic screen reveals mutations that disrupt the architecture of the zebrafish retinotectal projection</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>2955</fpage><lpage>2967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15930106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fajardo</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Shum</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang Schärer</surname> <given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedrich</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>High-resolution optical control of spatiotemporal neuronal activity patterns in zebrafish using a digital micromirror device</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>1410</fpage><lpage>1425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2012.072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743832</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.018</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>Indira M</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Northwestern University</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Wyart</surname><given-names>Claire</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>Hôpital Pitié-Salpêtrière, Sorbonne Universités, UPMC Univ Paris 06, Inserm, CNRS</institution><country>France</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Brain-wide cellular resolution imaging of Cre transgenic zebrafish lines for functional circuit-mapping&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Didier Stainier as the Senior Editor. The following individuals involved in review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Claire Wyart (Reviewer #1). The other reviewers remain anonymous.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>This tool/resource provides a large set of zebrafish Cre and Gal4 lines for use by the zebrafish research community for the generation of specific lines through intersectional genetics. The data are organized into an online platform that makes the content readily accessible to investigators.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>The reviewers expressed enthusiasm about the platform as well as the care that went into the work. These comments are listed below under &quot;general assessments&quot; from each reviewer. Two points of concern/interest were raised.</p><p>1) Reviewer 3 brought up the point that it is not clear whether the intersectional approach will work well or not with fish in which both Gal4 and cCre are expressed in only a small number of neurons. The idea here is that it should, but evidence is not provided that it does. (Reasons for questioning whether it does are given in the reviewer's comments, but include stochastic activity at target loxP sites for Cre, and variable expression and silencing for Gal4.) In the consultation, the other reviewers agreed with reviewer 3's concern, and therefore suggest that an example or two be provided. We realize this will require some breeding time if no such data is already in hand; please let us know if this is feasible.</p><p>2) Reviewer 1 suggested that the utility of the resource could be greatly increased by a somewhat deeper analysis of the existing data, e.g., by providing information on neurotransmitter type by quantifying overlap with transgenic lines targeting specific neurotransmitter types. This would not require new data, but additional information on the existing data.</p><p>These points are more fully spelled out in the collected major comments from the reviewers, which are listed below, with editorial indications in square brackets.</p><p>General assessments:</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1:</italic></p><p>The manuscript of Tabor et al. provide a very important set of cre and gal4 lines that will be extremely useful for intersectional genetics in the field of zebrafish neuronal circuits, together with a novel online platform, which is extremely convenient to analyse the profile of expression online using ZBB2. I believe that this effort is determinant for the expansion of the field of the investigation of neuronal circuits underlying behavior in zebrafish larvae.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2:</italic></p><p>This paper is a resources and tools contribution that presents many (100ish) new zebrafish CRE and gal4 lines to facilitate intersectional genetic strategies in fish. Importantly, the lines are presented in a beautiful online (or downloadable) browser that makes it very easy to explore them to decide which ones are useful, while learning about the larval fish brain at the same time. Accessibility and easy evaluation of the lines is as important as the lines themselves. The combination of lines with the ability to easily explore them and their relationships and intersection with other lines makes for a strong contribution. I have no substantive issues with a well presented and very useful tool. All the materials and fish are made accessible.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #3:</italic></p><p>In this manuscript Tabor et al. have generated more than 50 enhancer trap lines that express Cre in defined population of cells in the CNS. The authors obtained high-resolution images of these new lines along with 45 Gal4 enhancer trap lines that have not yet been reported. The authors then registered these images with the Zebrafish Brain Browser (ZBB) atlas, software that was created by the authors in a previous study (Marquart et al., 2015). Together with the images that have already been reported (109 lines), the new database (ZBB2) now include 65 Cre lines and 158 Gal4 lines. Additionally, the authors provide an online interface to the atlas. There is no doubt that these resources will be very useful for the zebrafish neuroscience community.</p><p>Major comments [concatenated and reordered, from all reviewers]:</p><p>1) [Related to Essential revision 1] Throughout the manuscript, the words, &quot;cellular resolution&quot;, &quot;single cell resolution&quot;, and &quot;intersectional targeting&quot; are used multiple times. With these words, readers would expect the following experiments: searching for Cre and Gal4 lines in the database, finding small numbers of neurons in which Cre and Gal4 expression overlap, and expressing reporter/effecter genes in these neurons. Nowhere in the manuscript, however, are examples of such experiments are provided. Thus, it is not clear whether targeting expression of reporter genes with cellular resolution is possible with the combination of Cre and Gal4. There are several potential concerns for the intersectional targeting of small numbers of neurons. These include stochastic activity at target loxP sites for Cre, and variable expression and silencing for Gal4. The authors cite the Current Biology paper (Tabor et al., 2018) as an example of intersectional targeting, but the Cre lines used in that study are broad expression lines (Cre expression in particular rhombomeres). So, the study does not serve as an example of intersectional targeting at cellular resolution. There is one place in the paper where the authors mention UAS:Switch expression experiments (in Discussion). However, it is written in a negative context: &quot;Occasionally, we have observed UAS:Switch expression in neurons outside the domain of Cre expression in the ZBB2 atlas&quot;. In any case, the authors need to show clear examples of intersectional targeting in small numbers of neurons where Cre and Gal4 expression overlap in the ZBB2database.</p><p>2) [Related to Essential revision 2] While I do not request more experiments to the authors, I think an in-depth analysis of the distribution of interneurons types based on neurotransmitter and neuromodulator expressions per brain area, which seems amenable to the authors based on the data acquired, would provide more relevant information to the reader and the field. In particular, it would be useful to take it a step further and analyze out of the ~92 000 neurons in the brain the putative distribution as a function of neurotransmitter, neuromodulator and/or neuropeptide types. This effort would constitute a critical resource for the field and seems possible to estimate with ZBB2 and the collection of transgenic lines mapped in the 6 dpf zebrafish larval brain.</p><p>3) [Related to Essential revision 2] Related to Figure 3: Seeing images of the lines or 3D views online is very nice qualitatively. Naive question here: I wonder if we could take it one step further to reach a quantitative representation of the expression over the entire brain space of the larva. Do the authors have a simple way to converge on a physical 3D map indexed in a matrix with absolute coordinates that we could refer to in publications from different labs?</p><p>4) [Related to Essential revision 2] In order to locate with absolute coordinates the expression of transgenes better than by eye on the atlas: could the authors come up with a matrix of ~1000 bins (containing on average 10 neurons) for which each index corresponds to a graded value of expression on a 0-1 scale?</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42687.019</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Major comments [concatenated and reordered, from all reviewers]:</p><p>1) [Related to Essential revision 1] Throughout the manuscript, the words, &quot;cellular resolution&quot;, &quot;single cell resolution&quot;, and &quot;intersectional targeting&quot; are used multiple times. With these words, readers would expect the following experiments: searching for Cre and Gal4 lines in the database, finding small numbers of neurons in which Cre and Gal4 expression overlap, and expressing reporter/effecter genes in these neurons. Nowhere in the manuscript, however, are examples of such experiments are provided. Thus, it is not clear whether targeting expression of reporter genes with cellular resolution is possible with the combination of Cre and Gal4. There are several potential concerns for the intersectional targeting of small numbers of neurons. These include stochastic activity at target loxP sites for Cre, and variable expression and silencing for Gal4. The authors cite the Current Biology paper (Tabor et al., 2018) as an example of intersectional targeting, but the Cre lines used in that study are broad expression lines (Cre expression in particular rhombomeres). So, the study does not serve as an example of intersectional targeting at cellular resolution. There is one place in the paper where the authors mention UAS:Switch expression experiments (in Discussion). However, it is written in a negative context: &quot;Occasionally, we have observed UAS:Switch expression in neurons outside the domain of Cre expression in the ZBB2 atlas&quot;. In any case, the authors need to show clear examples of intersectional targeting in small numbers of neurons where Cre and Gal4 expression overlap in the ZBB2database.</p></disp-quote><p>In the manuscript we have generally used the phrases like 'cellular resolution' to refer to the level of detail observable in the database rather than the level of resolution that we think can be usually obtained by intersectional targeting with transgenic reagents. Rather, our vision is that Cre lines with relatively broad expression can be used to select out sub-domains within Gal4 expression patterns. To achieve true single cell resolution, a third intersectional reagent is generally necessary (for example, the B3 recombinase that we used in Tabor et al., 2018).</p><p>However, the reviewers correctly observe, in Tabor et al., we performed intersectional targeting using Gal4 and Cre lines with relatively broad expression. We also agree that UAS lines (including the UAS:Switch) tend to silence and show variable expression. Therefore in the revised manuscript we have added:</p><p>A) A new Figure 5 which illustrates examples where Gal4 and Cre intersectionally drive expression in a small groups of neurons. In the accompanying text, we explicitly acknowledge the confound of variable expression.</p><p>B) A short description to the Materials and methods section describing the protocol that we use to minimize transgene silencing.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) [Related to Essential revision 2] While I do not request more experiments to the authors, I think an in-depth analysis of the distribution of interneurons types based on neurotransmitter and neuromodulator expressions per brain area, which seems amenable to the authors based on the data acquired, would provide more relevant information to the reader and the field. In particular, it would be useful to take it a step further and analyze out of the ~92 000 neurons in the brain the putative distribution as a function of neurotransmitter, neuromodulator and/or neuropeptide types. This effort would constitute a critical resource for the field and seems possible to estimate with ZBB2 and the collection of transgenic lines mapped in the 6 dpf zebrafish larval brain.</p></disp-quote><p>As requested, we provide new supplementary information (Supplementary files 4 and 5) that describe the density of neurotransmitter/neuromodulator expression in different brain regions. For this, we have used both manually curated anatomical masks from Z-Brain, and second set of computational defined spatially smaller masks recently described by our group (Gupta et al., 2018). However, we cannot reliably extend this to a neuron-level description (if we understand the idea correctly) due to biological variability. Almost all brain regions contain multiple cell types that are intermingled, and – with the possible exception of the Mauthner neuron – specific cells are not precisely located at the same coordinates in different individuals.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) [Related to Essential revision 2] Related to Figure 3: Seeing images of the lines or 3D views online is very nice qualitatively. Naive question here: I wonder if we could take it one step further to reach a quantitative representation of the expression over the entire brain space of the larva. Do the authors have a simple way to converge on a physical 3D map indexed in a matrix with absolute coordinates that we could refer to in publications from different labs?</p></disp-quote><p>The ZBB reference volume constitutes a 3D map with an absolute coordinate system in microns. We modified the code for the downloadable version so that irrespective of user-selected downscaling values, slices are now labeled by their position in ZBB reference space. The online version already displays the absolute coordinates of the selected voxel. This position can be reported in publications.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) [Related to Essential revision 2] In order to locate with absolute coordinates the expression of transgenes better than by eye on the atlas: could the authors come up with a matrix of ~1000 bins (containing on average 10 neurons) for which each index corresponds to a graded value of expression on a 0-1 scale?</p></disp-quote><p>This is a great idea – thank you. We have added new Supplementary file 3 that provides coordinates for 1804 bins (20 µm side volumes) and the density of transgene expression in each. Using the bin coordinates, users can quickly navigate to the selected region in the atlas.</p></body></sub-article></article>