<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">88335</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.88335</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi" specific-use="version">10.7554/eLife.88335.4</article-id><article-version article-version-type="publication-state">version of record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Physics of Living Systems</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Annihilation of action potentials induces electrical coupling between neurons</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Schloetter</surname><given-names>Moritz</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1264-7704</contrib-id><email>moritz.schloetter@uni-konstanz.de</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maret</surname><given-names>Georg U</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4069-648X</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kleineidam</surname><given-names>Christoph J</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0671-1455</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0546hnb39</institution-id><institution>Department of Physics, University of Konstanz</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Konstanz</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0546hnb39</institution-id><institution>Neurobiology, Department of Biology, University of Konstanz</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Konstanz</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Poirazi</surname><given-names>Panayiota</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01gzszr18</institution-id><institution>FORTH Institute of Molecular Biology and Biotechnology</institution></institution-wrap><country>Greece</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Poirazi</surname><given-names>Panayiota</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01gzszr18</institution-id><institution>FORTH Institute of Molecular Biology and Biotechnology</institution></institution-wrap><country>Greece</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="publication"><day>04</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>RP88335</elocation-id><history><date date-type="sent-for-review" iso-8601-date="2023-04-28"><day>28</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a preprint.</event-desc><date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2023-05-24"><day>24</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date><self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.05.24.542064"/></event><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a reviewed preprint.</event-desc><date date-type="reviewed-preprint" iso-8601-date="2023-08-16"><day>16</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date><self-uri content-type="reviewed-preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.88335.1"/></event><event><event-desc>The reviewed preprint was revised.</event-desc><date date-type="reviewed-preprint" iso-8601-date="2024-11-25"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><self-uri content-type="reviewed-preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.88335.2"/></event><event><event-desc>The reviewed preprint was revised.</event-desc><date date-type="reviewed-preprint" iso-8601-date="2025-01-24"><day>24</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date><self-uri content-type="reviewed-preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.88335.3"/></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2023, Schloetter et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Schloetter et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-88335-v1.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="figures-pdf" xlink:href="elife-88335-figures-v1.pdf"/><abstract><p>Neurons generate and propagate electrical pulses called action potentials which annihilate on arrival at the axon terminal. We measure the extracellular electric field generated by propagating and annihilating action potentials and find that on annihilation, action potentials expel a local discharge. The discharge at the axon terminal generates an inhomogeneous electric field that immediately influences target neurons and thus provokes ephaptic coupling. Our measurements are quantitatively verified by a powerful analytical model which reveals excitation and inhibition in target neurons, depending on position and morphology of the source-target arrangement. Our model is in full agreement with experimental findings on ephaptic coupling at the well-studied Basket cell-Purkinje cell synapse. It is able to predict ephaptic coupling for any other synaptic geometry as illustrated by a few examples.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>electrophysiology</kwd><kwd>ephaptic coupling</kwd><kwd>synaptic terminals</kwd><kwd>Purkinje cell</kwd><kwd><italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic></kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Other</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001659</institution-id><institution>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R. Koselleck project Ma 817/9</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Maret</surname><given-names>Georg U</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100010583</institution-id><institution>Universität Konstanz</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Kleineidam</surname><given-names>Christoph J</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Action potentials of neurons expel a charge when they reach the axon terminal, and classical electrodynamics predict the resulting electric fields and its influence to other neurons by ephaptic coupling.</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>publishing-route</meta-name><meta-value>prc</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Neurons are characterized by electrically excitable membranes and most neurons in a brain are able to generate action potentials (APs) which are propagating along the axon. At the synaptic terminal they eventually lead to electrochemical processes, allowing communication with postsynaptic target neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Eccles, 1982</xref>). The most prevalent form of communication between neurons is by transmitter release at the presynaptic terminal, and subsequent binding of these at postsynaptic sites leads to modulation, e.g., excitation or inhibition. Less common in nervous systems of any organism are gap junctions between neurons, resulting in an aggregated functional unit because internal current is transferred from one neuron to the other neuron.</p><p>Beside these two forms of communication between neurons, the electrical field itself which is generated at an excited membrane can have an impact on the membrane potential of cells in the vicinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Jefferys, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Anastassiou and Koch, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Rebollo et al., 2021</xref>). Rapid changes of the membrane potential, as it occurs when APs are generated, induce electrical fields, that by superposition are also present in neighboring cells. The impact of a single, propagating AP on adjacent neurons is very small, nevertheless, along active, parallel fibers synchronization of APs can occur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Katz and Schmitt, 1940</xref>). When the term ephaptic interaction was coined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Arvanitaki, 1942</xref>, she concluded that the blockage of APs is the main source of such effects (hereafter ephaptic coupling) in nervous systems. Indeed, APs arriving at the synaptic terminal of a neuron annihilate, thereby generating a more potent electrical field for ephaptic coupling. The functional significance of ephaptic coupling at synaptic terminals is well documented in at least two systems: at the Mauthner cell in teleost fish and at the Purkinje fibers of the cerebellum in vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Furukawa and Furshpan, 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>). In both systems, APs arriving at the synaptic terminal of the source neuron (e.g. the Basket cell of the cerebellum) modulate the initiation of an AP in the target neuron by transiently changing the membrane potential. Although the phenomenon of ephaptic coupling is known since many decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Arvanitaki, 1942</xref>), a quantitative physical description is missing. This is even more surprising when considering that ephaptic coupling at synaptic terminals is ubiquitous and may well contribute to communication between many different types of neurons, beside the mentioned Mauthner cell and Purkinje fiber.</p><p>In our study, we aim to describe the electric field of an AP arriving at the synaptic terminal in such detail that the ephaptic coupling and the change in membrane potential of a known target neuron can be predicted.</p><p>The propagating AP is driven by a voltage-dependent transition of the membrane from a resting to an excited state. As a consequence of electroneutrality, current flows across the membrane resulting in a closed loop through extracellular and intracellular medium. The current loop includes the resistive extracellular medium where the AP generates a voltage signature. In 1952, Hodgkin-Huxley introduced a model (HH model) for generation and propagation of APs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hodgkin and Huxley, 1952</xref>). It is based on the cable equation and incorporates Nernst equations for different ions and changing ion-specific conductances upon activation of ion channels.</p><p>The HH model is a powerful tool to study and evaluate the properties of ion channels in excitable membranes on a microscopic level, and the great attention it received since being introduced is more than justified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Catterall et al., 2012</xref>). However, the macroscopic phenomenon of current loops and associated electric fields is already well accounted for by a much simpler model introduced by Tasaki and Matsumoto (TM model) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Tasaki and Matsumoto, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Tasaki, 2006</xref>) without the need of a multitude of specific parameters as required for example in the HH model. While the TM model can be considered as a simplification of the HH model, the mechanism that the authors had in mind is very different (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Tasaki, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Tasaki et al., 1965</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Tasaki et al., 1971</xref>).</p><p>In general terms, neural membranes can go through transitions where the electric properties change extremely fast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fedosejevs and Schneider, 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Mussel et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Horkay et al., 2000</xref>). The TM model describes a resting and an excited state, each with a linear cable model. It uses the cable equation with two state-specific parameters, its equilibrium potential and conductivity, which undergo a sudden (voltage-dependent) switch at the boundary between resting and excited state. The boundary between an excited and a resting section propagates toward the resting side. The AP in the TM model has only 3 degrees of freedom, e.g., its propagation velocity, its amplitude, and its length. Nevertheless, the TM model is well suited to describe the current distribution that is driven by the inhomogeneity of local electric fields in the internal and the external medium. Thus, the TM model is already sufficient to describe the mutual influence of neurons by ephaptic coupling, using only three parameters for each neuron.</p><p>It is therefore of prime importance to evaluate the quantitative description of the TM model based on experimentally derived values. We explore the behavior of APs at boundaries to assess these three parameters. A suitable boundary condition (intracellular, axial current equals zero) can be generated experimentally by a collision of two counter-propagating APs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Tasaki, 1949</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Spach et al., 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Shrivastava, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Shrivastava et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Shrivastava et al., 2018</xref>). Within any cable model, the very same boundary condition also exists within the axon at the synaptic terminal due to the broken translation symmetry for the current loops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Spach and Kootsey, 1985</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we first focus on collisions of APs. Our experimental observation of colliding APs provides unique access to the spatial profile of the extracellular potential around APs that are blocked by collisions and thus annihilate. Our procedure is as follows: Recording propagating APs allows to determine both the propagation velocity and the amplitude of the extracellular electric potentials. The collision experiment provides additional information on the characteristic length <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf1"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, thereby fully determining the parameters of the TM model. We find that TM is sufficient to describe the onset of the electric field dynamics of an AP. However, as TM does not include the slow return of the excited membrane to the resting state, we introduce an extension of the TM model that we call the relaxing Tasaki model (RTM) which adds an empirical slow relaxation term to the TM model. We find that RTM accounts for the full spatiotemporal signature of propagating and colliding APs and is therefore also very useful to predict electric effects at axon terminals, e.g., at synapses. Since the RTM sets a complete framework to describe APs and to predict ephaptic interactions for a given morphology, the RTM is used in the last part of this paper to simulate various representative pre- and postsynaptic morphologies and geometries. Around AP propagation boundaries, we find excitatory as well as inhibitory regions, depending on timing, relative position, orientation, and morphology of source and target neuron. We expect these predictions to be robust, because the model is absolutely minimal and matches the experimental observations.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Extracellular potential around AP collisions</title><p>We record the extracellular electric potential of APs, generated by the median giant fibers (MGF) of the ventral nerve cord (VNC) of an earthworm using the setup shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A and B</xref>. In a first experiment the ends are stimulated individually and the APs are detected at several positions along the fiber. We verify the vitality of a nerve cord by asserting that both fibers (MGF and the lateral giant fibers [LGF]) reliably conduct APs in both directions, and in our experiments, we investigate selectively the MGF only.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Action potential (AP) collision experiment.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The ventral nerve cord (VNC) of an earthworm is positioned on a series of transverse, single-ended electrodes to excite and monitor APs. Individual or two counter-propagating APs are generated by stimulating the nerve at the outermost electrodes. Some of the inner electrodes (C1, C2, C3) are used for recording; all other electrodes are grounded. Propagating APs generate biphasic electrical potential as sketched above C1 and C3 whereas colliding APs provoke an essentially unipolar peak (cf. C2). By variation of the delay between the opposing stimuli, the collision can be generated anywhere along the nerve between the stimulation electrodes. (<bold>B</bold>) Photograph of the recording chamber with a white thread to illustrate the position of the VNC. Distance between the electrodes is 5 mm. (<bold>C</bold>) Extracellular recording of propagating and colliding APs. A collision sweep experiment yields multiple recordings with varying distance between recording site and point of collision. The collision is captured in the recording line at <italic>y</italic>-position 0 mm, while orthodromic propagation is at the top and antidromic propagation is at the bottom. (<bold>D</bold>) The peak amplitude as a function of the distance to the collision. Examples of four sweeps at three positions along the nerve cord. As a guide to the eye, the data points are connected by a cubic spline (thin lines).</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88335-fig1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Complete raw data from experiment number 3 (out of three).</title></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88335-fig1-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Gray crosses show the maximal negative deflection of the extracellular potential from 88 recordings (C1, C2, C3 from three experiments).</title><p>Gray dashed lines denote the full width at half maximum (from channel C2 from all three experiments), which is used to fit the models. Continuous lines are the Tasaki-Matsumoto (TM) model (blue), relaxing Tasaki model (RTM) (red), and Hodgkin-Huxley (HH) model (green). For better comparison, the simulated curves are shifted to peak at <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf2"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88335-fig1-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>The signatures <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf3"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of both orthodromic and antidromic propagating APs look indeed very similar. We observe a biphasic voltage spike propagating with <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf4"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>14.5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>11</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>).</p><p>In the main experiment, both ends are stimulated simultaneously and the APs collide close to the central recording electrode. We observe that the APs do not penetrate each other but always annihilate at the collision site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Tasaki, 1949</xref>). At this position, the trace of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf5"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> becomes more monophasic, with an almost doubled positive peak amplitude (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). The negative phase of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf6"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> at the collision site is considerably diminished and shows a distinct slow relaxation. The peak amplitude of propagating APs is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf7"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>2.9</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> while the colliding APs peak is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf8"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>5.2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>The width of the collision is a measure of the characteristic length <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf9"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of the AP and is uniquely revealed by a collision sweep experiment. We experimentally positioned the site of collision along the neuron by introducing a delay between the opposing stimuli. Assuming symmetric propagation velocities, a delay <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf10"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> displaces the collision by <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf11"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf12"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the propagation velocity and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf13"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the distance between the collision and the recording electrode. The spatial extend of the collision process is then found by repeating the experiment at various delays <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf14"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> between the opposing stimuli, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>. The propagation velocity is derived from the time of arrival at separate recording sites. The peak amplification can be used as a measure of the width of the collision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). We use four recordings at three positions (anterior, medial, and posterior) along the nerve cord and we assess the mean full width at half maximum as <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf15"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>3.8</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Model of the AP</title><p>We describe a neuron by a classical cable model as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref> (see ‘Materials and methods’ for further details). Such a model consists of a chain of RC circuits composed of resistors with conductivity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf16"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and capacitors <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf17"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>F</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> which are connected by an inner resistivity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf18"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. The inner axial current <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf19"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is driven by the gradient of the potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf20"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> inside the neuron. A common approach is to assume a constant capacity and to neglect external fields and inhomogeneities in the neuron. Then, the balance of currents results in the cable equation with the membrane potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf21"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="equ1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="m1"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>The classical cable model.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A chain of identical RC circuits with conductivity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf22"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, capacity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf23"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, and inner resistivity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf24"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> mimics the electric properties of the cellular membrane and connects the extracellular and intracellular space. The change of inner axial current <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf25"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is given by the transmembrane current density <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf26"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (Kirchhoff’s current law). (<bold>B</bold>) The propagating solution of the Tasaki-Matsumoto model. A boundary between a resting state and an excited state induces an axial current, that causes a propagation of the boundary. The axial current flows in closed loops and returns within the resistive extracellular medium, causing an extracellular potential that travels with the current source along the neuron.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88335-fig2-v1.tif"/></fig><p>The first term on the right describes the capacitive charging by an axial current which is linked to the rate of change in membrane potential. The second term describes the contribution of resistive membrane current to axial current. The relationship between the axial current <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf27"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and the membrane current <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf28"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is further described in the Materials (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ5">Equation 5</xref>).</p><p>APs are characterized by a solitary, i.e., non-spreading spatiotemporal shape. In the cable model, the generation of such APs requires an additional nonlinear response of the membrane. Commonly, living cells are electrically charged to a negative equilibrium potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf29"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> across their membrane. In excitable cells, e.g., neurons, a change of the membrane potential beyond a critical threshold value leads to a rapid transition from the resting into an excited state of the membrane which essentially differ in their respective resistivities. The excited state, with drastically increased conductivity, is indicated by the starred values <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf30"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf31"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>A local transition of a membrane from the resting to excited state results in a boundary between <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf32"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf33"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. The difference in membrane potentials between the resting and excited state induces an internal axial current. The increased conductivity at the excited state <italic>drives</italic> the internal current and depolarizes the adjacent membrane. The flow lines of internal, transmembrane, and external current form a closed loop around the position of the transition as sketched in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>. All internal current is present as an extracellular return current and in neurons, this process produces a propagating, dipolar local current source.</p><p>The TM model describes both the resting and the active state by linear cable models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Tasaki and Matsumoto, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Tasaki, 2006</xref>). The resting state has a negative electrochemical equilibrium potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf34"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and a very low conductivity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf35"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. In the excited state the conductivity is drastically increased to <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf36"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and the equilibrium potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf37"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is zero. The transition from the resting to the excited state is discontinuous and occurs at <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf38"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. The TM model does not address how the resting state is maintained before a transition, nor does it address how the resting state is restored thereafter.</p><p>A simple analytical solution of the TM model describes the propagating initial depolarization of a nerve signal. This includes an exact expression for the propagation velocity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf39"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and for the spatial length <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf40"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of the initial current dipole as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>. The velocity is determined by the delay in charging of neighboring capacitors, while the leak conductivity barely effects the process. Therefore, we base our study on simplified expressions by neglecting the leak conductivity, as it amounts to less than 1% of the conductivity in the excited state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Tasaki and Matsumoto, 2002</xref>). Then, the analytical solution of the TM model yields<disp-formula id="equ2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="m2"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:msqrt></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Note that the length scale <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf41"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> used here is not equivalent to <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf42"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> used in basically all previous models where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf43"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the damping length due ionic leakage neglected here. The products in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ1">Equation 1</xref> can be expressed as <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf44"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf45"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. According to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ1">Equation 1</xref> <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf46"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the diffusion constant of the spreading potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf47"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> which connects a typical timescale <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf48"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> with a typical diffusion length <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf49"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> by <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf50"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. The two products <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf51"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf52"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> are directly determined in our experiment from measurements of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf53"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf54"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> , and for a comparison of our AP measurements with the TM model only 1 degree of freedom is missing, which is the amplitude of the AP. At this point we fit the amplitude of the model to our experimental recording by estimating an appropriate extracellular conductivity.</p><p>The fast switch from resting to excited state in the generation of an AP is followed by a slow process of repolarization that restores the resting state. In order to provide a more general model that also accounts for repolarization, we add a simple extension to the TM model and refer to this as RTM. We approximate the repolarization in the extracellular potential by extending the TM model with an (ad hoc) exponential repolarization function (see Materials and methods).</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Comparison of measurements with model simulations</title><p>The above collision sweep experiment provides a detailed survey of the extracellular electric signature of APs. We now compare these results to the TM model, the RTM, and the classical HH model (see Materials and methods) by simulating a nerve of length 10 cm with 2000 compartments (conductivities in the HH model are area specific, here, we use a diameter of 80 µm). All models are adjusted to the MGF with identical procedure. The parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf55"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf56"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> are used to match the propagation velocity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf57"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and the width <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf58"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of the collision to the experimentally determined values. The fitting procedure is as follows: (i) Propagating APs are simulated. For a given <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf59"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> the velocity is adjusted using <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf60"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. (ii) An AP collision is simulated and the width is compared to the experiment (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>). If the width deviation is below 1%, the model is accepted. Otherwise <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf61"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is updated and the procedure is repeated from step (i). The TM model obeys the analytical expressions and converges immediately. The RTM deviates from the TM expressions only by a few percent and converges very fast. The HH model takes more iterations to converge. In all cases, the procedure is unambiguous and stable. The complete parameters for all models are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="app3table2">Appendix 3—table 2</xref>.</p><p>While the individual values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf62"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf63"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> depend on the choice of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf64"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, the product <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf65"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> does not. From our measurements we obtain <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf66"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>26</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, which is in good agreement with literature values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Tasaki and Matsumoto, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Tasaki, 2012</xref>). The resulting length parameter is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf67"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.8</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> which is about half the width of the peak in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>. The deviations between the TM model and the experiment are: (i) Propagating APs cause a negative peak greater than the positive peak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). (ii) There is a small but sustained negative phase at the collision site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). The repolarization time in the RTM is found by comparing the model to the experimental traces of the colliding AP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). A value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf68"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> provides an acceptable fit. All models allow the reconstruction of the extracellular field of propagating APs within satisfying accuracy.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Comparison of experimental data (gray) with models (color, see legend).</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Traces of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf69"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> from propagating action potentials (APs). (<bold>B</bold>) Traces of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf70"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> at the collision site. (<bold>C</bold>) Model predictions of the discharge (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf71"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) generated by AP annihilation and released around the collision site. (<bold>D</bold>) The extracellular discharge of annihilating APs, measured and calculated. The gray crosses are the experimental values from four recordings at three separate sites along the median giant fibers (MGF), where each recording consists of up to 46 traces with varying delay times.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88335-fig3-v1.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Discharge of colliding APs</title><p>In an active axon, current always flows in and out in equal amounts (electroneutrality) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Barbour, 2020</xref>). As long as APs propagate the current must sum up to zero in space at any time and in time at any position. However, AP propagation is blocked when the axial current <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf72"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is shut down at a boundary condition, e.g., by reaching the axon terminal or by AP collision. Such annihilating APs generate an effective net charge expelled into the extracellular space because the local sum in time can deviate from zero while the spatial sum remains zero. The associated current pulse may act like a stimulating electrode and as current source for ephaptic coupling. In order to access how much charge is expelled, we can calculate the charge as the integral of membrane current over time.</p><p>The membrane current <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf73"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is given by the cable equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ1">Equation 1</xref>) as the curvature of the membrane potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf74"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, divided by <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf75"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, the discharge <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf76"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total charge expelled at a boundary (site of collision or axon terminal) and described by<disp-formula id="equ3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="m3"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The discharge <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf77"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> can be calculated with our models and yield very different predictions about its magnitude (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). It has to be noted that <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf78"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> does not directly predict ephaptic coupling. However, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf79"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> generates a curvature in the extracellular potential and in order to quantify possible impact of current, we integrate the curvature in the extracellular potential over time and define (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf80"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) as<disp-formula id="equ4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="m4"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf81"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and thus <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf82"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> can be assessed with our collision measurements and can be used for model validation by comparing the models’ predictions. In our simulations with a multi-compartment model, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf83"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is calculated when APs are colliding, based on parameterization from propagation velocity (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf84"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) and width of the collision (length <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf85"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, see above). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref> illustrates that the TM model is in excellent agreement with the experiment and the RTM only slightly underestimates <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf86"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. From this observation we conclude that the discharge is driven by the rapid onset of the AP and that the contribution by the repolarizing phase is small. On the other hand, the HH model largely disagrees with the experiments both in the magnitude of the discharge and in its temporal shape.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Model of ephaptic coupling</title><p>First, we briefly investigate the effects of propagating APs on neighboring parallel cells which may give rise to synchronization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Katz and Schmitt, 1940</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Kriebel et al., 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Goldwyn and Rinzel, 2016</xref>). Then, we focus on synaptic terminals, i.e., situations where the (finite) electric discharge of <italic>annihilating</italic> APs may influence surrounding target neurons.</p><p>We showed above that colliding APs emit a charge <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf87"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and can act like a stimulating electrode. Within any cable model, the same boundary condition with <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf88"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> also exist at axon terminals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Plonsey, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Spach and Kootsey, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kléber and Rudy, 2004</xref>). It was our original idea to conduct the collision experiments and apply the multi-compartment simulations to then transfer the knowledge to annihilating APs at axon terminals. Likewise to our simulations for compartments around the site of collision, we can calculate the extracellular potential around the last compartments at the axon terminal. Knowledge of the generated inhomogeneity of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf89"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> allows to calculate the response of a target neuron that may be close to a site of AP annihilation. The details of this calculation are provided in the Materials and methods section.</p><p>Briefly, the above defined discharge from annihilation at terminals or collisions generates a distortion of the extracellular potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf90"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> which in turn induces current in nearby target neurons.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> we show simulations of ephaptic coupling in three different geometries: parallel neurons, end-shaft synapses, and end-end synapses. We use common literature values for the inner resistivity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf91"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and membrane capacity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf92"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Cole, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Carpenter, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bekkers, 2013</xref>). Estimates for the extracellular resistivity are rare and highly variable, in the range of  3–600 Ωm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Weiss et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Lindén et al., 2011</xref>). We derive <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf93"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> by an estimate based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>, as explained in Appendix 1.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Examples of ephaptic coupling.</title><p>Ephaptic coupling was calculated with the Tasaki-Matsumoto (TM) model (blue) and the Hodgkin-Huxley (HH) model (green): (<bold>A</bold>) in a parallel target neuron when an action potential (AP) is propagating in the source; (<bold>B, C</bold>) when the AP is annihilating at a bouton of a neuron terminal (upper neuron in end-to-shaft geometry, similar to the Basket cell-Purkinje cell synapse). The source and target neurons are 1 μm in diameter and are separated by 1 μm (2000 compartments each, length 1 mm, bouton size 2 μm). The neurons are placed next to each other, that is to say the numeric point compartments are separated by 1 μm. Traces denote the target membrane potential next to the point of axon termination. The initial hyperpolarization effect may be followed by a subsequent depolarization, depicted by the RTM (red) for different relaxation times. (<bold>D–F</bold>) Ephaptic coupling in an end-to-end synapse, illustrating the enhanced ephaptic coupling, due to enlarged neuron terminals (boutons). Here, the source and target neurons are 100 nm in diameter (2000 compartments each, length 300 μm, bouton size 400 nm). The target neurons are 1/4 in length and N (500 compartments, length 75 μm). The TM model generates a distant depolarization. Traces in D and E show the membrane potential of the target at the point where the TM model provokes its maximal depolarization (corresponding to the peaks in F). Traces in F show the spatial profile of the membrane potential along the target, at the time of maximal depolarization (corresponding to the peaks in <bold>D, E</bold>).</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88335-fig4-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Simulation of target potential in an end-shaft synapse.</title><p>The <italic>y</italic>-axis denotes the position along the target where y=0 refers to the target position next to the end of the source axon terminal.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88335-fig4-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Simulation of target potential in an end-end synapse.</title><p>The <italic>y</italic>-axis denotes the position along the target where <italic>y</italic>=0 refers to the tip of the target at the synaptic gap. The color scale is cropped at −10 µV.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88335-fig4-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>The peak membrane conductivity in the TM model and RTM is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf94"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>450</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the HH model is used with all classical parameters as specified in the supplementary material (e.g. <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf95"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1200</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref> shows the potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf96"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of the target neuron at the position marked by an arrow when excitation of a propagating AP occurs in the source neuron above. While the response in the target neuron calculated by the HH model is weak and broad, it is more asymmetric, peaked, shorter, and stronger in the TM model.</p><p>Next, we consider an axon terminal that ends near a neighboring, parallel target fiber. The chosen geometry as sketched in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref> is a coarse representation of the synapse between Basket cell and Purkinje cell with the synapse embedded in a highly resistive structure, called the Pinceau (or Basket) at the axon initial segment (AIS). The TM model and RTM predict a strong and sharp initial hyperpolarization of the target neuron while the HH model predicts a comparably weak and smooth effect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>, see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>In the RTM and HH model, this initial effect is followed by a more or less pronounced slow depolarization of the target neuron (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). The RTM also reveals that a faster repolarization of the source AP increases the late depolarization of the target neuron.</p><p>The modulation of activity in Purkinje cells, e.g., changes in the rate of APs in response to an AP arriving at the Pinceau of the Basket cell was described in detail by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>. Since the relationship of membrane potential and the rate of APs in Purkinje cells is reported by the authors to be around <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf97"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, we can compare our model predictions to the measured rate modulation of APs. We mapped the result of the models’ predictions for different morphologies to the experimental data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>) of AP rate modulation in Purkinje cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). Similarly to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>, we used a Gaussian filter with <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf98"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msqrt></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. In our two models (TM and RTM), the modulation of not terminating but propagating APs along the source axon on the AP rate of the target cell is minute (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). Note that this geometry does not correspond to the Purkinje cell-Basket cell connectivity. For annihilating APs at the axon terminal, with excitable segments up to the very end, our models reveal a moderate modulation, and only about half of what was reported for the Purkinje cell by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>. This illustrates the importance of AP annihilation for ephaptic coupling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). The Basket cell axon branches, forming the basket, and the branchlets or Pinceau embrace the initial part of the Purkinje cell axon. At the Pinceau a different set of ion channels is expressed and it is considered as being non-excitable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Laube et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Southan and Robertson, 2000</xref>). We implemented the morphology of the Pinceau (increased volume and surface area) by implementing a bouton (diameter: axon 1 µm, bouton: 2 µm) and non-excitable terminal segments of 15 µm total length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bobik et al., 2004</xref>). AP propagation is terminated before reaching the Pinceau terminal and the resulting modulation of AP rate in Purkinje cells highly depends on the morphology of the Basket cell and on <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf99"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of the RTM. Non-excitable segments at the last 15 µm result in very consistent predictions from both of our models (TM and RTM) for the reported inhibition and even the rebound activity (between 0.5 and 1.5 ms) is very well predicted by the RTM, using a <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf100"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of 0.5 ms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Comparison of experimental data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>, on modulation of Purkinje cell activity (gray lines) with our relaxing Tasaki model (RTM) predictions (red lines with two different <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf101"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) and the Tasaki-Matsumoto (TM) model prediction (blue) for three different geometries and physiological properties of the source neuron (e.g. the Basket cell).</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Excluding the annihilation of an action potential (AP) at the source neuron, i.e., a propagating AP, cause only minute modulation of the predicted AP rate in the target neuron. Note that this example does not represent the Basket cell terminal with annihilating APs. (<bold>B</bold>) Annihilation of an AP at the terminal of the source neuron, with all segments being excitable in our calculation, cause moderate modulation. (<bold>C</bold>) Source neuron with similar properties to the Basket cell, i.e., a bouton and last segments non-excitable (corresponding to 15 µm with no switch from resting state to excited state), cause inhibition and rebound that is very similar as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88335-fig5-v1.tif"/></fig><p>Beside the end-to-shaft geometry as in Basket cell-Purkinje cell connections, other morphologies and geometries are common in neural networks. We consider target neurons pointing toward the site of annihilation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D–F</xref>, see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>). The geometry is reminiscent of an excitatory synapse, where an axon terminal is facing toward a dendritic spine. We choose the same parameters that we used for the end-shaft synapse, but the target neuron is placed in projection of the source nerve with a gap in between them of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf102"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. We include enlargements at the ends since boutons are common at the source and target neuron. Such enlargements significantly amplify ephaptic coupling.</p><p>We observe that the strong hyperpolarization of nearby postsynaptic membranes is accompanied by a distant depolarization. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D and E</xref> we present the time course of the induced membrane potential in the target at the point of maximal depolarization. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F</xref> the spatial profile of the induced voltage is given at different times.</p><p>The total amplitude of ephaptic coupling strongly depends on the choice of parameters. If we use <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf103"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1200</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (as commonly used in the HH model) instead of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf104"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>450</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>, the effect more than doubles. Note that much higher values up to <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf105"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>30</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> have been reported for specific locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Holt and Koch, 1999</xref>), which suggests even stronger ephaptic interactions in certain situations. The distant depolarization shown for the end-end synapse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D and E</xref>) is only a few tens of µV, but as the amplitude of synchronized input from many dendrites adds up and cerebellar neurons have thousands of dendrites we may expect depolarization signal strengths in the mV range.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our experimental design of a custom-made recording chamber with a nerve, hanging over a series of electrodes, allows accurate measurements of the space and time-dependent extracellular field <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf106"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. Since, according to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ9">Equation 9</xref>, variations of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf107"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> mirror variations of the membrane current <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf108"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, we obtain information on <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf109"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, on the associated velocity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf110"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and length scale <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf111"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of APs. Both of them are measured with great accuracy (about 10%), which allows us critical benchmarking of current theoretical models of APs. We find that both the TM model and the HH model are well suited to describe the extracellular electric potential of propagating APs which have symmetric forward and backward flow of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf112"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>However, when an AP encounters a boundary, either at a axon terminal or in a collision with a counter-propagating AP, the current flow and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf113"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> become asymmetric. In fact, AP propagation is terminated when the overall local axial current is annihilated by a collision event and at axon terminals. At this point, the lack of internal stimulating current causes APs to disappear, as already described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Tasaki, 1949</xref>. During AP annihilation, the extracellular potential becomes a distinct monophasic spike. This phenomenon has been observed for artificially produced as well as naturally occurring collisions in various systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Spach et al., 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Steinhaus et al., 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Tasaki, 1949</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Tasaki, 1955</xref>).</p><p>We describe the annihilation process by the time integrated charge (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf114"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ3">Equation 3</xref>) which is expelled at boundary condition, e.g., the axon terminal. From our collision experiments, we extract the spatial shape of the generated extracellular potential. The impact of extracellular potentials that are applied with microelectrodes is often described with the term ‘activating function’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Rattay, 2008</xref>). We extended this view by the integration of the naturally occurring ‘activating function’ of neurons over time (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf115"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ4">Equation 4</xref>).</p><p>We find that the experimentally observed values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf116"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and thus the underlying discharge <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf117"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> can be predicted very well by the TM/RTM models, while it is drastically underestimated by the HH model. The excellent fit of the TM model suggests that the discharge of annihilating APs is predominantly driven by the rapid depolarization at the onset of AP generation. The failure of HH is in line with observations made in various studies, indicating that the rapidity of membrane dynamics is not well described by the HH model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Cole and Moore, 1960</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Baranauskas and Martina, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Naundorf et al., 2006</xref>). Our quantitative physical description of ephaptic coupling between neurons provides a theoretical framework for investigating biological systems in which the phenomenon of ephaptic coupling already has been described and to explore other neural connections. The general cable equation, linking field inhomogeneity to membrane current, applies to both source and target cell. This leads to a coupling between source and target, driven by the electric field and its inhomogeneities. The cable model directly explains why AP-induced membrane current in a neuron induces membrane current in targets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Durand, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Merrill et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Tung, 2021</xref>). Surprisingly, this straightforward concept has never been applied to ephaptic coupling at synapses. Virtually all numerical computations of ephaptic coupling rely on the HH model which, as shown above, is not suitable to predict the effects caused by AP annihilation.</p><p>Electrical fields of propagating APs create positive and negative currents in equal amounts and a propagating AP first hyperpolarizes, then depolarizes a parallel aligned target neuron. This may cause synchronization of APs and our proposed model can also be used to study the observed phenomena of synchronization due to ephaptic coupling, even in the case of zero discharge (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref> and local impact on the target, integrated on timescales &gt; <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf118"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>).</p><p>In contrast, AP annihilation in the source neuron acts as a strong local current injection. The nonzero discharge causes a more pronounced ephaptic coupling effect. AP annihilation occurs at the axon terminal and we have investigated ephaptic coupling for two neural connections to a greater extent. Both the pre- and postsynaptic neurons have similar morphology and orientation and, in addition, accessory structures at the site of connection. In teleost fish, an interneuron with an axon cap can have inhibitory, ephaptic coupling on the Mauthner cell’s AIS, where APs are initiated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Korn and Faber, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Korn and Faber, 2005</xref>).</p><p>In the vertebrate cerebellum, the Basket cells show ephaptic coupling with the Purkinje cell, and, comparably to the Mauthner cell, the generation of APs at the AIS is inhibited by a fast gating mechanism. In the following, we use the Basket cell-Purkinje cell connection as reference and for comparison to our model(s). As in all spiking neurons, an AP in the Basket cell generates a positive extracellular potential, and it is well documented that the Purkinje cell is very sensitive to extracellular potentials, since already <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf119"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>200</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> modulates its firing rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>). The cap structure (Pinceau or Basket; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Ramón y Cajal, 1909</xref>) around the terminal of the Basket cell restricts local currents to the Purkinje cell, increasing its sensitivity at the AIS to extracellular potentials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>). The TM model predicts a fast and strong inhibition when APs are annihilating at the Basket cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). Our numerical simulation revealed that in addition to the inhibitory effect of an annihilating AP at onset, a delayed (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf120"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> later) depolarization can occur at the target neuron. The magnitude of this depolarization depends on the time course of AP repolarization at the source (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). Presynaptic variation of AP width is a widespread mechanism for modulation of synaptic transmission by changing transmitter release, and ephaptic coupling possibly contributes to a direct modulation at the postsynaptic neuron (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Begum et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Southan and Robertson, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kole et al., 2015</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>, described a biphasic modulation of Purkinje cells with delayed and synchronized APs in Purkinje cells after ephaptic inhibition by the Basket cells. In their study, the drug GABAzine was used to investigate the controversially discussed role of GABA for this modulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Iwakura et al., 2012</xref>). However, a biphasic modulation is consistent with the purely electrical framework provided in our RTM, and it remains to be investigated whether presynaptic modulation of AP width is the underlying mechanism for modulating the biphasic ephaptic coupling of Purkinje cells.</p><p>Our finding and formal description of the strong ephaptic coupling generated by annihilating APs impose the need and provide the possibility to examine bioelectric effects in other areas. Endogenous electric fields can influence molecular processes within cells, leading to cell growth, maturation, migration, and regeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">McCaig et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Levin et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Funk, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Lyckman and Bittner, 1992</xref>). The orientation of molecules and resulting structures can be induced by homogeneous electric fields and dielectric molecules can accumulate in field inhomogenities by dielectrophoresis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Cifra, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pokorný, 2001</xref>). In principle, such effects can lead to persistent structural changes in neurons and, thus, may contribute to neural plasticity and memory. During synapse formation, presynaptic neurons interact with spines of the prospective postsynapse. Prior, or in parallel, to chemical communication between the neurons that will subsequently form a synapse, Hebb’s rule might be implemented by a discharge from the source and coincident activity in the target. In this case, ephaptic coupling might be instructive for synapse formation. We included calculations on ephaptic coupling with the geometry of an end-to-end synapse and boutons on source/target (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C–E</xref>) and we find that there is an initial sharp depolarization, followed by a slight hyperpolarization. Ephaptic coupling is highly amplified when source and target neurons have boutons, and such a morphology is omnipresent in spines and also presynaptic terminals commonly have enlargements as well. Our calculation further makes clear predictions where at the target (spine) depolarization can be expected, and this is the case about 1 µm away from the very tip of the target. It is important to highlight the importance of source-target geometry, predicted by our TM/RTM models, with opposite effects of ephaptic coupling in the two configurations: end-to-shaft and end-to-end.</p><p>Besides the annihilation of APs at the axon terminal, bidirectional propagation and hence collisions of APs might be more common than previously assumed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mateus et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Scott et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Debanne et al., 2011</xref>). In theory, collisions can be used to perform computations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Siccardi et al., 2016</xref>) and neural networks possibly also perform such kind of information processing. For example, neurons for sound source localization perform a timing analysis based on binaural input. A neural network described as Jeffress delay line can accomplish such computation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Jeffress, 1948</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Franken et al., 2021</xref>, performed a delay sweep experiment and their findings on integration at MSO neurons (medial superior olive neurons in vertebrates) look intriguingly similar to our collision experiment. Time differences and coincidence, in this case, is mapped on a location, e.g., the point of collision where a discharge with a center-surround profile is generated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Treue, 2014</xref>).</p><p>Irrespective of such speculative functionalities, ephaptic coupling is ubiquitous. Its effects span spectacular length and timescales, in some cases it can bridge up to hundreds of microns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Kriebel, 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chiang et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Shivacharan et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Our formal description of ephaptic coupling between neurons provides a framework to study the functional significance of electric fields as a general mechanism for information processing in neural networks.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Experimental design</title><p>The objectives of the study were (i) to measure the electric field around propagating and colliding APs with unprecedented accuracy; (ii) to benchmark a powerful yet simple model of APs; (iii) apply this model to demonstrate its predictive power for ephaptic coupling in general.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Sample preparation</title><p>The experiments were performed with the VNC of earthworms (<italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic>). The specimen is placed in anesthesia (0.2% butanol in tap water) for 20 min. Then, it is pinned in a basin, ventral side facing upward, and covered with preparation saline (0.04% butanol in saline, 26 mM NaSO<sub>4</sub>, 25 mM NaCl, 6 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 4 mM KCl, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 55 mM sucrose, 2 mM Tris, adjusted to pH 7.4; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Drewes and Pax, 1974</xref>). The dissection starts with a small lateral incision caudally of the clitellum and it is followed by two longitudinal cuts alongside the VNC down to the posterior end. Afterward the middle lappet is removed to lay open about 10 cm of the VNC. Gently pulling up the nerve cord reveals lateral connections which are then cut to disconnect the VNC from the rest of the nervous system. Once completely disconnected, the VNC is placed in chilled saline and kept at 4°C for about 1 hr.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Electrophysiological recording of colliding APs</title><p>We use a custom-made nerve chamber made from polyoxymethylene which is encapsulated in a temperature-controlled aluminium case (cover not shown, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>) and kept at 12°C. It contains a row of silver chloride electrodes (diameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf121"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>0.8</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>), located <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf122"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> above the bottom of the chamber and separated by <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf123"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> from each other. The recording chamber is prefilled with chilled saline. The isolated VNC is transferred to the chamber and the saline is drained, leaving the VNC resting on the electrodes. Finally, the chamber is sealed with a plastic sheet and the aluminium case is closed. Two stimulators (Grass SD-9) are connected to electrodes at the ends of the nerve. In between, three custom amplifiers connect the recording electrodes to a digital storage oscilloscope (LeCroy WaveRunner 6050). Triggering of stimulation and recording is done with an Arduino microcontroller. Data is acquired with <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf124"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, smoothed with a Savitzky-Golay filter (width <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf125"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>51</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>), and baseline-corrected with the asymmetric least squares method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Eilers, 2005</xref>). The VNC contains two giant fibers, the MGF and LGF. These are unambiguously distinguished by their individual stimulation threshold and propagation velocity. For the analysis we used three collision sweep experiments. Each experiment consists of numerous recordings from three channels and varying delay, the complete data of experiment 3 is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Models</title><sec id="s4-4-1"><title>General cable model for ephaptic coupling</title><p>The connection between inner electric potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf126"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and transmembrane current is given by the general cable equation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">McNeal, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Rubinstein and Spelman, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Rattay, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anastassiou et al., 2010</xref>).<disp-formula id="equ5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="m5"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>This equation describes both the generation of membrane current caused by an AP and the concomitant current induced by an external potential, as used in clinical applications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Durand, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Merrill et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Tung, 2021</xref>). In an infinite homogeneous neuron the membrane current is determined by the second derivative of the potential. The second term accounts for the spatial change of resistivity at any structural inhomogeneities, varicosities, or neuron endings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Basser and Roth, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Holt and Koch, 1999</xref>). Assuming a constant capacity and neglecting external fields and inhomogeneities in the neuron, one obtains the cable equation, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ1">Equation 1</xref>.</p><p>We assume the neurons being embedded in a large, homogeneous and isotropic conductor. In this case, the extracellular potential at a point <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf127"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> that is generated by the source neuron is given by<disp-formula id="equ6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="m6"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf128"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the resistivity of the extracellular medium. The external potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf129"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> adds to the membrane potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf130"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of the target neuron via <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf131"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. Note that the target is considered to be in the resting state, where the transmembrane conductivity is negligible. The response is a redistribution of internal charges. In a static potential, the target neuron approaches a steady state by mirroring the external potential inhomogeneity in its transmembrane potential <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf132"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4-2"><title>Relaxing Tasaki model</title><p>The repolarization of the extracellular potential missing in the TM model is added ad hoc by a repolarization function as follows. We introduce a state parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf133"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, which is 1 for the resting state. When the membrane voltage crosses the threshold value, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf134"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is set to 0 and its subsequent dynamic is given by<disp-formula id="equ7">,<label>(7)</label><mml:math id="m7"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf135"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the repolarization time. The membrane parameters are controlled by<disp-formula id="equ8">.<label>(8)</label><mml:math id="m8"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>For  <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf136"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, the RTM reproduces the TM model, but eventually the resting state is restored a long time after an AP. With decreasing <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf137"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> the repolarization affects the extracellular current and also the process of propagation. The exponent of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf138"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> effectively causes a delay of the repolarization. The values <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf139"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf140"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> remain closer to the excited values for <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf141"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">′</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf142"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi class="MJX-variant" mathvariant="normal">′</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the time since excitation. Under this condition the influence of the repolarization upon the initial rising phase is negligible. Consequently, the TM expressions for <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf143"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf144"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> given above are in good agreement with the extended model (RTM).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4-3"><title>HH model</title><p>The celebrated HH model also relies on the cable equation but adds a couple of additional equations to mimic the spatiotemporal shape of an AP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hodgkin and Huxley, 1952</xref>). In particular, it incorporates the Nernst equilibrium and specific voltage and time-dependent ionic conductances, resulting in a large number (typically of order 20!) of free parameters. This provides an enormous flexibility to account for almost any shape of AP. Nevertheless, our study reveals that the TM model and RTM which do not incorporate ion-specific conductances are capable to fit experimental APs very well with only 3 degrees of freedom. We compare our data with the HH model for reference because of its widespread use and popularity. The complete equations and parameters are provided in Appendix 2.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Simulations</title><sec id="s4-5-1"><title>Fitting to experiment</title><p>For simulations of the APs we use the three models introduced above (TM, RTM, HH), all with the same general parameters and morphology. The Python module BRIAN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Stimberg et al., 2019</xref>) is used to simulate the nerve with a multi-compartment model using a fourth-order Runge-Kutta method with time steps of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf145"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. After simulating the AP, the extracellular potential at the electrodes is calculated.</p><p>In the nerve chamber, the nerve cord is hanging free between electrodes. The measuring electrode is surrounded by two ground electrodes which are <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf146"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> apart. All sections of the VNC that are in between the surrounding ground electrodes contribute to the measured potential according to<disp-formula id="equ9">,<label>(9)</label><mml:math id="m9"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf147"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi class="MJX-variant" mathvariant="normal">′</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the distance to the point of contact with the recording electrode, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf148"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the length of the freely hanging nerve between two neighboring electrodes, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf149"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the resistance of the nerve cord between electrodes. We estimate the touching section of the nerve to be <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf150"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>0.8</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (here <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf151"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi class="MJX-variant" mathvariant="normal">′</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) and, accounting for the sagging of the nerve between electrodes, we integrate over <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf152"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> in our calculations. In our approach, the magnitude of the TM model is controlled by <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf153"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. For easier comparison, we first adjust the TM model to the magnitude of the HH model, which is achieved with <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf154"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.5</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. All parameters are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="app3table2">Appendix 3—table 2</xref>.</p><p>Velocities are calculated from the time of AP arrival with an effective distance between the recording sites of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf155"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. The width of the collision is measured by the full width at half maximum of the negative deflection of the extracellular potential, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>. The detailed settings as well as the calculated velocities and width are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="app3table1">Appendix 3—table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5-2"><title>Predicted ephaptic coupling at synapses</title><p>We extended the standard BRIAN library to calculate the effect of an external field upon the target neuron by implementing <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ5">Equation 5</xref>. The complete data for the end-shaft geometry with and without bouton for all models is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>. Complete data for the end-end synapse is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>. We provide the full source code at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/duyn3/">https://osf.io/duyn3/</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Data and materials availability</title><p>Source code and data have been deposited at the Center for Open Science, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/duyn3/">https://osf.io/duyn3/</ext-link> and at GitHub, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/moritz-s/Pyoelectricity">https://github.com/moritz-s/Pyoelectricity</ext-link>, (copy archived at <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Schloetter, 2025</xref>) under GPL-2.0 licence. The repository contains the following three data files. Each file contains a delay sweep experiment, that is numerous recordings (with varying delay between opposing stimulations) from three channels (three electrodes along the nerve). All the data are used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>. Please refer to <italic>ExperimentAnalysis.ipynb</italic> for information about the internal structure of the files and an example of how to open and use the data.</p><p><bold>ret0018.npz (exp.</bold>1̃<bold>)</bold> 21 recordings, delay varied from 0 to 4 ms.</p><p><bold>ret0019.npz (exp.</bold>2̃<bold>)</bold> 21 recordings, delay varied from 0 to 4.5 ms.</p><p><bold>ret0020.npz (exp.</bold>3̃<bold>)</bold> 46 recordings, delay varied from 0 to 4.5 ms (raw data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>The repository contains all source code files used in this publication:</p><p><bold>pyoelectricity.py</bold> A collection of functions to calculate propagating and colliding APs, the generated extracellular field, and its influence on surrounding cells.</p><p><bold>ExperimentAnalysis.ipynb</bold> Analysis of experimental data and model fitting. Generates <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>.</p><p><bold>end-end.py</bold> Calculates the examples of ephaptic coupling at end-shaft synapses.</p><p><bold>end-end-plots.ipynb</bold> Generates the figures for parallel propagation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>) and end-shaft synapses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B and C</xref>).</p><p><bold>end-end-plots.ipynb</bold> Calculates the examples of ephaptic coupling at end-end synapses. Generates the figures for end-end synapses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D, E, and F</xref>).</p><p><bold>Pinceau.ipynb</bold> Calculation and plot of the Pinceau synapse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>The repository contains the following additional examples and test cases that are not explicitly used in the manuscript:</p><p><bold>test-ExternalField.ipynb</bold> A general example of how to calculate the impact of extracellular fields via <italic>pyoelectricity.py</italic>.</p><p><bold>standalone-ExternalField.ipynb</bold> A general standalone explanation of how to implement extracellular fields with the <italic>generalized activating function</italic> in BRIAN.</p><p><bold>Example1.ipynb</bold> A simple example demonstrating the use of <italic>pyoelectricity.py</italic> to calculate ephaptic interactions.</p><p>Please refer to the <italic>Readme.md</italic> file for further instructions on usage and structure of the provided source code files.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information" id="s5"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Software, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing – original draft, Project administration, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Writing – original draft, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Writing – original draft, Project administration, Writing – review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>This study was performed in strict accordance with the Regional German Authorities (Regierungspräsidium Freiburg) according to the German animal protection regulations specified in TierSchG and TierSchVersV. The protocol for Lumbricus terrestris required no additional approval. All surgery was performed under Trichlorbutanol anesthesia, and every effort was made to minimize suffering.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="mdar"><label>MDAR checklist</label><media xlink:href="elife-88335-mdarchecklist1-v1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s7"><title>Data availability</title><p>Complete source code and data is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/moritz-s/Pyoelectricity">https://github.com/moritz-s/Pyoelectricity</ext-link>, (copy archived at <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Schloetter, 2025</xref>) and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/duyn3">https://osf.io/duyn3</ext-link> under GPL-2.0 licence. Please refer to the README.md file for detailed information.</p><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><element-citation publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy" id="dataset1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schloetter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleineidam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year><data-title>Annihilation of action potentials induces electrical coupling between neurons</data-title><source>Open Science Framework</source><pub-id pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://osf.io/duyn3/">duyn3</pub-id></element-citation></p></sec><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Mahlon Kriebel, Georg Raiser, Sabine Kreissl, Shamit Shrivastava, and Gerardo Alvarez for fruitful discussions. This work was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) in the frame of the R Koselleck project Ma 817/9 as well as from the Zukunftskolleg Konstanz.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anastassiou</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barahona</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buzsáki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The effect of spatially inhomogeneous extracellular electric fields on neurons</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>1925</fpage><lpage>1936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3635-09.2010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20130201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anastassiou</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Ephaptic coupling to endogenous electric field activity: why bother?</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2014.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25265066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arvanitaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1942">1942</year><article-title>Effects evoked in an axon by the activity of a contiguous one</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.1942.5.2.89</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baranauskas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Martina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Sodium currents activate without a Hodgkin-and-Huxley-type delay in central mammalian neurons</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2283-05.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Only negligible deviations from electroneutrality are expected in dendritic spines</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Neuroscience</source><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>53</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41583-019-0238-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31700151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basser</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>New currents in electrical stimulation of excitable tissues</article-title><source>Annual Review of Biomedical Engineering</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bioeng.2.1.377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11701517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakiri</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Volynski</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kullmann</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Action potential broadening in a presynaptic channelopathy</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>12102</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms12102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27381274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bekkers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><chapter-title>Resistivity, axial</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Encyclopedia of Computational Neuroscience</source><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>3026</fpage><lpage>3027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4614-7320-6_35-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Ultra-rapid axon-axon ephaptic inhibition of cerebellar Purkinje cells by the pinceau</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24413696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bobik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellisman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Martone</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Potassium channel subunit Kv3.2 and the water channel aquaporin-4 are selectively localized to cerebellar pinceau</article-title><source>Brain Research</source><volume>1026</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2004.07.088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15488478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1975">1975</year><article-title>Internal resistivity of giant axons of squid and myxicola</article-title><source>Journal of General Physiology</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.66.2.139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Catterall</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>HPC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>The Hodgkin-Huxley heritage: from channels to circuits</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>14064</fpage><lpage>14073</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3403-12.2012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23055474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shivacharan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Reyes</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Slow periodic activity in the longitudinal hippocampal slice can self-propagate non-synaptically by a mechanism consistent with ephaptic coupling</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>597</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/JP276904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30295923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cifra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Electrodynamic eigenmodes in cellular morphology</article-title><source>Bio Systems</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biosystems.2012.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22750075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1960">1960</year><article-title>Potassium ion current in the squid giant axon: dynamic characteristic</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0006-3495(60)86871-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13694549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1975">1975</year><article-title>Resistivity of extruded squid axoplasm</article-title><source>Journal of General Physiology</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.66.2.133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debanne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Campanac</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bialowas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcaraz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Axon physiology</article-title><source>Physiological Reviews</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00048.2009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21527732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drewes</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pax</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1974">1974</year><article-title>Neuromuscular physiology of the longitudinal muscle of the earthworm, <italic>Lumbricus Terrestris</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Biology</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.60.2.445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><chapter-title>Electrical stimulation of excitable tissue</chapter-title><source>Biomedical Engineering Fundamentals</source><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1982">1982</year><article-title>The synapse: from electrical to chemical transmission</article-title><source>Annual Review of Neuroscience</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ne.05.030182.001545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6122420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eilers</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><source>Baseline Correction with Asymmetric Least Squares Smoothing</source><publisher-name>Leiden University Medical Centre Report</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedosejevs</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Sharp, localized phase transitions in single neuronal cells</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>119</volume><elocation-id>e2117521119</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2117521119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35165183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franken</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bondy</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haimes</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldwyn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Joris</surname><given-names>PX</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Glycinergic axonal inhibition subserves acute spatial sensitivity to sudden increases in sound intensity</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e62183</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.62183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34121662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>RHW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Endogenous electric fields as guiding cue for cell migration</article-title><source>Frontiers in Physiology</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>143</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2015.00143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26029113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Furshpan</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1963">1963</year><article-title>Two inhibitory mechanisms in the Mauthner neurons of goldfish</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.1963.26.1.140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13945908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldwyn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Neuronal coupling by endogenous electric fields: cable theory and applications to coincidence detector neurons in the auditory brain stem</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>2033</fpage><lpage>2051</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00780.2015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26823512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huxley</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1952">1952</year><article-title>A quantitative description of membrane current and its application to conduction and excitation in nerve</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>117</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.1952.sp004764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12991237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Electrical interactions via the extracellular potential near cell bodies</article-title><source>Journal of Computational Neuroscience</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/a:1008832702585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10333161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horkay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Basser</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Osmotic swelling of polyacrylate hydrogels in physiological salt solutions</article-title><source>Biomacromolecules</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bm9905031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11709847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwakura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchigashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Lack of molecular-anatomical evidence for GABAergic influence on axon initial segment of cerebellar Purkinje cells by the pinceau formation</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>9438</fpage><lpage>9448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1651-12.2012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22764252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jefferys</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Nonsynaptic modulation of neuronal activity in the brain: electric currents and extracellular ions</article-title><source>Physiological Reviews</source><volume>75</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.1995.75.4.689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7480159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeffress</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1948">1948</year><article-title>A place theory of sound localization</article-title><source>Journal of Comparative and Physiological Psychology</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0061495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18904764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1940">1940</year><article-title>Electric interaction between two adjacent nerve fibres</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.1940.sp003823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16995178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kléber</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudy</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Basic mechanisms of cardiac impulse propagation and associated arrhythmias</article-title><source>Physiological Reviews</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00025.2003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kole</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Waase</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Klassen</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustine</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Noebels</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Selective loss of presynaptic potassium channel clusters at the cerebellar basket cell terminal pinceau in adam11 mutants reveals their role in ephaptic control of purkinje cell firing</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>11433</fpage><lpage>11444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1346-15.2015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26269648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1975">1975</year><article-title>An electrically mediated inhibition in goldfish medulla</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.1975.38.2.452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1127450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>The mauthner cell half a century later: a neurobiological model for decision-making?</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2005.05.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15996545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kriebel</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1968">1968</year><article-title>Electrical coupling between tunicate heart cells</article-title><source>Life Sciences</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0024-3205(68)90303-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kriebel</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MVL</given-names></name><name><surname>Waxman</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1969">1969</year><article-title>Oculomotor neurons in fish: electrotonic coupling and multiple sites of impulse initiation</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>166</volume><fpage>520</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.166.3904.520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4309628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laube</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Röper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sewing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kistner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pongs</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Veh</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Ultrastructural localization of Shaker-related potassium channel subunits and synapse-associated protein 90 to septate-like junctions in rat cerebellar Pinceaux</article-title><source>Brain Research. Molecular Brain Research</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0169-328x(96)00120-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8915580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pezzulo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkelstein</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Endogenous bioelectric signaling networks: exploiting voltage gradients for control of growth and form</article-title><source>Annual Review of Biomedical Engineering</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-bioeng-071114-040647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28633567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindén</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Potjans</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettersen</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Grün</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Diesmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Einevoll</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Modeling the spatial reach of the LFP</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22153380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyckman</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bittner</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>Axonal conduction and electrical coupling in regenerating earthworm giant axons</article-title><source>Experimental Neurology</source><volume>117</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-4886(92)90139-h</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1397166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mateus</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>CDF</given-names></name><name><surname>Aroso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerós</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meneses</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamghari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguiar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Bidirectional flow of action potentials in axons drives activity dynamics in neuronal cultures</article-title><source>Journal of Neural Engineering</source><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>066045</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1741-2552/ac41db</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34891149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCaig</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangster</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Neurotrophins enhance electric field-directed growth cone guidance and directed nerve branching</article-title><source>Developmental Dynamics</source><volume>217</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0177(200003)217:3&lt;299::AID-DVDY8&gt;3.0.CO;2-G</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNeal</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1976">1976</year><article-title>Analysis of a model for excitation of myelinated nerve</article-title><source>IEEE Transactions on Bio-Medical Engineering</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/tbme.1976.324593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1278925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bikson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jefferys</surname><given-names>JGR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Electrical stimulation of excitable tissue: design of efficacious and safe protocols</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience Methods</source><volume>141</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jneumeth.2004.10.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15661300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mussel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Basser</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Horkay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Ion-induced volume transition in gels and its role in biology</article-title><source>Gels</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>20</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/gels7010020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33670826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naundorf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Volgushev</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Unique features of action potential initiation in cortical neurons</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>440</volume><fpage>1060</fpage><lpage>1063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16625198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plonsey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1977">1977</year><article-title>Action potential sources and their volume conductor fields</article-title><source>Proceedings of the IEEE</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/PROC.1977.10539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pokorný</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Endogenous electromagnetic forces in living cells: implications for transfer of reaction components</article-title><source>Electro- and Magnetobiology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/JBC-100103160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramón y Cajal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1909">1909</year><source>Histologie Du Système Nerveux de l’homme &amp; Des Vertébrés</source><publisher-name>Biodiversity Heritage Library</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5962/bhl.title.48637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rattay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>The basic mechanism for the electrical stimulation of the nervous system</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(98)00330-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rattay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Current distance relations for fiber stimulation with pointsources</article-title><source>IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>1122</fpage><lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TBME.2008.915676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rebollo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Telenczuk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro-Guzman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Destexhe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Vives</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Modulation of intercolumnar synchronization by endogenous electric fields in cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Science Advances</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>eabc7772</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abc7772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33658192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Spelman</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year><article-title>Analytical theory for extracellular electrical stimulation of nerve with focal electrodes. I. Passive unmyelinated axon</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>975</fpage><lpage>981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(88)83035-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3233274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schloetter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year><data-title>Pyoelectricity</data-title><version designator="swh:1:rev:9bbc0414bf6b97858bf7cf2324bbe2634a8e9915">swh:1:rev:9bbc0414bf6b97858bf7cf2324bbe2634a8e9915</version><source>Software Heritage</source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/swh:1:dir:fcca371db33b8d09deeb0668ff052a1f77accc8b;origin=https://github.com/moritz-s/Pyoelectricity;visit=swh:1:snp:d9a5bac62f34bada8a48d425af30ce4c97300cee;anchor=swh:1:rev:9bbc0414bf6b97858bf7cf2324bbe2634a8e9915">https://archive.softwareheritage.org/swh:1:dir:fcca371db33b8d09deeb0668ff052a1f77accc8b;origin=https://github.com/moritz-s/Pyoelectricity;visit=swh:1:snp:d9a5bac62f34bada8a48d425af30ce4c97300cee;anchor=swh:1:rev:9bbc0414bf6b97858bf7cf2324bbe2634a8e9915</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hage</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Weak action potential backpropagation is associated with high-frequency axonal firing capability in principal neurons of the gerbil medial superior olive</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>583</volume><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2007.136366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17627992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shivacharan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Reyes</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Self-propagating, non-synaptic epileptiform activity recruits neurons by endogenous electric fields</article-title><source>Experimental Neurology</source><volume>317</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.expneurol.2019.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30776338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Detonation of shock-waves and action potentials in lipid interfaces</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of Meetings on Acoustics</conf-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1121/2.0000906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Collision and annihilation of nonlinear sound waves and action potentials in interfaces</article-title><source>Journal of the Royal Society, Interface</source><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>20170803</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2017.0803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29925577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siccardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuszynski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Adamatzky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Boolean gates on actin filaments</article-title><source>Physics Letters A</source><volume>380</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physleta.2015.09.024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Southan</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Patch-clamp recordings from cerebellar basket cell bodies and their presynaptic terminals reveal an asymmetric distribution of voltage-gated potassium channels</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>948</fpage><lpage>955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.18-03-00948.1998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9437016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Southan</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Electrophysiological characterization of voltage-gated K(+) currents in cerebellar basket and purkinje cells: Kv1 and Kv3 channel subfamilies are present in basket cell nerve terminals</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.20-01-00114.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10627587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spach</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Serwer</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kootsey</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1971">1971</year><article-title>Collision of excitation waves in the dog purkinje system</article-title><source>Circulation Research</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.RES.29.5.499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spach</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kootsey</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1985">1985</year><article-title>Relating the sodium current and conductance to the shape of transmembrane and extracellular potentials by simulation: effects of propagation boundaries</article-title><source>IEEE Transactions on Bio-Medical Engineering</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TBME.1985.325489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2414207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinhaus</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Isomura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1985">1985</year><article-title>Action potential collision in heart tissue-computer simulations and tissue expenrments</article-title><source>IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering</source><volume>BME-32</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TBME.1985.325488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stimberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brette</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Brian 2, an intuitive and efficient neural simulator</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e47314</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.47314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31429824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1949">1949</year><article-title>Collision of two nerve impulses in the nerve fibre</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-3002(49)90121-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1955">1955</year><article-title>New measurements of the capacity and the resistance of the myelin sheath and the nodal membrane of the isolated frog nerve fiber</article-title><source>American Journal of Physiology-Legacy Content</source><volume>181</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajplegacy.1955.181.3.639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1965">1965</year><article-title>Excitation of internally perfused squid giant axons in sodium-free media</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>769</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.54.3.763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5217455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1971">1971</year><article-title>Properties of squid axon membrane as revealed by a hydrophobic probe, 2-p-toluidinylnaphthalene-6-sulfonate</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>938</fpage><lpage>941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.68.5.938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4102563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Spread of discrete structural changes in synthetic polyanionic gel: A model of propagation of A nerve impulse</article-title><source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source><volume>218</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jtbi.2002.3095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12384052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>On the cable theory of nerve conduction</article-title><source>Bulletin of Mathematical Biology</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>1082</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bulm.2002.0310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12508531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>A note on the local current associated with the rising phase of a propagating impulse in nonmyelinated nerve fibers</article-title><source>Bulletin of Mathematical Biology</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11538-005-9012-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><source>Physiology and Electrochemistry of Nerve Fibers</source><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Attentional selection: Mexican hats everywhere</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>R838</fpage><lpage>R839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.08.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25247355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><chapter-title>The generalized activating function</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cardiac Bioelectric Therapy: Mechanisms and Practical Implications</source><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-63355-4_7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Preuss</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>A role of electrical inhibition in sensorimotor integration</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>18047</fpage><lpage>18052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0806145105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19004764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lackey</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Arancillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sillitoe</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Purkinje cell neurotransmission patterns cerebellar basket cells into zonal modules defined by distinct pinceau sizes</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e55569</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.55569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32990595</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><app-group><app id="appendix-1"><title>Appendix 1</title><sec sec-type="appendix" id="s8"><title>The specific conductivity between the Basket and the Purkinje cell</title><p>The Pinceau is ensheathing the axon of the Purkinje cell. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Blot and Barbour, 2014</xref>, report a resistance of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf156"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>300</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> from inside the Pinceau to the surrounding ground.</p><p>We can estimate the specific conductance (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf157"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> in <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf158"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) by assuming an effective geometry.</p><p>The Pinceau area is reported to be 100–600 <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf159"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Zhou et al., 2020</xref>), e.g., a surface of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf160"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>200</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> corresponds to a sphere of radius <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf161"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>For a spherical shell with outer radius <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf162"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and inner radius <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf163"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.5</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> we find<disp-formula id="equ10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="m10"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Pinceau</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>106</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>which is close to the <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf164"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> used by us. Please note that the numerical values used here are coarse estimates with large uncertainties, still the order of magnitude is well compatible with literature values.</p></sec></app><app id="appendix-2"><title>Appendix 2</title><sec sec-type="appendix" id="s9"><title>HH model</title><p>The HH model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hodgkin and Huxley, 1952</xref>) is implemented using standard parameters and expressions. We use the source code based on an example provided with the BRIAN package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://brian2.readthedocs.io/en/stable/examples/compartmental.hodgkin_huxley_1952.html">https://brian2.readthedocs.io/en/stable/examples/compartmental.hodgkin_huxley_1952.html</ext-link>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Stimberg et al., 2019</xref>). The total resistive current is given by<disp-formula id="equ11"><mml:math id="m11"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>These three terms (channels) drive the membrane toward specific equilibrium values<disp-formula id="equ12"><mml:math id="m12"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>115</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10.6</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The conductivities <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf165"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> are controlled by<disp-formula id="equ13"><mml:math id="m13"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1200</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>360</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>and<disp-formula id="equ14"> <mml:math id="m14"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="mediummathspace"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="mediummathspace"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>with<disp-formula id="equ15"><mml:math id="m15"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathvariant="script">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ16"><mml:math id="m16"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathvariant="script">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>18</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ17"><mml:math id="m17"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>70</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathvariant="script">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>20</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ18"><mml:math id="m18"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathvariant="script">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>30</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ19"><mml:math id="m19"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathvariant="script">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ20"><mml:math id="m20"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>125</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathvariant="script">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>80</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>To avoid singularities, this implementation uses the function <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf166"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> which is provided by BRIAN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Stimberg et al., 2019</xref>) and is defined as<disp-formula id="equ21"><mml:math id="m21"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="left left" rowspacing=".2em" columnspacing="1em" displaystyle="false"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>if </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>otherwise</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo fence="true" stretchy="true" symmetric="true"/></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec></app><app id="appendix-3"><title>Appendix 3</title><sec sec-type="appendix" id="s10"><title>Additional experimental results</title><table-wrap id="app3table1" position="float"><label>Appendix 3—table 1.</label><caption><title>Experiment details settings as well as measured velocity and width of each experiment.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom"/><th align="left" valign="bottom">Exp. 1</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Exp. 2</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Exp. 3</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">(Unit)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"># Recordings</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">21</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">21</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Delay range</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">4.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">4.5</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf167"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Delay step</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">0.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">0.23</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">0.1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf168"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sampling rate</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf169"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Duration</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">10</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">10</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">10</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf170"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf171"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">16.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">16.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">16.3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf172"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf173"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">15.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">15.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">16.2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf174"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf175"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">←</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">15.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">15.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">14.9</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf176"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf177"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">←</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">15.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">15.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">14.9</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf178"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf179"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">13.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">13.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">13.3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf180"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf181"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">13.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">13.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">13.4</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf182"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf183"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">←</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">13.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">14.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">14.5</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf184"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf185"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">←</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">13.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">14.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">14.8</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf186"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Width</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">10.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">9.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">8.7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf187"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="app3table2" position="float"><label>Appendix 3—table 2.</label><caption><title>Model parameters.</title><p>For all models, we used the measured propagation velocity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf188"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (14.9 m/s) and the width of the collision, which is described by <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf189"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="negativethinmathspace"/><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (1.8 mm) in the Tasaki-Matsumoto (TM) and relaxing Tasaki model (RTM), in order to adjust the parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf190"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf191"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. For the Hodgkin-Huxley (HH) model, we used literature values describing the different channels, their conductivities, and time constants. For the TM model, we used the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf192"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> as given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Tasaki, 2002</xref>. In order to compare the TM and the RTM with the HH model, we adjusted <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf193"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> such that the extracellular potential of the action potential (AP) is comparable. Although the predicted amplitudes of the extracellular potentials are very different, the products <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf194"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow class="MJX-TeXAtom-ORD"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> are very similar and in good agreement with literature values (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Tasaki, 2002</xref>).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">Model</th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf195"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf196"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> </th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf197"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf198"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Amp.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">TM</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">9.94</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">26</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">113.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">HH</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">61.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">0.46</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">28</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">–</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">TM<sub>HH</sub></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">39.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">0.65</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">26</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">RTM<sub>HH</sub></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">75.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">0.47</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">36</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">0.04</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></app></app-group></back><sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="sa0"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.88335.4.sa0</article-id><title-group><article-title>eLife Assessment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Poirazi</surname><given-names>Panayiota</given-names></name><role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>FORTH Institute of Molecular Biology and Biotechnology</institution><country>Greece</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="evidence-strength"><kwd>Convincing</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="claim-importance"><kwd>Important</kwd></kwd-group></front-stub><body><p>This <bold>important</bold> study enhances our understanding of ephaptic interactions by utilizing earthworm recordings to refine a general model and use it to predict ephaptic influences across various synaptic configurations. The integration of experimental evidence, a robust mathematical framework and computer simulations <bold>convincingly</bold> demonstrate the effects of action potential propagation and collision properties on nearby membranes. The study will interest both computational neuroscientists and physiologists.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="referee-report" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.88335.4.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Reviewer #2 (Public review):</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><anonymous/><role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><p>In this study, the authors measured extracellular electrical features of colliding APs travelling in different directions down an isolated earthworm axon. They then used these features to build a model of the potential ephaptic effects of AP annihilation, i.e. the electrical signals produced by colliding/annihilating APs that may influence neighbouring tissue. The model was then applied to some different hypothetical scenarios involving synaptic connections. In a revised version of the manuscript, it was also applied, with success, to published experimental data on the cerebellar basket cell-to-Purkinje cell pinceau connection. The conclusion is that an annihilating AP at a presynaptic terminal can emphatically influence the voltage of a postsynaptic cell (the 'electrical coupling between neurons' of the title), and that the nature of this influence depends on the physical configuration of the synapse.</p><p>As an experimental neuroscientist who has never used computational approaches, I am unable to comment on the rigour of the analytical approaches that form the bulk of this paper. The experimental approaches appear very well carried out, and the data showing equal conduction velocity of anti- and orthodromically propagating APs in every preparation are convincing.</p><p>The conclusions drawn from the synaptic modelling are considerably strengthened by the data in Figure 5. Here, the authors' model - including AP annihilation at a synaptic terminal - is used to predict the amplitude and direction of experimentally observed effects at the cerebellar basket cell-to-Purkinje cell synapse (Blot &amp; Barbour 2014). One particular form of the model (RTM with tau=0.5ms and realistic non-excitability of the terminal) matches the experimental data extremely well. The authors also include a convincing demonstration (Panel A) that a propagating but not annihilating AP has almost no effect on a neighbouring neuron's activity. Given that the authors' model of ephaptic effects can quantitatively explain key features of experimental data pertaining to synaptic function, the implications for the relevance of ephaptic coupling at different synaptic contacts may be widespread and important.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.88335.4.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schloetter</surname><given-names>Moritz</given-names></name><role specific-use="author">Author</role><aff><institution>University of Konstanz</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Konstanz</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maret</surname><given-names>Georg U</given-names></name><role specific-use="author">Author</role><aff><institution>University of Konstanz</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Konstanz</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kleineidam</surname><given-names>Christoph J</given-names></name><role specific-use="author">Author</role><aff><institution>University of Konstanz</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Konstanz</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><p>The following is the authors’ response to the previous reviews.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p><bold>Reviewer 1:</bold></p><p>The authors explain that an action potential that reach an axon terminal emits a small electrical field as it &quot;annihilates&quot;. This happens even though there is no gap junction, at chemical synapses. The generated electrical field is simulated to show that it can affect a nearby, disconnected target membrane by tens of microvolts for tenths of a microsecond. Longer effects are simulated for target locations a few microns away.</p><p>To simulate action potentials (APs), the paper does not use the standard HodgkinHuxley formalism because it fails to explain AP collision. Instead it uses the Tasaki and Matsumoto (TM) model which is simplified to only models APs with three parameters and as a membrane transition between two states of resting versus excited. The authors expand the strictly binary, discrete TM method to a Relaxing Tasaki Model (RTM) that models the relaxation of the membrane potential after an AP. They find that the membrane leak can be neglected in determining AP propagation and that the capacitive currents dominate the process.</p><p>The strength of the work is that authors identified an important interaction between neurons that is neglected by the standard models. A weakness of the proposed approach is the assumptions that it makes. For instance, the external medium is modeled as a homogeneous conductive medium, which may be further explored to properly account for biological processes. To the authors’ credit, the external medium can be largely varying and could be left out from the general model, only to be modeled specific instances.</p><p>The authors provide convincing evidence by performing experiments to record action potential propagation and collision properties and then developing a theoretical framework to simulate effect of their annihilation on nearby membranes. They provide both experimental evidence and rigorous mathematical and computer simulation findings to support their claims. The work has a potential of explaining significant electrical interaction between nerve centers that are connected via a large number of parallel fibers.</p><p>Comments on revisions:</p><p>The authors responded to all of my previous concerns and significantly improved the manuscript.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for his comments and are pleased that we were able to adequately address all of his previous concerns. As a small comment to the remark of the reviewer “potential of explaining ... interaction ... via a large number of parallel fibers” we would like to add: The ephaptic coupling is prominent when APs annihilate at axon terminals, as we illustrate in Figure 4 and 5. Across parallel fibers, the impact of propagating APs is much lower but still may result in synchronization of APs.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p><bold>Reviewer 2:</bold></p><p>In this study, the authors measured extracellular electrical features of colliding APs travelling in different directions down an isolated earthworm axon. They then used these features to build a model of the potential ephaptic effects of AP annihilation, i.e. the electrical signals produced by colliding/annihilating APs that may influence neighbouring tissue. The model was then applied to some different hypothetical scenarios involving synaptic connections. In a revised version of the manuscript, it was also applied, with success, to published experimental data on the cerebellar basket cell-to-Purkinje cell pinceau connection. The conclusion is that an annihilating AP at a presynaptic terminal can emphatically influence the voltage of a postsynaptic cell (this is, presumably, the ’electrical coupling between neurons’ of the title), and that the nature of this influence depends on the physical configuration of the synapse.</p><p>As an experimental neuroscientist who has never used computational approaches, I am unable to comment on the rigour of the analytical approaches that form the bulk of this paper. The experimental approaches appear very well carried out, and the data showing equal conduction velocity of anti- and orthodromically propagating APs in every preparation is now convincing.</p><p>The conclusions drawn from the synaptic modelling have been considerably strengthened by the new Figure 5. Here, the authors’ model - including AP annihilation at a synaptic terminal - is used to predict the amplitude and direction of experimentally observed effects at the cerebellar basket cell-to-Purkinje cell synapse (Blot &amp; Barbour 2014). One particular form of the model (RTM with tau=0.5ms and realistic non-excitability of the terminal) matches the experimental data extremely well. This is a much more convincing demonstration that the authors’ model of ephaptic effects can quantitatively explain key features of experimental data pertaining to synaptic function. As such, the implications for the relevance of ephaptic coupling at different synaptic contacts may be widespread and important.</p><p>However, it appears that all of the models in the new Fig5 involve annihilating APs, yet only one fits the data closely. A key question, which should be addressed if at all possible, is what happens to the predictive power of the best-fitting model in Fig5 if the annihilation, and only the annihilation, is removed? In other words, can the authors show that it is specifically the ephaptic effects of AP annihilation, rather than other ephaptic effects of, say AP waveform/amplitude/propagation, that explain the synaptic effects measured in Blot &amp; Barbour (2014)? This would appear to be a necessary demonstration to fully support the claims of the title.</p><p><bold>Reviewer 2 (Recommendations for the authors):</bold></p><p>Can you clarify whether all models shown in Fig5 involve an annihilating AP? Is it possible to plot the predicted effects of the most successful model (RTM 0.5ms in B) with *only* the annihilation selectively removed?</p></disp-quote><p>We are grateful for the reviewer’s comments and the specific suggestion for improvement (’...can the authors show that it is specifically the ephaptic effects of AP annihilation, rather than other ephaptic effects...’). For illustrating the importance of annihilation, we added the results of our calculation when no annihilation occurs, i.e. for propagating APs in the source neuron (Figure 5A) and we modified the geometry of the source neuron in Figure 5B such that only the annihilation takes place. Together with the source neuron with similar properties to the Basket cell (Figure 5C), we now show the effect of annihilation and the effect of Basket cell specific geometry and physiology. We added and edited in the main text the following 4 sentences:</p><p>ll 271: In our two models (TM and RTM), the modulation of not terminating but propagating APs along the source axon on the AP rate of the target cell is minute (Figure 5A). Note that this geometry does not correspond to the Purkinje cell-Basket cell connectivity. For annihilating APs at the axon terminal, with excitable segments up to the very end, our models reveal a moderate modulation, and only about half of what was reported for the Purkinje cell by Blot and Barbour (2014). This illustrates the importance of AP annihilation for ephaptic coupling (Figure 5B). We added and edited the figure legend:</p><p>Figure 5. ... (A) excluding the annihilation of an AP at the source neuron, i.e. a propagating AP, cause only minute modulation of the predicted AP rate in the target neuron. Note that this example does not represent the Basket cell terminal with annihilating APs. (B) annihilation of an AP at the terminal of the source neuron, with all segments being excitable in our calculation, cause moderate modulation. (C) source neuron with similar properties to the Basket cell, i.e. a bouton and last segments non-excitable (corresponding to 15 µm with no switch from resting state to excited state), cause inhibition and rebound that is very similar as described by Blot and Barbour (2014).</p><p>In the discussion, we extended one sentence to refer to Figure 5:</p><p>ll 346: This may cause synchronization of APs and our proposed model also can be used to study the observed phenomena of synchronization due to ephaptic coupling, even in the case of zero discharge (see Figure 4A, and local impact on the target, integrated on timescales &gt;1 ms in Figure 5).</p></body></sub-article></article>