<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">49570</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49570</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology and Infectious Disease</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Persistent <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> infection in mice requires PerM for successful cell division</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-149075"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Ruojun</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0519-2350</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-149078"><name><surname>Kreutzfeldt</surname><given-names>Kaj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-149079"><name><surname>Botella</surname><given-names>Helene</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-149080"><name><surname>Vaubourgeix</surname><given-names>Julien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-107751"><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname><given-names>Dirk</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-103150"><name><surname>Ehrt</surname><given-names>Sabine</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7951-2310</contrib-id><email>sae2004@med.cornell.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Microbiology and Immunology</institution><institution>Weill Cornell Medical College</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">New York</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Immunology and Microbial Pathogenesis Graduate Program</institution><institution>Weill Cornell Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Cornell University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">New York</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>Wendy S</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>Harvard TH Chan School of Public Health</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kana</surname><given-names>Bavesh D</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of the Witwatersrand</institution><country>South Africa</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa1"><label>†</label><p>MRC Centre for Molecular Bacteriology and Infection, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e49570</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2019-06-26"><day>26</day><month>06</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2019-11-11"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2019, Wang et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-49570-v1.pdf"/><abstract><p>The ability of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> (Mtb) to persist in its host is central to the pathogenesis of tuberculosis, yet the underlying mechanisms remain incompletely defined. PerM, an integral membrane protein, is required for persistence of Mtb in mice. Here, we show that <italic>perM</italic> deletion caused a cell division defect specifically during the chronic phase of mouse infection, but did not affect Mtb’s cell replication during acute infection. We further demonstrate that PerM is required for cell division in chronically infected mice and in vitro under host-relevant stresses because it is part of the mycobacterial divisome and stabilizes the essential divisome protein FtsB. These data highlight the importance of sustained cell division for Mtb persistence, define condition-specific requirements for cell division and reveal that survival of Mtb during chronic infection depends on a persistence divisome.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></kwd><kwd>chronic infection</kwd><kwd>persistence</kwd><kwd>cell division</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Other</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000060</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>U19 AI111143</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname><given-names>Dirk</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname><given-names>Sabine</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000060</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>U19 AI107774</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname><given-names>Dirk</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname><given-names>Sabine</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>PerM-mediated FtsB stabilization is essential for cell division of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> during chronic but not acute mouse infections.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The World Health Organization reports that an estimated 23% of the world’s population is latently infected with Mtb (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/tb/publications/global_report/en/">https://www.who.int/tb/publications/global_report/en/</ext-link>). Although asymptomatic and non-contagious, latent infections progress to active disease in 5–15% of cases, causing clinical symptoms and allowing for disease transmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Pai et al., 2016</xref>). The time before active disease develops following exposure to Mtb, ranges from a few months to two years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Behr et al., 2018</xref>). And, in regions with minimal TB transmission, Mtb can persist in individuals for decades before causing active disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Behr et al., 2018</xref>). This remarkable ability of Mtb to persist inside its host contributes greatly to its success as a pathogen yet the mechanisms facilitating persistence remain incompletely defined. The term ‘persistence’ used in this report refers to the ability of bacteria to remain viable in the host for a prolonged period of time, and should be distinguished from ‘persister cells’, a subpopulation of transiently antibiotic-tolerant cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Fisher et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>The mouse model has been used to evaluate bacterial factors that allow Mtb to persist within its host. After aerosol infection, Mtb replicates logarithmically in mouse lungs until the onset of adaptive immunity arrests replication, leading to a chronic infection that is contained but not eliminated. Experiments with genetic Mtb mutants identified mycobacterial pathways that are crucial for persistence following the onset of adaptive immunity despite being dispensable for cell replication in the acute phase of infection. Among those pathways, metabolic adaption and modulation of the cell envelope play key roles in Mtb’s persistence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Ehrt et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Glickman and Jacobs, 2001</xref>).</p><p>We have previously reported that PerM, an integral membrane protein with 10 transmembrane helices is essential for Mtb persistence in the mouse model of infection. Disruption of <italic>perM</italic> (<italic>rv0955</italic>) by transposon insertion led to a minor growth defect in the acute phase of mouse infection, but a strong attenuation in the chronic phase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Goodsmith et al., 2015</xref>). Further characterization of the mutant by transcriptome analysis, microscopy imaging and drug susceptibility assays suggested that PerM is associated with cell division. However, PerM’s specific roles in cell division and how its absence resulted in a persistence defect in vivo remained unknown.</p><p>TB is a complex disease that is highly heterogeneous with regards to outcomes of infection, pathology and nature of bacterial populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cadena et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Logsdon and Aldridge, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Rego et al., 2017</xref>). In fact, the apparent static, non-replicating population that persists in chronically infected mice consists of a mixture of heterogeneous populations of replicating, non-replicating but alive, and dead bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gill et al., 2009</xref>). Using a ‘replication clock’, a plasmid-based reporter of bacterial replication, Gill et al. showed that Mtb replicates during the chronic phase of mouse infection, although at a much slower rate than in the acute phase. This discovery suggests that growth is not only important for increasing the bacterial burden during acute infection, it may also be required for Mtb to persist in chronically infected mice.</p><p>Here, we demonstrate that PerM is a mycobacterial divisome component and facilitates cell division by stabilizing FtsB, a conserved divisome protein known to be essential for the initiation of septation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Buddelmeijer et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Levin and Losick, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Wu et al., 2018</xref>). We document that although PerM is dispensable during the acute phase of mouse infection, it is required for Mtb cell division during chronic mouse infection and in host-relevant stress conditions, during which maintaining an optimal FtsB level becomes crucial. To our knowledge, PerM represents the first reported bacterial divisome component that is conditionally essential for cell division at different stages of mouse infection.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Mtb requires PerM for optimal cell replication during chronic mouse infection</title><p>We previously reported that an Mtb <italic>perM</italic> transposon mutant failed to persist in the chronic phase of mouse infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Goodsmith et al., 2015</xref>). To distinguish whether this was the result of slowed bacterial replication or enhanced killing by the host, we constructed a <italic>perM</italic> deletion strain (<italic>ΔperM</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Xu et al., 2017</xref>) and determined cell replication rates of WT and the <italic>ΔperM</italic> mutant using the ‘replication clock’ plasmid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gill et al., 2009</xref>). Measurements of growth and plasmid loss showed that the two strains replicated at a similar rate in standard in vitro growth conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>During the initial two weeks after aerosol infection with approximately 1000 CFU, WT and <italic>ΔperM</italic> grew logarithmically in mouse lungs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). As expected, this was accompanied by a decrease in the frequency of bacteria carrying the ‘replication clock’ plasmid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). The rate of plasmid loss was similar between WT and <italic>ΔperM</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>), resulting in a calculated doubling time of around 20 hr for both strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>). During the first two weeks of infection, cell replication rates exceeded death rates in both Mtb strains and led to an increase in bacterial burden (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Mtb requires PerM for optimal cell division during chronic mouse infection.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Bacterial titers in lungs of C57BL/6 mice infected with WT Mtb or the <italic>∆perM</italic> mutant containing the replication clock plasmid pBP10 at the indicated time points post-infection. Data are means ± SD of five mice. (<bold>B</bold>) Fractions of bacteria containing the pBP10 plasmid at the indicated time points. Data are means ± SD of five mice. P-values were calculated using multiple <italic>t</italic> tests and adjusted for multiple comparisons. *, adj-P &lt;0.05; **, adj-P &lt;0.01; ****, adj-P &lt;0.0001. (<bold>C</bold>) Calculated cumulative bacterial burden (CBB) in mouse lungs. (<bold>D</bold>) Scatter plots of cell length of WT Mtb (black) or the <italic>∆perM</italic> mutant (red) in acid-fast stained lung sections at the indicated time points. The middle lines represent the medians and the top and bottom lines represent the 25<sup>th</sup> and 75<sup>th</sup> percentiles. P-values were calculated using Kruskal-Wallis test and corrected for multiple comparisons. ****, adj-P &lt;0.0001. Data in (<bold>A–C</bold>) are from one experiment, and data in (<bold>D</bold>) are representative of two independent experiments.</p><p> <supplementary-material id="fig1sdata1"><label>Figure 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Summary statistics of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig1-data1-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material> </p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Mtb WT and <italic>∆perM</italic> replicate similarly in vitro.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Growth measured by optical density of serially diluted WT-pBP10 and <italic>∆perM</italic>-pBP10 cultures. Cultures were diluted every three days to allow for continuous culturing. Data are means ± SD of triplicates (error bars are too small to be detected).(<bold>B</bold>) Plasmid loss from Mtb WT and the <italic>∆perM </italic>mutant in log phase continuous cultures in the absence of antibiotic selection. Data are means ± SEM of triplicates. Data in (<bold>A and B</bold>) are representative of two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig1-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Mtb <italic>∆perM</italic> replicates more slowly than WT in the chronic phase of mouse infection.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Calculated doubling time of WT-pBP10 and <italic>∆perM</italic>-pBP10 recovered from mouse lungs during the indicated time intervals. Data are represented as doubling time ± SE. (<bold>B</bold>) Calculated bacterial replication (empty bars) and death (filled bars) rates of WT-pBP10 and <italic>∆perM</italic>-pBP10 recovered from mouse lungs during the indicated time intervals. Calculations of the cell replication and death rates are described in Materials and methods. Data are replication or death rates ± SE. Statistical significance for cell replication rates (<bold>r</bold>) was computed using analysis of covariance (ANCOVA). <italic>P</italic> = 0.1995 comparing r of WT and <italic>∆perM</italic> during week 1-2. <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001 comparing r of WT and <italic>∆perM</italic> during week 2-12. Data in (<bold>A and B</bold>) are from one experiment.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig1-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Replication clock experiment with low Mtb inoculum reveals slower cell replication of <italic>∆perM</italic> than WT in the chronic phase of mouse infection.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Bacterial burden in lungs of C57BL/6 mice infected with WT-pBP10 or <italic>∆perM</italic>-pBP10. Data are means ± SD of five mice. (<bold>B</bold>) Fractions of bacteria containing the pBP10 plasmid at the indicated time points. Data are means ± SD of five mice. P-values were calculated using multiple <italic>t</italic> tests and adjusted for multiple comparisons. *, adj-P &lt;0.05. At week 8, adj-P equals 0.066. (<bold>C</bold>) Calculated cumulative bacterial burden (CBB) in mouse lungs. (<bold>D</bold>) Calculated doubling time during the indicated time intervals. Data are doubling time ± SE. (<bold>E</bold>) Calculated cell replication (empty bars) and death (filled bars) rates during the indicated time intervals. Data are rates ± SE. Statistical significance for cell replication rates (<bold>r</bold>) was computed using ANCOVA. <italic>P</italic> = 0.2102 comparing r of WT and <italic>∆perM</italic> during week 1-4. <italic>P</italic> = 0.0047 comparing r of WT and <italic>∆perM</italic> during week 4-12. Data in (<bold>A–E</bold>) are from one experiment.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig1-figsupp3-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>From 2 to 12 weeks post infection, WT Mtb persisted with stable bacterial titers, while <italic>ΔperM</italic> titers decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). Both strains lost the ‘replication clock’ plasmid more slowly than during the acute phase of infection, but plasmid loss was significantly slower in <italic>ΔperM</italic> than in WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). The calculated doubling time of <italic>ΔperM</italic> was 280 ± 61 hr, more than twice the doubling time of WT, which was 111 ± 8 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>). Consistently, the cell replication rate of <italic>ΔperM</italic> was significantly lower than that of WT while death rates were comparable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref>). Next, we quantified the cumulative bacterial burden (CBB), defined as the total number of bacteria in the mouse lung including live, dead and those cleared by host immunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gill et al., 2009</xref>). We found that the CBB of WT increased steadily during weeks 2–12. In marked contrast, the CBB of <italic>ΔperM</italic> increased only slightly during the same time interval (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). A second mouse infection with approximately 100 CFU administered by aerosol yielded similar results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>). Overall, these data demonstrate that the failure of <italic>ΔperM</italic> to persist in the chronic phase of mouse infection can be attributed to a cell replication defect.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>PerM facilitates cell division in Mtb during chronic mouse infection</title><p>We quantified bacterial cell length in acid fast-stained infected lung sections. At week two, WT and <italic>ΔperM</italic> had comparable median cell lengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). At week three, <italic>ΔperM</italic> cells were significantly longer than WT cells and this difference in cell length remained at weeks four and five. These measurements strongly suggest that the observed cell replication defect is associated with impaired cell division during the chronic phase of mouse infection.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Depletion of PerM leads to defects in septum formation and resolution in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic></title><p>To explore how PerM facilitates cell division, we studied its homolog in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, a non-pathogenic mycobacterium; MSMEG_5517 (PerM<sub>msm</sub>) shares 73% identity with PerM from Mtb. Unexpectedly, we failed to isolate a <italic>perM<sub>msm</sub></italic> deletion mutant, which suggested that <italic>perM<sub>msm</sub></italic> is essential for growth of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>. We therefore constructed a PerM dual-control (DUC) mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A–C</xref>), in which PerM expression is controlled by both transcriptional silencing and proteolytic degradation in response to anhydrotetracycline (atc) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Kim et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Schnappinger et al., 2015</xref>). The number of viable cells remained constant in the PerM-depleted population, indicating that PerM depletion was bacteriostatic over the course of the experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1D</xref>). PerM depletion resulted in an increase of median cell length from 4.46 µm to 11.1 µm in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A,B</xref>). Additionally, peptidoglycan labeling with the fluorescent D-alanine analog HCC‐amino‐D‐alanine (HADA) revealed that the elongated cells formed filaments, with the majority containing either none or only one septum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A,C</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kuru et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kuru et al., 2015</xref>). DNA staining with SYTO 13 revealed separated nucleoids spanning the entire length of each bacterium, suggesting that PerM depletion did not affect DNA segregation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>). The phenotypes associated with PerM depletion in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> demonstrate that PerM is involved in septation.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Depletion of PerM leads to a septation defect in <italic>M. smegmatis.</italic></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative microscopy images of WT <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> and the <italic>perM</italic>-DUC mutant after 9 hr of incubation in 7H9 medium supplemented with 1 mM HADA and in the absence or presence of 200 ng/ml atc. Scale bar, 1 µm. (<bold>B</bold>) Scatter plots of bacterial cell length of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> strains from (<bold>A</bold>). The middle lines represent the medians and the top and bottom lines represent the 25<sup>th</sup> and 75<sup>th</sup> percentiles. P-values were computed using Kruskal-Wallis test and adjusted for multiple comparisons. ****, adj-P &lt;0.0001. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of bacterial cells that contain 0, 1, 2 or 3 septa of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> strains from (<bold>A</bold>). Data in (<bold>A–C</bold>) are representative of two independent experiments.</p><p> <supplementary-material id="fig2sdata1"><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Summary statistics of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig2-data1-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material> </p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig2-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Construction and characterization of a PerM<sub>msm</sub> depletion mutant (<italic>perM</italic>-DUC).</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Map of <italic>perM<sub>msm</sub></italic> genomic region in WT and the att-site mutant <italic>∆perM<sub>msm</sub>::hsp60-perM<sub>mtb</sub>-gfp</italic>. To construct the att-site mutant, we first generated a merodiploid strain by integrating a copy of <italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub>-gfp</italic> into the attL5 site expressed under the constitutive hsp60 promoter. Next, we replaced the first 971 bp of <italic>perM<sub>msm</sub></italic> with a hygromycin resistance cassette using homologous recombination. (<bold>B</bold>) Southern blots of genomic DNA from WT and two att-site mutant candidates after digestion with <italic>Eco</italic>RI and probed with probe 1 (left) and probe 2 (right) as marked in (<bold>A</bold>). Bands at around 1 kb from the two candidates showed the successful deletion of <italic>perM<sub>msm</sub></italic>. (<bold>C</bold>) Schematic of constructing the <italic>perM</italic>-DUC mutant from the <italic>perM</italic> att-site mutant. We first replaced the construct in the attL5 site of <italic>∆perM<sub>msm</sub>::hsp60-perM<sub>mtb</sub>-gfp</italic> with DAS tagged <italic>perM-gfp</italic> expressed under the P766-9T promoter and controlled by reverse tet repressor. A construct that expresses the SspB adaptor protein was integrated into the att-tweety site. (<bold>D</bold>) Bacterial titers of WT and <italic>perM</italic>-DUC cultured in standing 7H9 medium with and without atc. At the indicated time points, samples were collected and CFU recovered on 7H10 agar that contains 0.4% charcoal to remove carryover of atc. Data are means ± SD of three replicates and representative of two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig2-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Nucleoid morphology of WT <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> and <italic>perM</italic>-DUC in the absence and presence of atc.</title><p>Representative microscopy images of WT and <italic>perM</italic>-DUC incubated in 7H9 medium containing 1 mM HADA and in the absence or presence of 200 ng/ml atc for 9 hr. Cells were stained with 5 µM SYTO 13 to label the DNA. Arrowheads point to multiple stained nucleoids (visualized as distinct globular structures) within the <italic>perM</italic>-DUC mutant incubated in the presence of atc. Scale bar, 1 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig2-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>We then monitored septum formation and resolution in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> by sequential peptidoglycan labeling with HADA and a second fluorescent D-alanine analog, NBD‐amino‐D‐alanine (NADA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). As expected, incubation of <italic>perM</italic>-DUC with atc led to increased cell length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B,C</xref>); the median cell length increased from 3.79 μm (no atc) to 4.598 μm, 5.191 μm and 6.948 μm after 1.5, 4 and 10 hr of atc treatment. Next, we quantified the formation of new septa (labeled with NADA alone) and the resolution of old septa (labeled with HADA alone or both D-alanine probes) after PerM depletion. The percentage of septa labeled with NADA alone declined from 23.77% (no atc) to 14.62%, 12.56% and 15.92% after 1.5, 4 and 10 hr incubation with atc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>), suggesting that PerM-depleted cells had an impaired ability to form new septa. In contrast, the proportion of HADA-containing septa increased with time, from 0.61% (no atc) to 1.14%, 5.34% and 8.48% after 1.5, 4 and 10 hr atc treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). Collectively, these results indicate that PerM depletion affects both septum formation and cell separation in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, causing the bacteria to form filaments.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>PerM depletion leads to defects in septum formation and resolution in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic of peptidoglycan labeling of <italic>M. smegmatis perM</italic>-DUC. Bacterial cells were incubated in growth medium containing 1 mM HADA and 200 ng/ml atc for 0.5, 3, or 9 hr. Cells were then washed to remove excess HADA and incubated with 1 mM NADA and 200 ng/ml atc for 1 hr. <italic>PerM</italic>-DUC cells incubated in growth medium containing D-alanine probes but without atc were used as controls. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative microscopy images of <italic>perM</italic>-DUC after the sequential peptidoglycan labeling. Arrowheads point to septa labeled with NADA only; and arrows point to septa co-labeled with HADA and NADA. Scale bar, 1 µm. (<bold>C</bold>) Scatter plots of <italic>perM</italic>-DUC cell lengths from (<bold>B</bold>). Lines represent median and the 25<sup>th</sup> and 75<sup>th</sup> percentiles. Data are representative of three biological replicates. (<bold>D</bold>) Proportion of bacteria that contain septa labeled exclusively with NADA. Lines indicate means ± SD of three independent experiments. (<bold>E</bold>) Proportion of bacteria that contain septa labeled exclusively with HADA or co-labeled with NADA. Lines indicate means ± SD of septa labeled with HADA+NADA from three independent experiments. Statistics are reported on the HADA+NADA datasets. For data in (<bold>D and E</bold>), P-values were computed using ANOVA and adjusted for multiple comparisons. *, adj-P &lt;0.05; **, adj-P &lt;0.01; ***, adj-P &lt;0.001.</p><p> <supplementary-material id="fig3sdata1"><label>Figure 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Summary statistics of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig3-data1-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material> </p><p> <supplementary-material id="fig3sdata2"><label>Figure 3—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Summary of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D and 3E</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig3-data2-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material> </p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig3-v1.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Ectopic FtsB expression rescues the phenotypes caused by PerM depletion in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> and PerM deletion in Mtb</title><p>Septation requires the coordinated activities of cell wall biosynthetic and lytic enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kieser and Rubin, 2014</xref>). To identify proteins that might rescue the septation defects caused by PerM depletion in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, we performed a forward genetic screen. We transformed <italic>perM</italic>-DUC with an Mtb genomic library and selected for colonies able to grow on agar containing atc, a non-growth-permissive condition for the <italic>perM</italic>-DUC mutant. The plasmids that rescued growth of <italic>perM</italic>-DUC contained either <italic>rv0955</italic> (<italic>perM</italic>) or <italic>rv1024</italic>.</p><p><italic>Rv1024</italic> encodes the Mtb homolog of FtsB (FtsB<sub>mtb</sub>), an integral membrane protein of the bacterial divisome that is conserved across different bacterial species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Buddelmeijer et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Levin and Losick, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Wu et al., 2018</xref>). In model bacteria such as <italic>E. coli</italic>, FtsB is recruited to the septum as part of a complex that also contains FtsQ and FtsL, two other bitopic proteins essential for cell division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Buddelmeijer and Beckwith, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Glas et al., 2015</xref>). The FtsQLB complex is thought to drive septation by stimulating peptidoglycan synthesis by the peptidoglycan synthases FtsI and FtsW along with their associated proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kureisaite-Ciziene et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Liu et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Taguchi et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Tsang and Bernhardt, 2015</xref>). <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> encodes homologs of all three proteins. Like in <italic>E. coli</italic>, depletion of FtsQ, FtsL or FtsB in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> resulted in morphological changes indicative of impaired septation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Buddelmeijer et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Carson et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Guzman et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Wu et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> is 72% identical to FtsB<sub>msm</sub>, and ectopic expression of either protein from a multicopy plasmid rescued the growth defect caused by PerM depletion in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Furthermore, ectopically-expressed FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> or FtsB<sub>msm</sub> reversed the cell elongation phenotype as did complementation with <italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub></italic> or <italic>perM<sub>msm</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). Therefore, PerM likely acts on FtsB to facilitate septum formation in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>. Moreover, FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> and FtsB<sub>msm</sub> appear to be functionally conserved.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Ectopic <italic>ftsB</italic> expression rescues the phenotypes caused by PerM depletion in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> and <italic>perM</italic> deletion in Mtb.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) <italic>M. smegmatis perM-</italic>DUC transformed with a control plasmid or plasmids that express <italic>perM<sub>msm</sub></italic>, <italic>ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic> or <italic>ftsB<sub>msm</sub></italic> under the constitutive hsp60 promoter were cultured on 7H10 agar. The paper disks in the center of the plates contained 50 ng atc, which diffused and created an atc gradient from the center to the periphery. Images of plates were taken on day 4 (<italic>perM</italic>-DUC-control, <italic>perM-</italic>DUC<italic>-perM<sub>msm</sub></italic> and <italic>perM-</italic>DUC<italic>-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic>) or day 7 (<italic>perM-</italic>DUC<italic>-ftsB<sub>msm</sub></italic>). (<bold>B</bold>) Scatter plots of the lengths of <italic>perM</italic>-DUC-control, <italic>perM-</italic>DUC<italic>-perM<sub>mtb</sub>, perM-</italic>DUC<italic>-perM<sub>msm</sub></italic>, <italic>perM-</italic>DUC<italic>-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic> and <italic>perM-</italic>DUC<italic>-ftsB<sub>msm</sub></italic> incubated in 7H9 medium without and with atc for 24 hr. The lines represent the 25<sup>th</sup>, 50<sup>th</sup> and 75<sup>th</sup> percentiles. P-values were computed using Kruskal-Wallis test and adjusted for multiple comparisons. ****, adj-P &lt;0.0001. (<bold>C</bold>) Growth curves of Mtb incubated in chelated Sauton’s medium supplemented with Mg<sup>2+</sup> at the indicated concentrations. (<bold>D</bold>) Scatter plots of Mtb cell lengths after 5 days of incubation in Sauton’s medium containing Mg<sup>2+</sup> at the indicated concentrations. The lines represent the 25<sup>th</sup>, 50<sup>th</sup> and 75<sup>th</sup> percentiles. P-values were computed using Kruskal-Wallis test and corrected for multiple comparisons. The adjusted P-values are &lt;0.0001 for the following comparisons: WT with <italic>∆perM</italic> at 25 µM, 100 µM, 250 µM Mg<sup>2+</sup>, WT with <italic>∆perM::ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic> at 25 µM Mg<sup>2+</sup>; <italic>∆perM</italic> with <italic>∆perM::ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic> at 25 µM Mg<sup>2+</sup>. Adj-P = 0.0762, 0.1095 and 0.7284 comparing WT to <italic>∆perM::ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic> at 100 µM, 250 µM and 2000 µM Mg<sup>2+</sup>, respectively. Data in (<bold>A–C</bold>) are representative of two independent experiments, and data in (<bold>D</bold>) are from one experiment.</p><p> <supplementary-material id="fig4sdata1"><label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Summary statistics of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig4-data1-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material> </p><p> <supplementary-material id="fig4sdata2"><label>Figure 4—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Summary statistics of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig4-data2-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material> </p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig4-v1.tif"/></fig><p>As we reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Goodsmith et al., 2015</xref>), PerM is required for cell replication and survival of Mtb in media with reduced magnesium (Mg<sup>2+</sup>) and Mtb lacking PerM elongated in response to Mg<sup>2+</sup> limitation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C,D</xref>). Both the growth and elongation phenotypes were, to a large extent, rescued by ectopic expression of FtsB, indicating that PerM likely functions via FtsB in Mtb as well.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>PerM interacts with FtsB</title><p>To assess the molecular mechanism by which PerM contributes to cell division and to determine if FtsB and PerM interact physically, we immunoprecipitated FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> containing an N-terminal Flag-tag from Mtb protein lysates and identified its interactors using mass spectrometry (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). PerM<sub>mtb</sub> co-immunoprecipitated with FtsB<sub>mtb</sub>, suggesting that the two proteins are part of the same complex. This interaction was verified in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> strains that co-expressed PerM<sub>mtb</sub> and FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> with different protein tags (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>). The mass spectrometry data also revealed that FtsB interacts with FtsQ in Mtb (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). Similar to its homologs in <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, FtsQ<sub>mtb</sub> has been shown to be a septal-localizing integral membrane protein that modulates cell division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Buddelmeijer and Beckwith, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jain et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Katis et al., 2000</xref>). FtsB, FtsL and FtsQ form a complex in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Buddelmeijer and Beckwith, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kureisaite-Ciziene et al., 2018</xref>), and here we provide evidence that the interaction between FtsB and FtsQ is conserved in mycobacteria.</p><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Mass spectrometry identification of protein interaction partners of FtsB in Mtb.</title><p> <supplementary-material id="table1sdata1"><label>Table 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Mass spectrometry data of FtsB pulldown in Mtb.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-table1-data1-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material> </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Rv #</th><th>Gene</th><th>Annotation</th><th valign="top">Sum total spectrum count</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Rv1687c</td><td/><td>ABC transporter ATP-binding protein</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>Rv2901c</td><td/><td>Hypothetical protein</td><td>16</td></tr><tr><td>Rv1280c</td><td><italic>oppA</italic></td><td>Probable periplasmic oligopeptide-binding lipoprotein OppA</td><td>16</td></tr><tr><td>Rv2151c</td><td><italic>ftsQ</italic></td><td>Cell division protein FtsQ</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td>Rv1697</td><td/><td>Hypothetical protein</td><td>14</td></tr><tr><td>Rv3330</td><td><italic>dacB1</italic></td><td>Probable penicillin-binding protein DacB1</td><td>14</td></tr><tr><td>Rv1698</td><td><italic>mctB</italic></td><td>Outer membrane protein MctB</td><td>14</td></tr><tr><td>Rv1266c</td><td><italic>pknH</italic></td><td>Serine/threonine protein kinase</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>Rv2748c</td><td><italic>ftsK</italic></td><td>Cell division protein FtsK</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Rv0955</td><td><italic>perM</italic></td><td/><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Rv0050</td><td><italic>ponA1</italic></td><td>Peptidoglycan glycosyltransferase</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Rv3493c</td><td/><td>MCE-associated alanine and valine rich protein</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Rv0497</td><td/><td>Probable conserved transmembrane protein</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Rv3212</td><td/><td>Conserved alanine valine rich protein</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>Rv0046c</td><td><italic>ino1</italic></td><td>Inositol-1-phosphate synthase</td><td>8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Flag-FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> was immunoprecipitated from whole-cell lysates of Mtb. Whole-cell lysates of an Mtb strain constitutively expressing only the Flag-tag served as control. The protein interaction partners were identified by mass spectrometry and data are from two independent biological replicates.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>FtsB localizes to the mid-cell independently of PerM</title><p>We next investigated the spatiotemporal dynamics of FtsB and PerM during the cell cycle by co-expressing FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> and PerM<sub>mtb</sub> fused to different fluorescent proteins in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>. Time-lapse microscopy showed that FtsB localized to the mid-cell ahead of PerM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). PerM localized to the same site approximately 15 min later with both proteins present at the mid-cell prior to septum constriction. We quantified the fluorescence intensities at the mid-cell and observed that the FtsB signals started to increase at ~30% and peaked at ~50% of the cell cycle, whereas the PerM signals increased at ~40% and stabilized by ~50% of the cell cycle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>), confirming that FtsB precedes PerM at the division site. This sequential localization was not an artifact caused by the fluorescent tags, as exchanging the tags resulted in the same order, with FtsB detectable at the mid-cell before PerM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2A</xref>). In addition, in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> lacking PerM but ectopically expressing a second copy of FtsB, FtsB also localized to the septum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2B</xref>). This suggests that the localization of FtsB to mid-cell does not depend on the presence of PerM.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>PerM co-localizes with FtsB and stabilizes FtsB.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative image series from time lapse movies of replicating <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> constitutively expressing both GFP-FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> and PerM<sub>mtb</sub>-mCherry over the duration of 1 hr and 45 mins. Arrows point to the presence of both FtsB and PerM at the mid-cell, and arrowheads point to the presence of FtsB and lack of PerM at the mid-cells. Scale bar, 1 µm. Numbers in the upper right corner indicate time. (<bold>B</bold>) Measurements of the maximum fluorescence intensities of GFP-FtsB and PerM-mCherry as a function of the cell cycle from time lapse movies shown in (<bold>A</bold>). The lines and shaded areas indicate means and the 95% confidence intervals of 20 bacteria. (<bold>C</bold>) FtsB protein in whole-cell lysates of log-phase Mtb measured by western blotting with anti-FtsB antibody. Arrowheads point to cleavage products of FtsB. Dihydrolipoamide acyltransferase (DlaT) was used as loading control. (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>FtsB</italic> mRNA in log-phase Mtb culture measured by quantitative real time PCR. mRNA levels were normalized to expression of the housekeeping gene <italic>sigA</italic>. Data are means ± SD of triplicates. (<bold>E</bold>) Detection of FtsB in whole-cell lysates collected from Mtb strains by western blotting with anti-FtsB antibody. 20 µg/ml chloramphenicol were added to each culture at time 0 to inhibit protein synthesis and samples were collected at the indicated time points. Western blotting with anti-DlaT was used as loading control. Data in (<bold>C–E</bold>) are representative of two independent experiments. Biological replicates of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C and E</xref> are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s3">Figure 5—figure supplement 3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig5-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> and PerM<sub>mtb</sub> interact in vivo.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Co-immunoprecipitation of FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> and PerM<sub>mtb</sub> from whole-cell protein lysates of <italic>M. smegmatis ∆perM::perM<sub>mtb</sub>-mCherry::gfp-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic>. Lysates from <italic>M. smegmatis ∆perM::perM<sub>mtb</sub>-mCherry::gfp</italic> served as a control. GFP-containing proteins were immunoprecipitated with anti-GFP mAB-agarose beads. Whole-cell lysates (input) and eluates (pull-down) were analyzed by western blotting with anti-GFP or anti-mCherry antibodies. GFP (cyan arrows), GFP-FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> (red arrows), PerM<sub>mtb</sub>-mCherry (black arrows). (<bold>B</bold>) Reverse pull-down with PerM<sub>mtb</sub> as ‘bait’ protein from whole-cell protein lysates of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> WT::<italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub>-gfp</italic> transformed with a plasmid expressing <italic>snap-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic>. Lysates from <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> WT::<italic>gfp</italic> transformed with a plasmid expressing <italic>snap-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic> served as a control. Following immunoprecipitation of GFP-containing proteins with anti-GFP magnetic beads, we analyzed whole-cell lysates and eluates with anti-GFP or anti-SNAP antibodies. GFP (cyan arrows), PerM<sub>mtb</sub>-GFP (black arrows), SNAP-FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> (red arrows). Data in (<bold>A and B</bold>) are representative of two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig5-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Localization of FtsB to the mid-cell does not depend on the presence of PerM.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative microscopy images of <italic>M. smegmatis ∆perM</italic> expressing PerM<sub>mtb</sub>-GFP and mCherry-FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> under constitutive promoters. Arrows point to the absence of PerM and presence of FtsB at the mid-cell. Scale bar, 1 µm. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative microscopy images of <italic>M. smegmatis ∆perM</italic> expressing GFP-FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> under a constitutive promoter. Arrows point to FtsB signals at the mid-cell. Scale bar, 1 µm. Images are representative of two independent experiments. In the top panel, bacteria were incubated in the presence of 1 mM HADA for 6 hr to visualize the septa.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig5-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>PerM stabilizes FtsB.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Biological replicates of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of FtsB band intensities from the western blots shown in Figure 5E and Figure 5 - figure supplement 3C. FtsB band intensities were normalized to that of DlaT and the FtsB/DlaT ratios at 0 hour were set to 100% for each strain. Data are means ± SD of biological duplicates. (<bold>C</bold>) Biological replicates of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig5-figsupp3-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>PerM stabilizes FtsB</title><p>FtsB protein levels were markedly reduced in Mtb<italic>ΔperM</italic> relative to WT or the complemented mutant, despite similar <italic>ftsB</italic> mRNA levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C,D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s3">Figure 5—figure supplement 3A</xref>). We therefore tested whether PerM stabilizes FtsB by monitoring FtsB levels after blocking protein synthesis with chloramphenicol. In both WT Mtb and the complemented mutant, FtsB amounts were stable over 96 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s3">Figure 5—figure supplement 3B,C</xref>). In contrast, FtsB abundance decreased over time in <italic>ΔperM</italic>. Because FtsB levels were low in <italic>ΔperM</italic> and thus difficult to assess, we also evaluated FtsB stability in <italic>ΔperM</italic> containing an additional copy of <italic>ftsB</italic> (<italic>ΔperM::ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic>) resulting in increased FtsB levels. In the absence of PerM, the abundance of FtsB still decreased over time. These results demonstrate that PerM stabilizes FtsB.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>PerM is required for normal growth and cell division of Mtb in host-relevant stress conditions</title><p>Mtb<italic>ΔperM</italic> was specifically attenuated during the chronic phase of mouse infection following the onset of adaptive immunity when T-cell derived IFN-γ activates macrophages to control Mtb (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Flynn et al., 1993</xref>). In IFN-γ-activated macrophages, Mtb faces acidic pH, reactive oxygen and nitrogen intermediates and limited amounts of iron and other nutrients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Ehrt and Schnappinger, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Stallings and Glickman, 2010</xref>). We reported previously that an Mtb <italic>perM</italic> transposon mutant survived these stresses similarly to WT in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Goodsmith et al., 2015</xref>), consistent with our finding that the death rates of <italic>ΔperM</italic> and WT were similar during the chronic phase of mouse infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref>). Because the growth rate of <italic>ΔperM</italic> was significantly reduced compared to that of WT during chronic infection, we tested whether PerM is required to sustain bacterial replication under host-relevant stress conditions, such as acidic conditions and iron-restricted medium. In contrast to its near normal growth at pH 7, <italic>ΔperM</italic> exhibited a growth defect and elongated cell morphology at pH 5.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A–C</xref>). Ectopically-expressed FtsB reversed the growth defect and cell elongation phenotype, suggesting that both were caused by insufficient amounts of FtsB. Notably, FtsB levels were similar at pH 7 and pH 5.5, suggesting an increased demand for FtsB during growth at low pH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). Growth in iron-depleted medium resulted in phenotypic changes similar to those observed at low pH, and these could also be reversed by ectopic FtsB expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>). Therefore, in host-relevant stress conditions, PerM is required to maintain FtsB at levels that are sufficient for growth and cell division.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>PerM is required for normal growth and cell division of Mtb in host-relevant stress conditions.</title><p>(<bold>A,B</bold>) Growth curves of Mtb strains sequentially cultured in 7H9 medium adjusted to either pH 5.5 (<bold>A</bold>) or pH 7 (<bold>B</bold>). At day 6 (arrows), the cultures were diluted in the same medium and samples collected for length quantification. Data are means ± SD of three replicates. (<bold>C</bold>) Scatter plots of the cell length of Mtb 6 days post incubation at either pH 5.5 or pH 7. The middle lines represent the medians and the bottom and top lines represent the 25<sup>th</sup> and 75<sup>th</sup> percentiles. P-values were calculated using Kruskal-Wallis test and corrected for multiple comparisons. ****, adj-P &lt;0.0001. (<bold>D</bold>) FtsB levels in whole-cell protein lysates assayed by western blotting with anti-FtsB antibody. Whole-cell protein lysates were collected from Mtb cultured in 7H9 medium adjusted to either pH 7 or pH 5.5 for 3 or 6 days. DlaT was used as loading control. (<bold>E</bold>) Bacterial titers in lungs of C57BL/6 mice infected with indicated Mtb strains. Data are means ± SD of four mice and normalized to input. Data in (<bold>A, B and D</bold>) are representative of two independent experiments, and data in (<bold>C and E</bold>) are from one experiment.</p><p> <supplementary-material id="fig6sdata1"><label>Figure 6—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Summary statistics of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig6-data1-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material> </p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig6-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>PerM is required for normal growth and cell division of Mtb in low-iron medium.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Growth curves of Mtb sequentially cultured in chelated Sauton’s medium without adding Fe<sup>3+</sup> or with addition of 500 µM FeCl<sub>3</sub>. On day 6, we diluted the cultures in the same medium, and collected samples for length quantifications. Data are means ± SD of three replicates. (<bold>B</bold>) Scatter plots of the cell lengths of Mtb after incubation in chelated Sauton’s medium or Sauton’s medium supplemented with 500 µM FeCl<sub>3</sub> for 6 days. The middle lines represent the medians and the bottom and top lines represent the 25<sup>th</sup> and 75<sup>th</sup> percentiles. P-values were calculated using Kruskal-Wallis test and corrected for multiple comparisons. ****, adj-P &lt;0.0001. Data in (<bold>A</bold>) are representative of two independent experiments, and measurements in (<bold>B</bold>) are from one experiment.</p><p> <supplementary-material id="fig6s1sdata1"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Summary statistics of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1B</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig6-figsupp1-data1-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material> </p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-49570-fig6-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>To extend these findings to the in vivo environment, we infected mice with <italic>ΔperM::ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic> and found that ectopic FtsB expression rescued the persistence defect of <italic>ΔperM</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref>). Thus, PerM-mediated FtsB stabilization is required for growth and cell division in vivo, specifically in the chronic phase of infection.</p><p>Taken together, these results indicate that PerM, a member of the mycobacterial divisome, stabilizes FtsB and maintains it at levels sufficient for cell division in the host-imposed stress conditions that characterize the chronic phase of mouse infection. Our results additionally highlight that Mtb cell division during the chronic phase of mouse infection depends on specific divisome components that differ from those required during the acute phase of infection.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Subclinical persistent infections caused by actively-growing bacteria have been described for multiple bacterial pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Certain et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Fisher et al., 2017</xref>). In individuals with latent TB infection, bacterial populations are heterogeneous, exhibit differences in metabolic state and susceptibility to antibiotics, and are likely to include actively-replicating subpopulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aldridge et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cadena et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Esmail et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Malherbe et al., 2016</xref>). In mice Mtb continues to replicate during chronic infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gill et al., 2009</xref>), but little is known about the required divisome components. We found that PerM is part of the mycobacterial divisome and facilitates cell division by stabilizing FtsB during chronic mouse infection. FtsB is a member of the divisome in many bacterial species. In <italic>E. coli</italic>, FtsB is associated with two other bitopic membrane proteins, FtsQ and FtsL, and promotes septation and cell constriction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Buddelmeijer and Beckwith, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Glas et al., 2015</xref>), (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Goehring and Beckwith, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Liu et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Tsang and Bernhardt, 2015</xref>). Mycobacterial FtsQ, FtsL and FtsB are structurally conserved and functionally similar to their <italic>E. coli</italic> homologs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jain et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Wu et al., 2018</xref>); however, regulation of FtsB differs between the two species. In <italic>E. coli</italic>, the stability of FtsB depends on FtsL and vice versa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gonzalez and Beckwith, 2009</xref>), while we found that PerM is required to stabilize FtsB in Mtb; FtsL alone does not protect FtsB from degradation in the absence of PerM. PerM is highly conserved among mycobacteria and other actinobacteria but has no homologs outside of this group, implying its function may be specific to actinobacteria. Within mycobacteria, we have shown that PerM encoded by Mtb and <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> are conserved in function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>), but the two proteins differ in essentiality for growth under standard experimental conditions. This difference may be due to a varied demand for FtsB during cell division in the sister species. Immunoprecipitation experiments revealed that PerM physically interacts with FtsB (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>), although it is not clear whether this represents direct binding, or an interaction mediated by other proteins. Nonetheless, PerM may protect FtsB from recognition or access by an unidentified protease. A similar scenario has been observed in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, the FtsB homolog DivIC interacts with FtsL, preventing proteolysis of FtsL by the intramembrane protease RasP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Wadenpohl and Bramkamp, 2010</xref>). Alternatively, PerM may stabilize FtsB and possibly the FtsQLB complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Wu et al., 2018</xref>) by facilitating protein-protein interactions within the divisome.</p><p>What could be the benefit of expressing an inherently unstable protein such as FtsB along with a stabilizing factor such as PerM, as opposed to simply expressing a more stable form of the former? Examples of other cell division proteins suggest that their inherent instability is important for temporal control of cell division. In <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, FtsL degradation by RasP has been proposed to occur after the cell cycle has been completed and the divisome disassembled, thus preventing reassembly of the divisome and subsequent cell division at the wrong time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Wadenpohl and Bramkamp, 2010</xref>). In <italic>E. coli</italic>, the concentration of FtsZ has been shown to oscillate during the cell cycle in slow growth conditions and FtsZ is degraded by the ClpXP protease at the end of the cell cycle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Männik et al., 2018</xref>). Further, the amplitude of FtsZ oscillation increased in conditions where growth is slowed, indicating that growth conditions may impact the regulation of cell division. In Mtb, the expression of an unstable FtsB along with its stabilizer PerM may allow for fine-tuning of FtsB levels during the cell cycle, which could be important in adaptation to the host environment. Consistent with this hypothesis, <italic>ΔperM</italic> showed growth and cell division defects in stress conditions mimicking the intracellular environment.</p><p>The abundance of FtsB was not significantly changed upon exposure of the bacteria to stress despite a marked reduction in cell replication rate. This observation indicates that either FtsB activity is altered under stress conditions or that the divisome formed in Mtb under stress conditions differs from the standard log-phase divisome, displaying an increased demand for FtsB. These hypotheses are supported by studies in mycobacteria that showed alterations in activities or protein-protein interactions of divisome components in response to stress. For example, MarP, a periplasmic protease, interacts more strongly with the peptidoglycan hydrolase RipA in acidic pH, resulting in RipA activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Botella et al., 2017a</xref>). In addition, FtsZ requires interaction with FipA for mid-cell localization and Z-ring formation in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> during oxidative stress, but not in normal growth conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Sureka et al., 2010</xref>). Z-ring formation has also been shown to be compromised in intracellular Mtb, likely due to altered FtsZ stability or activity in stresses imposed by the intracellular environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Chauhan et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>The environmental stimuli regulating cell division proteins are often transduced by protein kinases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Molle and Kremer, 2010</xref>). In addition to PerM and FtsQ, our co-immunoprecipitation experiment revealed interaction of FtsB with PknH, a Ser/Thr protein kinase involved in regulation of cell division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Sharma et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Zheng et al., 2007</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). Other FtsB interactors include cell division-related proteins such as DacB1, FtsK and PonA1; an ATP-binding protein; membrane proteins; an inositol 1-phosphate synthase; transporters; and proteins of unknown function. Future research will aim to delineate the pathways connecting environmental changes to FtsB regulation in Mtb.</p><p>In summary, this work provides new insights into the regulation of cell division in Mtb and its importance for persistence in the host. The cell division and in vivo persistence defects caused by inactivating PerM, a protein dispensable for bacterial replication in standard in vitro growth conditions, reveal that the requirements for cell division differ in vitro between standard growth conditions and host-relevant stress conditions, as well as in vivo between acute and chronic phases of mouse infection. Whether sustained cell replication also facilitates persistence of Mtb in humans is as yet unknown, but evidence for ongoing bacterial transcription and bacterial heterogeneity during latent TB infection support this hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Esmail et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Malherbe et al., 2016</xref>). Given the importance of cell division for persistence of Mtb in chronically-infected mice and its potential importance for persistence in latently-infected humans, future work will identify and characterize cell division factors that are specifically required for persistence in vivo. This will not only provide insights into host-pathogen interactions, but also lay the groundwork for potential strategies to combat persistent Mtb infections.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Reagent type <break/>(species) or resource</th><th valign="top">Designation</th><th valign="top">Source or reference</th><th valign="top">Identifiers</th><th valign="top">Additional <break/>information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>)</td><td valign="top">WT</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">H37Rv</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>∆perM</italic></td><td valign="top">doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/AAC.01334-17">10.1128/AAC.01334-17</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">H37Rv</td></tr><tr><td>Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>∆perM</italic>::<italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">H37Rv <break/><italic>∆perM</italic>::hsp60-<italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>∆perM</italic>::<italic>ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">H37Rv <break/><italic>∆perM</italic>::hsp60-<italic>ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>)</td><td valign="top">WT-pBP10</td><td valign="top">This work <break/>Plasmid information in doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nm.1915">10.1038/nm.1915</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">H37Rv pBP10 plasmid obtained from Dr. David Sherman (University of Washington)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>∆perM</italic>-pBP10</td><td valign="top">This work <break/>Plasmid information in doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nm.1915">10.1038/nm.1915</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">H37Rv pBP10 plasmid obtained from Dr. David Sherman <break/>(University of Washington)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>)</td><td valign="top">WT::hsp60-<italic>flag</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">H37Rv</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>)</td><td valign="top">WT::hsp60-<italic>flag-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">H37Rv</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top">WT</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>perM</italic>-DUC</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155 <break/><italic>ΔperM</italic>::T38S38-P766-9T-<italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub>-gfp</italic>-das+4::TSC10M1-SD2-SSPB</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>perM</italic>-DUC-control</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155 <break/><italic>perM</italic>-DUC + hsp60-empty</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>perM</italic>-DUC- <italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155 <break/><italic>perM</italic>-DUC + hsp60-<italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub>-gfp</italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>perM</italic>-DUC- <italic>perM<sub>msm</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155 <break/><italic>perM</italic>-DUC + hsp60-<italic>perM<sub>msm</sub>-gfp</italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>perM</italic>-DUC-<italic>ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155 <break/><italic>perM</italic>-DUC + hsp60-<italic>ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>perM</italic>-DUC-<italic>ftsB<sub>msm</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155 <break/><italic>perM</italic>-DUC + hsp60-<italic>ftsB<sub>msm</sub></italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>ΔperM</italic>::P38-<italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub>-mcherry</italic>:: hsp60-<italic>gfp-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>ΔperM</italic>::P38-<italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub>-mcherry</italic>:: hsp60-<italic>gfp</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top">WT::P38-<italic>gfp +</italic> hsp60-<italic>snap-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top">WT::P38-<italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub>-gfp +</italic> hsp60-<italic>snap-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>ΔperM</italic>::P38-<italic>perM<sub>mtb</sub>-gfp</italic>::hsp60-<italic>mcherry-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>ΔperM</italic>::P38-<italic>gfp-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>ΔperM</italic>::hsp60-<italic>gfp-ftsB<sub>mtb</sub></italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">mc<sup>2</sup>155</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-Flag M2 affinity gel</td><td valign="top">Sigma</td><td valign="top">A2220</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-GFP mAb-agarose beads</td><td valign="top">MBL</td><td valign="top">D153-8</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-GFP mAb-magnetic beads</td><td valign="top">MBL</td><td valign="top">D153-11</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-FtsB (Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">GenScript</td><td valign="top">U1550BG270</td><td valign="top">(1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-DlaT (Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1067798">10.1126/science.1067798</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Antibody from Drs. Carl Nathan and Ruslana Bryk (Weill Cornell Medicine) (1:10000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-GFP (Mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Clontech</td><td valign="top">632380</td><td valign="top">(1:8000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-mCherry (Mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Clontech</td><td valign="top">632543</td><td valign="top">(1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-SNAP (Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">New England BioLabs</td><td valign="top">P9310S</td><td valign="top">(1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">donkey anti-rabbit 680</td><td valign="top">LI-COR Biosciences</td><td valign="top">926–68023</td><td valign="top">(1:10000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">donkey anti-rabbit 800</td><td valign="top">LI-COR Biosciences</td><td valign="top">926–32213</td><td valign="top">(1:10000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">goat anti-mouse 800</td><td valign="top">LI-COR Biosciences</td><td valign="top">926–32210</td><td valign="top">(1:5000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Peptide, recombinant protein</td><td valign="top">FLAG peptide <break/></td><td valign="top">Sigma</td><td valign="top">F3290</td><td valign="top">(100 ng/µl)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="top">Prism 7</td><td valign="top">Graphpad</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="top">ImageJ</td><td valign="top">doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2089">10.1038/nmeth.2089</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="top">Icy</td><td valign="top">doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2075">10.1038/nmeth.2075</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software, algorithm</td><td valign="top">Scaffold 4</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">SYTO 13 Green Fluorescent Nucleic Acid Stain</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">S7575</td><td valign="top">(5 μM)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">HADA</td><td valign="top">doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/anie.201206749">10.1002/anie.201206749</ext-link>;doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2014.197">10.1038/nprot.2014.197</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">(1 mM) <break/>Synthesized by the Chemical Synthesis Core <break/>Facility at MSKCC</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Other</td><td valign="top">NADA</td><td valign="top">doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/anie.201206749">10.1002/anie.201206749</ext-link>;doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2014.197">10.1038/nprot.2014.197</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">(1 mM) <break/>Synthesized by the Chemical Synthesis Core <break/>Facility at MSKCC</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Bacterial culture conditions</title><p><italic>M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup>155 and derivative strains were cultured in Middlebrook 7H9 medium (BD Difco) containing 0.2% glycerol and 0.05% Tween 80 or Middlebrook 7H10 agar (BD Difco) containing 0.5% glycerol. <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv and derivative strains were cultured in Middlebrook 7H9 medium containing 0.2% glycerol, 0.2% dextrose, 0.5% BSA (Roche), 0.05% Tween 80 or tyloxapol, and 0.085% NaCl ﻿or Middlebrook 7H10 agar containing 10% OADC supplement (BD) and 0.5% glycerol. Selection antibiotics were used at the following concentrations: ﻿ hygromycin (50 μg/ml), zeocin (25 μg/ml), kanamycin (25 μg/ml) or streptomycin (20 μg/ml).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Mutant construction</title><p>The Mtb<italic>ΔperM</italic> mutant was constructed by allelic exchange using a recombineering approach as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Gee et al., 2012</xref>). The <italic>ΔperM</italic> strain was complemented by introducing a copy of <italic>perM</italic>, expressed under the control of the hsp60 promoter, into the attL5 site of the Mtb genome. The <italic>ΔperM::ftsB</italic> mutant was constructed by integrating a copy of <italic>ftsB</italic>, expressed under the control of the hsp60 promoter, into the attL5 site of the Mtb genome. The <italic>M. smegmatis perM</italic>-DUC mutant was generated as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Schnappinger et al., 2015</xref>). Complementation with <italic>ftsB</italic> was either on a multicopy plasmid or integrated in the chromosomal attL5 site under control of the hsp60 promoter. For FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> fusion proteins, N-terminal GFP, mCherry, Flag or SNAP tags were introduced to FtsB<sub>mtb</sub> by PCR. PerM<sub>mtb</sub> fusion proteins were cloned by fusing mCherry or GFP to the C-terminus of PerM<sub>mtb</sub>. The genotypes of all strains are reported in the key resources table.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Mouse infections</title><p>Female 7–8 week old C57BL/6 mice (Jackson Laboratory) were infected using an inhalation exposure system (Glas-Col) with mid-log phase Mtb culture delivering approximately 10<sup>2</sup> or 10<sup>3</sup> bacilli per mouse. At each time point, lungs were homogenized in PBS and bacteria were enumerated by plating serially diluted homogenates on 7H10 agar.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Replication clock</title><p>Experiments were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gill et al., 2009</xref>). Mtb strains were transformed with the ‘replication clock’ plasmid pBP10. For in vitro experiments, cultures were maintained in log phase by sub-culturing every 3 days for ~20 generations in the absence of antibiotics. The plasmid carriage of each Mtb strain was calculated as the number of CFU on 7H10 agar with 30 μg/ml kanamycin divided by the number of CFU on non-selective plates. Segregation rates (s) and errors were calculated using mathematical equations developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gill et al. (2009)</xref> and the error propagation equation. We determined the plasmid segregation constants for WT (S<sub>WT</sub> = 0.1904 ± 0.0516) and <italic>ΔperM</italic> (S<italic><sub>Δ</sub></italic>=0.1586 ± 0.0349) before measuring cell replication rates in vivo.</p><p>For in vivo experiments, cell replication rates (r) were calculated as the slopes of the regression lines fitted through plots of ln [f(t)] versus t and multiplied with (−1/s), where s is the segregation constant determined in vitro. Death rates were calculated by subtracting slope N from r. Doubling time equals ln (2)/r. The errors of both death rate and doubling time were calculated using error propagation equations. The cumulative bacterial burden (CBB) was calculated using mathematical models developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gill et al. (2009)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>In situ Mtb cell length quantification</title><p>Mice were infected with log-phase Mtb by aerosol to deliver ~10<sup>3</sup> bacilli per mouse. At each time point, lungs were isolated, and the upper left lung lobes were fixed in 10% buffered formalin for 48 hr prior to removal from BSL-3 containment. The lung lobes were subsequently embedded in paraffin, sectioned and stained with acid-fast staining. Slides were blinded before microscopy and the identity of the samples was revealed after length quantifications were completed. Approximately 40 lung sections were examined for each time point with each strain. Tissue slides were visualized in bright-field using Olympus BX60 microscope with a 100x oil objective and images were captured with Olympus DP71 digital camera. Bacteria in the focal plane of the sections were imaged and their cell lengths were quantified using ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Schneider et al., 2012</xref>). The remaining lung lobes were homogenized in PBS and cultured on 7H10 agar to determine CFU.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>High-resolution microscopy</title><p>Microscopy imaging was performed with the same methods and equipment as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Botella et al., 2017b</xref>). For length measurements, Mtb or <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> cultures were collected at indicated time points and washed with PBS containing 0.05% Tween 80 (PBST). The Mtb samples were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 4 hr prior to removal from BSL-3 containment. Single cell suspensions were prepared by centrifugation at 800 rpm for 10 min. After spreading on soft agar pads, bacteria were visualized with appropriate filter sets. For peptidoglycan labeling, 1 mM HCC‐amino‐D‐alanine (HADA) or NBD‐amino‐D‐alanine (NADA) was added to <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> cultures as indicated. Aliquots were removed, washed three times with PBST, and then fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 30 min before microscopy. The nucleoid staining was performed by incubating <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> cultures with 5 μM SYTO 13 for 5 min. Images were analyzed with ImageJ and Icy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">de Chaumont et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Schneider et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>For time lapse microscopy experiments, a drop of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> culture (5 ~ 10 μl) was placed on a glass bottom microwell dish (MatTek, 35 mm, 14 mm microwell), and 1% low melting point agarose (UltraPure, Invitrogen) prepared in 7H9 broth was added gently to the dish until it covered the bacteria drop. Agarose was left to solidify prior to microscopy. Cells were visualized by fluorescence microscopy and snapshots were captured every 15 min. We analyzed the time lapse movies with ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Schneider et al., 2012</xref>). First, the fluorescence intensities were measured lengthwise across a single cell at every time point, from which we determined the maximum fluorescence intensities of the middle 1/2 of the cell. Next, each time point was interpolated to 1/10 of the cell cycle of each cell to allow many bacterial cells to be averaged consistently.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Forward genetic screen</title><p>A total of 10<sup>8</sup> CFU of Msm <italic>perM</italic>-DUC mutant were transformed with an Mtb genomic library generated as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Niederweis et al., 1999</xref>). Bacteria were cultured on 7H10 agar with 400 ng/ml atc and 50 µg/ml hygromycin. Colonies were picked and lysed in 20 µl ice-cold 10% glycerol and transformed into 100 µl <italic>E. coli</italic> top10 competent cells by electroporation. The transformants were selected on LB agar containing 200 µg/ml hygromycin. Plasmids were isolated and sequenced to identify Mtb DNA fragments.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Immunoprecipitation and mass spectrometry</title><p>150 ml of Mtb culture in mid-log phase was pelleted and washed twice with PBST. Cells were resuspended in 600 μl lysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, 50 mM NaCl, pH 7.4) containing protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche) and subjected to mechanical lysis with 0.1 zyrconia beads in a homogenizer. After adding 1% dodecyl maltoside, we incubated the protein lysates on ice for 2 hr. Lysates were clarified by centrifugation for 2 min at 7,500 g. 50 μl anti-Flag M2 affinity beads (Sigma, A2220) were added to supernatants and incubated overnight shaking at 4°C. Beads were collected by centrifugation and washed 5 times with PBS. Proteins bound to beads were eluted by incubation with 100 ng/μl flag peptide (Sigma) 1 hr shaking at 4°C. Samples were boiled in Laemmli sample buffer (Bio-Rad) for 10 min prior to removal from BSL-3 containment. Peptides in the eluates were identified by mass spectrometry. Results were analyzed using Scaffold 4 software. Non-specific binding peptides were removed from the results by setting the filter of ‘Total Spectrum Count’ of each replicate to ‘&lt;2’ in the control samples and ‘&gt;3’ in Flag-FtsB samples. Hits were ranked based on ‘Sum Total Spectrum Count’ of the Flag-FtsB samples. The ‘Sum Total Spectrum Count’ is the sum of two independent biological replicates. Hits were assigned utilizing publicly available databases PATRIC (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.patricbrc.org/">https://www.patricbrc.org/</ext-link>) and FLUTE (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orca2.tamu.edu/U19/">http://orca2.tamu.edu/U19/</ext-link>). For pulldown validations, 150 ml M. <italic>smegmatis</italic> was grown to mid-log phase and protein lysates were collected as described above. Protein lysate (10–30 mg) was incubated with 25 μl anti-GFP mAb-agarose beads or 50 μl anti-GFP mAb-magnetic beads (MBL) overnight shaking at 4°C. After incubation, beads were collected by centrifugation or using a DynaMag-Magnet 2 rack (Thermo Fisher scientific) and washed three times with PBS. Proteins bound to beads were eluted by boiling in Laemmli sample buffer for 10 min and analyzed by western blotting.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Antibodies and western blots</title><p>Rabbit polyclonal antibody for FtsB was generated by GenScript. DlaT antibody (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bryk et al., 2002</xref>) was a gift from R. Bryk and C. Nathan at Weill Cornell Medicine. GFP (Clontech #632380), mCherry (Clontech #632543) and SNAP (NEB #P9310S) antibodies are commercially available. All secondary antibodies were purchased from LI-COR biosciences.</p><p>For western blots, protein lysates were prepared by mechanical lysis with 0.1 mm zirconia beads, followed by 2 hr incubation on ice with 1% dodecyl maltoside. Unbroken bacterial cells and beads were removed by centrifugation. Mtb protein lysates were filtered using 0.22 µm spin-X columns (Corning) prior to removal from BSL3 containment. Protein lysates were separated using SDS-PAGE and transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane. For FtsB analysis, membrane was cut at 37kD and incubated with either FtsB antibody or DlaT antibody. After washing and incubation with secondary antibodies, proteins were visualized using Odyssey Infrared Imaging System (LI-COR Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Analysis of protein stability</title><p>Chloramphenicol (Sigma) stock was prepared at 100 mg/ml in ethanol and added to mid-log phase Mtb cultures at a final concentration of 20 μg/ml. At each time point, 30 ml Mtb cultures were removed and protein lysates collected as described above. Stability of FtsB was analyzed by western blotting.</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Mtb growth assays</title><p>Mtb was grown to mid-log phase in Middlebrook 7H9 medium prior to each experiment. The precultures were pelleted at 4000 rpm for 10 min and washed once in PBS, then diluted to OD 0.05 in assay media. For growth curves in acidic or low iron conditions, Mtb cultures were diluted to OD 0.05 in assay media at day 6. Conditions for the growth curves were as follows: Magnesium-free Sauton’s media was prepared as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Goodsmith et al., 2015</xref>). Magnesium was supplemented in the form of MgCl<sub>2</sub> at the indicated concentrations. 7H9 medium at pH 5.5 or pH 7 were prepared by adjusting 7H9 broth containing 0.2% glycerol, 0.2% dextrose, 0.5% fatty-acid-free BSA (Roche), 0.085% NaCl, 1.95% MES, and 0.05% tyloxapol to pH as indicated. 0.005% sodium oleate was supplemented every other day. Medium with defined iron concentrations was prepared by chelating Sauton’s medium (0.4% L-asparagine, 0.27% sodium citrate tribasic dehydrate, 0.015% citric acid, 0.05% potassium phosphate dibasic, and 6% glycerol) with 1% Chelex-100 (sodium form, Bio-Rad) twice for 24 hr. Subsequently Chelex-100 was removed by filtration and 0.05% magnesium sulfate heptahydrate, 5 μM zinc sulfate, 0.1% ethanol, and 0.05% tyloxapol was added to the medium and the medium was adjusted to pH 7.4. Iron was supplemented in the form of FeCl<sub>3</sub> at the indicated concentrations.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All statistical analyses were performed using Prism 7 (GraphPad Software) with the statistical tests indicated in figure legends and the corresponding two-tailed P-values reported. *, p&lt;0.05, **, p&lt;0.01, ***, p&lt;0.001 and ****, p&lt;0.0001 were considered significant results.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Materials and correspondence</title><p>Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to the corresponding author Sabine Ehrt (sae2004@med.cornell.edu).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank C Nathan, K Rhee (Weill Cornell Medicine) and J Rock (Rockefeller University) for insightful suggestions. We thank J Xavier (Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center) for helpful discussions as well as advice on mathematical calculations. We thank ﻿KG Papavinasasundaram (University of Massachusetts) and SA Shaffer (University of Massachusetts Mass Spectrometry Facility) for LC-MS/MS analysis and A North at the Bio-Imaging Resource Center (Rockefeller University) for microscopy training and advice. We thank D Sherman (University of Washington) for providing the pBP10 plasmid, R Bryk and C Nathan (Weill Cornell Medicine) for the DlaT antibody and A Fay (Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center) for advice. We thank P Tamayo, J McConnell and C Healy (Weill Cornell Medicine) for assisting with the animal experiments. We thank S Schrader (Weill Cornell Medicine) for careful editing of the manuscript.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Investigation, Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Conceptualization, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Project administration, Writing—review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Animal experimentation: The animal experiments were performed in accordance with National Institutes of Health guidelines for housing and care of laboratory animals and according to institutional regulations after protocol review and approval by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Weill Cornell Medicine (Protocol Number 0601441A).</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49570-transrepform-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files. Source data files have been provided for Figures 1, 2, 3, 4 and 6 and Table 1.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aldridge</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Suarez</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heller</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambravaneswaran</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Irimia</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Toner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortune</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Asymmetry and aging of mycobacterial cells lead to variable growth and antibiotic susceptibility</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>335</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1216166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22174129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behr</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Edelstein</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Revisiting the timetable of tuberculosis</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>362</volume><elocation-id>k2738</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.k2738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30139910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botella</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaubourgeix</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Makinoshima</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Glickman</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017a</year><article-title><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> protease MarP activates a peptidoglycan hydrolase during acid stress</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201695028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28057704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botella</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouerfelli</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathan</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaubourgeix</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017b</year><article-title>Distinct Spatiotemporal Dynamics of Peptidoglycan Synthesis between <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> and <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>mBio</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>123</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01183-17</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bryk</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdjument-Bromage</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tempst</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathan</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Metabolic enzymes of mycobacteria linked to antioxidant defense by a thioredoxin-like protein</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>295</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1067798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11799204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buddelmeijer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Judson</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekalanos</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckwith</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>YgbQ, a cell division protein in Escherichia coli and Vibrio cholerae, localizes in codependent fashion with FtsL to the division site</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>6316</fpage><lpage>6321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.092128499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buddelmeijer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckwith</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>A complex of the Escherichia coli cell division proteins FtsL, FtsB and FtsQ forms independently of its localization to the septal region</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>1315</fpage><lpage>1327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04044.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15165235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cadena</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortune</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Heterogeneity in tuberculosis</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Immunology</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri.2017.69</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28736436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carson</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barondess</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckwith</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>The FtsQ protein of Escherichia coli: membrane topology, abundance, and cell division phenotypes due to overproduction and insertion mutations</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>173</volume><fpage>2187</fpage><lpage>2195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.173.7.2187-2195.1991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Certain</surname> <given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Way</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pezone</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Using engineered Bacteria to characterize infection dynamics and antibiotic effects in Vivo</article-title><source>Cell Host &amp; Microbe</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2017.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28867388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chauhan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Madiraju</surname> <given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fol</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofton</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloney</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajagopalan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Mycobacterium tuberculosis cells growing in macrophages are filamentous and deficient in FtsZ rings</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>188</volume><fpage>1856</fpage><lpage>1865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.188.5.1856-1865.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16484196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Chaumont</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dallongeville</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chenouard</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hervé</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Provoost</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meas-Yedid</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pankajakshan</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecomte</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Montagner</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagache</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufour</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivo-Marin</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Icy: an open bioimage informatics platform for extended reproducible research</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>690</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehrt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname> <given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Metabolic principles of persistence and pathogenicity in Mycobacterium tuberculosis</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-018-0013-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29691481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehrt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Mycobacterial survival strategies in the phagosome: defence against host stresses</article-title><source>Cellular Microbiology</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1170</fpage><lpage>1178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-5822.2009.01335.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19438516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esmail</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesosky</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coussens</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Oni</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Warwick</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Said-Hartley</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Koegelenberg</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Walzl</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry Iii</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Garra</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Characterization of progressive HIV-associated tuberculosis using 2-deoxy-2-[18F]fluoro-D-glucose positron emission and computed tomography</article-title><source>Nature Medicine</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1090</fpage><lpage>1093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.4161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27595321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gollan</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Helaine</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Persistent bacterial infections and persister cells</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2017.42</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28529326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flynn</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Triebold</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalton</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>An essential role for interferon gamma in resistance to Mycobacterium tuberculosis infection</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><volume>178</volume><fpage>2249</fpage><lpage>2254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.178.6.2249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7504064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gee</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Papavinasasundaram</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Falick</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Venghatakrishnan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zukauskas</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhiman</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Crick</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassetti</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alber</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>A phosphorylated pseudokinase complex controls cell wall synthesis in mycobacteria</article-title><source>Science Signaling</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>ra7</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.2002525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22275220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harik</surname> <given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiddon</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittler</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>A replication clock for Mycobacterium tuberculosis</article-title><source>Nature Medicine</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.1915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19182798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glas</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Berg van Saparoea</surname> <given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Roseboom</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Koningstein</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fish</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>den Blaauwen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Heck</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitter</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>de Esch</surname> <given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Luirink</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>The soluble periplasmic domains of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Cell Division Proteins FtsQ/FtsB/FtsL Form a Trimeric Complex with Submicromolar Affinity</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>290</volume><fpage>21498</fpage><lpage>21509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M115.654756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26160297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glickman</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname> <given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Microbial pathogenesis of Mycobacterium tuberculosis: dawn of a discipline</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)00236-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goehring</surname> <given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckwith</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Diverse paths to midcell: assembly of the bacterial cell division machinery</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>R514</fpage><lpage>R526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2005.06.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16005287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckwith</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Divisome under construction: distinct domains of the small membrane protein FtsB are necessary for interaction with multiple cell division proteins</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>191</volume><fpage>2815</fpage><lpage>2825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01597-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19233928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodsmith</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>XV</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandal</surname> <given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaubourgeix</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Botella</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatt</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Liba</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salgame</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Disruption of an M. tuberculosis membrane protein causes a magnesium-dependent cell division defect and failure to persist in mice</article-title><source>PLOS Pathogens</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1004645</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25658098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guzman</surname> <given-names>L-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barondess</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckwith</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>FtsL, an Essential Cytoplasmic Membrane Protein Involved in Cell Division in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>174</volume><fpage>7717</fpage><lpage>7728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.174.23.7717.1992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Malakar</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lochab</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandicoori</surname> <given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Delineating FtsQ-mediated regulation of cell division in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>293</volume><fpage>12331</fpage><lpage>12349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.RA118.003628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29903917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katis</surname> <given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wake</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Harry</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Septal localization of the membrane-bound division proteins of Bacillus subtilis DivIB and DivIC is codependent only at high temperatures and requires FtsZ</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>182</volume><fpage>3607</fpage><lpage>3611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.182.12.3607-3611.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10852898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kieser</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>How sisters grow apart: mycobacterial growth and division</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>550</fpage><lpage>562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24998739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Boshoff</surname> <given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehren</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallach</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteleone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname> <given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>A genetic strategy to identify targets for the development of drugs that prevent bacterial persistence</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>19095</fpage><lpage>19100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1315860110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24191058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kureisaite-Ciziene</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Varadajan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Glas</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Montón Silva</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Luirink</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>den Blaauwen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossmann</surname> <given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Luirink</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Löwe</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Structural analysis of the interaction between the bacterial cell division proteins FtsQ and FtsB</article-title><source>mBio</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>321</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01346-18</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuru</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>HV</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tekkam</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cava</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>de Pedro</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname> <given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>VanNieuwenhze</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>In Situ probing of newly synthesized peptidoglycan in live Bacteria with fluorescent D-amino acids</article-title><source>Angewandte Chemie International Edition</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>12519</fpage><lpage>12523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201206749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23055266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuru</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tekkam</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname> <given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Nieuwenhze</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Synthesis of fluorescent D-amino acids and their use for probing peptidoglycan synthesis and bacterial growth in situ</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2014.197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25474031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levin</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Losick</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Characterization of a cell division gene from Bacillus subtilis that is required for vegetative and sporulation septum formation</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>176</volume><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.176.5.1451-1459.1994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8113187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Persons</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>de Boer</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Roles for both FtsA and the FtsBLQ subcomplex in FtsN-stimulated cell constriction in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>945</fpage><lpage>970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.12906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25496160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Logsdon</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldridge</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Stable regulation of cell cycle events in mycobacteria: insights from inherently heterogeneous bacterial populations</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>514</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29619019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malherbe</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Shenai</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronacher</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Loxton</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolganov</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Warwick</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Via</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoolnik</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tromp</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alland</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Walzl</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Spuy</surname> <given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiart</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Du Plessis</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltran</surname> <given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Maasdorp</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellmann</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Joh</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodd</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Allwood</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Koegelenberg</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vorster</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith-Richards</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><collab>Catalysis TB–Biomarker Consortium</collab></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Persisting positron emission tomography lesion activity and Mycobacterium tuberculosis mRNA after tuberculosis cure</article-title><source>Nature Medicine</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1094</fpage><lpage>1100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.4177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27595324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Männik</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname> <given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Männik</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Cell cycle-dependent regulation of FtsZ in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in slow growth conditions</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>1044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.14135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30230648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molle</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremer</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Division and cell envelope regulation by ser/Thr phosphorylation: <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> shows the way</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>75</volume><fpage>1064</fpage><lpage>1077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.07041.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20487298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niederweis</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinz</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Klöcker</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Karosi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Swiderek</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname> <given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Benz</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Cloning of the mspA gene encoding a porin from Mycobacterium smegmatis</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>933</fpage><lpage>945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1999.01472.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10476028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pai</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Behr</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowdy</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dheda</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Divangahi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boehme</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsberg</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaminathan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spigelman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Getahun</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Menzies</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Raviglione</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Tuberculosis</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Disease Primers</source><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>16076</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2016.76</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27784885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rego</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Audette</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Deletion of a mycobacterial divisome factor collapses single-cell phenotypic heterogeneity</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>546</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature22361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28569798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><chapter-title>Construction of Conditional Knockdown Mutants in Mycobacteria</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname> <given-names>S. H</given-names></name></person-group><source>Antibiotic Resistance Protocols</source><volume>1285</volume><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>175</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasband</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliceiri</surname> <given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>NIH image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathak</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Koul</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarangi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baweja</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Transcriptional control of the mycobacterial embCAB operon by PknH through a regulatory protein, EmbR, in vivo</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>188</volume><fpage>2936</fpage><lpage>2944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.188.8.2936-2944.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16585755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stallings</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Glickman</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Is Mycobacterium tuberculosis stressed out? A critical assessment of the genetic evidence</article-title><source>Microbes and Infection</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1091</fpage><lpage>1101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2010.07.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20691805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sureka</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kundu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Basu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Novel role of phosphorylation-dependent interaction between FtsZ and FipA in mycobacterial cell division</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e8590</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20066037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taguchi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Welsh</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marmont</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sjodt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruse</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahne</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhardt</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>FtsW is a peptidoglycan polymerase that is functional only in complex with its cognate penicillin-binding protein</article-title><source>Nature Microbiology</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41564-018-0345-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30692671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsang</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhardt</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A role for the FtsQLB complex in Cytokinetic ring activation revealed by an ftsL allele that accelerates division</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>925</fpage><lpage>944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.12905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25496050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wadenpohl</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramkamp</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>DivIC Stabilizes FtsL against RasP Cleavage</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>192</volume><fpage>5260</fpage><lpage>5263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00287-10</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranowski</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rego</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname> <given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutte</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Characterization of conserved and novel septal factors in <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>200</volume><elocation-id>8</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00649-17</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>DeJesus</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rücker</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhart</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Healy</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioerger</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Chemical genetic interaction profiling reveals determinants of intrinsic antibiotic resistance in Mycobacterium tuberculosis</article-title><source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source><volume>61</volume><elocation-id>159</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01334-17</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Papavinasasundaram</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Av-Gay</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Novel substrates of Mycobacterium tuberculosis PknH ser/Thr kinase</article-title><source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications</source><volume>355</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2007.01.122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17286964</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49570.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kana</surname><given-names>Bavesh D</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of the Witwatersrand</institution><country>South Africa</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Boutte</surname><given-names>Cara</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Rego</surname><given-names>E Hesper</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>Yale School of Medicine</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife publishes the most substantive revision requests and the accompanying author responses.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Acceptance summary:</bold></p><p>This study demonstrates that a mycobacterial protein, PerM, is required for cell division during chronic tuberculosis infection in mice. Further interrogation of PerM function in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> and the non-pathogenic model host, <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> revealed that PerM is required for the formation of septa in mycobacteria, hence facilitating cell division. The authors’ approach demonstrates that PerM exerts this function through interaction with, and stabilization of, FtsB, a component of the bacterial divisome. This work provides novel insight on mycobacterial division mechanics during tuberculosis infection in an animal model system. The clever use of combinations of fluorescent D-amino acid probes to demonstrate that PerM depletion leads to reduced septum formation demonstrates how these probes can be used to gain novel mechanistic insight in disease-specific model systems. The value of your study is further enhanced through the use of a replication clock plasmid that allows for a coupled view of cell division and DNA replication during in vivo infection, something that is not often seen in the literature. This study also paves the way to application of similar approaches to studying mycobacterial cell division in human disease and the effects of antibiotic therapy on these events. The techniques applied are also relevant for the study of cell division in other bacteria.</p><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Persistent <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> infection in mice requires PerM controlled cell division&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, one of whom is a member of our Board of Reviewing Editors, and the evaluation has been overseen by Wendy Garrett as the Senior Editor. The following individuals involved in review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Cara Boutte (Reviewer #2); E Hesper Rego (Reviewer #3).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>Cell division in mycobacteria differs from other well-characterized organisms such as <italic>E. coli</italic> in that elongation occurs at the cell pole in mycobacteria whilst <italic>E. coli</italic> cells elongate by insertion of cell wall material along the sidewall. As a result of this, the divisome machinery is spatially well segregated from the elongasome and upon cell division, divisome components need to disassemble or remodel to allow for development and subsequent extension of the new pole. Considering this, the mycobcacterial divisome requires further characterization to elucidate how these cells coordinate and regulate the division process. Previously, this group identified PerM, an integral membrane protein in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> that was required for persistence of tubercle bacilli during the chronic phase of infection in the murine model of TB infection. Preliminary evidence suggested that PerM was involved in cell division however, the mechanistic basis for this phenotype was unclear. In this study, the authors attempt to further unravel how PerM is involved in division.</p><p>Key findings:</p><p>1) Using a replication clock plasmid that is lost if <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> replicates in mouse lungs, the authors confirm that their previously reported persistence defect for a perM mutant during chronic infection was due to the inability to replicate after the onset of adaptive immunity. The doubling time for the mutant during chronic infection was significantly longer than that of the wild type and this defect was seen with both a high and low initial dose of aerogenic infection. PerM mutant cells were longer than that of the wild type during chronic infection, suggesting that the persistence defect was due to defective cell division</p><p>2) They further study this in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> with a perM knockdown strain, as perM appears to be essential in this case. Depletion of perM using a dual control depletion system, resulted in the formation of long cells that were filamentous with either one or no septum. PerM depletion was bacteriostatic in this case</p><p>3) Using a forward genetic screen to identify suppressors for perM essentiality in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, the authors identified FtsB, a member of the FtsQLB complex that is implicated in septum synthesis. They confirm that PerM interacts with FtsB using a co-immune precipitation assay with whole cell lysates and localization of fluorescently tagged proteins, both of which localized at the septum. Using time-lapse microscopy, the authors show that PerM localizes to the septum after FtsB.</p><p>4) PerM appears to stabilize FtsB as levels of this protein were reduced when perM was deleted in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>. Ectopic expression of FtsB rescued the persistence defect in mice.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) Figure 1—figure supplement 1A – Please confirm that this is the correct graph, as there is apparently no error, and it does not look like a typical growth curve. <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> should double every cell cycle, it doesn't increase by 10-fold, so the growth curve shouldn't be linear on a log10 axis. Unless there was no lag? What does continuous culture mean in this context? Are OD values really as high as 10e6?</p><p>2) It's hard to see the reduced colony sizes alluded to in Figure 3A – median colony diameters should be provided</p><p>3) The authors indicate that PerM localized to mid-cell 15 minutes after FtsB, this is not clear from the data they provide, which are images in some cases without time stamps. A better way of illustrating this is to plot the localization of PerM and FtsZ as a function of time between division cycles.</p><p>4) Some of the most important mechanistic data in this paper is the protein stability data in Figures 4B and D. However, this does not appear to have been replicated. Please show quantification of these gel bands, with error. The results need to be shown to be reproducible.</p><p>5) The conclusion that PerM is involved in septum formation is somewhat confusing. If that were true, it seems that the elongated cells would have fewer septa. Instead, they have more (Figure 2C) than WT, suggesting a defect in late septum formation/cell separation. Indeed, the perM depletion mutant does not truly phenocopy a ftsB depletion which forms long, branching cells. Please re-assess the conclusion that PerM is involved in septal formation or address the discrepancy in perM depletion vs. ftsB depletion phenotypes.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49570.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) Figure 1—figure supplement 1A – Please confirm that this is the correct graph, as there is apparently no error, and it does not look like a typical growth curve. M. tuberculosis should double every cell cycle, it doesn't increase by 10-fold, so the growth curve shouldn't be linear on a log10 axis. Unless there was no lag? What does continuous culture mean in this context? Are OD values really as high as 10e6?</p></disp-quote><p>We apologize that the figure legend was confusing. For this experiment, <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> cultures were maintained in log phase by sub-culturing every three days for ~20 generations. We started the culture at OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.05 and diluted it to OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.05-0.1 every three days. We have replotted the data and edited the figure legend to more accurately describe the experiment.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) It's hard to see the reduced colony sizes alluded to in Figure 3A – median colony diameters should be provided</p></disp-quote><p>We agree and have removed comments on colony sizes from the main text. We included the incubation time for each plate in the figure legend to allow for judgement of relative growth.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) The authors indicate that PerM localized to mid-cell 15 minutes after FtsB, this is not clear from the data they provide, which are images in some cases without time stamps. A better way of illustrating this is to plot the localization of PerM and FtsZ as a function of time between division cycles.</p></disp-quote><p>We have quantified the time lapse videos, as suggested, and included the data in Figure 5B in the revised manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) Some of the most important mechanistic data in this paper is the protein stability data in Figures 4B and D. However, this does not appear to have been replicated. Please show quantification of these gel bands, with error. The results need to be shown to be reproducible.</p></disp-quote><p>We have included the biological replicates of both figures and quantifications of band intensities as Figure 5—figure supplement 3 in the revised manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) The conclusion that PerM is involved in septum formation is somewhat confusing. If that were true, it seems that the elongated cells would have fewer septa. Instead, they have more (Figure 2C) than WT, suggesting a defect in late septum formation/cell separation. Indeed, the perM depletion mutant does not truly phenocopy a ftsB depletion which forms long, branching cells. Please re-assess the conclusion that PerM is involved in septal formation or address the discrepancy in perM depletion vs. ftsB depletion phenotypes.</p></disp-quote><p>We have performed pulse-chase experiments with two fluorescent D-alanine probes to address this concern (new Figure 3). Our data demonstrated that PerM depletion led to impaired septum formation and separation in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>. This result agrees with the observation in Figure 2 that a higher fraction of PerM-depleted bacteria than WT contained one septum.</p><p>It is true that PerM depletion did not fully phenocopy FtsB-depleted cells. This may be due to continued FtsB synthesis in the <italic>perM</italic>-DUC strain, and that reducing FtsB stability following PerM depletion may not reduce FtsB levels to the same extent as repressing FtsB expression in the FtsB-depletion strain.</p></body></sub-article></article>