<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">36221</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cell Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology and Infectious Disease</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Timing of ESCRT-III protein recruitment and membrane scission during HIV-1 assembly</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-108428"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Daniel S</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8906-0509</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-108429"><name><surname>Bleck</surname><given-names>Marina</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4175-8363</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-16587"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>Sanford M</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8615-4224</contrib-id><email>Sanford.Simon@rockefeller.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Laboratory of Cellular Biophysics</institution><institution>The Rockefeller University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">New York</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Physics and Astronomy</institution><institution>Hofstra University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Hempstead</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>Stephen P</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Columbia University</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>Wendy S</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>Harvard School of Public Health</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>04</day><month>07</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e36221</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-02-26"><day>26</day><month>02</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-07-02"><day>02</day><month>07</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018, Johnson et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Johnson et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-36221-v2.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.001</object-id><p>The Endosomal Sorting Complexes Required for Transport III (ESCRT-III) proteins are critical for cellular membrane scission processes with topologies inverted relative to clathrin-mediated endocytosis. Some viruses appropriate ESCRT-IIIs for their release. By imaging single assembling viral-like particles of HIV-1, we observed that ESCRT-IIIs and the ATPase VPS4 arrive after most of the virion membrane is bent, linger for tens of seconds, and depart ~20 s before scission. These observations suggest that ESCRT-IIIs are recruited by a combination of membrane curvature and the late domains of the HIV-1 Gag protein. ESCRT-IIIs may pull the neck into a narrower form but must leave to allow scission. If scission does not occur within minutes of ESCRT departure, ESCRT-IIIs and VPS4 are recruited again. This mechanistic insight is likely relevant for other ESCRT-dependent scission processes including cell division, endosome tubulation, multivesicular body and nuclear envelope formation, and secretion of exosomes and ectosomes.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>Viruses need to be able to enter and leave the cells of their hosts to multiply and spread infections. Once inside the cell, many viruses, including the HIV virus, hijack the cell’s genetic material to produce more HIV particles and release them back into the surroundings. As the new viruses leave the cell, they wrap themselves in the membrane of their host cell.</p><p>The shell of HIV consists of thousands of copies of a protein called Gag, which helps to release the viruses. Gag aggregates inside of the host cell membrane, which then begins to bulge outwards forming a spherical bud that subsequently pinches off. These released virus particles are now able to infect other cells.</p><p>Both assembling and budding of the virus particles requires the help of specific cell proteins called ESCRTs. Cells usually use ESCRTs to cut membrane-bound compartments during cell division. HIV can control ESCRTs to separate the bud from the cell, but where and how they are involved is still not fully understood. Some models propose that the ESCRTs bend the membrane, while others suggest that the ESCRTs are required during the split, providing the force for the cutting process.</p><p>Now, Johnson et al. used fluorescent light to follow how individual viruses in human cells grown in the laboratory assemble, and polarized light to detect how the orientation of Gag changed as the membrane bends into a sphere. The experiments revealed that the virus particles started to form a sphere at the same time Gag began to gather at the cell membrane, before any ESCRTs were present. Once enough Gag proteins had accumulated, the ESCRTs were recruited to the spot and removed within tens of seconds, just before the virus was cut off from the host cell. This suggest that the ESCRTs may help prepare the membrane to split, but are not involved in the actual cutting process.</p><p>The findings of Johnson et al. will help us to better understand the behavior of HIV viruses. Knowing how they assemble and leave the host cell may help to create new strategies for disrupting these processes in particular, so stopping the virus from spreading. Moreover, ESCRTs are involved in numerous activities of a cell, such as cell division or repair of the cell surface after rupture, but little is known about how they work. For the first time, it has been shown that ESCRTs are neither the driving force for bending the membrane nor are they present when the cutting of a virus happens. This may also apply to other processes in the cell that involve membrane-splitting by ESCRT proteins, and researchers may be compelled to reevaluate their proposed role in other systems.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>HIV-1</kwd><kwd>ESCRT</kwd><kwd>viral assembly</kwd><kwd>membrane scission</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Human</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>5R01GM119585</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Daniel S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleck</surname><given-names>Marina</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>Sanford M</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2U54GM103297</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Daniel S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleck</surname><given-names>Marina</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>Sanford M</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>During viral assembly, ESCRTIII and VPS4 are recruited after most of the HIV-1 membrane is bent but disappear prior to scission of the virion from the cell.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>ESCRTs are categorized into groups −0 through -III and act in various cellular processes including cell division, multivesicular body formation, and wound repair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hurley, 2015</xref>). An investigation of protein sorting between endosomes and lysosomes initially led to the discovery of ESCRT-I (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Katzmann et al., 2001</xref>), with other ESCRTs identified soon afterwards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Babst et al., 2002a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">2002b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Katzmann et al., 2003</xref>). Sequential recruitment of the ESCRTs enables division of membrane compartments, with ESCRT-III being critical for the membrane scission process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Henne et al., 2013</xref>). ESCRT-IIIs have a five alpha-helix core structure and assemble in vitro into macromolecular rings or spirals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">McCullough et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Muzioł et al., 2006</xref>). ESCRT-IIIs are believed to polymerize in the neck of the membrane constriction to drive membrane fission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cashikar et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Dobro et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fabrikant et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hanson et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Henne et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lata et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">McCullough et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>Scission of the membrane, even in the presence of ESCRT-IIIs, stalls in the absence of the hexameric AAA<sup>+</sup> ATPase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Morita et al., 2010</xref>), VPS4A/B, which contains a microtubule interacting and transport (MIT) domain that binds to MIT interacting motifs (MIM) of ESCRT-IIIs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Obita et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Stuchell-Brereton et al., 2007</xref>). The final scission process is believed to be associated with VPS4 working on ESCRT-IIIs, but the mechanism is still unresolved. In some models, the ESCRT-IIIs provide the motive force for scission and the VPS4 is required after scission to recycle the ESCRT-IIIs for subsequent scissions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lata et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Wollert et al., 2009</xref>). In other models, the VPS4 is actively engaging the ESCRT-IIIs prior or during scission by actively remodeling ESCRT-IIIs in order to force scission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Saksena et al., 2009</xref>), by rearranging ESCRT-IIIs as part of the pathway toward scission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cashikar et al., 2014</xref>), or by binding to ESCRT dome structures in order to add rigidity necessary for scission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fabrikant et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>ESCRT complexes are hijacked by HIV to enable separation of the viral particle from the host cell plasma membrane. The production of enveloped HIV-1 at the plasma membrane occurs with the recruitment of the structural protein Gag at individual assembly sites. The carboxyl terminus of Gag has a motif that is essential for recruitment of ESCRTs. First, Gag recruits the ‘early’ factors like ESCRT-I/TSG101 and ALIX which contribute to subsequent recruitment of ESCRT-III proteins. The ESCRT-IIIs then polymerize into structures that are believed to constrict the neck and drive membrane fission. HIV release appears to require fewer members of the ESCRT family than other processes. Redundancy likely makes many variants, such as CHMP5, CHMP6 and CHMP7, only conditionally necessary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Morita et al., 2011</xref>). ESCRT-IIIs that are essential for assembly of HIV-1 include CHMP2 (either A or B variant) and CHMP4B, which are recruited to site of budding with other proteins such as ESCRT-I/TSG101 and ALIX which interact with Gag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Morita et al., 2011</xref>). The reduced number of required ESCRTs makes HIV assembly an approachable system for studying the biophysics of ESCRT-mediated membrane scission.</p><p>Prior to viral particle separation from a host cell, a roughly spherical particle is formed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Martin-Serrano et al., 2003</xref>), but the topological pathway and timing of events to reaching the Gag sphere has not previously been followed in vivo. The order of some of the events in virion assembly has been resolved by live-cell microscopy. First, the HIV- genome is recruited to the membrane, potentially with a few Gag molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jouvenet et al., 2009</xref>). Then, over a 5–30 min period, the Gag accumulates around the genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Ivanchenko et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jouvenet et al., 2008</xref>). Once Gag reaches a steady-state, ESCRT-III and VPS4 are transiently recruited at the site of assembly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Baumgärtel et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jouvenet et al., 2011</xref>). The timing of some critical steps is not known impacting our understanding of the mechanism. It is not known whether bending occurs before, during, or after the transient recruitment of ESCRTs. Thus, is membrane bending driven by Gag multimerization, by Gag engagement with the HIV-1 genome or by the ESCRTs? It is also not known if scission occurs before, during, or after the transient recruitment of ESCRT-IIIs or VPS4. Do they generate the force for scission, do they prepare the membrane for scission, or does VPS4 recycle ESCRT-IIIs after scission?</p><p>Here, we investigated, during the assembly of HIV Gag, the temporal recruitment of ESCRT-III proteins and VPS4 relative to membrane scission. We also examined membrane curvature during Gag assembly to determine when a spherical particle forms relative to ESCRT-III recruitment. We find that membrane bending occurs contemporaneous with recruitment of Gag and prior to arrival ESCRT-III. The ESCRT-IIIs and the VPS4 ATPase arrive after Gag assembly has concluded, remain at the membrane for tens of seconds, and then leave tens of seconds before scission. During the period after departure of the ESCRT-IIIs, neutralizing the surface charge on the membrane accelerates the membrane scission.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>ESCRT-IIIs appear and disappear from site of virus-like particle assembly prior to scission</title><p>To determine the timing of ESCRT recruitment relative to membrane bending and scission, we quantified ESCRT recruitment during the assembly of HIV-1 virus like particles (VLPs) while assaying membrane bending and scission. Scission was assayed by monitoring the ability of protons to flow between the cytosol and the lumen of the virion. The pH in the lumen of the virion was monitored with a pH-sensitive GFP (pHlourin) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Miesenböck et al., 1998</xref>) fused to Gag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jouvenet et al., 2008</xref>) while modulating the cytoplasmic pH by cycling the pCO<sub>2</sub> every 10 s between 0 and 10%, thus an average of 5% pCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>). CO<sub>2</sub> rapidly diffuses across plasma membranes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Hulikova and Swietach, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Simon et al., 1994</xref>) and is converted to carbonic acid by cytoplasmic carbonic anhydrase, altering the cytoplasmic pH. We have previously observed that Gag-pHlourin in a budded VLP is less sensitive to changes of pCO<sub>2</sub> than in the cytosol, suggesting carbonic anhydrase is excluded from VLPs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jouvenet et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>At sites of VLP assembly, the average Gag-pHluorin fluorescence increase was similar to the increase of Gag-mEGFP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jouvenet et al., 2008</xref>), but the intensity oscillated in sync with switching the pCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig1video1">Figure 1—video 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig1video2">Figure 1—video 2</xref>). At various times after Gag accumulation reached a steady-state maximum the magnitude of oscillations decreased, indicating a loss of the ability of protons to move between the VLP and cytoplasm due to scission. CO<sub>2</sub> may still cross the VLP membrane after scission and enter via gaps in the lattice of the immature Gag lattice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Briggs et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Carlson et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Woodward et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Wright et al., 2007</xref>). However, the greatly reduced sensitivity to pH indicates carbonic anhydrase is not present, consistent with analysis of cellular proteins in HIV particles by mass spectrometry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Ott, 2008</xref>). Not surprisingly, scission was never observed before Gag had finished accumulating at individual VLPs. Unexpectedly, the ESCRT-III CHMP4B both appeared (Avg = 59 s, N = 30 out of 30) and disappeared (Avg = 22 s, N = 27 out of 30) prior to scission (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.003</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>ESCRT-IIIs and VPS4A transiently recruited prior to scission.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Example trace of Gag-pHluorin assembling into single VLP while the pCO<sub>2</sub> in the imaging media was repeatedly switched between 0% and 10% every 10 s. Moment of scission is indicated by red dashed line. CHMP4B-mCherry was temporarily recruited (indicated by grey zone) to the site of VLP assembly following the loss of pH modulation sensitivity. (<bold>B</bold>) Histograms of appearance and disappearance of CHMP4B prior to scission. (<bold>C-H</bold>) Example traces and histograms of appearance and disappearance, relative to scission of the VLP, for mCherry-CHMP2A (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>), mCherry-CHMP2B (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>) and mCherry-VPS4A (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Flow chamber configuration for ESCRT-III assisted membrane scission studies.</title><p>Imaging media in reservoirs was preequilibrated with gas containing 0 and 10% CO<italic><sub>2</sub></italic> (balanced with air). During assembly of single HIV particles in cells, the imaging media was modulated between reservoirs, enabling detection of scission of the VLP from the cell.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig1-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.005</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Example traces of scission relative to recruitment of ESCRT-III or VPS4A.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Gag-pHluorin was observed as pCO<sub>2</sub> was cycled between 0 and 10% every 10 s. VLP scission time (red dashed line) was characterized by half drop in lock-in signal. mCherry-CHMP4B, mCherry-CHMP2A, mCherry-CHMP2B and mCherry-VPS4A recruitment (left to right panels, recruitment highlighted in grey) were simultaneously monitored during Gag assembly. (<bold>B</bold>) Additional traces of VLP scission during recruitment of mCherry-CHMP4B, mCherry-CHMP2A, mCherry-CHMP2B, and mCherry-VPS4A (left to right columns).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig1-figsupp2-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.006</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Knockdown of CHMP2A or CHMP2B by siRNA.</title><p>HeLa cell lines stably expressing either mEGFP-CHMP2A or mEGFP-CHMP2B were transfected with siRNA to either CHMP2A or CHMP2B or a control siRNA. 48 hr after transfection, presence of tagged ESCRT was significantly reduced and resulted in fewer cells, presumably because of decreased cell division.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig1-figsupp3-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.007</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>CHMP4B was recruited prior to VPS4A.</title><p>The times associated with the rising fluorescence edge of VPS4A and CHMP4B were compared relative to each other. CHMP4B appeared on average 5.1 s prior to VPS4A.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig1-figsupp4-v2"/></fig><media id="fig1video1" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig1-video1.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.008</object-id><label>Figure 1—video 1.</label><caption><title>Gag-pHluorin (left side of video) and mCherry-CHMP4B (right side) were imaged while the CO<sub>2</sub> in the media was modulated between 0 and 10% every 10 s.</title></caption></media><media id="fig1video2" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig1-video2.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.009</object-id><label>Figure 1—video 2.</label><caption><title>Example of individual puncta of Gag-pHluorin assembly (left side, CO<sub>2</sub> switching every 10 s) with mCherry-CHMP4B (right side) recruitment.</title><p>CHMP4B begins to appear at 13:29 min.</p></caption></media><media id="fig1video3" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig1-video3.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.010</object-id><label>Figure 1—video 3.</label><caption><title>Gag-pHluorin (top of video) and mCherry-VPS4A (bottom) were imaged while the CO<sub>2</sub> in the media was modulated between 0 and 10% every 10 s.</title></caption></media><media id="fig1video4" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig1-video4.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.011</object-id><label>Figure 1—video 4.</label><caption><title>Example of individual puncta of Gag-pHluorin assembly (left side, CO<sub>2</sub> switching every 10 s) with mCherry-VPS4A (right side) recruitment.</title><p>VPS4A begins to appear at 20:49 min.</p></caption></media></fig-group><p>CHMP4B has been proposed to form a circular/spiral structure which supports assembly of a smaller CHMP2(A/B) dome which generates fission by pulling the neck together (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fabrikant et al., 2009</xref>). Thus, it is possible that CHMP4B may be removed prior to scission leaving CHMP2A or CHMP2B present to facilitate fission. To probe the timing of CHMP2, endogenous CHMP2A and CHMP2B were lowered with siRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>) to facilitate observation of mCherry-CHMP2A or mCherry-CHMP2B (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C and E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>). CHMP2A and CHMP2B both appeared (Avg. = 77 s, N = 29 out of 29; and 63 s, N = 23 out of 23, respectively) and disappeared prior to scission (Avg. = 23 s, N = 26 out of 29; and 27 s, N = 23 out of 23, respectively <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D,F</xref>). This observation indicates their assembly and disassembly is also not physically forcing scission.</p><p>Next the dynamics of recruitment of VPS4, the energy providing ATPase, was monitored (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1G</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig1video3">Figure 1—video 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig1video4">Figure 1—video 4</xref>). Similar to the ESCRT-IIIs, VPS4A also appeared prior to scission (Avg = 42 s, N = 28 out of 28) and disappeared prior to scission (Avg = 17 s, N = 27 out of 28, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1H</xref>). On average VPS4A disappeared from the assembly site closer to the time of scission than CHMP4B (5 s), CHMP2A (6 s) or CHMP2B (10 s). A simultaneous measurement of CHMP4B and VPS4A confirmed CHMP4B was recruited ~5 s prior to VPS4A (N = 41) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s4">Figure 1—figure supplement 4</xref>), which agrees with previous results in HeLa cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Acidification of cytosol accelerates scission</title><p>Our results indicate that the ESCRT-IIIs and the ATPase VPS4 leave the membrane prior to scission. It is possible that the ESCRT-IIIs play an essential role in tightening the membrane neck, but then need to be cleared away to allow for the opposing membranes to come closer for the scission reaction. The specific lipid composition in the neck is not known. However, both HIV-1 Gag and the ESCRT complexes are recruited to regions rich in phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate (PIP<sub>2</sub>), which has four negative charges at pH 7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Kooijman et al., 2009</xref>), with the net negative charge being the critical parameter for engaging ESCRTs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2015</xref>). Thus, ESCRTs at the neck may bias the composition toward more negatively charged lipids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Chiaruttini et al., 2015</xref>). The pK<sub>a</sub> values for the two phosphate groups on the inositol of PIP<sub>2</sub> are 6.5 and 7.7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">van Paridon et al., 1986</xref>). The change in pHluorin intensity from 0 and 10% pCO<sub>2</sub>, indicates the cytosolic pH ranges from ~7.5 to ~6.5. Therefore, lowering the pH by raising the pCO<sub>2</sub> to 10% should protonate and reduce the charge of these negatively charged lipids thus reducing the repulsive force between the membranes. To test if scission was affected by changes in cytosolic pH, we switched the pCO<sub>2</sub> at a slower rate, every 120 s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig2video1">Figure 2—video 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig2video2">Figure 2—video 2</xref>). Scission was ~3X more likely when the cytoplasm was in the low pH state (10% pCO<sub>2</sub>) than the high pH state (0% pCO<sub>2</sub>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>) consistent with the idea that scission is more likely when the net negative charge on phospholipids in the viral neck is reduced by protonation. Other common phospholipids like phosphatidic acid (PA), phosphatidylethanolamine (PE), phosphatidylcholine (PC), phosphatidylserine (PS), and phosphatidylglycerol (PG), have pK<sub>a</sub> values outside the pH range used in these experiments so are not expected to be as sensitive to charge modulation during pH switching as PIP<sub>2</sub>. However, other lipids or components with pH-dependent charge sensitivity might also or alternatively result in these observations.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.012</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Scission more likely at lower cytoplasmic pH.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Example traces of Gag-pHluorin assembly while pCO<sub>2</sub> was switched every 120 s between 0% (red dashed line, greater fluorescence emission) and 10% (black dashed line, lower fluorescence emission). In these traces the fluorescence intensity became fixed in the low pH state (10% pCO<sub>2</sub>) after reaching an assembly plateau. VPS4A appeared and disappeared during the first low pH state. (<bold>B</bold>) Examples in which fluorescence intensity became fixed in the high pH state (0% pCO<sub>2</sub>). VPS4A appeared and disappeared during the first trapped high pH state. (<bold>C</bold>) Example in which fluorescence became fixed in low pH state. VPS4A disappeared during the first trapped low pH state, but appeared during the previous high pH state. (<bold>D</bold>) Example in which fluorescence became fixed in high pH state. VPS4A disappeared during the first trapped high pH state, but appeared during the previous low pH state. (<bold>E</bold>) Example trace in which fluorescence intensity because fixed in an intermediate state. (<bold>F</bold>) Bar graph of cytoplasmic pH condition in which scission occurs (N = 45). Scission is ~3-fold more likely at low pH (10% pCO<sub>2</sub>) compared to high pH (0% pCO<sub>2</sub>) condition. A small percentage of VLPs were trapped in an intermediate state.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig2-v2"/></fig><media id="fig2video1" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig2-video1.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.013</object-id><label>Figure 2—video 1.</label><caption><title>Gag-pHluorin (left side of video) and mCherry-VPS4A (right side) were imaged while the CO<sub>2</sub> in the media was modulated between 0 and 10% every 120 s.</title></caption></media><media id="fig2video2" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig2-video2.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.014</object-id><label>Figure 2—video 2.</label><caption><title>Example of individual puncta of Gag-pHluorin assembly (left side, CO<sub>2</sub> switching every 120 s) with mCherry-VPS4A (right side) recruitment.</title><p>VPS4A begins to appear at 14:33 min.</p></caption></media></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Additional rounds of ESCRT-III/VPS4 recruitment occur following failed scission</title><p>Multiple rounds of ESCRT-III/VPS4 recruitment were previously observed following completion of Gag accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Baumgärtel et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jouvenet et al., 2011</xref>). It is possible that the first wave of ESCRT-III/VPS4 led to productive scission and the subsequent rounds are inconsequential. Alternatively, the initial waves could be non-productive, perhaps a consequence of a failure to recruit both ESCRT-IIIs and VPS4A concurrently, necessitating additional rounds. While simultaneously imaging Gag-pHluorin, CHMP4B and VPS4A, when there were multiple waves, both CHMP4B and VPS4A were recruited (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). Multiple waves of recruitment were observed in ~20% of traces, consistent with our previous observations of repeat rounds of recruitment of CHMP1B, CHMP4B, CHMP4C and VPS4A during assembly of HIV-1 and EIAV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jouvenet et al., 2011</xref>). Scission was only observed after the final wave of recruitment of ESCRT-III/VPS4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B,C</xref>). Thus, not every cycle of arrival and then dispersal of ESCRT-III/VPS4 leads to subsequent scission. If scission does not occur then a subsequent cycle of recruitment and dispersal of the ESCRT-III/VPS4 is required to complete the process. If the function of VPS4A is to recycle ESCRT-IIIs after scission then only a single wave would be expected since ESCRT-IIIs would not be removed until after the single scission event has occurred.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.015</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>A new round of ESCRT-III recruitment required following failed scission event.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Example traces of multiple waves of VPS4A and CHMP4B recruited following cessation of Gag accumulation. (<bold>B</bold>) Example trace of multiple recruitments of VPS4A prior to scission (red dashed line). (<bold>C</bold>) Example traces of multiple recruitments of CHMP4B prior to scission (red dashed line).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig3-v2"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Membrane bending occurs throughout assembly of virus-like particle</title><p>Next, we set out to determine when membrane bending occurs relative to the assembly of Gag and recruitment of ESCRT-IIIs. We expressed a fluorescent protein (either EGFP or one of two circularly permutated superfolder variants, sf3 or sf11 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Pédelacq et al., 2006</xref>) as a fusion to Gag (at the carboxyl terminus, p6-GFP, or in the matrix protein of Gag, MA-sf3 or MA-sf11) to be able to follow membrane bending in live-cell imaging via changes in anisotropy of the GFP tag.</p><p>The orientation of the chromophore was characterized with a custom built polarized total internal reflection fluorescence (TIRF) illuminator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Johnson et al., 2014</xref>). During accumulation of Gag at VLPs, the emission of the GFP was quantified while excitation alternated with polarization perpendicular (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf1"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> polarized) followed by parallel (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf2"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> polarized) to the glass surface. Orientation was characterized by the ratio of emission intensities (P/S) and total Gag was monitored by P+2S (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig4video1">Figure 4—video 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig4video2">Figure 4—video 2</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anantharam et al., 2010</xref>). As Gag accumulated, the ratio of P/S dropped from ~2 to ~1.4, with little variation (±0.1) between the Gag-GFP versions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). The drop in P/S correlated with the increase in Gag as would be expected if the plasma membrane was bending during Gag assembly. The halfway decrease of P/S occurred prior to the halfway increase of the total Gag fluorescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). Following Gag recruitment, as indicated by a plateau in Gag signal, there was no transition in P/S. This observation is inconsistent with the subsequent recruitment of the ESCRT-IIIs facilitating the transition from a flat lattice to a spherical particle.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.016</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Structural changes in VLPs throughout Gag accumulation.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Example traces of wild-type Gag-GFP (black line, sf3 in Matrix of Gag) and Gag-∆p6 (grey line, missing ESCRT-I recruiting p6 domain) assembling into single VLPs. Images were collected every 30 s with excitation illumination polarized either perpendicular (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf3"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) or parallel (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf4"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) to the glass surface. Total Gag characterized by P+2S (top) and relative average dipole orientation by P/S (bottom). P+2S from wild-type Gag was fit to an exponential and used to predict an expected P/S (blue dashed line) assuming membrane bending throughout assembly. (<bold>B</bold>) Comparison of average P/S from all traces before VLP assembly (membrane background) and after VLP assembly (plateau region) for three different tagged versions of wild-type Gag. p6-GFP (N = 8), MA-sf3 (N = 9), and MA-sf11 (N = 7). Error bars represent s.d. (<bold>C</bold>) To compare the evolution of VLP structure to the assembly of Gag the time for each assembly trace was normalized from 0 (beginning of Gag assembly) to 1 (end of Gag assembly). A normalized time difference for each trace between Gag half assembly [½ (P+2S)<sub>max</sub>] and the dipole half drop [½ (P/S)<sub>max</sub>] was found and all normalized differences were compiled into a histogram. (<bold>D</bold>) Illustration of sphere budding from flat membrane. (<bold>E</bold>) Illustration of coordinate system with <italic>θ</italic> and <italic>ϕ</italic> representing position on the sphere and <italic>β</italic> and <italic>ψ</italic> representing orientation of excitation dipole. (<bold>F</bold>) Predicted P/S when <italic>β = 45°</italic>, background intensity is 45% of full assembly intensity, and evanescent field penetration depth is the same as the radius of the VLP.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig4-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.017</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Example traces of Gag accumulation (quantified as P+2S) and fluorophore polarization (quantified as P/S) during VLP assembly.</title><p>Three different tagging schemes were used: labeled with mEGFP after p6 domain at carboxy terminal of Gag (<bold>A</bold>), labeled with circularly permutated GFP variant three in matrix of Gag (<bold>B</bold>), labeled with circularly permutated GFP variant 11 in matrix of Gag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Pédelacq et al., 2006</xref>) (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig4-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.018</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Example traces of Gag-∆p6-mEGFP accumulation (quantified as P+2S) and fluorophore polarization (quantified as P/S) during VLP assembly.</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig4-figsupp2-v2"/></fig><media id="fig4video1" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig4-video1.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.019</object-id><label>Figure 4—video 1.</label><caption><title>Images of Gag-mEGFP were acquired with excitation perpendicular (P) or parallel (S) to the glass surface.</title><p>Left side of video is calculated P+2S (quantification of Gag intensity) and right side is ratio image P/S (measurement of structure).</p></caption></media><media id="fig4video2" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig4-video2.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.020</object-id><label>Figure 4—video 2.</label><caption><title>Example of individual puncta of Gag-mEGFP with P/S and P+2S images.</title></caption></media></fig-group><p>Bending was also investigated during the assembly of a Gag that is missing its carboxyl terminal p6 domain which functions to recruit early acting proteins like ESCRT-I/TSG101 or ALIX. A similar drop in P/S during assembly of Gag was observed with Gag-∆p6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>) indicating that the ESCRTs recruited via p6 are also not necessary for the transition from a flat lattice to a spherical particle.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>A simulation of spherical budding reproduced the time course of the P/S ratio relative to P+2S</title><p>In order to better understand the observed P/S ratio, we formulated an expected P/S ratio for a spherical cap growing out of a flat membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). Briefly, we assumed the growing bud consisted of excitation dipoles uniformly distributed across the surface, with the dipoles oriented an angle <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf5"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> relative to the surface normal. A predicted P/S with respect to <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf6"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and the normalized budded surface area (area from 0 to 1) was then found by integrating over all defined dipole orientations and the extent budded surface area.</p><p>More specifically, using coordinates described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anantharam et al., 2010</xref>), position on the surface of the sphere was given in terms of a polar angle <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf7"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and an azimuthal angle <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf8"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the current extent budded was defined by <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf9"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>). Thus, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf10"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> there was no budding, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf11"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>90</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> the sphere was half budded with dipoles from <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf12"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>90</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, and when <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf13"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>180</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> the sphere was fully budded with dipoles from <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf14"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>180</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. A uniform distribution of excitation dipoles was assumed on the bud (no dependence on <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf15"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf16"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>); however, at any given position these dipoles had an angular distribution that depended on the polar angle <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf17"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> relative to the surface normal: <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf18"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. For instance, if all dipoles were oriented at <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf19"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>45</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> then <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf20"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>45</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf21"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is a delta function. The angular distribution was assumed to be uniform relative to the surface azimuthal angle <italic>ψ</italic> and the sphere was assumed to be smaller than the optical resolution of the microscope.</p><p>A predicted <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf22"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> relative to extent budded <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf23"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> was found by determining the average component of the dipole excitation in <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf24"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (parallel to glass surface) and in <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf25"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (normal to glass surface). Note: Experimentally due to azimuthal scanning we excited in both <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf26"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf27"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, each 50% the time, but for simplicity in this analysis 100% excitation in <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf28"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> was assumed since <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf29"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf30"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> are symmetric. The total collected fluorescence, S and P, in <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf31"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf32"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> were predicated by:<disp-formula id="equ1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="m1"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">∣</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">∣</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="m2"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">⊥</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf33"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf34"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> are the components of the excitation dipole in <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf35"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf36"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> with respect to positon on the bud surface, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf37"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf38"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> are the excitation electric field components in <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf39"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf40"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf41"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">∣</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">∣</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf42"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">⊥</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> are the light collection efficiencies of the microscope objective for dipoles parallel and perpendicular to the glass surface. The excitation field intensity in <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf43"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf44"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> were assumed to be the same, though this was an approximation since in reality <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf45"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> had a small component of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf46"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sund et al., 1999</xref>). In addition, in TIR the excitation field decayed exponentially with distance from the glass surface, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf47"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> where the characteristic decay constant was defined in terms of a fraction of the radius of the VLP. The collection efficiency for emission parallel <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf48"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">∣</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">∣</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> versus perpendicular <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf49"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">⊥</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>were also assumed to be the same (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf50"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">∣</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">∣</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">⊥</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>), which was an approximation based on the use of a high numerical aperture objective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anantharam et al., 2010</xref>). From coordinate transforms described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anantharam et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sund et al., 1999</xref>), the components of the dipoles in <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf51"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf52"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> are given by:<disp-formula id="equ3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="m3"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="m4"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">z</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf53"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> was solved computationally (Mathematica, Wolfram) with <italic>θ</italic> parameterized in terms of normalized surface area (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf54"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) as <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf55"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. In addition, contribution from fluorescence outside of the puncta was accounted for as follows:<disp-formula id="equ5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="m5"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula>where C<sub>back</sub> was the background intensity relative to final VLP intensity and P/S<sub>Background</sub> was the ratio of fluorescence when puncta <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf56"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, that is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf57"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>We found an angle <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf58"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>45</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∘</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.45</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf59"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> approximately replicated the observed results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A and F</xref>), reproducing the <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf60"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> of 0.16 (normalized time) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref> an exponential fit to P+2S was assumed in order to directly equate the VLP area to the predicted P/S. Similar results were obtained by using a uniform distribution of dipoles over an angular range, such as <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf61"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> between <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf62"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>°</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf63"><mml:mn>68.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>°</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf64"><mml:mn>20</mml:mn><mml:mo>°</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf65"><mml:mn>63.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>°</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, our observation is consistent with formation of a spherical bud throughout the recruitment and multimerization of Gag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Woodward et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Carlson et al., 2008</xref>), and is independent of the presence of early acting factors like ESCRT-I/TSG101 or ALIX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>). The bending also occurs many minutes before the recruitment of ESCRT-IIIs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In retroviral assembly, the late domains of Gag are believed to indirectly recruit ESCRT-IIIs which then polymerize into ring or spiral structures at the bud neck to drive bending and scission of the neck membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cashikar et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fabrikant et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hanson et al., 2008</xref>). However, our observations compel a new formulation of the role of ESCRTs in bending and scission. First, the initial bending of the membrane from a flat sheet to a spherical bud occurs during Gag assembly and does not require factors recruited by the late domains like ESCRT-1/TSG101 or ALIX. This bending also occurs prior to the arrival of ESCRT-IIIs and thus ESCRT-IIIs are also not required to initiate curvature. Instead, this process may be encouraged by Gag multimerization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Briggs et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Wright et al., 2007</xref>). Second, the ESCRT-IIIs are only recruited after the accumulation of Gag is complete, indicating that Gag is not sufficient for recruitment. Third, the ESCRT-III/VPS4 are only recruited for tens of seconds and can no longer be detected at the moment of scission. While the ESCRTs and VPS4 cannot be detected in the tens of seconds prior to scission, it does not eliminate the possibility that a subpopulation of fewer than 20% of the ESCRT-III/VPS4, which are not detectable in the background fluctuations, stay around for a longer period of time (further discussed in Materials and methods).</p><p>Factors beyond the late domains which might assist ESCRT-III recruitment include activation through ubiquitination or phosphorylation of Gag or one of the early ESCRTs, such as ESCRT-II (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Meng et al., 2015</xref>) or ESCRT-I/TSG101, which is co-recruited along with Gag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jouvenet et al., 2011</xref>). Additionally, ESCRT-III recruitment might be facilitated by high curvature in the neck or specific lipids recruited to these regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2015</xref>). These conditions may also facilitate recruitment of ESCRT-IIIs even in the absence of ESCRT-I or ESCRT-II, although likely at lower rates, potentially accounting for the much slower viral particle release rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bendjennat and Saffarian, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Meng et al., 2015</xref>). The observation that the bulk of measured curvature of the nascent virion occurs prior to the recruitment of ESCRT-IIIs does not rule out any role for ESCRTs in membrane curvature. Indeed, the transient recruitment of ESCRT-IIIs may further constrict the neck linking the virion to the cell to prepare it for scission. The ESCRT-IIIs might facilitate scission by polymerizing into a spiral structure to constrict the neck (‘polymerization constriction’) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cashikar et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Wollert et al., 2009</xref>) or into a ring which when removed constricts the neck (‘purse string constriction’, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Saksena et al., 2009</xref>). The VPS4 may remove the ESCRT-IIIs potentially acting as a unfoldase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Yang et al., 2015</xref>). VPS4 may also remodel the ESCRT-IIIs throughout polymerization, potentially rearranging or tightening the structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cashikar et al., 2014</xref>). Remodeling is consistent with our observation that recruitment of VPS4 was virtually contemporaneous with the ESCRT-III, with a slight 5 s lag in HEK293T cells and 10 s in HeLa cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al., 2014</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.021</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Proposed temporal model of ESCRT-III-mediated scission of HIV from cell plasma membrane.</title><p>(<bold>I</bold>) The viral particle structure changes throughout accumulation of Gag until (<bold>II</bold>) a spherical topology prevents incorporation of additional Gags. (<bold>III</bold>) ESCRT-IIIs (examples: CHMP2, CHMP4) are recruited to the neck and polymerize, with (<bold>IV</bold>) removal by VPS4 resulting in constriction of the neck. (<bold>V</bold>) After removal of all ESCRT-IIIs the narrow neck undergoes spontaneous fission, (<bold>VI</bold>) freeing the virus. If membrane fission does not occur a new round of ESCRT-III recruitment is required (<bold>V</bold>→ <bold>II</bold>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36221-fig5-v2"/></fig><p>We suggest that fission can only occur when the neck is narrow and after the ESCRT-IIIs are removed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). What is driving the scission event if ESCRT-IIIs are gone? When the neck is sufficiently narrow (a few nm) fission may be a spontaneous event, possibly through a hemifission intermediate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fabrikant et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kozlovsky and Kozlov, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Liu et al., 2006</xref>). Narrowing of the neck by ESCRT-IIIs may allow additional Gag molecules adjacent to the neck to oligomerize, thereby keeping the constricted structure stable while the ESCRTs are displaced. However, cryo-EM images indicate a gap in the Gag lattice might be present at the site of the neck (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Carlson et al., 2008</xref>). Alternatively, constriction might encourage exchange or modification of phospholipids with shapes and charges that help to retain a narrow neck following ESCRT-III disappearance. The ESCRT-IIIs are dependent on phospholipids with negative charges. This could explain the greater than three fold increased scission rate at a lower pH (10% pCO<sub>2</sub>), which would raise the proton concentration to that of the pK<sub>a</sub> (6.5 and 7.7) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">van Paridon et al., 1986</xref>), thereby reducing the surface charges (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>). If scission does not occur sufficiently soon after removal of ESCRT-IIIs, a new round of ESCRT-III recruitment and assembly is required to achieve scission (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Reagent type (species) <break/>or resource</th><th>Designation</th><th>Source or reference</th><th>Identifiers</th><th>Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Cell line (<italic>H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>HEK-293T</td><td>Bieniasz Lab</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Cell line (<italic>H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>HeLa</td><td>ATCC</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(HIV-1, <italic>A. victoria</italic>)</td><td>Gag-mEGFP</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al. (2014)</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(HIV, <italic>A. macrodactyla</italic>)</td><td>Gag-mTagBFP</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al. (2014)</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(<italic>A. victoria, H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>pLNCX2-mEGFP-VPS4A</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al. (2014)</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(<italic>A. marginale, H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP4B</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al. (2014)</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(HIV)</td><td>Gag∆p6</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al. (2014)</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(HIV)</td><td>pCR3.1/Syn-Gag</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jouvenet et al. (2008)</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(HIV, <italic>A. victoria</italic>)</td><td>pCR3.1/Syn-Gag-pHluorin</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jouvenet et al. (2008)</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(<italic>A. marginale, H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2A</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>CHMP4B in pLNCX2-mCherry- <break/>CHMP4B was replaced by CHMP2A <break/>from HEK293T cDNA library</td></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(<italic>A. marginale, H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2B</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>CHMP4B in pLNCX2-mCherry- <break/>CHMP4B was replaced by CHMP2B <break/>from HEK293T cDNA library</td></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(<italic>A. marginale, H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2A- <break/>siRNAres</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>added six silent point mutations <break/>to pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2A <break/>using site directed mutagenesis</td></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(<italic>A. marginale, H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2B- <break/>siRNAres</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>added six silent point mutations <break/>to pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2B <break/>using site directed mutagenesis</td></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(<italic>A. marginale, H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>pLNCX2-mEGFP-CHMP2A</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>replaced mCherry in pLNCX2- <break/>mCherry-CHMP2A with EGFP <break/>(pEGFP-N1, Clontech)</td></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(<italic>A. marginale, H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>pLNCX2-mEGFP-CHMP2B</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>replaced mCherry in pLNCX2- <break/>mCherry-CHMP2B with EGFP <break/>(pEGFP-N1, Clontech)</td></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(<italic>A. marginale, H. sapiens</italic>)</td><td>pLNCX2-mCherry-VPS4A</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>replaced mEGFP in pLNCX2- <break/>mCherry-VPS4A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al., 2014</xref>) <break/>with mCherry (pmCherry- N1, Clontech)</td></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(HIV, <italic>A. victoria</italic>)</td><td>Gag-∆p6-mEGFP</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>p6 domain removed from Gag-mEGFP <break/>using site directed mutagensis</td></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(HIV, <italic>A. victoria</italic>)</td><td>Gag-MA-sf3</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>sf3 GFP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Pédelacq et al., 2006</xref>) <break/>inserted in pCR3.1/Syn-Gag</td></tr><tr><td>Transfected construct <break/>(HIV, <italic>A. victoria</italic>)</td><td>Gag-MA-sf11</td><td>This study</td><td/><td>sf11 GFP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Pédelacq et al., 2006</xref>) <break/>inserted in pCR3.1/Syn-Gag</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>CHMP2A DsiRNA</td><td>Integrated DNA <break/>Technologies</td><td>5'-AAGAUGAAGAGGAG <break/>AGUGAUGCUdGdT-3'</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>CHMP2A DsiRNA (reverse)</td><td>Integrated DNA <break/>Technologies</td><td>5'-ACAGCAUCACUCUC <break/>CUCUUCAUCUUCC-3'</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>CHMP2B DsiRNA</td><td>Integrated DNA <break/>Technologies</td><td>5'-GGAACAGAAUCGAG <break/>AGUUACGAGdGdT-3'</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>CHMP2B DsiRNA (reverse)</td><td>Integrated DNA <break/>Technologies</td><td>5'-ACCUCGUAACUCUC <break/>GAUUCUGUUCCUU-3'</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, <break/>drug</td><td valign="bottom">DMEM</td><td>Thermo Fisher <break/>Scientific</td><td>#11965</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, <break/>drug</td><td valign="bottom">FBS</td><td>MilliporeSigma</td><td>#F4135</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, <break/>drug</td><td>HEPES</td><td>MilliporeSigma</td><td>#H3375</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Metamorph</td><td>Molecular Devices</td><td>version 7.8.10</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>ImageJ</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Schneider et al. (2012)</xref></td><td>version Fiji</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>LabView</td><td>National Instruments</td><td>version 2013</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Microscope-Control</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Johnson, 2018c</xref>)</td><td/><td>LabView Code</td></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Average-puncta-center</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Johnson, 2018a</xref>)</td><td/><td>LabView Code</td></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Puncta-Fit</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Johnson, 2018d</xref>)</td><td/><td>LabView Code</td></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>CO2-switch-analysis</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Johnson, 2018b</xref>)</td><td/><td>LabView Code</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Plasmid construction</title><p>Plasmids Gag-mEGFP, Gag-mTagBFP, pLNCX2-mEGFP-VPS4A and pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP4B, Gag-∆p6 were described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al. (2014</xref>), and the plasmids pCR3.1/Syn-Gag and pCR3.1/Syn-Gag-pHluorin were described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jouvenet et al. (2008</xref>). The Gag in this study was based on the sequence from HIV-1 clone HXB2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kotsopoulou et al., 2000</xref>).</p><p>pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2A-siRNAres and pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2B-siRNAres were generated as follows. CHMP2A and CHMP2B were PCR amplified (Platinum PCR SuperMix, Thermo Fisher) from a cDNA library created from HEK293T cells (made via Invitrogen SuperScript III CellDirect kit #46–6320). PCR primers for CHMP2A (NM_014453.3) were 5’-GCGCTCCGGACTCAGATCCCCGGAATTCATGGACCTATTGTTCGGGCG-3’ and 5’-GCGCCTCGAGTCAGTCCCTCCGCAGGTTCT-3’ and primers for CHMP2B (NM_014043.3) were 5’-GCGCTCCGGACTCAGATCCCCGGAATTCATGGCGTCCCTCTTCAAGAA-3’ and 5’-GCGCCTCGAGCTAATCTACTCCTAAAGCCT-3’. After PCR amplification, the fragments were digested with XhoI and BspEI (New England BioLabs, Ipswich, MA) and ligated into the plasmid pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP4B (which was first digested with the same restriction enzymes to remove CHMP4B) using T4 DNA Ligase (New England BioLabs) yielding the plasmids pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2A and pLNCX2-mCherry-CHMP2B. Six silent coding mutations were then incorporated into these plasmids (QuickChange Lightning Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit, Agilent, Santa Clara, CA) to make them insensitive to siRNA knockdown targeted at the cellular CHMP2A and CHMP2B RNA. The primers for the CHMP2A site-directed mutagenesis were 5'-ACCTGGGACACCACAGCATCGCTTTCTTCCTCGTCCTCCTCATCACCCATGGCATC-3’ and 5'-GATGCCATGGGTGATGAGGAGGACGAGGAAGAAAGCGATGCTGTGGTGTCCCAGGT-3’ and for CHMP2B were 5’-AACCGTGGATGATGTAATAAAGGAGCAAAACCGTGAATTACGAGGTACACAGAGGGCTAT-3’ and 5’-ATAGCCCTCTGTGTACCTCGTAATTCACGGTTTTGCTCCTTTATTACATCATCCACGGTT-3’. The siRNA sequence for CHMP2A knockdown was 5’-rArArGrArUrGrArArGrArGrGrArGrArGrUrGrAdTdT-3’ (begins at position 464 in NM_014453.2) and for CHMP2B was 5’-rGrGrArArCrArGrArArUrCrGrArGrArGrUrUrAdTdT-3’ (begins at position 45 in NM_014043.3) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Morita et al., 2011</xref>). The forward and reverse DsiRNA for CHMP2A knockdown was 5'-rArArGrArUrGrArArGrArGrGrArGrArGrUrGrArUrGrCrUdGdT-3' and 5'-rArCrArGrCrArUrCrArCrUrCrUrCrCrUrCrUrUrCrArUrCrUrUrCrC-3'. The forward and reverse DsiRNA for CHMP2B knockdown was 5'-rGrGrArArCrArGrArArUrCrGrArGrArGrUrUrArCrGrArGdGdT-3' and 5'-rArCrCrUrCrGrUrArArCrUrCrUrCrGrArUrUrCrUrGrUrUrCrCrUrU-3'. All ssDNA and ssRNA oligos were purchased from Integrated DNA Technologies (Coralville, IA) and manufacturers’ protocols were used for all preparations.</p><p>pLNCX2-mEGFP-CHMP2A and pLNCX2-mEGFP-CHMP2B were generated by replacing mCherry in pLNCX-mCherry-CHMP2A and pLNCX-mCherry-CHMP2B with monomeric variant (A206K) of mEGFP from pEGFP-N1 (Clontech/Takara Bio USA, Mountain View, CA). Restriction enzymes AgeI and BspEI (New England BioLabs) were used to digest the backbone and fragments, and these fragments were then ligated into the backbones with T4 DNA ligase. The clonal HeLa cell lines were generated from these plasmids using a previously described protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al., 2014</xref>). pLNCX2-mCherry-VPS4A was generated by replacing mEGFP in pLNCX2-mCherry-VPS4A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al., 2014</xref>) with mCherry. mCherry was PCR amplified from pmCherry-N1 (Clontech) using In-Fusion recombination primers 5'-CTCTAGCGCTACCGGTCGCCACCATGGTGAGCAAGGGC-3’ and 5'-CTCTAGCGCTACCGGTCGCCACCATGGTGAGCAAGGGC-3’. pLNCX2-mEGFP-VPS4A was digested with AgeI and BspEI and the fragment containing VPS4A was gel purified (Thermo Fisher PureLink Quick Gel Extraction Kit). The PCR product was then inserted into purified backbone using In-Fusion HD Cloning Kit (Clontech) according to manufacturer’s instructions.</p><p>Gag-∆p6-mEGFP was generated by deleting p6 and SP2 from Gag-mEGFP via site-directed mutagenesis (QuickChange Lightning Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit). The following primers were used for the deletion 5'- TACTGAGAGACAGGCTAATTCGGATCCACCGGT-3'; 5'- ACCGGTGGATCCGAATTAGCCTGTCTCTCAGTA −3'. Gag-MA-sf3 and Gag-MA-sf11 were generated by inserting the circularly permuted superfolder GFPs (provided by Jeffrey Waldo lab) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Pédelacq et al., 2006</xref>) into a variant of pCR3.1/Syn-Gag that has an EcoRV restriction enzyme site near the carboxy terminal of MA (Asn-Gln-Val-Ser modified to Asn-Gln-<bold>Asp-Ile</bold>-Val-Ser). Circularly permuted version 3 was PCR amplified with recombination In-Fusion primers 5’-CACAGCAACCAGGATGGCAGCAGCCATCATCATC-3’ and 5’-GTTCTGGCTGACGATGGTACCTCCAGTAGTGCAAATAA-3’. The primers for circularly permuted version 11 were 5’-CACAGCAACCAGGATGGCAGCAGCCATCATCATC-3’ and 5’-GTTCTGGCTGACGATGGTACCATCTTCAATGTTGTGG-3’. After digesting pCR3.1/Syn-Gag-EcoRV with EcoRV (New England BioLabs) the In-Fusion HD kit was used to insert PCR fragments into the Syn-Gag backbone.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Sample preparation</title><p>With the exception of 120 s pCO<sub>2</sub> switching data, all imagings were conducted in HEK293T cells grown in DMEM (#11965, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) with 10% FBS (#F4135, MilliporeSigma, St. Louis, MO). HEK293T cells were gift from P. Bieniasz Laboratory and were not further authenticated but tested negative for mycoplasma contamination. 120 s pCO<sub>2</sub> switching experiments imaged in HeLa cells which were grown in the same growth medium. HeLa cells were from ATCC and were not authenticated or tested for mycoplasma contamination. For polarization excitation experiments, cells were grown on 35-mm glass bottom dishes (#P35G-1.0–20 C, MatTek, Ashland, MA) coated with fibronectin (#33010, Thermo Fisher) by incubating the dish with 10 µg/ml fibronectin in PBS for 1 hr. For pCO<sub>2</sub> switching experiments, perfusion slides (#80186 µ-Slide, Ibidi, Martinsried, Germany) were incubated with 60 µg/ml fibronectin in PBS for 1 hr before plating cells. For all experiments, cells at ~ 75% confluency were transfected with expression plasmids ~3.5 hr prior to beginning to image. For transfection 8 µl of Lipofectamine2000 (#11668, Thermo Fisher) was incubated for 5 min in 250 µl of Opti-MEM I (#31985, Thermo Fisher) and 2000 µg of DNA was incubated for 5 min in 250 µl of Opti-MEM I. Both solutions were then mixed and incubated for 20 min before adding to adhered cells on MatTek dish in 2000 µl of DMEM. The same procedure was used for cells in the flow slide, but the transfection mixture was added to 2000 µl of DMEM and then 1000 µl was perfused through the chamber. At least four cells were used for each experimental condition in order to account for potential variability between cells. Both CHMP2A and CHMP2B were knocked down with siRNA for mCherry-CHMP2A and mCherry-CHMP2B experiments. siRNA transfections were conducted 48 hr prior to DNA plasmid transfection using Lipofectamine RNAiMAX (following manufacturer’s instructions; #13778, Thermo Fisher). A second round of siRNA transfection was performed at the time of DNA transfection.</p><p>The open-reading frame was verified via sequencing for all plasmids and the following DNA ratios were used for transfections: Gag:Gag-mEGFP (4:1), Gag:Gag-MA-sf3 (4:1), Gag:Gag-MA-sf3 (4:1), Gag-∆p6:Gag-∆p6-mEGFP (4:1), Gag:Gag-pHluorin:mCherry-VPS4A (12:3:5), Gag:Gag-pHluorin:mCherry-CHMP4B (12:3:5), Gag:Gag-pHluorin:mCherry-CHMP2A-siRNAres (4:1:5), Gag:Gag-pHluorin:mCherry-CHMP2B-siRNAres (4:1:5), Gag:Gag-TagBFP:mEGFP-VPS4A:mCherry-CHMP4B (24:6:5:5). Note: The Gag to tagged Gag ratio was 4:1 in all experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>CO<sub>2</sub> modulation system</title><p>Gas from compressed cylinders was bubbled into two imaging media reservoirs (140 ml open piston Monoject syringe, Medtronic, Minneapolis, MN) partially filled with cell imaging media (10 mM HEPES, 9.7 g/L of Hanks BBS (MilliporeSigma), and NaOH to adjust the pH to 7.4) with 1% FBS. One reservoir was equilibrated with compressed air (labeled 0% in these experiments but actually contained 0.04% CO<sub>2</sub>), and the other reservoir was equilibrated with 10% CO<sub>2</sub> (balanced with air) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>). The reservoirs were mounted to a flow perfusion system (ValveBank II, AutoMate Scientific, Berkeley, CA), which enabled automated selection of desired media via solenoid valves under the reservoirs. Tygon tubes (R-3603) from each valve carried the media to a fluid combiner just prior to the perfusion slide chamber containing adhered cells. After the flow chamber, a single tube carried the discharge media to a collection container. This container was placed below the height of equilibration reservoirs so that fluid flow was driven by gravity. The flow rate (~3 ml/min) was controlled with a clamp regulator attached to the discharge tube. At this flow rate, the response time of the fluorophores to a pCO<sub>2</sub> change, characterized in terms of an exponential decay constant, was ~7 s. A peristaltic pump (MS-Reglo, Ismatec/Cole-Parmer, Wertheim, Germany) then passed the media from the collection reservoir back to the equilibration reservoirs so that the media could be recycled. The microscope and entire imaging media flow system were enclosed in a temperature control box held at 37°C. Valve regulation, camera trigger and laser excitation were all controlled via custom software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Microscope-Control">https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Microscope-Control</ext-link>; copy archived at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/Microscope-Control">https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/Microscope-Control</ext-link>) written in LabView (National Instruments, Austin, TX).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Imaging with pCO<sub>2</sub> switching</title><p>For experiments with pCO<sub>2</sub> switching every 10 s the media was continuously flowed through the imaging chamber, with the reservoir supplying the media being switched every 10 s. Two images were collected every 2.5 s (4.0 s for CHMP4B experiments) with 488 nm excitation for pHluorin (100 ms exposure with power between 1 and 5 mW), followed by 594 nm excitation for mCherry (100 ms exposure with laser power between 5 and 20 mW; 100 mW DPSS laser, Cobolt, Solna, Sweden). A multipass emission filter (zet405/488/594 m, Chroma Technology, Bellows Falls, VT) enabled rapid sequential wavelength imaging. For experiments with pCO<sub>2</sub> switching every 120 s the desired media was only applied to the chamber for 10 s, followed by no flow for 110 s. During this time sequential 488 nm (100 ms, 1 mW) and 594 nm (100 ms, 1 mW) excitation images were captured every 10 s. All experiments were conducted with 100 Hz azimuthal scanning TIRF microscopy illumination.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Temporal determination of scission</title><p>The cytosolic pH was oscillated by switching the pCO<sub>2</sub> from 0% to 10% (for an average of 5%) every 10 s or every 120 s. The cytosolic carbonic anhydrase ensures that the pH in the cytosol closely tracks the pCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Simon et al., 1994</xref>). At scission, the luminal pH of the VLP or virion is no longer continuous with the cytosol and no longer tracks the cytosolic pH. Individual VLPs were identified from the Gag-pHluorin images using Metamorph (version 7.8.10, Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA) and the peak pixel amplitude in a 15 pixel (975 nm) diameter regions of interests centered on individual VLPs was found for all frames (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>).</p><p>For switching every 10 s, we used a custom LabView software lock-in amplifier to find changes in VLP sensitivity to pCO<sub>2</sub> modulation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/CO2-switch-analysis">https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/CO2-switch-analysis</ext-link>; copy archived at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/CO2-switch-analysis">https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/CO2-switch-analysis</ext-link>). The data were high-pass filtered (2-pole Butterworth with 0.01 Hz cutoff) to bias the pCO<sub>2</sub>-dependent pHluorin intensity fluctuations (with a period of 20 s) around 0. This signal was then multiplied by an in-phase sine wave with the same period and a moving average was calculated over a period of 60 s. A significant change in signal indicated a change in sensitivity to pCO<sub>2</sub> modulation. At many of the identified VLPs, a clear transition from a high plateau to a low plateau in the lock-in signal was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>). The moment of scission was classified as the halfway amplitude between the two plateaus, with half of the moving window containing pre-scission data and the other half containing post-scission data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>). In the same regions of interest, the average mCherry signal (tagged to VPS4A, CHMP4B, CHMP2A, or CHMP2B) was analyzed and peaks were identified in which there was a clear increase followed by decrease in fluorescence intensity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A,C,E,G</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>). The appearance time was identified when a signal was first observed above cellular background, and the disappearance time when the signal dropped to cellular background. Appearance and disappearance relative to scission were then found by comparing these times to the scission time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B,D,F,H</xref>). Based on the observed distribution of appearance and disappearance times relative to scission, with an average of roughly a minute, we excluded data in which scission and ESCRT-III/VPS4A recruitment were more than 4 min apart. Excluded data was attribute to a failed or uncorrelated scission event. ~25 traces under each condition were collected to gain understanding of the distribution of events.</p><p>The average signal-to-noise was approximately 7:1 (peak signal:S.D.) across all ESCRT-III/VPS4A measurements, and ESCRT-III/VPS4A recruitment was estimated to be detectable when the sustained signal deviated from the mean by ~ 1–2 standard deviations. Based on this deviation, it is estimated that ESCRT-III/VPS4A recruitment below ~20% of peak recruitment would be undetected. We estimate that there are between 10 and 100 ESCRTs in a complex at peak signal, with the possibility of &lt; 10 ESCRTS undetectable in the background noise. Assuming a peak signal (100 ESCRTs) decreases exponentially into the noise after 10 s (10 ESCRTS), we estimate only ~1 ESCRTs would remain after another 10 s. This time is comparable to the ~20 s measured between peak disappearance and scission. If the disappearance is faster than exponential, for example linear, the ESCRTs will be gone even sooner. This interpolation of ESCRT-IIIs or VPS4A disappearance profiles into the noise indicates the ESCRTs predominantly leave the budding site prior to scission (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>). For a significant number (&gt;1) of either ESCRT-IIIs or VPS4A to be around following scission there would need to be a second, smaller population that follows much slower disappearance kinetics.</p><p>For pCO<sub>2</sub> switching every 120 s for each tracing we determined the first transition of pCO<sub>2</sub> for which the fluorescence had decreased sensitivity, indicating protons were no long freely flowing between cytosol and lumen of the VLP. We assumed that scission must have occurred during the previous plateau of pCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A–E</xref>). For example, if scission occurred during the 10% pCO<sub>2</sub> cycle (low fluorescence) then after the next transition to 0% pCO<sub>2</sub>, and all subsequent transitions, the fluorescence would be closer to that of the 10% (low fluorescence state) than the 0% pCO<sub>2</sub> (high fluorescence) state. Conversely, if scission occurred during the 0% (high fluorescence), future 10% pCO<sub>2</sub> plateaus would be closer to the high fluorescence state. Occasionally traces appeared to be trapped in an intermediate pH state, which we attribute to scission occurring during the transition between pCO<sub>2</sub> states. Individual VLP traces were categorized into being trapped in a high, middle, or low pH state by comparing the Gag-pHLuorin signal before and after the VLP became insensitive to pCO<sub>2</sub> switching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Simultaneous VPS4A and CHMP4B imaging</title><p>Gag-mTagBFP, mEGFP-VPS4A and mCherry-CHMP4B were imaged with TIRF with sequential illumination of 594 nm (100 ms, 10–20 mW), 488 nm (100 ms, 4–10 mW) and 405 nm (100 ms, 2–4 mW; 120 mW LuxX diode laser, Omicron). mEGFP-VPS4A and mCherry-CHMP4B images were acquired every 5 s and Gag-TagBFP images were acquired every 60 s. VPS4A and CHMP4B relative appearance time were conducted using the same method as described previously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s4">Figure 1—figure supplement 4</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bleck et al., 2014</xref>). </p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>mEGFP-CHMP2A/B knockdown imaging</title><p>HeLa cell lines stably expressing either mEGFP-CHMP2A or mEGFP-CHMP2B and transfected with the respective siRNA (48 hr in advance) were imaged on an inverted microscope (IX-70, Olympus, Shinjuku, Japan) with epi-illumination via a Xenon lamp and transmitted bright-field illumination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Polarized excitation imaging</title><p>Images were collected on an inverted microscope (IX-81, Olympus) with a custom built through-the-objective (100X UAPON 1.49 NA, Olympus) polarized TIRF microscopy illuminator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Johnson et al., 2014</xref>). Throughout imaging the excitation TIR light was azimuthally scanned at 200 Hz with mirror galvanometers (Nutfield Technology, Hudson, NH) in order to reduce spatial illumination nonuniformities. A multiband polychroic (zt405/488/594/647rpc 2 mm substrate, Chroma) was positioned between the galvanometers and objective in order to isolate the excitation light from the emitted light. Light from a 488 nm laser (100 mW LuxX diode laser, Omicron, Rodgau-Dudenhofen, Germany) was modulated between being polarized perpendicular (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf66"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) or parallel (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf67"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>) to the glass surface by passing the light through an electro-optic modulator (EOM) (Conoptics, Danbury, CT) and quarter-wave plate prior to the galvanometer scan-head. The polarization generated by the EOM was modulated in sync with the galvanometers such that during scanning a <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf68"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf69"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> state was maintained at all azimuthal positions. The scanning polar angle was selected such that the excitation light was just beyond the TIR critical angle, minimizing <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf70"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> polarized light contaminating <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf71"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> excitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Johnson et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>A combined <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf72"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> ratio image was collected every 30 s. To generate this ratio image a sequential series of 10 <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf73"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf74"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> images were collected, divided (after subtracting camera offset), and then averaged. Each <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf75"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf76"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> image had an exposure of 5 ms (laser power between 25 and 50 mW), with a new image collected every 15 ms. Thus, in 30 ms, a single <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf77"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> image was generated, and then 10 of these images (over a 300 ms duration) were averaged (ImageJ) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Schneider et al., 2012</xref>) to create the combined ratio image. The short period was utilized in order to minimize artifacts in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf78"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> ratio image from VLP or cell movement. The galvonometers, EOM, camera shutter, and laser shutters were all driven/triggered by a multifunction data acquisition board (PCIe-6323, National Instruments) and controlled from custom written software in LabView (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Microscope-Control">https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Microscope-Control</ext-link>; copy archived at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/Microscope-Control">https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/Microscope-Control</ext-link>). Images were streamed from a CMOS camera (Flash-4.0, Hamamatsu, Hamamatsu City, Japan) to a workstation (T7500, Dell, Round Rock, TX) running image acquisition software (Metamorph). A single band emission filter (ET525/50 m, Chroma) was used to isolate fluorophore emission. In order to characterize the amount of Gag in an assembling VLP, an average <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf79"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> image was also generated at each time point.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Polarization analysis</title><p>Puncta were found in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf80"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> images which increased and then plateaued in amplitude. These puncta were then selected for orientation analysis with <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf81"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. A 2D Gaussian was fit to these assembling puncta to find a frame by frame subpixel peak location (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Puncta-Fit">https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Puncta-Fit</ext-link>; copy archived at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/Puncta-Fit">https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/Puncta-Fit</ext-link>). Using bilinear interpolation, the <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf82"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf83"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> images were resampled 10X in the horizontal and vertical directions (65 to 6.5 nm wide pixels). On these resampled images P/S and P+2S values were found by averaging the resampled pixel intensities that are within 100 nm of the peak fit locations (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Average-puncta-center">https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Average-puncta-center</ext-link>; copy archived at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/Average-puncta-center">https://github.com/elifesciences-publications/Average-puncta-center</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). For frames prior to the appearance of a puncta P/S and P+2S values were determined using the fit location of the first frame in which there was a puncta fit. For each tagged version of Gag, the average P/S value for background and assembled VLPs was calculated by finding an average P/S for each trace before assembly and after a plateau was reached, and then averaging across all traces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). A relative time to half growth for each VLP was determined by finding the halfway to assembly point (i.e. the point where the intensity is halfway between the intensity at assembly beginning and plateau) and then finding the normalized time at this point relative to the time assembly began and appeared to reach a plateau. This normalized time was between 0 and 1. A normalized time to halfway drop in P/S was also found (normalized to the same time scale) and these values were subtracted to find: <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf84"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (normalized). All fluorophore combinations were included in the P/S histogram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>) since all combinations had similar P/S characteristics.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank M Will and M A Lockard for assisting with plasmid preparations. We also thank M S Itano, M D Tomasini, K Bredbenner and P Bieniasz for discussion during manuscript preparation. This work was supported by NIH grants 1P50GM103297 and R01 GM11958 to SMS.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Software, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Project administration, Writing—review and editing, Designed experiments, Prepared samples, Collected and analyzed data</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing, Designed experiments, Prepared samples</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Project administration, Writing—review and editing, Designed experiments</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.022</object-id><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36221-transrepform-v2.pdf"/></supplementary-material><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data generated or analyzed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anantharam</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Onoa</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Holz</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelrod</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Localized topological changes of the plasma membrane upon exocytosis visualized by polarized TIRFM</article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>188</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200908010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20142424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babst</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Katzmann</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Estepa-Sabal</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meerloo</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002a</year><article-title>Escrt-III: an endosome-associated heterooligomeric protein complex required for mvb sorting</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1534-5807(02)00220-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12194857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babst</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Katzmann</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendland</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002b</year><article-title>Endosome-associated complex, ESCRT-II, recruits transport machinery for protein sorting at the multivesicular body</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1534-5807(02)00219-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12194858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumgärtel</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanchenko</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupont</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sergeev</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiseman</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kräusslich</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bräuchle</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Live-cell visualization of dynamics of HIV budding site interactions with an ESCRT component</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21394086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bendjennat</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saffarian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>The race against protease activation defines the role of ESCRTs in HIV budding</article-title><source>PLoS Pathogens</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e1005657</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1005657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27280284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bleck</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itano</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>North</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieniasz</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Temporal and spatial organization of ESCRT protein recruitment during HIV-1 budding</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>12211</fpage><lpage>12216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1321655111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25099357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briggs</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Riches</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartonova</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanetti</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kräusslich</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Structure and assembly of immature HIV</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>11090</fpage><lpage>11095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0903535106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19549863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlson</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Riches</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grünewald</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kräusslich</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Three-dimensional analysis of budding sites and released virus suggests a revised model for HIV-1 morphogenesis</article-title><source>Cell Host &amp; Microbe</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2008.10.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19064259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cashikar</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shim</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Maldazys</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Heuser</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>PI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Structure of cellular ESCRT-III spirals and their relationship to HIV budding</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e02184</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiaruttini</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Redondo-Morata</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Colom</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Humbert</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenz</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheuring</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Relaxation of loaded ESCRT-III spiral springs drives membrane deformation</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>163</volume><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.10.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26522593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobro</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Samson</surname> <given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>McCullough</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Electron cryotomography of ESCRT assemblies and dividing Sulfolobus cells suggests that spiraling filaments are involved in membrane scission</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>2319</fpage><lpage>2327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.e12-11-0785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23761076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabrikant</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lata</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Riches</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissenhorn</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozlov</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Computational model of membrane fission catalyzed by ESCRT-III</article-title><source>PLoS Computational Biology</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e1000575</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Heuser</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Plasma membrane deformation by circular arrays of ESCRT-III protein filaments</article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>180</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200707031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18209100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henne</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchkovich</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>The endosomal sorting complex ESCRT-II mediates the assembly and architecture of ESCRT-III helices</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>151</volume><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.08.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23063125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henne</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenmark</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of the membrane sculpting ESCRT pathway</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>a016766</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a016766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24003212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hulikova</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Swietach</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Rapid CO2 permeation across biological membranes: implications for CO2 venting from tissue</article-title><source>The FASEB Journal</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>2762</fpage><lpage>2774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.13-241752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24652949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurley</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>ESCRTs are everywhere</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>2398</fpage><lpage>2407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201592484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26311197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivanchenko</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Godinez</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kräusslich</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Eils</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohr</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bräuchle</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Dynamics of HIV-1 assembly and release</article-title><source>PLoS Pathogens</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e1000652</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19893629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo-Crow</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattheyses</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Polarization-controlled TIRFM with focal drift and spatial field intensity correction</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>1008</fpage><lpage>1019</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2013.12.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24606926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018a</year><data-title>Average-puncta-center</data-title><source>GitHub</source><version designator="C7ce5e4">C7ce5e4</version><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Average-puncta-center"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Average-puncta-center">https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Average-puncta-center</ext-link></ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018b</year><data-title>CO2-switch-analysis</data-title><source>GitHub</source><version designator="4b8d200">4b8d200</version><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/CO2-switch-analysis"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/CO2-switch-analysis">https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/CO2-switch-analysis</ext-link></ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018c</year><data-title>Microscope-Control</data-title><source>GitHub</source><version designator="7fff16d">7fff16d</version><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Microscope-Control"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Microscope-Control">https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Microscope-Control</ext-link></ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018d</year><data-title>Puncta-Fit</data-title><source>GitHub</source><version designator="E2750c2750">E2750c2750</version><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Puncta-Fit"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Puncta-Fit">https://github.com/SimonLab-RU/Puncta-Fit</ext-link></ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jouvenet</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieniasz</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Imaging the biogenesis of individual HIV-1 virions in live cells</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>454</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18500329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jouvenet</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieniasz</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Imaging the interaction of HIV-1 genomes and Gag during assembly of individual viral particles</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>19114</fpage><lpage>19119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0907364106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19861549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jouvenet</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhadina</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieniasz</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Dynamics of ESCRT protein recruitment during retroviral assembly</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21394083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katzmann</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Babst</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Ubiquitin-dependent sorting into the multivesicular body pathway requires the function of a conserved endosomal protein sorting complex, ESCRT-I</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)00434-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11511343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katzmann</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefan</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Babst</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Vps27 recruits ESCRT machinery to endosomes during MVB sorting</article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>162</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200302136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12900393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kooijman</surname> <given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gangoda</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gericke</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Ionization properties of phosphatidylinositol polyphosphates in mixed model membranes</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>9360</fpage><lpage>9371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi9008616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19725516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kotsopoulou</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsman</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsman</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitrophanous</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>A Rev-independent human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1)-based vector that exploits a codon-optimized HIV-1 gag-pol gene</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>4839</fpage><lpage>4852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.74.10.4839-4852.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10775623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozlovsky</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozlov</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Membrane fission: model for intermediate structures</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><volume>85</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(03)74457-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12829467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lata</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoehn</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pires</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Piehler</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottlinger</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissenhorn</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Helical structures of ESCRT-III are disassembled by VPS4</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>321</volume><fpage>1354</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1161070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18687924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kai</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Groves</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Negative membrane curvature catalyzes nucleation of endosomal sorting complex required for transport (ESCRT)-III assembly</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>15892</fpage><lpage>15897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1518765113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26668364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaksonen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Drubin</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Oster</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Endocytic vesicle scission by lipid phase boundary forces</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>10277</fpage><lpage>10282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0601045103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16801551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin-Serrano</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yarovoy</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Caballero</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieniasz</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaravoy</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Divergent retroviral late-budding domains recruit vacuolar protein sorting factors by using alternative adaptor proteins</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>12414</fpage><lpage>12419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2133846100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14519844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCullough</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clippinger</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Talledge</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Skowyra</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Naismith</surname> <given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Colf</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Afonine</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arthur</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundquist</surname> <given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Structure and membrane remodeling activity of ESCRT-III helical polymers</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>350</volume><fpage>1548</fpage><lpage>1551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aad8305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26634441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ip</surname> <given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Prestwood</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbink</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lever</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Evidence that the endosomal sorting complex required for transport-II (ESCRT-II) is required for efficient human immunodeficiency virus-1 (HIV-1) production</article-title><source>Retrovirology</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>72</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12977-015-0197-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26268989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miesenböck</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>De Angelis</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothman</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Visualizing secretion and synaptic transmission with pH-sensitive green fluorescent proteins</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>394</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/28190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9671304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morita</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Colf</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Karren</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandrin</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodesch</surname> <given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundquist</surname> <given-names>WI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Human ESCRT-III and VPS4 proteins are required for centrosome and spindle maintenance</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>12889</fpage><lpage>12894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1005938107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20616062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morita</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandrin</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>McCullough</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuyama</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baci Hamilton</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundquist</surname> <given-names>WI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>ESCRT-III protein requirements for HIV-1 budding</article-title><source>Cell Host &amp; Microbe</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2011.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21396898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muzioł</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pineda-Molina</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravelli</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamborlini</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Usami</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Göttlinger</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissenhorn</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Structural basis for budding by the ESCRT-III factor CHMP3</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>821</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2006.03.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obita</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saksena</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghazi-Tabatabai</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Perisic</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Structural basis for selective recognition of ESCRT-III by the AAA ATPase Vps4</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>449</volume><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17928861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ott</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Cellular proteins detected in HIV-1</article-title><source>Reviews in Medical Virology</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rmv.570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18265424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pédelacq</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabantous</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Terwilliger</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldo</surname> <given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Engineering and characterization of a superfolder green fluorescent protein</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16369541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saksena</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahlman</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Teis</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Functional reconstitution of ESCRT-III assembly and disassembly</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>136</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.11.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19135892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasband</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliceiri</surname> <given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schindler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Intracellular pH and the control of multidrug resistance</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>1128</fpage><lpage>1132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.3.1128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8302842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stuchell-Brereton</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Skalicky</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieffer</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Karren</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghaffarian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundquist</surname> <given-names>WI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>ESCRT-III recognition by VPS4 ATPases</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>449</volume><fpage>740</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17928862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sund</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelrod</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Cell membrane orientation visualized by polarized total internal reflection fluorescence</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>2266</fpage><lpage>2283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(99)77066-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10512845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Paridon</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Kruijff</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouwerkerk</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz</surname> <given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1986">1986</year><article-title>Polyphosphoinositides undergo charge neutralization in the physiological pH range: a 31P-NMR study</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - Lipids and Lipid Metabolism</source><volume>877</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0005-2760(86)90137-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3013316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wollert</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunder</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippincott-Schwartz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Membrane scission by the ESCRT-III complex</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>458</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19234443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodward</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Electron cryotomography studies of maturing HIV-1 particles reveal the assembly pathway of the viral core</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>1267</fpage><lpage>1277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02997-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25392219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Schooler</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieffer</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fillmore</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundquist</surname> <given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Electron cryotomography of immature HIV-1 virions reveals the structure of the CA and SP1 Gag shells</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>2218</fpage><lpage>2226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7601664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17396149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stjepanovic</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Vps4 disassembles an ESCRT-III filament by global unfolding and processive translocation</article-title><source>Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.3015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25938660</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.025</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>Stephen P</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Columbia University</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Timing of ESCRT-III protein recruitment and membrane scission during HIV-1 assembly&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by 3 peer reviewers, one of whom is a member of our Board of Reviewing Editors, and the evaluation has been overseen Wendy Garrett as the Senior Editor. The following individuals involved in review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Stuart Neil (Reviewer #2); Andrew Lever (Reviewer #3).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Our reviewers had several suggestions for improvement. We include here their reviews and some ranking of the importance of responses to their comments.</p><p>Editorial comments on the reviews below:</p><p>Re: Review #1:</p><p>No edits requested.</p><p>Reviewer #1</p><p>The mode of action of the ESCRT proteins in narrowing and pinching off a membranous neck has been a puzzle for many years. Using TIRF imaging of budding virus, this paper provides much new information about the process, mainly concerning the timing of the ESCRT presence at the buds. The data show the arrival of various components late in the game, and then (significantly) their departure right before closure. There is nice quantification of the ESCRTs. The strength of the paper is the detailed measurement of the timing. The findings explain such issues as the absence of the ESCRTs in the final virions and limit the models for the structures used for the narrowing. Various manipulations of the system reveal some parameters of the reaction. Basically, this is cutting-edge imaging that is pushed to give great kinetic and stoichiometric information about ESCRT functions. The paper represents a significant advance in the field.</p><p>Re: Comments on Review #2:</p><p>This review is strongly positive.</p><p>Adding some discussion of the number of waves of recruitment that are typically seen would be very helpful. Highly encouraged. The reviewer is surprised by the inefficiency of this system, so some comments on that might be warranted. Whether the need for multiple tries would be true of wild-type virus might be raised.</p><p>Looking at L-domain-negative mutants could be interesting, but the extent of L-domain-negative budding might be too low to measure, or too aberrant to evaluate. This is probably of lower priority. Could be addressed by discussion.</p><p>Including movies would be attractive indeed. We could imagine it may be difficult to provide ones that convey the data in a format that is helpful to readers, but <italic>eLife</italic> is good at this. Try to add these.</p><p>The carbonic anhydrase measurements would be helpful if data are in hand.</p><p>Reviewer #2:</p><p>Having previously established TIRF microscopy techniques to analyse the budding of HIV-1 virions in real time, and the coordination of the recruitment of ESCRT proteins, the Simon lab now further develop these studies to the recruitment and disappearance of individual ESCRT-III components and VPS4 in the context of the actual membrane scission event itself. To visualize the moment of scission by live imaging, the authors have adapted their CO<sub>2</sub>-mediated manipulation of cytoplasmic pH and pHluorinGFP-fused Gag by imaging assembly and Gag recruitment under conditions where CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations oscillate every 10s. Since the pHluorin in released virions becomes much less sensitive to these perturbations, this allows the authors to precisely define the moment of membrane scission in live cells – a really inventive solution to a key problem. By doing this, the authors show that ESCRT-III components and VPS4 are removed from the virion several seconds before the scission event, favouring a model whereby ESCRT-III constricts the neck of the virion to a point favourable to scission but must be removed by VPS4 to allow the reaction to take place rather than directly participating in it. If scission fails after their removal, subsequent rounds of ESCRT-III recruitment appear to occur to allow viral release. By varying the time of pH oscillation, the authors find that low cytoplasmic pH promotes scission. From this they suggest that protonation of phospholipid heads in the constricted neck may explain this, raising the possibility that it is proximity of the lipid heads that drive local destabilization resulting scission. Finally, using GFP variants embedded in Gag that only fluoresce under polarized excitation and therefore are restricted in an assembling particle, the authors model the membrane curvature of the budding virion, providing realtime evidence that Gag alone is the driving force of budding, and ESCRT-III recruitment occurs only when the spherical structure is formed.</p><p>Overall, this is a very interesting manuscript whose key strength is imaging of ESCRT function in relation to precise timing of scission in live cells using inventive and complex methodology. Despite this, the take home message is simple and important. I have some comments and queries below that the authors should consider addressing:</p><p>1) It is not clear from the manuscript how many waves of ESCRT-III recruitment happen for the average budding event. Do most scission events require only one? How many fail to progress to scission over the time frame despite multiple waves of ESCRT-III recruitment?</p><p>2) It is well established in artificial systems that Gag can induce membrane curvature, but the key novelty here is measuring it in real time in live cells. However, to definitively demonstrate ESCRT-independence, it would seem important to me to examine the membrane curvature of assembly of a Gag lacking the late domain in comparison – one should expect the same profile but subtle differences in timing might be interesting.</p><p>3) The authors should include representative videos of the events described.</p><p>4) Can the authors measure the relative concentration to carbonic anhydrase in purified virions vs the cytoplasm?</p><p>Re: Comments on Review #3:</p><p>This reviewer is also positive, with some suggested experiments. Some comments on his suggestions:</p><p>The issue of whether the readouts are revealing closure of the sphere, or pinching off of the membrane, is a real one, but it is not clear whether or not this can be fully determined experimentally (perhaps some aspects of this are known already?). At a minimum the issue should be directly discussed.</p><p>Looking at budding mutants (L-domain mutants again?) might be informative but might be hard to interpret, as noted above. It seems likely the authors have already looked at these, and if so, the issue can be addressed by discussion.</p><p>If there is a discrepancy with earlier work with respect to to CHMP4 recruitment, it should be addressed.</p><p>Comparing the effects on budding seen here, with effects on other host-mediated fusion effects (e.g. MVB fusion) would be helpful but might require setting up entire new assays. This would not seem absolutely required for acceptance.</p><p>The potential roles of Gag-Pol and viral RNA in the processes examined here are very interesting issues. I would include PR-mediated processing. But repeating all the work with and without these factors is a major effort, and it would probably be adequate to discuss the potential roles.</p><p>ESCRT-II is very likely involved and should be mentioned.</p><p>Reviewer #3:</p><p>The authors have used a number of interesting biophysical techniques to analyse the later stages of HIV budding and the temporal dynamics of recruitment of ESCRT-III components and membrane scission. Oscillating fluorescence of a pH dependent fluorophore was used to determine the point of membrane scission. I am curious to know whether they are actually measuring completion of the Gag sphere or actual membrane pinching off. In the original work of Gottlinger many of the particles that remained adherent to the cell appeared to have completed Gag sphere formation. Would it be useful to test out their oscillating pH system using such a budding mutant to determine whether they see slowing of oscillation caused by Capsid shell completion without particle release?</p><p>They previously showed ESCRT-III recruitment kinetics using a fluorophore based super resolution microscopy approach so some of the data here is more confirmatory rather than novel. The timing of CHMP4 recruitment and departure appears to be shorter than in their previously published work.</p><p>Acidification of the cytosol accelerates scission. My understanding is that the inner surface of the plasma membrane carries a generalized negative charge, so I am not sure how important the PIP<sub>2</sub> components are in affecting scission. PIP<sub>2</sub> acts as an important bridge binding the Matrix region of Gag to the inner plasma membrane but this occurs with all the Gag polyproteins from the first stages of assembly even before membrane bending and is not specific to those interactions involved at the budding neck. It would be of interest to see whether formation of vesicles triggered by ESCRT, such as in MVB formation, is similarly affected by pH changes to define how specific this is (or isn't) for virion budding and whether PIP<sub>2</sub> is of specific importance.</p><p>The demonstration of repeated recruitment and loss of VPS4A and CHMP4B is interesting and novel. It begs the question as to what is the critical trigger for scission as it would appear that although they are important for the process they themselves are necessary but not sufficient. A significant caveat is that the experiments as far as I can tell are performed with Gag alone and there is evidence that the Gag/Pol polyprotein may influence budding significantly with a suggestion that cargo size affects ESCRT function (Bendjennat et al., 2016). Similarly, there is no genomic RNA, and this may affect virion assembly. Either of these may be involved in effecting the scission pathway and might be part of the definitive trigger, which would render repeated VPS4A/CHMP4B recruitment unnecessary.</p><p>I note that nowhere is the role of ESCRT-II mentioned. There is now clear biochemical and EM evidence that it is involved in HIV budding (Meng et al., 2015).</p><p>The membrane bending experiments are elegant although I am not mathematical enough to give an opinion on the calculations although the results are highly plausible.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.026</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #2:</p><p>[…] Overall, this is a very interesting manuscript whose key strength is imaging of ESCRT function in relation to precise timing of scission in live cells using inventive and complex methodology. Despite this the take home message is simple and important. I have some comments and queries below that the authors should consider addressing:</p><p>1) It is not clear from the manuscript how many waves of ESCRT-III recruitment happen for the average budding event. Do most scission events require only one? How many fail to progress to scission over the time frame despite multiple waves of ESCRT-III recruitment?</p></disp-quote><p>A majority of our scission events occurred following the first recruitment of ESCRTs, but multiple rounds of ESCRT recruitment were also observed. In this work approximately 20% of our scission events consisted of more than one round of ESCRT recruitment. This is in rough agreement with our previous work in which we quantified the number of rounds of waves of recruitment (Jouvenet et al., 2011). In the previous work we did not simultaneously study scission, but in the current manuscript we demonstrate that scission only occurs following the last ESCRT recruitment. We have added a statement to the main text to clarify how often we observed multiple recruitment events. We rarely observed the recruitment of ESCRT-III without subsequent scission (~5%). However, we imaged cells for only a finite time and for those few events where we did not observe scission, we believe it occurred after we stopped imaging.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) It is well established in artificial systems that Gag can induce membrane curvature, but the key novelty here is measuring it in real time in live cells. However, to definitively demonstrate ESCRT-independence, it would seem important to me to examine the membrane curvature of assembly of a Gag lacking the late domain in comparison – one should expect the same profile but subtle differences in timing might be interesting.</p></disp-quote><p>To address this question, we have repeated the Gag assembly experiments with either the intact Gag or with a deletion of the late domain (p6) of Gag, which contains sites for ESCRT recruitment. These were imaged and quantified using the same polarization-based excitation technique to monitor the orientation of the fluorophore (new Figure 4A). By measuring relative emission of GFP when excited with an electric field parallel (S-polarized) or perpendicular (P-polarized) to the glass we observed a similar change in the emission ratio (P-polarized/S-polarized) in the native Gag and Gag deleted of p6. Like wild type Gag assembly, the Gag missing p6 also had an initial P/S ratio of ~2 which then dropped to ~1.4 during the early parts of VLP formation (example trace added to Figure 4A; and additional examples shown in a new figure, Figure 4—figure supplement 2). We attribute this change to the VLP assembling into a spherical shell throughout assembly.</p><p>These results demonstrate that eliminating the late domain and the recruitment of early acting ESCRTs (like TSG101 or ALIX), have no effect that can be detected on the timing or extent of membrane bending. Thus, they are not required for VLPs to form the spherical shell structure, consistent with previous electron microscopy results in which Gag missing the late domain still formed spherical shells (Martin-Serrano and Bieniasz, 2003).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) The authors should include representative videos of the events described.</p></disp-quote><p>We have now included representative movies for the following scenarios:</p><p>Video 1: Gag-pHluorin assembly (left) in whole cells with CO<sub>2</sub> switching every 10s along with simultaneous recruitment of mCherry-CHMP4B (right).</p><p>Video 2: Example of individual puncta of Gag-pHluorin assembly with CO<sub>2</sub> switching (left, every 10s) with simultaneous recruitment of mCherry-CHMP4B (right). CHMP4B was visible starting at 13:29 min.</p><p>Video 3: Gag-pHluorin assembly (top) in whole cells with CO<sub>2</sub> switching every 10s along with simultaneous imaging of mCherry-VPS4A recruitment (right).</p><p>Video 4: Example of individual puncta of Gag-pHluorin assembly with CO<sub>2</sub> switching (left, every 10s) with simultaneous recruitment of mCherry-VPS4A (right). VPS4A was visible starting at 20:49 min.</p><p>Video 5: Gag-pHluorin assembly (left) in whole cells with CO<sub>2</sub> switching every 120s along with simultaneous imaging of mCherry-VPS4A recruitment (right).</p><p>Video 6: Example of individual puncta of Gag-pHluorin assembly with CO<sub>2</sub> switching (left, every 120s) with simultaneous recruitment of mCherry-VPS4A (right). VPS4A was visible starting at 14:33 min.</p><p>Video 7: Gag-mEGFP assembly in whole cells with ratio image of perpendicular and parallel excitation (P/S) and total emission (P+2S).</p><p>Video 8: Example of individual puncta of Gag-mEGFP with P/S and P+2S images</p><p>We have added references and legends for these videos to the text.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) Can the authors measure the relative concentration to carbonic anhydrase in purified virions vs the cytoplasm?</p></disp-quote><p>This is a good question, which has previously been addressed. Mass spectrometry studies of purified virions of HIV-1 that have probed for cellular proteins could not detect the presence of carbonic anhydrase (Ott, 2008). This is consistent with our observation that in isolated VLPs, modulating the pCO<sub>2</sub> does not affect the pH in the VLPs. If there was significant carbonic anhydrase in isolated VLPs then CO<sub>2</sub> modulation would result in pH (and thus fluorescence) changes – which we don’t observe (this work and Jouvenet, 2008).</p><p>Thus, the change in pH reported by the Gag-pHluorin in the forming bud is not the consequence of carbonic anhydrase in the bud. It is the result of a diffusive pathway in the neck that is sufficient size to allow the transit of protons. After scission, the connecting pathway is lost and protons in the cell cannot enter the nascent VLP. We have expanded the text to clarify our hypothesis on carbonic anhydrase in the VLPs.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #3:</p><p>The authors have used a number of interesting biophysical techniques to analyse the later stages of HIV budding and the temporal dynamics of recruitment of ESCRT-III components and membrane scission. Oscillating fluorescence of a pH dependent fluorophore was used to determine the point of membrane scission. I am curious to know whether they are actually measuring completion of the Gag sphere or actual membrane pinching off. In the original work of Gottlinger many of the particles that remained adherent to the cell appeared to have completed Gag sphere formation. Would it be useful to test out their oscillating pH system using such a budding mutant to determine whether they see slowing of oscillation caused by Capsid shell completion without particle release?</p></disp-quote><p>As described above, we believe that we are measuring scission of the membrane as opposed to completion of the Gag shell. Electron microscopy studies (Briggs et al., 2009; Carlson et al., 2008; Woodward et al., 2015; Wright et al., 2007) show that the immature Gag lattice is generally incomplete with openings in the Gag lattice at the junction with the mother cell, thus continued movement of protons back and forth. The rapid transition to a state where protons cannot move between the mother and bud indicates a loss of continuity thus scission. Based on our results carbonic anhydrase is not in the nascent VLP. Additionally, mass spectrometry of nascent virions looking at cellular proteins did not detect carbonic anhydrase in the virions (Ott, 2008). Thus, any CO<sub>2</sub> that passes the membrane of the VLP can only be very slowly converted to bicarbonate and protons. We have previously demonstrated that with a late domain mutant, the Gag inside the nascent virion remains sensitive to the cytosolic pH (Jouvenet, 2008, Figure 3F).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>They previously showed ESCRT-III recruitment kinetics using a fluorophore based super resolution microscopy approach so some of the data here is more confirmatory rather than novel. The timing of CHMP4 recruitment and departure appears to be shorter than in their previously published work.</p></disp-quote><p>First, one of the key novelties in this work is imaging the recruitment kinetics of ESCRT-III simultaneously with membrane bending or simultaneously with scission. This has not been done before by us, or anyone else.</p><p>Second, there is a difference in relative timing between recruitment of CHMP4B and VPS4A, but it is a difference not between previous work and this work, but a subtle difference that varies with the cell type. In both this work, which mainly examined HEK293T cells, and in our previous work on HeLa cells (Bleck et al., 2014), we monitored the time course of recruitment of CHMP4B simultaneously with recruitment of VPS4A. In both cell types, after ESCRT-III appeared (see red tracing in Figure 3 of the current manuscript), we detected VPS4A (see the green tracing). The ESCRT-III fluorescence increased, with the VPS4A following. The CHMP4B reached a maximum shortly before VPS4A, and then they both decreased.</p><p>In the HEK293T cells we observed that the lag to VPS4A reached its ½ max 5.1 seconds after CHMP4B and in the HeLa cells the lag was 9 seconds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="respfig1">Author response image 1</xref> and Figure 1E from our previous paper, Bleck et al., 2014). From re-examining the histograms we are uncertain what, if any, the significance is of that delay. For this work we performed the majority of measurements in HEK293T cells because scission was observed to occur much more frequently, allowing us to study many more events. The difference in the lag between the HeLa and HEK293T is consistent between our previous work and this work (here we examined both). However, we did not examine the difference in the lag closely and therefore we are reticent to make any statements about its biochemical significance. For this publication we focused on the relative timing of the ESCRTs and VPS4 to the scission – where there is a much greater and consistent difference.</p><fig id="respfig1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36221.023</object-id><label>Author response image 1.</label><caption><title>Measurement of the lag in the rise to ½ max between CHMPB and VPS4A in HEK293T cells.</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="png" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36221-resp-fig1-v2"/></fig><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Acidification of the cytosol accelerates scission. My understanding is that the inner surface of the plasma membrane carries a generalized negative charge, so I am not sure how important the PIP<sub>2</sub> components are in affecting scission. PIP<sub>2</sub> acts as an important bridge binding the Matrix region of Gag to the inner plasma membrane but this occurs with all the Gag polyproteins from the first stages of assembly even before membrane bending and is not specific to those interactions involved at the budding neck. It would be of interest to see whether formation of vesicles triggered by ESCRT, such as in MVB formation, is similarly affected by pH changes to define how specific this is (or isn't) for virion budding and whether PIP<sub>2</sub> is of specific importance.</p></disp-quote><p>Thank you for the emphasizing the presence of PIP<sub>2</sub> throughout the Gag bud, and pointing out that PIP<sub>2</sub> might not be a critical lipid for the scission. Based on the pHluorin fluorescence change we observed when switching between 0% and 10% CO<sub>2</sub> we believe the cytosolic pH is modulated between ~7.5 and ~6.5. Phosphatidic acid (PA), phosphatidylethanolamine (PE), phosphatidylcholine (PC), phosphatidylglycerol (PG), and phosphatidylserine (PS) all have pK<sub>a</sub> values that are away from this range. The two phosphates on the inositol of PIP<sub>2</sub> have a pK<sub>a</sub> of 6.5 and 7.7, which are in the range of sensitivity of our measurements and therefore we highlighted the possibility of this lipid being sensitive to charge change in the pH range for our experiments. However, we acknowledge that this is just one possible component that is sensitive to charge modulation in this pH range, and we have modified the discussion to more clearly state this possibility.</p><p>MVB formation would be an excellent system to also study membrane scission and although outside the scope of this work, we hope our research will provide inspiration for a similar study. In particular, due to differences in lipid composition in MVBs, it would be interesting to determine how scission in MVBs are sensitive to pH.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>The demonstration of repeated recruitment and loss of VPS4A and CHMP4B is interesting and novel. It begs the question as to what is the critical trigger for scission as it would appear that although they are important for the process they themselves are necessary but not sufficient. A significant caveat is that the experiments as far as I can tell are performed with Gag alone and there is evidence that the Gag/Pol polyprotein may influence budding significantly with a suggestion that cargo size affects ESCRT function (Bendjennat et al., 2016). Similarly, there is no genomic RNA and this may affect virion assembly. Either of these may be involved in effecting the scission pathway and might be part of the definitive trigger, which would render repeated VPS4A/CHMP4B recruitment unnecessary.</p></disp-quote><p>We have previously observed the repeated recruitment and loss of VPS4A and ESCRT components (Jouvenet et al., 2011). We had struggled with the meaning of this until this current work. The results now demonstrate that the durations of ESCRT recruitment and loss are fairly stereotypic in duration. At the end of each round, there is either scission, or not. If there is scission, there are no further rounds of ESCRT recruitment. If there is not scission, then there is another round. We think that the ESCRTs are pulling the neck just an extra bit closer to facilitate scission, but then have to move out of the way. This is repeated until scission occurs. This suggests that it may be possible for scission to occur even in the absence of ESCRTs, albeit at a reduced rate. Thus, we don’t believe there is a definitive trigger for ESCRT-III recruitment. Instead, we hypothesize that the presence of the late domains helps to initiate recruitment of ESCRT-IIIs in a probabilistic fashion and may also be governed by the current neck structure. This is supported by Bendjennat and Saffarian (2016) which showed that the absence of the late domain (deletion of PTAP) delayed particle release by 10 hours but did not prevent viral particle release. Thus, without the late domains, scission events might still be observed, though would be rarer. We have updated the text to include information that scission may occur in the absence of late domain. However, when we previously monitored for scission in the presence of a late domain mutant (Jouvenet et al., 2008), we did not see scission during the 30-60 minute imaging periods we used.</p><p>We have previously examined if this assembly is affected by whether Gag or Gag and Gag-Pol was recruited, and at the level of the single virion, the assembly kinetics were the same for Gag alone and for the provirus Gag/Gag-Pol (Jouvenet et al., 2008). We also could not distinguish any differences in assembly rate in the presence of the HIV-1 genome (Jouvenet et al., 2009). The referee points out that in ensemble measurements larger cargo sizes appear to slow down rate of viral particle release (Bendjennat and Saffarian, 2016). We think that this may be an indirect effect seen at the macroscopic level not seen at the level of single virions. Larger cargos take longer to synthesize and slow the overall rate of synthesis in the cell. We have previously demonstrated that rate of viral assembly is very sensitive to concentration of Gag. Gag-Pol takes longer to synthesize than just Gag and thus, it would take longer to get to a critical concentration to initiate assembly and longer to assemble.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>I note that nowhere is the role of ESCRT-II mentioned. There is now clear biochemical and EM evidence that it is involved in HIV budding (Meng et al., 2015).</p></disp-quote><p>Just as viral particle release rate may depend on presence of ESCRT-I/TSG101 and particle size (Bendjennat and Saffarian, 2016), the presence of ESCRT-II, which works in concert with ESCRT-I, is also expected to affect the rate of viral particle release (Meng et al., 2015) which we have now added to the manuscript.</p></body></sub-article></article>