<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">eLife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20640</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cell Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genes and Chromosomes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Modularity and determinants of a (bi-)polarization control system from free-living and obligate intracellular bacteria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-19193"><name><surname>Bergé</surname><given-names>Matthieu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="data-ro1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-66595"><name><surname>Campagne</surname><given-names>Sébastien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-61664"><name><surname>Mignolet</surname><given-names>Johann</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3721-4307</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-61665"><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>Seamus</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7169-907X</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa2">‡</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-15024"><name><surname>Théraulaz</surname><given-names>Laurence</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-61667"><name><surname>Manley</surname><given-names>Suliana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-57977"><name><surname>Allain</surname><given-names>Frédéric H-T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-7149"><name><surname>Viollier</surname><given-names>Patrick H</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5249-9910</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="data-ro1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department Microbiology and Molecular Medicine, Institute of Genetics and Genomics in Geneva, Faculty of Medicine</institution>, <institution>University of Geneva</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Geneva</named-content></addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Institute of Molecular Biology and Biophysics</institution>, <institution>Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule Zürich</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Zürich</named-content></addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Laboratory of Experimental Biophysics</institution>, <institution>École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Lausanne</named-content></addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Veening</surname><given-names>Jan Willem</given-names></name><aff id="aff4"><institution>University of Groningen</institution>, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><email>patrick.viollier@unige.ch</email></corresp><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa1"><label>†</label><p>Biochemistry and Molecular Genetics of Bacteria (BGMB), Institutdes Sciences de la Vie, Université Catholique de Louvain, Louvain-la-Neuve, Belgium</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa2"><label>‡</label><p>Centre for Bacterial Cell Biology, Newcastle University, Newcastle, United Kingdom</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e20640</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>08</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016, Bergé et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bergé et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-20640-v1.pdf"/><related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="ra1" related-article-type="article-reference" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.18647"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.001</object-id><p>Although free-living and obligate intracellular bacteria are both polarized it is unclear whether the underlying polarization mechanisms and effector proteins are conserved. Here we dissect at the cytological, functional and structural level a conserved polarization module from the free living α-proteobacterium <italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic> and an orthologous system from an obligate intracellular (rickettsial) pathogen. The NMR solution structure of the zinc-finger (ZnR) domain from the bifunctional and bipolar ZitP pilus assembly/motility regulator revealed conserved interaction determinants for PopZ, a bipolar matrix protein that anchors the ParB centromere-binding protein and other regulatory factors at the poles. We show that ZitP regulates cytokinesis and the localization of ParB and PopZ, targeting PopZ independently of the previously known binding sites for its client proteins. Through heterologous localization assays with rickettsial ZitP and PopZ orthologs, we document the shared ancestries, activities and structural determinants of a (bi-)polarization system encoded in free-living and obligate intracellular α-proteobacteria.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.001">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.001</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Author Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Rickettsia massiliae</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic></kwd><kwd>polarity</kwd><kwd>PopZ</kwd><kwd>ZitP</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research Organism</title><kwd><italic>E. coli</italic></kwd><kwd>Other</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="par-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001711</institution-id><institution>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds zur Förderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31003A_162716</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Viollier</surname><given-names>Patrick H</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>elife-xml-version</meta-name><meta-value>2.5</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Common ancestries, activities and structural determinants of a modular (bi-)polarization control system encoded in free-living and obligate intracellular α-proteobacteria, including the rickettsial pathogens, are described.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Polarity is an ancient trait underlying developmental patterning and morphogenesis in eukaryotes and bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Martin and Arkowitz, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Shapiro et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">St Johnston and Ahringer, 2010</xref>). Cell pole-organizing proteins arose more than once during bacterial evolution as indicated by the fact that distinct polarization mechanisms exist in different bacterial phyla (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Davis and Waldor, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kirkpatrick and Viollier, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Strahl and Hamoen, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Treuner-Lange and Søgaard-Andersen, 2014</xref>). The Gram-negative α-proteobacterial lineage encompasses polarized free-living (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Davis and Waldor, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Haglund et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Hallez et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kirkpatrick and Viollier, 2011</xref>) and obligate intracellular bacteria including the mitochondrial ancestors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Andersson et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Haglund et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>The fresh-water bacterium <italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic> is a model system for the genetic analysis of α-proteobacterial cell polarity because polar differentiation is tightly coordinated with cell cycle progression and because of the availability of a myriad of genetic tools to study this species compared to the obligate intracellular (rickettsial) pathogens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Curtis and Brun, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ely, 1991</xref>). The <italic>C. crescentus</italic> predivisional cell features the flagellum and a pilus biosynthesis machine at the new pole and a stalk, a cylindrical extension of the cell envelope, at the old pole. Upon completion of cell division, the replicative stalked (ST) cell progeny begins chromosome replication and an asymmetric cell division cycle. By contrast, the motile and piliated swarmer (SW) cell progeny resides temporarily in a non-replicative (G1-like) state. At the SW to ST cell transition, the flagellated and piliated (SW) pole is remodeled into a ST pole and the developing cell acquires DNA replication competence. Replication of the circular chromosome proceeds bi-directionally from the single origin of replication (<italic>Cori</italic>) located at the nascent ST pole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Curtis and Brun, 2010</xref>). Once duplicated, the <italic>Cori</italic> region is rapidly segregated towards the nascent SW pole by the ParAB chromosome segregation system that targets the <italic>parS</italic> centromeric sequence located <italic>circa</italic> 8 kbp from <italic>Cori</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mohl and Gober, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Viollier et al., 2004</xref>). The <italic>cis</italic>-encoded ParB protein binds <italic>parS</italic> and the resulting ParB•<italic>parS</italic> complex is guided pole-ward by the ParA ATPase, likely reinforced by poorly understood biophysical constraints and properties of the chromosome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lim et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mohl and Gober, 1997</xref>). The PopZ polar organizing protein is thought to assemble a porous homo-polymeric matrix at the cell poles that captures the segregated ParB•<italic>parS</italic> complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>) via a direct interaction with ParAB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ebersbach et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Holmes et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.002</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>The Zinc finger (ZnR) of ZitP and orthologs is a polar localization signal.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematics of PopZ and ParB localization and chromosome organization during the <italic>C. crescentus</italic> cell cycle. Each cell cycle yields two different daughter cells: a swarmer (SW) and a stalked (ST) cell residing in G1- and S-phase, respectively. The replication origin region (red, including the centromeric sequence eight kbp from the origin) and the terminus region (yellow) are shown. (<bold>B</bold>) Schematic of the domain organization in ZitP: the N-terminal zinc-finger domain (ZnR), the transmembrane domain (TM) and the C-terminal <underline>d</underline>omain-of-<underline>u</underline>nknown <underline>f</underline>unction (DUF3426). The green arrowhead points to the codon in the <italic>zitP</italic> coding sequence harboring the GFP insertion in the <italic>zitP</italic>::<italic>Tn5-GFP</italic> strain. All regions are drawn to scale. Numbers indicate residues. (<bold>C</bold>) Alignment of the ZnR from α-proteobacterial ZitP orthologs (in red) and one δ-proteobacterium (in blue) (accession nos.: YP_002517671 [Cc, <italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic>], ADU14901 [Ae, <italic>Asticcacaulis excentricus</italic>], ABI66665 [Mm, <italic>Maricaulis maris</italic>], ADG11315 [Cs, <italic>Caulobacter segnis</italic>], WP_003168465 [Bd, <italic>Brevundimonas diminuta</italic>], WP_014365322 [Rm, <italic>Rickettsia massiliae</italic>], WP_011909408 [Rs, <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>] and ABF87224 [Mx, <italic>Myxococcus xanthus</italic>]). The four cysteine residues coordinating the zinc ion are highlighted (blue arrowheads). Asterisks indicate the conserved residues promoting ZitP•PopZ complex formation. (<bold>D</bold>) Overlays of fluorescence and phase contrast images showing the subcellular localization of ZitP<italic><sup>Tn-GFP</sup></italic> encoded by the <italic>zitP</italic>::Tn<italic>5</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> allele in <italic>WT</italic> or Δ<italic>popZ C. crescentus</italic> cells (top). The graphs below show the quantitation of the localization from above. The left graph indicates the distribution of foci along the longitudinal axis. Focus (n = 1048) position is given in relative coordinates from 0 (pole) to 0.5 (midcell). P, pole; M, midcell. The right graph shows the percentage of cells containing at least one focus of ZitP<italic><sup>Tn-GFP</sup></italic> in <italic>WT</italic> (n = 1048) or in Δ<italic>popZ</italic> cells (n = 426). (<bold>E</bold>) Overlay images as in D showing the subcellular localization of the first 90 residues of ZitP from <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (Cc) and orthologs from <italic>A. excentricus</italic> (Ae), <italic>M. maris</italic> (Mm), <italic>C. segnis</italic> (Cs) in <italic>C. crescentus WT</italic> (upper panels) or Δ<italic>popZ</italic> (bottom panels) cells. Strains expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-90</sup> from the chromosomal <italic>xylX</italic> locus were induced with xylose for 4 hr before imaging (phase contrast and Dendra2-fluorescence). (<bold>F</bold>) Overlay images as in D showing the subcellular localization of the ZnR of ZitP (Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup>) of <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (Cc) and orthologs from <italic>B. diminuta</italic> (Bd) in <italic>WT</italic> (upper panels) or Δ<italic>popZ</italic> (bottom panels) <italic>C. crescentus</italic> cells. Strains expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> from the chromosomal <italic>xylX</italic> locus were induced with xylose for 4 hr before imaging (phase contrast and Dendra2- fluorescence). (<bold>G</bold>) Time-lapse imaging of swarmer cells from Δ<italic>zitP</italic> cells expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> from the chromosomal <italic>xylX</italic> locus after induction for 1 hr with 0.3% xylose. Cells were then synchronized and transferred onto an agarose pad containing 0.3% xylose (t = 0 min), and visualized at 40 min intervals (time in minutes is indicated in the images) by phase contrast and Dendra2-fluorescence microscopy, respectively. Shown above the overlays are the schematics representing ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> localization during the <italic>C. crescentus</italic> cell cycle. (<bold>H</bold>) Images of Δ<italic>zitP</italic> cells expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> from the chromosomal <italic>xylX</italic> locus and mCherry-PopZ from the native chromosomal <italic>popZ</italic> locus. Fluorescence and phase contrast images were acquired after 4 hr of induction with 0.3% xylose. Cells expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> (left panel, green) and mCherry-PopZ (middle panel, red) are shown. Co-localized red and green foci appear yellow in the overlay (right panel).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.002">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.002</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.003</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Conservation of ZitP and PopZ.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Distribution of PopZ-, ZitP-, ZnR- and DUF3426-encoding sequences in various α-proteobacterial orders. A 5000-residue long concatamer of universal proteins used to create the phylogeny based on the Neighbor-Joining method with a Dayhoff evolutionary model and 100 bootstrap replicates by Brilli et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brilli et al., 2010</xref>) was modified. Blue and white boxes indicate the presence or absence of orthologs as identified by bi-directional BLASTP searches. (<bold>B</bold>) AgmX from <italic>M. xanthus</italic> is not polarly localized in <italic>C. crescentus</italic>. Subcellular localization of the AgmX ZnR (encoded in the δ-proteobacterium <italic>M. xanthus</italic>) expressed form the <italic>xylX</italic> locus in <italic>WT C. crescentus</italic> cells. Dendra2-fluorescence (left panels) and overlay between phase and Dendra2-fluorescence and phase channel (right panels) are shown. Synthesis of the Dendra2-AgmX<sup>1-90</sup> was induced for 4 hr with 0.3% xylose before imaging. (<bold>C</bold>) Immunoblots showing the abundance of the Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> in WT or Δ<italic>popZ C. crescentus</italic> cells. Expression of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> integrated at the chromosomal <italic>xylX</italic> locus was induced during 4 hr by the addition of 0.3% xylose. The abundance of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> in <italic>WT</italic> or Δ<italic>popZ</italic> cells was monitored using antibodies to Dendra2 (top) or MreB (bottom) as a loading control. A strain that does not express Dendra2 was used as a negative control (empty).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.003">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.003</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig1-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>The polar localization of PopZ is cell cycle-regulated: in newborn cells PopZ is localized to the old cell pole, whereas the newborn pole initially lacks a PopZ cluster (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ebersbach et al., 2008</xref>). During S-phase, PopZ adopts a bipolar disposition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>) coincident with ParB•<italic>parS</italic> segregation to facilitate its capture at the opposite pole. Formation of the second polar PopZ cluster may depend on the ParA ATPase and the TipN landmark protein, a coiled-coil protein that interacts with ParA and that marks the new pole as flagellar assembly site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Huitema et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lam et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Ptacin et al., 2010</xref>). Although ParAB are essential for viability in <italic>C. crescentus</italic>, TipN or PopZ are individually dispensable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ebersbach et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Huitema et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lam et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mohl and Gober, 1997</xref>), but joint inactivation of both genes arrests growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Schofield et al., 2010</xref>). As most α-proteobacterial genomes encode PopZ and ParAB, but not TipN, TipN-independent control mechanism(s) for PopZ polarization should exist in α-proteobacteria.</p><p>In the Rhizobiales order of the α-proteobacteria, PopZ does not appear to fasten ParB at the cell poles as polar PopZ does not co-localize with ParB: while PopZ is monopolar, ParB localizes in a bipolar fashion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Deghelt et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Grangeon et al., 2015</xref>). Thus, compared to the bipolar co-localization of PopZ and ParB observed in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ebersbach et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>), PopZ seems to have undergone functional specialization in the Rhizobiales, presumably interacting with other (unknown) client proteins. The genomes of the obligate intracellular (rickettsial) lineage also encode PopZ and ParAB orthologs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Andersson et al., 1998</xref>), but not several other known client proteins of <italic>C. crescentus</italic> PopZ that depend on a short N-terminal stretch in PopZ to interact with it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bowman et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Holmes et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Here, we unearth a reciprocal, physical and conserved interaction between PopZ and the cytoplasmic N-terminal zinc-finger domain (ZnR) from ZitP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hughes et al., 2010</xref>), a bifunctional and bipolar membrane protein whose C-terminal DUF3426 domain is required for polar pilus biogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mignolet et al., 2016</xref>)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Christen et al., 2016</xref>), but dispensable for motility. We locate the structural determinants governing PopZ•ZitP complex formation and we show that this interaction is required to control cytokinesis and centromere positioning from the membrane. The PopZ•ZitP interaction differs for previously described interactions between PopZ and client proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Holmes et al., 2016</xref>) in that it does not require the aforementioned PopZ N-terminal segment. We show that ZitP induces PopZ bipolarity in the heterologous host <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and we reconstitute a bipolar ZitP•PopZ•ParB tripartite complex in this system. Examining rickettsial PopZ and ZitP orthologs, we find that the PopZ•ZitP complex is modular and that the structure-function relationship is maintained in the obligate intracellular lineage.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>PopZ-dependent localization of the ZitP zinc-finger domain (ZnR) of α-proteobacteria</title><p>We previously isolated a <italic>C. crescentus</italic> strain bearing a Tn5-<italic>GFP</italic> insertion in the 5’-proximal third of the poorly characterized and conserved <italic>CC_2215</italic>/<italic>CCNA_02298</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>, dubbed <italic>zitP</italic>, <underline>zi</underline>nc-finger <underline>t</underline>argeting <underline>P</underline>opZ, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B–D</xref>). The resulting strain expresses a bipolarly localized and truncated ZitP-GFP fusion protein and is viable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hughes et al., 2010</xref>). Consistent with this result, genome-wide transposon insertion sequencing (Tn-Seq) revealed that ZitP is not essential for viability, but required for pilus biogenesis and motility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Christen et al., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hughes et al., 2010</xref>)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mignolet et al., 2016</xref>). The predicted ZitP protein harbors an N-terminal zinc-finger domain (zinc_ribbon_5 or PF13719 superfamily, residues 1–37, henceforth ZnR, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B–C</xref>) and a trans-membrane segment (TM, residues 106–127) preceding the C-terminal DUF3426 (residues 128–245). While the DUF3426 is required for polar pilus biogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mignolet et al., 2016</xref>), it is not required for motility or to direct ZitP to the cell poles since in polar ZitP<italic><sup>Tn-GFP</sup></italic> the GFP moiety is fused in-frame to codon 49 of ZitP (green triangle in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>).</p><p>Quantitative live-cell fluorescence imaging of ZitP<italic><sup>Tn-GFP</sup></italic> in <italic>zitP</italic>::Tn<italic>5</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> cells (n = 1048) revealed monopolar fluorescent foci in non-constricted cells, while bipolar foci are present in constricted cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>), suggesting that the ZnR and/or adjacent residues are necessary and sufficient for ZitP polarization and that bipolarization is cell cycle-regulated. We engineered strains expressing a Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-90)</sup> fusion protein (an N-terminal translational fusion of the Dendra2 fluorescent protein to only the cytoplasmic part of ZitP) from the xylose-inducible promoter (P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>) at the <italic>xylX</italic> locus in the wild-type (<italic>WT</italic>, NA1000) or Δ<italic>zitP</italic> background and found an identical localization pattern as for the ZitP<italic><sup>Tn-GFP</sup></italic> strain, indicating that residues 1–90 carry the necessary information for polar localization of ZitP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>). To test if polarization is also a feature of ZitP from other α-proteobacteria, we expressed orthologous Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-90)</sup> variants in <italic>WT</italic> or Δ<italic>zitP C. crescentus</italic> cells and observed an identical localization pattern of these fusion proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>). By contrast, the zinc-finger domain from the unrelated AgmX protein encoded in the δ-proteobacterium <italic>Myxococcus xanthus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Nan et al., 2010</xref>) is not polar in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>), indicating that the zinc-finger domain of AgmX diverged.</p><p>Next, we asked if the highly conserved 43 residues encompassing the <italic>C. crescentus</italic> ZitP ZnR domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>) suffice to direct Dendra2 to the cell poles. Expression of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> from <italic>xylX</italic> in <italic>C. crescentus WT</italic> or Δ<italic>zitP</italic> cells indeed gave rise to cell cycle-dependent bipolar fluorescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1G</xref>): while Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> is initially monopolar in G1-phase cells, it switches to a bipolar disposition during S-phase, 60 min after the release of G1 cells into fresh medium. Since this cell cycle localization pattern of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> closely resembles that of the polar matrix protein PopZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ebersbach et al., 2008</xref>), we co-expressed Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> and mCherry-PopZ in Δ<italic>zitP</italic> (<italic>xylX::dendra-zitP</italic><sup>1-43</sup><italic>popZ::mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ)</italic> cells and found that mCherry-PopZ co-localizes with Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1H</xref>). Importantly, ZitP<italic><sup>Tn-GFP</sup></italic>, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-90)</sup> and Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> are all delocalized (diffuse) in Δ<italic>popZ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D, E and F</xref>) and immunoblotting revealed that the abundance of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> is not significantly affected by the Δ<italic>popZ</italic> mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1C</xref>).</p><p>Knowing that polar localization of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> depends on PopZ, we then tested if Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> is sequestered into the large monopolar PopZ patch (‘plug’) that forms when PopZ is overexpressed in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ebersbach et al., 2008</xref>). This PopZ ‘plug’ seems to exclude cytoplasmic macromolecular structures as ribosomes and genomic DNA from the cell poles, while capturing PopZ-interacting proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bowman et al., 2010</xref>). We observed Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> and full length Dendra2-ZitP to adopt a monopolar ‘plug’-like disposition when PopZ is overexpressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A</xref>), suggesting that Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> is indeed recruited to PopZ ‘plugs’.<fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.004</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>The ZnR of ZitP directly interacts with PopZ.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Images showing the localization of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> in Δ<italic>zitP</italic> cells harbouring the empty vector (upper panel) or a plasmid to overproduce PopZ under control of the vanillate-inducible P<italic><sub>van</sub></italic> promoter (lower panel). Images were taken before (- van) or after PopZ overexpression was induced by the addition of 0.5 mM vanillate for 5 hr (+ van). (<bold>B</bold>) Images of <italic>E. coli</italic> TB28 cells co-expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> from <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (Cc), <italic>B. diminuta</italic> (Bd) or <italic>M. maris</italic> (Mm) and mCherry-PopZ. The Dendra2-fluorescence (green channel, right), the mCherry-fluorescence (red, middle) or the combined fluorescence (yellow) channels are shown as overlays with phase contrast images. Cells were grown in LB media for 2 hr, then Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants were induced with 1 mM IPTG and mCherry-PopZ was induced with 0.2% L-arabinose for 2 hr. (<bold>C</bold>) Isothermal titration calorimetry experiments (upper) measuring changes upon injection of 4 μL of a 300 μM PopZ solution into a 15 μM solution of ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> (left panel) or ZitP<sup>1-43W35I</sup> (right panel). (Lower) Plot showing the integrated heat changes following each injection as a function of the molar ratio of PopZ to ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> (left panel) or ZitP<sup>1-43W35I</sup> (right panel). (<bold>D</bold>) Stereo view of the NMR solution structure of ZitP<sup>1-43</sup>. The secondary structure elements, the cysteine residues coordinating the zinc ion and W35 are indicated. (<bold>E</bold>) Electrostatic surface potential representation of ZitP<sup>1-43</sup>. Several residues in the basic patch are labelled. (<bold>F</bold>) Overlay of the 2D <sup>1</sup>H-<sup>15</sup>N TROSY HSQC spectra of ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> (black spectrum) or ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> in complex with PopZ (red spectrum). Black arrows indicate spectroscopic shifts/appearance of new species.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.004">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.004</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.005</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Purification of ZitP and PopZ.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Overlays of Dendra2-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>C. crescentus</italic> cells expressing Dendra2-ZitP from the <italic>xylX</italic> locus without PopZ overproduction (-van, top panel) or with PopZ overproduction (+van. lower). To achieve PopZ expression, cells were induced with in 0.5 mM vanillate for 5 hr prior to imaging. (<bold>B</bold>) Chromatograms of the size exclusion chromatography (SEC) experiments performed on superdex S75 in the NMR buffer with purified His<sub>6</sub>-tagged PopZ alone or incubated with one molar equivalent ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> shown in blue and orange respectively. PopZ alone elutes already as a high molecular weight oligomer. Using these experiments, we found that ZitP co-purifies with PopZ in agreement with the NMR data and the ITC data. (<bold>C</bold>) SDS-PAGE analysis of the PopZ elution peak. Numbers indicate the molecular masses in kDa. (<bold>D</bold>) SDS-PAGE analysis of the PopZ-ZitP elution peak. Numbers indicate the molecular masses in kDa. (<bold>E</bold>) 2D 1 H-15N HSQC spectrum of ZitP<sup>1-43</sup>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.005">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.005</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig2-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>To test whether PopZ is sufficient to recruit Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup>, we expressed both proteins in the γ-proteobacterium <italic>E. coli</italic> and observed that Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> indeed co-localizes with mCherry-PopZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). By contrast, in the absence of PopZ, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> remains diffuse (cytoplasmic, see below) in this heterologous host. All orthologous Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> variants tested share this pattern (with the exception of the <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> variant, see below), co-localizing with <italic>C. crescentus</italic> mCherry-PopZ in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Thus, PopZ recruits the (predicted) ZitP ZnR and this property is conserved in most ZitP orthologs.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>NMR structure of ZitP ZnR and determinants for PopZ binding</title><p>To determine if <italic>C. crescentus</italic> ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> and PopZ interact directly, we separately purified soluble ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> and PopZ with a C-teminal-hexa-histidine (His<sub>6</sub>)-tag from an <italic>E. coli</italic> overexpression system. In size exclusion chromatography (SEC), PopZ elutes with an apparent molecular mass of oligomers (~200 kDa), while ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> elutes as a monomer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B–D</xref>). ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> and PopZ can be co-purified by SEC and the resulting ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup>•PopZ complex has a high apparent molecular mass, suggesting that ZitP binds oligomeric PopZ. Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) estimated the dissociation constant (K<sub>D</sub>) between ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> and PopZ at 700 nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>), confirming the specific interaction between both proteins in vitro.</p><p>To identify determinants within ZitP that are required for the interaction with PopZ, we first resolved the NMR solution structure of ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> by following a classical nuclear Overhauser effect (NOE)-based approach (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1-data">Supplementary file 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1E</xref>, see Materials and methods). The resonance assignment revealed that cysteine residues C5, C8, C28 and C31 are reduced and harbor typical Cβ chemical shifts of a zinc ion coordination module comprised between 31.58 ppm and 32.96 ppm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kornhaber et al., 2006</xref>). The 20 NMR structures of ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> were overlaid with a root mean square deviation of 0.23 Å over the backbone atoms (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1-data">Supplementary file 1</xref>), revealing two double-stranded antiparallel β-sheets (ββαββ), forming a ‘crab claw’ in which C5, C8, C28, C31 are located at the turns of β1/β2 and β3/β4 chelate a zinc ion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D–E</xref>). This ZitP ZnR structure is unusual, though related to the family of the ‘ribbon zinc-fingers’ (zinc_ribbon_5 or PF13719 superfamily), albeit it lacks the additional β-strand typically located in between the two β-sheets.</p><p>Next, we monitored the interaction between <sup>15</sup>N-labeled ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> and unlabeled PopZ to locate residues in ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> that are influenced by the interaction with PopZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>). This turned our attention to the aromatic side-chain of an invariant tryptophan at position 35 (W35, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>) that stacks above the zinc-coordination module of ZitP and that is replaced by a new species upon the addition of PopZ. W35 is interesting because the aromatic side chain at this position is replaced by an isoleucine in the primary structure of the AgmX zinc-finger (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>) that does not localize in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Moreover, W35 is surrounded by a surface-exposed patch of basic residues (K18, R24, R27, R34, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>) and it is required to bind PopZ in vitro, as determined by ITC with a W35I mutant derivative of ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> [ZitP<sup>(1-43)W35I</sup>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>]. Consistent with these ITC experiments, W35I impairs the interaction of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> with polar PopZ in vivo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A and B</xref>), as indicated by the diffuse fluorescence of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> and in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells expressing PopZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A–B</xref>). Similarly, a C5S/C8S/C28S/C31S quadruple or a R24A/R27A double mutation both disrupt polarization of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> and in PopZ-expressing <italic>E. coli</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A–B</xref>). As all of the substituted Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> variants are stably expressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1A</xref>), we conclude that these residues are required for the formation of a polar ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup>•PopZ complex.<fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.006</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Molecular determinants underpinning the ZitP•PopZ complex.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Images showing the subcellular localization of <italic>WT C. crescentus</italic> cells expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(WT)</sup>, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(CS)</sup>, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(W35I)</sup> or Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(R24A/R27A)</sup> from the <italic>xylX</italic> locus. Synthesis of the Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants was induced with xylose for 4 hr before phase contrast and Dendra2-fluorescence imaging. (<bold>B</bold>) Images of <italic>E. coli</italic> TB28 cells expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(WT)</sup>, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(CS)</sup>, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(W35I)</sup> or Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(R24A/R27A)</sup> (left panels) in the presence of mCherry-PopZ (middle panels). Overlays between green (Dendra2) and/or red (mCherry) fluorescence and phase contrast images are shown (right panels). Cells were grown in LB for 2 hr, then the expression of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants and of mCherry-PopZ was induced with 1 mM IPTG and 0.2% L-arabinose, respectively, for 2 hr. (<bold>C</bold>) Images of <italic>WT C. crescentus</italic> cells expressing <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> (Rs) Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(WT)</sup>, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(Q27R)</sup> or Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(Q27R/W35I)</sup> and of Δ<italic>popZ C</italic>. crescentus cells expressing <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(WT)</sup>. Synthesis of the Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants was induced from the <italic>xylX</italic> locus 4 hr before phase contrast and Dendra2-fluorescence imaging. (<bold>D</bold>) Images of <italic>E. coli</italic> TB28 cells expressing <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> (Rs) Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(WT)</sup>, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(Q27R)</sup> or Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(Q27R/W35I)</sup> (left panels) in the presence of mCherry-PopZ (middle panels). Overlays between green (Dendra2) and/or red (mCherry) fluorescence channels with phase contrast images are shown (right panel). Cells were grown in LB for 2 hr, then the expression of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants and of mCherry-PopZ was induced with 1 mM IPTG and 0.2% L-arabinose, respectively, for 2 hr.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.006">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.006</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.007</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Steady-state levels of Dendra-ZitP<sup>1-143</sup> variants.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Immunoblots using antibodies to Dendra2 (top) or MreB (bottom, loading control) showing the abundance of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants in <italic>C. crescentus WT</italic> strains. Expression of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants (CS: C5S/C8S/C28S/C31S quadruple; W35I and R24A/R27A double mutants) was induced from the <italic>xylX</italic> locus for 4 hr by the addition of 0.3% xylose. A strain that does not encode the Dendra2 was used as negative control (empty). (<bold>B</bold>) Immunoblots using antibodies to Dendra2 (top) or MreB (bottom, control) showing the abundance of the Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants from <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> (Rs) in <italic>C. crescentus WT</italic> strains. Expression of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants (WT, Q27R and Q27R/W35I double mutants) was induced from the <italic>xylX</italic> locus for 4 hr by the addition of 0.3% xylose. A strain that does not encode the Dendra2 was used as negative control (empty).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.007">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.007</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig3-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Interestingly, <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> is also largely diffuse in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>) or in PopZ-expressing <italic>E. coli</italic>, but some faint polar signals are noticeable as well (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>). Questioning the basis for this poor polar localization in <italic>C. crescentus</italic>, we noted that this ZitP ortholog contains a naturally-occurring substitution (corresponding to R27Q in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>) in the aforementioned basic patch. We therefore asked if polar localization could be improved if this substitution is ‘corrected’ (i.e. reversed) by a Q27R substitution of <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup>. This ‘corrected’ <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> ZitP<sup>(1-43)Q27R</sup> version is indeed robustly polar in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>) and in PopZ-expressing <italic>E. coli</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>). When the W35I substitution is introduced into this ‘corrected’ <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> variant, polar localization is again lost without compromising abundance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1B</xref>). We conclude that W35, the basic patch and the integrity of the Zn<sup>2+</sup> coordinating center are required for the formation of a polar ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup>•PopZ complex.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>ZitP controls PopZ localization</title><p>As PopZ interacts with the centromere (<italic>parS)</italic>-binding protein ParB and is required to anchor <italic>parS</italic> at both <italic>C. crescentus</italic> poles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ebersbach et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>), we tested if the ZitP•PopZ complex associates, directly or indirectly, with <italic>parS in vivo</italic>. To this end, we conducted c<underline>h</underline>romatin <underline>i</underline>mmuno<underline>p</underline>recipitation-deep-<underline>seq</underline>uencing (ChIP-Seq) using antibodies recognizing ParB (anti-ParB) or ZitP (anti-ZitP specific for either the N-terminus or the C-terminus, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). These experiments confirmed that ParB exclusively occupies the <italic>parS</italic> site in vivo and additionally showed that i) the ZitP•PopZ complex associates with two chromosomal regions flanking, but not overlapping, <italic>parS</italic> (by 2–3 kpb) and that ii) the ParAB interaction sites in PopZ are critical for this association (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>As ZitP is perfectly positioned to influence the subcellular position of ParB and/or PopZ, we examined the localization of both proteins in strains lacking or overproducing ZitP. While inactivation of ZitP has a mild effect on CFP-ParB localization in <italic>WT</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>), we observed aberrant CFP-ParB localization and perturbed cytokinesis in Δ<italic>zitP</italic> cells expressing variants of PopZ impaired in binding ParB and/or ParA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>)(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Quantification revealed that Δ<italic>zitP</italic> Δ<italic>popZ</italic> cells expressing mCherry-PopZ<sup>KE</sup> (impaired in ParB binding, Δ<italic>zitP mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ<sup>KE</sup></italic>) had fewer bipolar foci compared to <italic>zitP</italic><sup>+</sup> cells and an increase of cells without polar signals. Importantly, these abnormalities were not seen in <italic>zitP</italic><sup>+</sup> cells, indicating that ZitP promotes polar localization of PopZ when the ParAB-dependent (and/or another) localization pathway requiring the PopZ N-terminal region is impaired. Consistent with these results, we found that the <underline>e</underline>fficiency <underline>o</underline>f <underline>p</underline>lating (EOP) of Δ<italic>zitP</italic> cells harboring the <italic>popZ</italic><sup>Δ</sup><italic><sup>26</sup></italic> allele (Δ<italic>zitP mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ</italic><sup>Δ</sup><italic><sup>26</sup></italic>) that encodes a PopZ variant lacking the N-terminal 26 residues to bind ParAB and other client proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Holmes et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>) is markedly reduced compared to <italic>zitP</italic><sup>+</sup> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). EOP was similarly diminished in Δ<italic>zitP</italic> Δ<italic>popZ</italic> cells expressing PopZ<sup>KEP</sup> (Δ<italic>zitP mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ<sup>KEP</sup></italic>) a version of PopZ in which the interaction sites for ParAB (and other PopZ client proteins) are inactivated by site-directed muatgenesis [E12K/R19E/S22P](<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.008</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>The ZitP•PopZ complex controls the <italic>C.</italic></title><p><italic>crescentus</italic> cell division cycle. (<bold>A</bold>) Overlays of mCherry-fluorescence and phase contrast images of <italic>WT</italic> (upper panels) or Δ<italic>zitP</italic> (bottom) <italic>C. crescentus</italic> expressing the mCherry-PopZ<sup>KE</sup> variant that no longer interacts with ParB. mCherry-PopZ<sup>KE</sup> is expressed from the native locus (<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ<sup>KE</sup></italic>) in lieu of untagged PopZ. Below the micrographs are quantifications of cells with and without bipolar or monopolar fluorescent foci of mCherry-PopZ<sup>KE</sup>. (<bold>B</bold>) Efficiency of plating (EOP) assays of <italic>C. crescentus</italic> strains expressing <italic>WT</italic> mCherry-PopZ (<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ</italic>) or variants that no longer interact with ParB (<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ<sup>KE</sup></italic>), with ParA (<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ<sup>SP</sup></italic>) or both (<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ<sup>KEP</sup></italic> and <italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ<sup>Δ26</sup></italic>) in <italic>WT</italic> or Δ<italic>zitP</italic> cells. Serial ten-fold dilutions were plated on PYE agar containing spectinomycin. (<bold>C</bold>) Growth measurements of various strains monitored by optical density at 660 nm (OD660) in PYE. (<bold>D</bold>) Overlays of CFP- and mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images from <italic>C. crescentus popZ::mCherry-popZ parB::CFP-parB</italic> cells harbouring an empty plasmid (pMT464, left panel) or the pP<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(WT)</sup> derivative followed by time-lapse analysis with images acquired every 40 min. (<bold>E</bold>) Overlays of mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images from <italic>C. crescentus popZ::mCherry-popZ parB::CFP-parB</italic> cells harbouring an empty plasmid (pMT464, left panel) or derivatives: pP<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(WT)</sup> (second panel), pP<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(CS)</sup> (third panel), pP<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(W35I)</sup> (fourth panel) and pP<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(R24A/R27A)</sup> (right panel). Overexpression of ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> variants was induced with xylose 0.3% for 6 hr prior to imaging. (<bold>F</bold>) Overlays of mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images from <italic>C. crescentus popZ::mCherry-popZ parB::CFP-parB</italic> cells harbouring a P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(MalF-TM)</sup>, P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(WT)</sup> or a P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-90</sup> overexpression plasmid. Overexpression was induced by growth in 0.3% xylose for 6 hr prior to imaging. (<bold>G</bold>) Overlays of mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images from <italic>C. crescentus popZ::mCherry-popZ<sup>KEP</sup> parB::CFP-parB</italic> cells harbouring a P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(WT)</sup> or a P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(W35I)</sup> overexpression plasmid. Overexpression was induced by growth in 0.3% xylose for 6 hr prior to imaging.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.008">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.008</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig4-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.009</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>ChIP-Seq analysis of ZitP.</title><p>Genome-wide occupancies of ParB in <italic>WT</italic> cells and ZitP in <italic>WT</italic>, Δ<italic>zitP</italic> and <italic>popZ</italic> mutant cells as determined by ChIP-Seq using antibodies to ParB (α-ParB) and different antibodies to (the N-terminal and C-terminal domains of) ZitP [α-ZitP(NTD) and α-ZitP(CTD), respectively]. The <italic>x</italic> axis denotes the nucleotide position on the genome, whereas the <italic>y</italic> axis denotes the relative abundance of reads for each probe (see Supplementary Methods for detailed description). Note that only the region from nucleotide 4,025,000 to 4,045,000 of the <italic>C. crescentus WT</italic> (NA1000) genome containing the <italic>parS</italic> centromere region is shown. Genes encoded from right to left are shown as blue bars, whereas the red bars indicate genes on the reverse strand. The numbers above the coding sequences refer to the CCNA gene annotation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Marks et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.009">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.009</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig4-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.010</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Quantification of polar CFP-ParB and mCherry-PopZ in <italic>C.crescentus WT</italic> and mutants.</title><p>Quantification of CFP-ParB and mCherry-PopZ localization in <italic>zitP</italic><sup>+</sup> or Δ<italic>zitP</italic> strains expressing CFP-ParB in lieu of untagged ParB from the <italic>parB</italic> locus and mCherry-PopZ from the <italic>popZ</italic> locus in lieu of native PopZ.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.010">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.010</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig4-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig4s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.011</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Localization of ParB and ParA upon ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> overexpression in <italic>C.crescentus</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Kymograph showing GFP-ParB localization along the <italic>C. crescentus</italic> cell cycle in <italic>WT</italic> or ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> overproduction. Swarmer (G1-phase) cells harbouring an empty plasmid or overexpressing ZitP<sup>1-133(WT)</sup> were cultivated in M2G before synchronization and transferred onto an agarose pad containing 0.3% xylose (t = 0 min) to induce ZitP<sup>1-133</sup>, and visualized at 20 min intervals by light and fluorescence microscopy, respectively. Images were analysed using the kymograph tool from Microbe tracker. One representative cell from the <italic>parB::GFP-parB</italic> strain harbouring the empty plasmid is shown as well as two representative cells from the <italic>parB::GFP-parB</italic> strain overexpressing ZitP<sup>1-133</sup>. Green arrowheads indicate the localization of GFP-ParB according to the cell length. (<bold>B</bold>) Images of <italic>C. crescentus</italic> harbouring an empty plasmid (pMT464, top panel), pP<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(WT)</sup> (middle panel), pP<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic>-ZitP<sup>1-133(CS)</sup> (bottom panel) and expressing from the chromosomal <italic>xylX</italic> locus a ParA<sub>G16V</sub>-eYFP (dimerization deficient mutant which localize preferentially at the cell pole rather than nucleoid)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Ptacin et al., 2010</xref>). ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> over-expression was induced by growth in xylose 0.3% for 6 hr prior to imaging. Overlays between phase contrast and YFP-fluorescence images are shown. (<bold>C</bold>) Immunoblot showing the steady-state levels of <italic>C. crescentus</italic> ZitP or ZitP derivatives expressed from P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic> on pMT464 in <italic>C. crescentus WT</italic> cells. <italic>WT</italic> harbouring empty pMT464 was used as a control. The blot was probed with the polyclonal antibody to the ZitP N-terminal domain (NTD). Note that endogenous ZitP expressed form the <italic>zitP</italic> locus is not detectable on this exposure due to the strong overproduction of the ZitP variants from the high copy plasmid.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.011">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.011</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig4-figsupp3-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>While exploring which region in ZitP is required to control PopZ, we noted that Δ<italic>zitP</italic> Δ<italic>popZ</italic> cells expressing the mCherry-PopZ<sup>KE</sup> have a reduced growth rate in broth and that this defect is rescued by expression of (full-length) Dendra2-ZitP from the <italic>xylX</italic> locus using the xylose-inducible P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). The C-terminal DUF3426 that is required for polar pilus biogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mignolet et al., 2016</xref>) is not required to improve growth , as revealed by growth measurements of cells expressing the ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> variant. However, when the interaction with PopZ is abrogated [in the ZitP<sup>(1-133W35I)</sup> mutant], cells grow poorly. By contrast, no dependency on ZitP is seen in Δ<italic>popZ</italic> cells expressing otherwise unmodified mCherry-PopZ (<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ</italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). Taken together, these results show that ZitP is important for growth and viability for Δ<italic>popZ</italic> cells expressing PopZ that no longer interacts efficiently with ParAB, and that the ability of membrane-anchored ZitP to bind PopZ via the ZnR is important to regulate PopZ. Thus, there exist at least two (redundant) mechanisms of PopZ localization control in <italic>C. crescentus</italic>: one regulated directly or indirectly by ParAB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>) (or the N-terminal region of PopZ) and another that is modulated by membrane-anchored ZitP [ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup>].</p><p>Further insight for the role of this truncated (membrane-anchored) ZitP came from overexpression of ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> from P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic> on a multi-copy plasmid (pMT464) in <italic>cfp-parB mCherry-popZ</italic> cells. We found that localization of ParB and PopZ is strongly perturbed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>) upon induction of ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> with xylose. Time lapse-fluorescence imaging revealed that the pole-ward movement of CFP-ParB normally seen in S-phase of <italic>WT</italic> cells stalls halfway through in cells overexpressing ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s3">Figure 4—figure supplement 3A</xref> for GFP-ParB). In these cells, mCherry-PopZ forms internal clusters, often proximal to CFP-ParB clusters. By contrast, CFP-ParB movement and mCherry-PopZ localization proceeds normally through the cell cycle in cells overexpressing the W35I derivative of ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). Also, ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> overexpression displaces a monomeric ParA derivative [ParA(G16V)] whose localization is PopZ-dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>) from the cell poles into aberrant cytoplasmic clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s3">Figure 4—figure supplement 3B</xref>). These defects seen at the single cell level are accompanied by cell filamentation at the population level and are not apparent either with full-length ZitP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>) overexpressed to comparable levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s3">Figure 4—figure supplement 3C</xref>) or with ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> variants harboring the W35I single mutation, the R24A/R27A double mutation or the C5S/C8S/C28S/C31S quadruple mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>). As overexpression of the ZnR without any membrane anchoring domain [ZitP<sup>(1-90)</sup>] does not cause such cell cycle defects either (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F</xref>), we asked if membrane-anchoring is specific for this ZitP activity. The aforementioned overexpression phenotypes are still supported by overexpression of a ZitP version in which the TM of ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> had been replaced with an unrelated TM from the <italic>E. coli</italic> MalF protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F</xref>). Finally, we also observed that overproduction of ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> in <italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ<sup>KEP</sup></italic> cells [in which the interaction with ParAB is impaired, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>) recapitulates the overxpression phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4G</xref>) seen in <italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ</italic> cells. Taken together, these results show that ZitP is able to redirect PopZ localization via a direct interaction at the membrane independently of the known interaction sites for ParA and ParB (and/or potentially other PopZ client proteins). As a consequence of PopZ delocalization, the localization of DNA segregation proteins like ParB and ParA is perturbed and cells divide infrequently owing to the tight coupling of chromosome segregation and cytokinetic control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Thanbichler and Shapiro, 2006</xref>). Since <italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ<sup>KEP</sup></italic> cells are also affected by ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> in growth and division, an unknown PopZ client protein(s) may contribute to the PopZ-dependent phenotypes caused by under- or over-expression of ZitP<sup>1-133</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>ZitP imparts bipolarity upon PopZ in E. coli</title><p>Knowing that membrane-anchored ZitP controls PopZ localization in <italic>C. crescentus</italic>, we attempted to recapitulate these effects in a heterologous system by co-expression of ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> or ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> with mCherry-PopZ in <italic>E. coli</italic>. When ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> is co-expressed with mCherry-PopZ in this system, mCherry-PopZ forms a single cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A</xref>) resembling the ones previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ebersbach et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>) whose location is fairly sporadic and infrequently associated with the cell extremity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A</xref>). By contrast, co-expression of full-length ZitP or ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> directs mCherry-PopZ into a robust bipolar disposition in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A</xref>). Conversely, the localization of Dendra2-ZitP in <italic>E. coli</italic> co-expressing PopZ provided matching results: Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> and full length Dendra2-ZitP are both bipolar, whereas Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-133)W35I</sup> is dispersed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). To confirm that Dendra2-ZitP associates with the polar membrane in <italic>E. coli</italic> rather than inclusion bodies, we localized it by super-resolution photo-activated localization microscopy (PALM)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Betzig et al., 2006</xref>) and observed the fluorescent signals to line exclusively the polar caps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). By contrast, Dendra2-ZitP is dispersed along the cell envelope when PopZ is absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). Thus, these interdependent clusters of PopZ and ZitP at the polar caps are clearly distinct from the internal (cytoplasmic) aggregates typically seen for PopZ when expressed without ZitP in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>) or in division-inhibited (filamentous) <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>) and that resemble fluorescent aggregates of inclusion bodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Miller et al., 2015</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.012</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>ZitP controls PopZ bipolarity in <italic>E.</italic></title><p><italic>coli</italic> and <italic>C. crescentus.</italic> (<bold>A</bold>) Overlays of mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>E. coli</italic> TB28 cells co-expressing mCherry-PopZ and various (untagged) ZitP versions: full length ZitP, or the derivatives ZitP<sup>1-133</sup>, ZitP<sup>1-133(W35I)</sup> and ZitP<sup>1-133(MalF-TM)</sup>. Cells were grown in LB for 2 hr, then ZitP variants and mCherry-PopZ were induced with 1 mM IPTG and 0.2% L-arabinose, respectively, for 2 hr before imaging. (<bold>B</bold>) Overlays of Dendra2-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>E. coli</italic> TB28 cells co-expressing (untagged) PopZ and full length Dendra2-ZitP, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-133(WT)</sup>, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-133(W35I)</sup> or Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-133(MalF-TM)</sup>. Cells were grown in LB for 2 hr, then Dendra2-ZitP and mCherry-PopZ were induced with 1 mM IPTG and 0.2% L-arabinose, respectively, for 2 hr before imaging. (<bold>C</bold>) PALM (photo-activated localization microscopy) images of <italic>E. coli</italic> cells expressing Dendra2-ZitP from pSRK-Km (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Khan et al., 2008</xref>) and either no PopZ (empty pBAD101(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Guzman et al., 1995</xref>) vector, strain EC127, left panel) or untagged PopZ from pBAD101 (strain EC132, right panel). (<bold>D</bold>) Overlays of Dendra2- and mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images showing the co-localization of Dendra2-ParB (from P<italic><sub>lac</sub></italic> on pSRK-Km) with WT or W35I mCherry-ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> derivatives in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells co-expressed with untagged PopZ from P<italic><sub>ara</sub></italic> on pBAD22. (<bold>E</bold>) Overlays of CFP- and/or mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>C. crescentus popZ::mCherry-popZ parB::CFP-parB</italic> cells co-overexpressing (untagged) full-length ZitP, ZitP<sup>1-90</sup>, ZitP<sup>1-133(W35I)</sup> or ZitP<sup>1-133(WT) </sup>with (untagged) PopZ under P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic> control from pMT464. Over-expression was induced by growth in xylose 0.3% for 4 hr prior to imaging. mCherry-PopZ (upper panel) and CFP-ParB (middle panel) are expressed from their native promoters at the respective endogenous chromosomal loci in lieu of the untagged form.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.012">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.012</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig5-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.013</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Co-localization of ZitP and PopZ in <italic>E.coli</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Quantification of mCherry-PopZ localization in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells co-expressing mCherry-PopZ and Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> or Dendra2-ZitP. The top panel indicates the number of PopZ foci per cell when mCherry-PopZ is co-expressed with Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> (blue) (n = 151) or Dendra2-ZitP (red) (n = 502). The bottom left and right panels show the relative position of foci (n = 502) along longitudinal axis of mCherry-PopZ foci in cells co-expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> (middle, for cells having one focus) or Dendra2-ZitP (right, for cells having two foci). Position 0 reflects one pole and position one the opposite pole. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>C. crescentus</italic> PopZ<sup>Δ26</sup> still interacts with <italic>C. crescentus</italic> ZitP in <italic>E. coli</italic>. Overlays of Dendra2- and/or mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>E. coli</italic> TB28 cells expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> (left, upper panel) or Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> (left, bottom panel) in the presence of mCherry-PopZ (middle panel). Co-localized red and green foci appear yellow in the overlay (right panel). Cells were grown in LB media for 2 hr, then expression of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants and mCherry-PopZ was induced with 1 mM IPTG and 0.2% L-arabinose, respectively, for 2 hr. (<bold>C</bold>) Biochemical fractionation of ZitP from extracts of cells expressing Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> or Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup>. Expression of Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> or Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> integrated at the chromosomal <italic>xylX</italic> locus was induced for 4 hr by the addition of 0.3% xylose. The cells were lysed by sonication (CE, cell extract) and the soluble fraction (<bold>S</bold>) was separated from the membrane fraction (pellet, <bold>P</bold>) by centrifugation. This fraction (<bold>P</bold>) was taken up in re-suspension buffer (control) with or without a 2 M NaCl final buffer (NaCl) or 1% Triton X-100 (Triton X-100). After centrifugation, the soluble fraction (<bold>S</bold>) and insoluble fraction (<bold>P</bold>) were collected. All the fractions were analysed by immunoblotting using antibodies to the ZitP (NTD) (top), DivJ as a membrane protein control (middle panel) and CtrA as a soluble protein control (bottom panel).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.013">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.013</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig5-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig5s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.014</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Steady-state levels of PopZ and ZitP variants upon co-overexpression in <italic>C.crescentus</italic>.</title><p>Immunoblots showing the steady-state levels of <italic>C. crescentus</italic> ZitP or ZitP derivatives co-expressed with <italic>C. crescentus</italic> PopZ from P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic> on pMT464 in <italic>C. crescentus WT</italic> cells. <italic>WT</italic> harbouring empty pMT464 was used as a control. The blot shown in the top panel was probed with polyclonal antibodies to the ZitP N-terminal domain (NTD). The blot in the lower panel shows the same blot re-probed with the polyclonal antibodies to PopZ. Note that endogenous ZitP and PopZ expressed from the <italic>zitP</italic> and <italic>popZ</italic> locus, respectively, are not detectable on this exposure due to the strong overproduction of the ZitP variants and PopZ from the high-copy plasmid.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.014">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.014</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig5-figsupp2-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> also induces the redistribution of the ParAB-blind version of mCherry-PopZ (mCherry-PopZ<sup>Δ26</sup>) in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>). By contrast, Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> is unable to do so, yet it still co-localizes (interacts) with mCherry-PopZ<sup>Δ26</sup>. This indicates that Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> can still interact with mCherry-PopZ<sup>Δ26</sup>, but no longer controls its localization since Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> is not membrane-anchored. Thus, ZitP regulates mCherry-PopZ localization either via the conserved C-terminal DUF2497 domain that is conserved in PopZ orthologs or via sequences distal to the N-terminal (26) residues where the ParAB recognition sites reside. As these findings imply that ZitP and ParB do not compete for the same binding site in PopZ, we reasoned that it should be possible to reconstitute a tripartite bipolar complex by co-expression of PopZ and Dendra2-ParB together with either mCherry-ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> or mCherry-ZitP<sup>(1-133)W35I</sup> in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>). We found that mCherry-ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> can indeed direct Dendra2-ParB to the poles of PopZ-expressing <italic>E. coli</italic>, whereas it remains in a cytoplasmic aggregate in the presence of mCherry-ZitP<sup>(1-133)W35I</sup>.</p><p>These experiments in <italic>E. coli</italic> prompted us to examine if ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> can redistribute mCherry-PopZ from the monopolar ‘plug’ of overexpressed PopZ in <italic>C. crescentus</italic>. Fluorescence microscopy of <italic>mCherry-popZ CFP-parB</italic> cells harboring either a PopZ/ZitP or a PopZ/ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> co-overexpression plasmid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>) revealed bipolar signals of mCherry-PopZ and CFP-ParB in the presence of ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup>. By contrast only monopolar ‘plugs’ containing mCherry-PopZ and CFP-ParB were seen with the W35I derived or ZitP<sup>(1-90)</sup> co-overexpression plasmids at similar expression levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2</xref>). In the latter condition, there is co-localization between PopZ and ParB. However, ParB is no longer at the periphery of bipolar PopZ in cells harboring the PopZ/ZitP or the PopZ/ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> co-overexpression plasmid. Cell length quantification revealed that cells containing monopolar ‘plugs’ are longer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>) than the PopZ/ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> co-overexpressing cells. As biochemical fractionation experiments confirmed the predicted localization of ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> and ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1C</xref>), we conclude that membrane-anchored ZitP robustly and directly controls PopZ localization in <italic>E. coli</italic> and in <italic>C. crescentus</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>ZitP control of PopZ is conserved</title><p>To investigate if the ZitP<italic>-</italic>dependent control of PopZ localization is common to closely and distantly related α-proteobacterial lineages, we overexpressed ZitP<sup>(1-120)</sup> from <italic>Brevundimonas diminuta</italic> and ZitP<sup>(1-104)</sup> from <italic>Rickettsia massiliae</italic> [corresponding to <italic>C. crescentus</italic> ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup>] in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> and found that both induced filamentation with mislocalized CFP-ParB and mCherry-PopZ akin to <italic>C. crescentus</italic> ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). As for <italic>C. crescentus</italic> ZitP or ZitP<sup>(1-133)</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>), ZitP<sup>(1-104)<italic>Rm</italic></sup> prevents the accumulation of monopolar ‘plugs’ of overexpressed PopZ<italic><sup>Cc</sup></italic> in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>). As expected, this <italic>R. massiliae</italic> ZnR [ZitP<sup>(1-43)<italic>Rm</italic></sup>] also localizes to the <italic>C. crescentus</italic> cell poles in a PopZ-dependent manner, but no longer when the analogous W35I mutation is introduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). Rickettsial ZnR also co-localizes with <italic>C. crescentus</italic> mCherry-PopZ in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>) and ZitP<sup>(1-104)<italic>Rm</italic></sup> directs mCherry-PopZ into bipolarity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref>). Finally, we found that i) <italic>R. massiliae</italic> PopZ can also recruit <italic>C. crescentus</italic> Dendra2-ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup> to clusters in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6F</xref>) and that ii) it promotes the bipolar localization of full-length Dendra2-ZitP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6G</xref>). We conclude that the PopZ-ZitP bipartite bipolarization system is conserved in α-proteobacteria and modular.<fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.015</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Conservation of PopZ•ZitP localization and activity (<bold>A</bold>) Overlays of CFP- and mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>C.</italic></title><p><italic>crescentus popZ::mCherry-popZ parB::CFP-parB</italic> cells over-expressing ZitP<sup>1-104</sup> from <italic>R. massiliae</italic> (upper panel) or <italic>B. diminuta</italic> (lower panel) from P<italic><sub>xyl</sub></italic> on a multi-copy plasmid (pMT464). mCherry-PopZ and CFP-ParB are expressed from the chromosome in lieu of the untagged versions. ZitP<sup>1-104</sup> over-expression was induced by the addition of 0.3% xylose for 6 hr prior to imaging. (<bold>B</bold>) Overlays of CFP- and mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>C. crescentus popZ::mCherry-popZ parB::CFP-parB</italic> cells over-expressing ZitP<sup>1-104</sup> from <italic>R. massiliae</italic> with <italic>C. crescentus</italic> PopZ. Over-expression was induced by the addition of 0.3% xylose for 6 hr prior to imaging. (<bold>C</bold>) Overlays of Dendra2-fluorescence with phase contrast images of the <italic>R. massiliae</italic> (Rm) ZitP ZnR version expressed from the <italic>xylX</italic> locus in <italic>WT</italic> and Δ<italic>popZ C. crescentus</italic> cells. Synthesis of the Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(WT)<italic>Rm</italic></sup> or Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(W35I) <italic>Rm</italic></sup> was induced for 4 hr with 0.3% xylose before imaging. (<bold>D</bold>) Overlays of Dendra2- and/or mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>E. coli</italic> TB28 cells expressing <italic>R. massiliae</italic> (Rm) Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(WT)</sup> (upper panels), Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43(W35I)</sup> (lower panel) in the presence of mCherry-tagged PopZ from <italic>C. crescentus</italic>. Cells were grown in LB for 2 hr, then Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants and mCherry-PopZ were induced with 1 mM IPTG and 0.2% L-arabinose, respectively, for 2 hr. (<bold>E</bold>) Overlay of mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>E. coli</italic> TB28 cells co-expressing mCherry-ZitP<sup>1-104Rm</sup> from <italic>R. massiliae</italic> (Rm) with <italic>C. crescentus</italic> PopZ from P<italic><sub>ara</sub></italic> encoded on the same pBAD22-derived plasmid. Cells were grown in LB for 2 hr, then expression of mCherry-ZitP<sup>1-104Rm</sup> and PopZ was induced with 0.2% L-arabinose for 2 hr before imaging. (<bold>F</bold>) Overlays of Dendra2- and/or mCherry-fluorescence with phase contrast images of <italic>E. coli</italic> TB28 cells expressing <italic>C. crescentus</italic> Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> (Cc) in the presence of mCherry-PopZ from <italic>R. massiliae</italic> (Rm). Cells were grown in LB for 2 hr, then Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> and mCherry-PopZ were induced with 1 mM IPTG and 0.2% L-arabinose, respectively, for 2 hr. (<bold>G</bold>) Images of <italic>E. coli</italic> cells co-expressing <italic>C. crescentus</italic> Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> (Cc, upper panel) or Dendra2-ZitP full-length (Cc, bottom panel) and PopZ from <italic>R. massiliae</italic> (Rm). Fluorescence (Dendra2) images (left panels) and overlays between phase contrast and Dendra2 fluorescence images (right panels) are shown. Cells were grown in LB to during 2 hr, then Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> variants were induced with 1 mM IPTG and PopZ was induced with 0.2% L-arabinose for 2 hr. (<bold>H</bold>) The (bi)polar PopZ•ZitP complex of free-living (Caulobacterales) and obligate intracellular (Rickettsiales) α-proteobacteria. Pink dots denote PopZ monomers that assemble into a bipolar or monopolar patch, while blue dots denote ZitP molecules. An obligate intracellular rickettsial (rod with bipolar PopZ) cell is depicted within a vacuole (dashed structure) of a host cell (closed structure) and presumed also to polarize PopZ•ZitP (grey arrow). As ZitP is not present in the Rhizobiales, another mechanism of PopZ control is likely operational to drive it into a monopolar disposition. Similarly, we suggest that PopZ localization in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> can be accomplished by another pathway that operates independently of ZitP and likely involves ParAB and/or another pathway (see Discussion).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.015">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.015</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-fig6-v1"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Eukaryotic zinc-finger (ZnR) domains are typically used to bind DNA, but they can also mediate protein-protein interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Klug, 2010</xref>). Here we described a small (43-residue) ZnR that acts as a conserved polar localization sequence, reminiscent of the nuclear localization signal (NLS) of eukaryotes, by promoting the interaction with the PopZ polar organizer of α-proteobacteria. This ZnR interacts directly with PopZ and controls its localization from the membrane, even when PopZ no longer carries the interaction sites for ParAB, indicating that PopZ localization is regulated by redundant mechanisms in <italic>C. crescentus.</italic> One mechanism may require ParAB or at least it depends on the N-terminal region of PopZ that promotes the interaction with ParAB and other PopZ client proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Holmes et al., 2016</xref>). However, ZitP controls PopZ independently of this region, underscoring the multivalent interactions and multifunctional properties of PopZ.</p><p>ZitP emerges as new a component of the α-proteobacterial polarity control pathway using an N-terminal ZnR to regulate PopZ localization. Interestingly, ZitP is bifunctional, controlling the localization of polar pilus biogenesis proteins via its C-terminal DUF3426 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mignolet et al., 2016</xref>). While the DUF3426 is less conserved among the α-proteobacteria and dispensable for PopZ localization control, the membrane-anchored ZitP ZnR and PopZ binding is featured by many ZitP orthologs from the branch of obligate intracellular α-proteobacteria (the Rickettsiae) and regulates PopZ subcellular positioning.</p><p>The NMR solution structure of the ZitP ZnR revealed an atypical ββαββ-architecture, resembling that of the crenarchaeal DNA-binding protein Cren7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Zhang et al., 2010</xref>). However, the ZitP ZnR lacks a fifth β-strand (β5) that is used by Cren7 to establish critical sequence-specific contacts with DNA. An unexpected finding was that PopZ-bound ZitP associates indirectly with sites flanking the ParB-bound centromere (<italic>parS</italic>), rather than <italic>parS</italic> itself that ParB binds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). We found that the interaction between PopZ and ParAB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ebersbach et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">2010</xref>), or at least the N-terminal region of PopZ, is required for ZitP to associate with these <italic>parS</italic>-flanking sites. It is also possible that another (unknown) component(s) of the PopZ complex influences the association of ZitP at these sites or that it underlies an unprecedented mode of occupancy of the macromolecular ZitP•PopZ•ParB complex on the chromosome in proximity to <italic>parS</italic>. Interestingly, the ParB-centromeric complex was recently proposed to self-assemble via nucleation and ‘caging’ in vivo, i.e. three-dimensional stochastic interactions between ParB and <italic>parS,</italic> and possibly reinforced or delimited by adjacent nucleoprotein complexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sanchez et al., 2015</xref>) or accessory factors that may allow super-complexes to extend into neighboring chromosomal regions.</p><p>With the juxtaposition of PopZ•ZitP at the ParB-bound centromere and our reconstitution of the ZitP•PopZ•ParB tripartite complex in <italic>E. coli,</italic> ZitP is well positioned to exert control of ParB•<italic>parS</italic> dynamics and to impair segregation by sequestering the adjacent centromere into aberrant PopZ•ZitP clusters. The ParB-control function of PopZ•ZitP depends on the ability of membrane-anchored ZitP ZnR to interact with PopZ. Our molecular dissections provide evidence that ZitP targets residues flanking the conserved C-terminal DUF2497 of PopZ. Thus, the DUF2497 region may serve as a key determinant in PopZ to regulate its association with (known and unknown) client proteins and its bipolar localization and/or dynamics.</p><p>The bipolar localization of DivIVA of the Gram-positive Firmicutes has been intensively studied and is governed by the biophysical properties of DivIVA that attract it to concavely curved membranes and thus both cell poles when expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lenarcic et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ramamurthi and Losick, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Strahl and Hamoen, 2012</xref>). The α-proteobacterial PopZ system is of distinct ancestry and structural features compared to DivIVA, and it aggregates into (sporadic) monopolar and non-polar (cytoplasmic) clusters in (filamentous) <italic>E. coli</italic> in the absence of ZitP. While these PopZ clusters do not rely on membrane curvature to find the <italic>E. coli</italic> poles, their localization mechanism is not understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laloux and Jacobs-Wagner, 2013</xref>) and could reflect aggregation in a partially folded form into cellular inclusion bodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Miller et al., 2015</xref>). A clearly different mechanism underlies the robust assembly of (near native) bipolar PopZ•ZitP complexes at the polar membrane as observed by PALM. It is possible that these PopZ•ZitP complexes scout the poles by a similar mechanism as DivIVA, a possibility that warrants further investigation. As these bipolar PopZ•ZitP complexes in <italic>E. coli</italic> can also be reconstituted with components from different α-proteobacteria, it is unlikely that it is mediated by specialized phospholipids as the composition differs between <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>Caulobacterales</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">De Siervo, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">De Siervo and Homola, 1980</xref>) and other α-proteobacteria, for example the Rickettsiales.</p><p>There are intriguing evolutionary implications based on the finding that rickettsial ZitP retains the aforementioned PopZ control activities. It suggests that these obligate intracellular pathogens also feature a polarized PopZ•ZitP complex. The rickettsial actin filament organizer Sca2 is polarized and promotes actin-mediated motility of some <italic>Rickettsiae</italic> inside the host cell cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Haglund et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Madasu et al., 2013</xref>). It is therefore conceivable that the PopZ•ZitP bipolarity system served as a primordial platform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6H</xref>) for the acquisition of specialized polarity based functions conferred via PopZ-interacting proteins that reinforce bipolarity and/or confer other polarized traits. For example, PopZ is also required for stalk biogenesis in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bowman et al., 2010</xref>), a structure that requires specialized peptidoglycan (PG) biosynthesis enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kühn et al., 2010</xref>). As several Rhizobiales members also sequester PopZ to the site of PG synthesis to promote unipolar growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anderson-Furgeson et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brown et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Curtis and Brun, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Grangeon et al., 2015</xref>), the current challenge is to determine which proteins interact with PopZ in the different α-proteobacterial branches, particularly in the Rhizobiales. PopZ is unipolar in this branch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Deghelt et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Grangeon et al., 2015</xref>) and no ZitP orthologs are encoded, suggesting that unknown PopZ-control mechanisms exist (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6H</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>). By contrast, many members of the Rhodobacterales, do not encode a conspicuous PopZ ortholog in their genome. This, along with the structural divergence of the ZitP<sup>ZnR</sup> in this lineage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>), suggests that ZitP has been appropriated for other functions or interactions with partners differing in primary structure.</p><p>Proper control of polarization is critical for efficient cellular proliferation and fitness in many cell types. In yeast, aberrant or misregulated polarity complexes impair the fitness of yeast cells to the extent where it is favorable to cells to eliminate these functions completely than retaining them improperly regulated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Laan et al., 2015</xref>). Similar selective forces must have ensured the evolution and retention of related polarity control modules in free-living and obligate intracellular bacteria since misregulation of polarity similarly perturbs the α-proteobacterial cell division cycle.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Strains, plasmids and oligos</title><p>Strains, plasmids and oligos are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Supplementary file 2</xref>. Plasmids expressing Dendra2 variants were used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Holden et al., 2014</xref>) and strains are derivatives of <italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic> NA1000 whose genome is sequenced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Marks et al., 2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Growth conditions</title><p><italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic> NA1000 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Marks et al., 2010</xref>) and derivatives were cultivated at 30°C in peptone yeast extract (PYE)-rich medium (2 g/L bactopeptone, 1 g/L yeast extract, 1 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, and 0.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>) or in M2 minimal salts (M2G) (0.87 g/L Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 0.54 g/L KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.50 g/L NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, 0.2% [wt/vol] glucose, 0.5 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 0.01 mM FeSO<sub>4</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ely, 1991</xref>). <italic>E. coli</italic> strains were grown at 37°C in Luria Bertani (LB)–rich medium (10 g/L NaCl, 5 g/L yeast extract, and 10 g/L tryptone). When appropriate, media were supplemented with antibiotics at the following concentrations (µg/mL in liquid/solid medium for <italic>C. crescentus</italic> strains; µg/mL in liquid/solid medium for <italic>E. coli</italic> strains): kanamycin (5/20 μg.mL<sup>−1</sup>; 20/20 μg.mL<sup>−1</sup>), tetracycline (1/1 μg mL<sup>−1</sup>; not appropriate), spectinomycin and streptomycin (in solid for <italic>C. crescentus</italic> only) (25/25, five respectively; 30/90 μg.mL<sup>−1</sup>), gentamycin (1/1; 10/25 μg.mL<sup>−1</sup>) and nalidixic acid (in solid only) (20 μg.mL<sup>−1</sup>). When needed, for <italic>Caulobacter</italic>, D-xylose or sucrose was added at 0.3% final concentration, glucose at 0.2% final concentration and vanillate at 500 μM final concentration. When needed, for <italic>E. coli</italic>, arabinose and IPTG were added at a final concentration of 0.3% and 1 mM, respectively.</p><p>Swarmer cell isolation, electroporation, biparental mating (intergeneric conjugations) and bacteriophage φCr30-mediated generalized transduction were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ely, 1991</xref>). Briefly, swarmer cells were isolated by Ludox or Percoll density-gradient centrifugation at 4°C, followed by three washes and final re-suspension in pre-warmed (30°C) M2G. Electroporation was done from 1 ml overnight cells that had been washed three times in sterile water. Biparental matings were done using exponential phase <italic>E. coli</italic> S17-1 donor cells and <italic>C. crescentus</italic> recipient cells washed in PYE and mixed at 1:10 ratio on a PYE plate. After 4–5 hr of incubation at 30°C, the mixture of cells was plated on PYE harbouring nalidixic acid (to counter select <italic>E. coli</italic>) and the antibiotic that the conjugated plasmid confers resistance to. Generalized transductions were done by mixing 50 μL ultraviolet-inactivated transducing lysate with 500 μL stationary phase recipient cells, incubation for 2 hr, followed by plating on PYE containing antibiotic to select for the transduced DNA.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>ZitP purification and production of antibodies</title><p>ZitP N-TER or C-TER recombinant protein, comprising only the first 90 amino acids or lacking the last 119 residues respectively, was expressed from pET28a in <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3)/ pLysS and purified under native conditions using Ni<sup>2+</sup> chelate chromatography. Cells were grown in LB at 37°C to an OD<sub>600nm</sub> of 0.6 and induced by the addition of IPTG to 1 mM during 3 hr, and harvested at 5000 RPM at 4°C during 30 min. Cells were pelleted and re-suspended in 25 mL of lysis buffer (10 mM Tris HCl (pH 8), 0.1 M NaCl, 1.0 mM β-mercaptoethanol, 5% glycerol, 0.5 mM imidazole Triton X-100 0.02%). Cells were sonicated in a water–ice bath, 15 cycles 30 s ON; 30 s OFF. After centrifugation at 5000g for 20 min at 4°C, the supernatant was loaded onto a column containing 5 mL of Ni-NTA agarose resin (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) pre-equilibrated with lysis buffer. The column was rinsed with lysis buffer, 400 mM NaCl and 10 mM imidazole, both prepared in lysis buffer. Fractions were collected (in 300 mM Imidazole buffer, prepared in lysis buffer) and used to immunize New Zealand white rabbits (Josman LLC). </p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Fractionation</title><p>Fifty mL of an exponential culture of <italic>Caulobacter</italic> (OD<sub>600nm</sub> = 0.4) was harvested by centrifugation for 15 min at 8000g at 4°C. Cell pellets were re-suspended in 1 mL of lysis buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 300 mM NaCL, 0.5 mM EDTA, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> at 4°C freshly supplemented with 1 mM DTT, 12500 U ready-lyse (Epicentre technologies), and one tablet of EDTA-free protease inhibitor cocktail ([Complete; Roche] per 50 mL). Ten μL of DNAse 1 mg.mL<sup>−1</sup>, 5 μL of RNAseA 20 mg.mL<sup>−1</sup> were added before sonication in an ice-water bath, 15 cycles 30 s ON; 30 s OFF. Twenty μL of this was mixed with 20 μL of loading buffer 2X (0.25 M Tris pH 6.8, 6% (wt/vol) SDS, 10 mM EDTA, 20% (vol/vol) Glycerol) containing 10% (vol/vol) β-mercaptoethanol to obtain the crude extract (CE). Sonicated samples were centrifuged for 30 min at 20,000<italic>g</italic> at 4°C, and the supernatant was diluted in 2X loading buffer to obtain the soluble fraction (S). The pellet, containing the insoluble fraction, was resuspended in 1 mL resuspension buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 300 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT) and 20 μL was diluted in loading buffer 2X to obtain the insoluble fraction (P). The membrane fraction was split in 3 fractions of 300 μL to add 300 μL re-suspension buffer (control) or 300 μL 4M NaCl buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 4 M NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT) (solubilize proteins associated with membrane) or 300 μL 2% Triton-X100 (20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 300 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT, 2% Triton-X100) (solubilize integral membrane proteins). Samples were incubated 1 hr with shaking at 4°C and harvested by centrifugation at 20,000g during 30 min at 4°C. Forty μL of the supernatant was diluted in 40 μL loading buffer 2X to obtain the soluble fraction (S). The pellet, containing the insoluble fraction, was resuspended in 600 μl of resuspension buffer. Forty μL of this was diluted in 40 μL loading buffer 2X to obtain the insoluble fraction (P) All the fraction were analysed by immunoblot using antibodies to ZitP (NTER), DivJ (as control of integral membrane protein) and CtrA (as control of soluble proteins).</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Whole-cell extracts preparation</title><p>Five hundred μL of an exponential <italic>Caulobacter</italic> or <italic>E. coli</italic> cells (OD<sub>600nm</sub> = 0.4 and 0.8 respectively) were harvested with 20,000g at room temperature for 5 min. Whole-cell extracts were prepared by resuspension of cell pellets in 75 µL TE buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0 and 1 mM EDTA) followed by addition of 75 µL loading buffer 2X (0.25 M Tris pH 6.8, 6% (wt/vol) SDS, 10 mM EDTA, 20% (vol/vol) Glycerol) containing 10% (vol/vol) β-mercaptoethanol. Samples were normalized for equivalent loading using OD<sub>600nm</sub> and were heated for 10 min at 90°C prior to loading.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Immunoblot analysis</title><p>Protein samples were separated by SDS–polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and blotted on polyvinylidenfluoride membranes (Merck Millipore). Membranes were blocked overnight with Tris-buffered saline 1X (TBS) (50 mM Tris-HCl, 150 mM NaCl, pH 8) containing, 0.1% Tween-20 and 8% dry milk and then incubated for an additional 3 hr with the primary antibodies diluted in TBS 1X, 0.1% Tween-20, 5% dry milk. The different polyclonal antisera to ZitP (NTER, 1:5000 dilution and CTER, 1:5000), CtrA (1:10,000) and DivJ (1:10,000) were used. Commercial and polyclonal antibodies to Dendra2 (Antibodies-Online) and mCherry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Chen et al., 2005</xref>) were used at 1:5,000 and 1:10,000 dilutions respectively. Primary antibodies were detected using HRP-conjugated donkey anti-rabbit antibody (Jackson ImmunoResearch) with ECL Western Blotting Detection System (GE Healthcare) and a luminescent image analyzer (Chemidoc<sup>Tm</sup> MP, Biorad).</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>ChIP-SEQ</title><p>Mid-log phase cells were cross-linked in 10 mM sodium phosphate (pH 7.6) and 1% formaldehyde at room temperature for 10 min and on ice for 30 min thereafter, washed three times in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and lysed in a Ready-Lyse lysozyme solution (Epicentre Technologies) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Lysates were sonicated in a ice-water bath, 15 cycles 30 s ON; 30 s OFF to shear DNA fragments to an average length of 0.3–0.5 kbp and cleared by centrifugation at 14,000 g for 2 min at 4°C. Lysates were normalized by protein content, diluted to 1 mL using ChIP buffer (0.01% SDS, 1.1% Triton X-100, 1.2 mM EDTA, 16.7 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.1), 167 mM NaCl plus protease inhibitors (Roche, Switzerland) and pre-cleared with 80 μl of protein-A agarose (Roche) and 100 μg BSA. To immunoprecipate the chromatin, two µL of polyclonal antibodies were added to the supernatant, incubated overnight at 4°C with 80 μL of protein-A agarose beads pre-saturated with BSA. Antibodies to ZitP NTER, ZitP CTER and ParB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mohl and Gober, 1997</xref>) were used for ChIP. The immunoprecipitate was washed once with low salt buffer (0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 2 mM EDTA, 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.1) and 150 mM NaCl), high salt buffer (0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 2 mM EDTA, 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.1) and 500 mM NaCl) and LiCl buffer (0.25 M LiCl, 1% NP-40, 1% sodium deoxycholate, 1 mM EDTA and 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.1)), and twice with TE buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.1) and 1 mM EDTA). The protein DNA complexes were eluted in 500 μL freshly prepared elution buffer (1% SDS and 0.1 M NaHCO3), supplemented with NaCl to a final concentration of 300 mM and incubated overnight at 65°C to reverse the crosslinks. The samples were treated with 2 μg of Proteinase K for 2 hr at 45°C in 40 mM EDTA and 40 mM Tris-HCl (pH 6.5). DNA was extracted using phenol:chloroform:isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1), ethanol precipitated using 20 μg of glycogen as carrier and resuspended in 100 μL of water.</p><p>Immunoprecipitated chromatin was used to prepare sample libraries used for deep-sequencing at Fasteris SA (Geneva, Switzerland). ChIP-Seq libraries were prepared using the DNA Sample Prep Kit (Illumina) following manufacturer's instructions. Single-end run were performed on an Illumina Genome Analyzer IIx or HiSeq2000, 50 cycles were read and yielded several million reads. The single-end sequence reads stored in FastQ files were mapped against the genome of <italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic> NA1000 (NC_011916) and converted to SAM using BWA and SAM tools respectively from the galaxy servor (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://usegalaxy.org/">https://usegalaxy.org/</ext-link>). The resulting SAM was imported into SeqMonk (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/seqmonk/">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/seqmonk/</ext-link>, version 0.21.0) to build sequence read profiles. The initial quantification of the sequencing data was done in SeqMonk: the genome was subdivided into 50 bp probes, and for every probe we calculated a value that represents a normalized read number per million. All ChIP-seq data was deposited in the GEO database under accession number GSE79918 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE79918">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE79918</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC)</title><p>ITC experiments were performed on a VP-ITC instrument (Microcal). Both partners were prepared in the same NMR spectroscopy buffer, ZitP at 0.015 mM and PopZ at 0.300 mM. ZitP was titrated using a solution of PopZ by 65 injections of 4 μL every 300 s at 20°C. The raw data were integrated, normalized for the molar concentration and analyzed using Origin7.0 according to a 1:1 binding model.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Growth measurements in broth</title><p>The overnight cultures were started in PYE supplemented with D-xylose 0.3% final. The cultures were diluted to obtain an OD<sub>600nm</sub> of 0.1 in PYE supplemented with D-xylose 0.3% final. The OD<sub>600nm</sub> was recorded every hour during 9 hr. The graph represents the trend of the growth curve of three independent experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Plasmid constructions</title><sec id="s4-10-1"><title>pMB123 (pNTPS138- Δ<italic>zitP</italic>)</title><p>The plasmid construct used to delete <italic>zitP</italic> (<italic>CCNA_02298</italic>) was made by PCR amplification of two fragments. The first, a 771 bp fragment was amplified using primers OMB87 and OMB88 (table S?), flanked by an <italic>Eco</italic>RI and a <italic>Bam</italic>HI site. The second, a 889 bp fragment was amplified using primers OMB89 and OMB90, flanked by a <italic>Bam</italic>HI site and a <italic>Hin</italic>dIII site. These two fragments were first digested with appropriate restriction enzymes and then triple ligated into pNTPS138 (M.R.K. Alley, Imperial College London, unpublished) previously restricted with <italic>EcoR</italic>I<italic>/Hind</italic>III.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-2"><title>pXdendra2<italic>-</italic>N2</title><p>We PCR amplified the photoactivatable variant <italic>dendra2</italic> from the pX-<italic>ftsZ</italic>-<italic>dendra2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Biteen et al., 2012</xref>) with dendra2N_F and dendra2N _R primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Pac</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Pac</italic>I-digested pMT582 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Thanbichler et al., 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-3"><title>pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>WT</sup></title><p>The <italic>zitP</italic>-coding sequence (nt 2444803–2445738, NA1000 genome) was PCR amplified from the NA1000 strain using the 2215sh + 2_SacI and CC2215_E primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pX-<italic>dendra2</italic>N2</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-4"><title>pMB22 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-90(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The first 270nt of the ZitP coding sequence were PCR amplified from the NA1000 strain using the OMB12 and OMB13 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2 (Seamus Holden, unpublished).</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-5"><title>pMB33 (pXdendra2-N2-zitP<sup>1-80(Ae)</sup>)</title><p>The first 240 nt of the Astex_3267 coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment one using the Van and T7pro primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-6"><title>pMB38 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-87(Mm)</sup>)</title><p>The first 261 nt of the Mmar10_2373 coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment two using the Van and T7pro primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-7"><title>pMB39 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-89(Cs)</sup>)</title><p>The first 267 nt of the <italic>Cseg_28671</italic> coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment three using the Van and T7pro primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-8"><title>pMB26 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic><sup>agmX1-90</sup></italic>)</title><p>The 90 first amino acid of AgmX coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment 20 using Van and T7pro primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-9"><title>pMB66 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43WT(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The first 129 nt of the ZitP coding sequence were PCR amplified from the NA1000 strain using the OMB12 and OMB41 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-10"><title>pMB164 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43CS(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The first 129 nt of the ZitP coding sequence were PCR amplified from the pMT335-2215CS strain using the OMB12 and OMB41 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-11"><title>pMB23 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-133</sup>)</title><p>The first 396 nt of the ZitP coding sequence were PCR amplified from the NA1000 strain using the OMB12 and OMB14 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-12"><title>pMB25 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-133CS</sup>)</title><p>The <italic>zitP<sup>CS</sup></italic> tetracysteine mutant allele was PCR amplified from the pMT335-2215CS using the 2215shCS + 2_SacI and OMB14 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pX-dendra2N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-13"><title>pMB73 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-49(Bd)</sup>)</title><p>The first 147 nt of HMPREF0185_02600 coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment four using the xyl and lac290 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-14"><title>pMB115 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43W35I(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The first 129 nt of the ZitP coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment 5 (containing the W35I mutation) using the T7pro and T7ter primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-15"><title>pMB170 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43R24A/R27A(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The first 129 nt of the ZitP coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment 6 (containing the R24A/R27A mutation) using the van and T7pro primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-16"><title>pMB184 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43WT(Rs)</sup>)</title><p>The first 129 nt of the Rsph17025_2450 coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment seven using the van and xylAS primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-17"><title>pMB91 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43Q27R(Rs)</sup>)</title><p>The first 129 nt of the Rsph17025_2450 coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment eight using the van and xylAS primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-18"><title>pMB185 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43Q27R/W35I(Rs)</sup>)</title><p>The first 129 nt of the Rsph17025_2450 coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment 18 using the van and T7pro primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-19"><title>pMB81 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-50WT(Rm)</sup>)</title><p>The first 150 nt of RMB_01390 coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment nine using the van and xylAS primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-20"><title>pMB116 (pXdendra2-N2-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43W35I(Rm)</sup>)</title><p>The first 150 nt RMB_01390 coding sequence were PCR amplified from the synthetic fragment 10 using the van and xylAS primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pXdendra2-N2.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-21"><title>pMT335-<italic>zitP<sup>CS:</sup></italic></title><p>We PCR amplified the <italic>zitP<sup>CS</sup></italic> tetracysteine mutant allele from pMT335-<italic>2215<sup>CS</sup></italic> with 2215shCS_NdeI and CC2215_E primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pMT335 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Thanbichler et al., 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-22"><title>pMB21 (pMT335-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The PopZ coding sequence was PCR amplified from NA1000 using the OMB7 and OMB11 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pMT335.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-23"><title>pMB93 (pMT464-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-132WT(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The first 396 nt of ZitP coding sequence was PCR amplified from NA1000 using the 2215sh_NdeI and OMB14 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pMT464.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-24"><title>pMB94 (pMT464-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-132CS(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The first 396nt of <italic>zitP</italic> sequence was PCR amplified from fragment 11 (containing the cysteines C5, C8, C28 and C31 mutated in serine) using the Van and OMB14 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pMT464.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-25"><title>pMB113 (pMT464-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-132W35I(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The first 396nt of <italic>zitP</italic> sequence was PCR amplified from fragment 12 (containing the mutation W35I) using the Van and T7 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pMT464.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-26"><title>pMB127 (pMT464-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-132malF</sup>)</title><p>The first 396 nt of the ZitP coding sequence was PCR amplified from fragment 13 (containing the MalF transmembrane domain instead the natural transmembrane domain from ZitP) using the Van and T7 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pMT464.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-27"><title>pMB156 (pMT464-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-120WT(Bd)</sup>)</title><p>The first 360 nt of the HMPREF0185_02600 coding sequence was PCR amplified from fragment 14 (containing the ZnR from <italic>B. diminuta</italic> and its transmembrane domain) using the Van and T7 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pMT464.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-28"><title>pMB114 (pMT464-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-104WT(Rm)</sup>)</title><p>The first 312nt of the ZitP coding sequence was PCR amplified from fragment 15 (containing the ZnR from <italic>R. massiliae</italic> and its transmembrane domain) using the Van and T7 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>EcoR</italic>I-digested pMT464.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-29"><title>pMB145 (pMCS-4-<italic>popZ</italic><sup>Δ26</sup>)</title><p>The PopZ coding sequence deleted for the 26 first amino acids was PCR amplified from NA1000 using the OMB70 and OMB11 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Kpn</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and cloned into <italic>Kpn</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pJP312 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ptacin et al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-30"><title>pMB49 (pBAD101<italic>-popZ</italic>)</title><p>The <italic>popZ</italic> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB21 using the OMB31 and M13(−20) primers. These fragments were digested with <italic>Nco</italic>I/<italic>Nde</italic>I and <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I respectively and triple ligated into <italic>Nco</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pBAD101.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-31"><title>pMB59 (pBAD101-<italic>mCherry-popZ</italic>)</title><p>The <italic>mCherry</italic> coding sequence was PCR amplified using the OMB35 and OMB36 and <italic>popZ</italic> was PCR amplified from pMB21 using the van and M13(−20) primers. These fragments were digested with <italic>Nco</italic>I/<italic>Nde</italic>I and <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I respectively and triple ligated into <italic>Nco</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pBAD101.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-32"><title>pMB128 (pBAD101-<italic>mCherry-popZ</italic><sup>Δ26</sup>)</title><p>The mCherry coding sequence was PCR amplified using the OMB35 and OMB36 and <italic>popZ</italic> was PCR amplified from NA1000 using the OMB65 and OMB66 primers. These fragments were digested with <italic>Nco</italic>I/<italic>Nde</italic>I and <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I respectively and triple ligated into <italic>Nco</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pBAD101.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-33"><title>(pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-43WT(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB66 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I /<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-34"><title>pMB193 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-43CS(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The ZitP<sup>1-43CS</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB164 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I /<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-35"><title>pMB194 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-43R24A/R27A(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The ZitP<sup>1-43R24A/R27A</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB170 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I /<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-36"><title>pMB195 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-43WT(Rs)</sup>)</title><p>The ZitP<sup>1-43WT(Rs)</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB184 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I /<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-37"><title>pMB196 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-43Q27R(Rs)</sup>)</title><p>The ZitP<sup>1-43Q27R(Rs)</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB91 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I /<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-38"><title>pMB197 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-43Q27R/W35I(Rs)</sup>)</title><p>The ZitP<sup>1-43Q27R/W35I(Rs)</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB185 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I /<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-39"><title>pMB166 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-49WT(Bd)</sup>)</title><p>The HMPREF0185_02600<sup>1-49</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB73 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-40"><title>pMB167 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP2373</italic><sup>1-87WT(Mm)</sup>)</title><p>The Mmar10_2373<sup>1-87</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB38 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>SacI</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-41"><title>pMB97 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-50WT(Rm)</sup>)</title><p>The RMB_01380<sup>1-50WT</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB81 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-42"><title>pMB168 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-50W35I(Rm)</sup>)</title><p>The RMB_01380<sup>1-50W35I</sup> coding sequence PCR amplified from pMB116 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-43"><title>pMB169 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-43W35I(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The ZitP<sup>1-43W35I</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB115 using OMB76 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-44"><title>pMB43 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>WT</sup>)</title><p>The Dendra2-ZitP coding sequence was PCR amplified from pX-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>WT</sup> using xylseq2 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pSRK.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-45"><title>pMB45 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP<sup>1-90</sup></italic>)</title><p>The Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-90</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pX-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>WT</sup> using xylseq2 and OMB13 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pSRK.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-46"><title>pMB86 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-133WT(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The Dendra2-ZitP<sup>1-133WT</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB23 using xylseq2 and M13(−20) primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pSRK.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-47"><title>pMB178 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-133W35I(Cc)</sup>)</title><p>The ZitP<sup>1-133W35I</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB113 using OMB80 and OMB84 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-48"><title>pMB179 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-133malF</sup>)</title><p>The ZitP<sup>1-133malF</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB127 using OMB81 and OMB84 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-49"><title>pMB181 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2-zitP</italic><sup>1-104WT(Rm)</sup>)</title><p>The RMB_01390<sup>1-104WT</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from pMB114 using OMB83 and OMB84 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB86.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-50"><title>pMB175 (pMT464-zitP<sup>1-133WT</sup>-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The PopZ coding sequence was PCR amplified from NA1000 using the OMB78 and OMB79 primers adding an <italic>Eco</italic>RI plus an RBS and an <italic>Xba</italic>I site respectively. This fragment was digested with <italic>Eco</italic>RI/<italic>Xba</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Eco</italic>RI/<italic>Xba</italic>I -digested pMB93.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-51"><title>pMB177 (pMT464-zitP<sup>1-133W35I</sup>-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The PopZ coding sequence was PCR amplified from NA1000 using the OMB78 and OMB79 primers adding an <italic>Eco</italic>RI plus an RBS and an <italic>Xba</italic>I site respectively. This fragment was digested with <italic>Eco</italic>RI/<italic>Xba</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Eco</italic>RI/<italic>Xba</italic>I -digested pMB113.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-52"><title>pSC</title><p>: pSC is a derivative of pET26b (Novagen) in which expression of the protein of interest is in frame with a coding sequence for C-terminal thrombin cleavage site and a His<sub>6</sub>-tag. The coding sequence can be cloned between <italic>Nde</italic>I and <italic>Xho</italic>I. An <italic>Nhe</italic>I site was also introduced after the stop codon that enables an easy construction of polycistronic synthetic genes.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-53"><title>pMB64 (pSC-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The PopZ coding sequence (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>) was PCR amplified from fragment 16 using Van and T7 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xho</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xho</italic>I-digested pSC.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-54"><title>pMB54 (pSC-<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-90</sup>)</title><p>The first 270 nt of the ZitP coding sequence (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>) was PCR amplified from fragment 17 using Van and T7 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xho</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xho</italic>I-digested pSC.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-55"><title>pET28a-<italic>zitP<sup>Cterm</sup></italic></title><p>The <italic>zitP</italic>-coding sequence lacking the first 189 bp from the start codon (nt 1082122–1082481) was PCR amplified from the NA1000 strain using the zitP_Cterm_nde and zitP_Cterm_eco primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and cloned into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pET28a (Novagen).</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-56"><title>pSC-<italic>zitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>-43WT</sup></title><p>The first 129 nt of the ZitP coding sequence (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>) was PCR amplified from fragment 17 using zitP1-43_fw_NdeI and zitP1-43_fw_XhoI primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xho</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xho</italic>I-digested pSC.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-57"><title>pMB140 (pSC-<italic>zitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>-43W35I</sup>)</title><p>The first 129 nt of the ZitP coding sequence (carrying the W35I mutation and codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>) was PCR amplified from fragment 19 using Van and T7 primers. This fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xho</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xho</italic>I-digested pSC.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-58"><title>pMB233 (pSRK-<italic>dendra2</italic>-<italic>parB</italic>)</title><p>The <italic>dendra2</italic> and <italic>parB</italic> coding sequence were PCR amplified from pXdendra2N2 with OMB18 and OMB134 and from NA1000 with OMB130 and OMB131 respectively. These fragment were digested with <italic>NdeI</italic>/<italic>BamHI</italic> and <italic>Bam</italic>HI/<italic>Hin</italic>dIII and triple ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Hin</italic>dIII-digested pSRK.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-59"><title>pMB267 (pBAD22-<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The <italic>mCherry</italic> coding sequence was PCR amplified using the OMB35 and OMB36 and <italic>popZ</italic> was PCR amplified from pMB21 using the van and M13(−20) primers. These fragments were digested with <italic>Nco</italic>I/<italic>Nde</italic>I and <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I respectively and triple ligated into <italic>Nco</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pBAD22.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-60"><title>pMB224 (pBAD22-<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>zitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>−133</sup>-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The <italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-133</sup>-<italic>popZ</italic> was digested from pMB175 using <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I enzyme and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB267.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-61"><title>pMB225 (pBAD22-<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>zitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>-133(W35I)</sup>-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The <italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-133(W35I)</sup>-<italic>popZ</italic> was digested from pMB177 using <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I enzyme and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB267.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-62"><title>pMB255 (pMT464-<italic>zitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>−90</sup>)</title><p>The <italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-90</sup> coding sequence was PCR amplified from NA1000 using the 2215sh_ndeI and OMB13 primers. The fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pMT464.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-63"><title>pMB256 (pMT464-<italic>zitP</italic>)</title><p>The <italic>zitP</italic> coding sequence was PCR amplified from NA1000 using the 2215sh_ndeI and CC2215_E primers. The fragment was digested with <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pMT464.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-64"><title>pMB257 (pMT464-<italic>zitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>−90</sup>-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The <italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-90</sup> coding sequence was digested from pMB255 using <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pMB175.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-65"><title>pMB258 (pMT464-<italic>zitP</italic>-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The <italic>zitP</italic> coding sequence was digested from pMB256 using <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pMB175.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-66"><title>pMB265 (pMT464-<italic>zitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>-104(Rm)</sup>-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The ZnR from <italic>R. massiliae</italic> and its transmembrane domain (<italic>zitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>-104(Rm)</sup>) coding sequence was digested from pMB114 using <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Eco</italic>RI-digested pMB175.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10-67"><title>pMB266 (pBAD22-<italic>mCherry</italic>-<italic>zitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>-104(Rm)</sup>-<italic>popZ</italic>)</title><p>The (<italic>ZitP<sup>1</sup></italic><sup>-104(Rm)</sup>)-<italic>popZ</italic> co-expression construct was digested from pMB265 using <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into <italic>Nde</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pMB267.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Synthetic fragment used in this study</title><sec id="s4-11-1"><title>Fragment 1 : <italic>Astex_3267</italic><sup>1-80</sup></title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaaGAGCTCTGATGCTGCTGACGTGCCCGAAGTGCGCCCTGTCGTACGCGATCGATGGTGCGCAGCTGGGCCCCCAGGGCCGCACGGTGCGCTGCGCCAGCTGTAAGACCACCTGGCACGCCGAGAAGCCGGAGGAGCCGATCGAGCTGCCCCTCGAGAAGGCCGTCGAAAAGCCCGCGACGGGCCTGAAGGAGGTGAAGGCCAAGAAGATCCCGAGCCTGTACCGCGACATGATCGAGAGCCAGAAGCGCTGAGAATTCtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-2"><title>Fragment 2 : <italic>Mmar10_2373</italic><sup>1-90</sup></title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaagagctcccATGTCGATCGTCCTGTCCTGCCCCTCGTGTACCACCCGCTATCGCGCGAACCCGAATGCCATCGGCACGAATGGCCGCCGCGTGCGTTGCGCCTCGTGCGGCCACGTGTGGACCGCCGAGGTGGAAGATCCCTCGGATCTGCCGTCGCTCCAGCCGGCCCCCCCGGTCACGCCGGAAGCGCCGGCCGAAGAAGCGGGCGCCGAAAAGAAGGTCCACACGGCCTTCCGCGAGCGCCAGGAGAAGAAGCGGCGTACGCTGTCCtgaattctatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-3"><title>Fragment 3 : <italic>Cseg_28671</italic><sup>1-90</sup></title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaaGAGCTCCCATGATCCTGACGTGCCCGGAATGCGCCAGCCGTTATTTCGTGGACGACAGCAAGGTCGGTCCGGAAGGTCGCGTCGTCCGCTGTGCCGCCTGTGGCCATCGGTGGACGGCGCGCAATGAAGATGCCACCGATCTGTTCGAAGATCCGGAAAACCCCTCGCTGGCCTCGCGTGGTGCCGCGGATGTCGCCACGGCCAGCGCCGAAGAACCCCCCCAACCGGAAGCGGCGGAAGAACCCCCGGTGTCGGCGCTGCCGGGTGAAGAGCTGTGAATTCtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-4"><title>Fragment 4 : <italic>HMPREF0185_02600</italic><sup>1-50</sup></title><p>aggatttcgcgctggtcagacaaGAGCTCTGATGATCCTGACCTGCCCGGCTTGCGCTACCTCTTACTTCGTTCCGGACGAAGCTATCGGTCCGAACGGTCGTCGTGTTCGTTGCAAAACCTGCGGTCACGACTGGCGTGCTTCTCTGGAAGACGCTCCGCTGGAACTGGAACCGGCTTGAATTCagctatgaccatgattacggatt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-5"><title>Fragment 5 : <italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43W35I</sup></title><p>tcaagaccggtttagaggccccaaGAGCTCTAATGATACTGACCTGCCCGGAGTGCGCCAGCCGCTATTTCGTCGACGACTCCAAGGTCGGGCCGGACGGTCGCGTCGTGCGTTGCGCCTCTTGCGGCAATCGCATCACCGCCTTCAAGGACGAAGCTGAATGAattctatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-6"><title>Fragment 6 : <italic>zitP<sup>1-43R24A/R27A</sup></italic></title><p>TCGTGACGTTCGTTGCTCTAACTGCGGTCACGGTATGATACTGACCTGCCCGGAGTGCGCCAGCCGCTATTTCGTCGACGACTCCAAGGTCGGGCCGGACGGTGCCGTCGTGGCCTGCGCCTCTTGCGGCAATCGCTGGACCGCCTTCAAGGACGAAGCTGAATGAATTCtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-7"><title>Fragment 7 : <italic>Rsph17025_2450</italic><sup>1-43WT</sup></title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaaGAGCTCTGATGCGTCTGATCTGCCCGAACTGCGACGCTCAGTACGAAGTTTCTGACGACGCTATCCCGCCGGAAGGTCGTGACGTTCAGTGCTCTAACTGCGGTCACGGTTGGTTCCAGCGTCCGGTTTCTCTGGCTTGAATTCaggatttcgcgctggtcagacaa</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-8"><title>Fragment 8 : <italic>Rsph17025_2450</italic><sup>1-43Q24R</sup></title><p>TCGTGACGTTCGTTGCTCTAACTGCGGTCACGGTATGCGTCTGATCTGCCCGAACTGCGACGCTCAGTACGAAGTTTCTGACGACGCTATCCCGCCGGAAGGTCGTGACGTTCGTTGCTCTAACTGCGGTCACGGTTGGTTCCAGCGTCCGGTTTCTCTGGCTTGAATTCaggatttcgcgctggtcagacaa</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-9"><title>Fragment 9 : <italic>RMB_01390</italic><sup>1-50WT</sup></title><p>aggatttcgcgctggtcagacaaGAGCTCTGATGTATATCACCTGCCCGAACTGCCAGACCCGTTTTATCGTTACCTCTAACCAGATCGGCATCAACGGTCGTCGTGTTAAATGCTCTAAATGCTCCCACCTGTGGTACCAGAAGCTGGACTACAACACCTCTACTCTGAACGACTTCAAATGAATTCagctatgaccatgattacggatt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-10"><title>Fragment 10 : <italic>RMB_01390</italic><sup>1-50W35I</sup></title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaaGAGCTCTGATGTATATCACCTGCCCGAACTGCCAGACCCGTTTTATCGTTACCTCTAACCAGATCGGCATCAACGGTCGTCGTGTTAAATGCTCTAAATGCTCCCACCTGATCTACCAGAAGCTGGACTACAACACCTCTACTCTGAACGACTTCAAATGAATTCaggatttcgcgctggtcagacaa</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-11"><title>Fragment 11 : <italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-133CS</sup></title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaaAACATATGTCGATCCGCAAGGCGCGTCACTGGGCTTTCTGGACATCAGGGTTAAAATCAGCGACCCCAGTAAGTTATGTGGGGTTCGTTCGATTCGCGGCCATGATACTGACCTCCCCGGAGTCCGCCAGCCGCTATTTCGTCGACGACTCCAAGGTCGGGCCGGACGGTCGCGTCGTGCGTTCCGCCTCTTCCGGCAATCGCTGGACCGCCTTCAAGGACGAAGCTGAAGAGCTGCTCGACCTCTTCGAAGAGCCTGCCGCCGCCAGCGCCAGATCCCAGGGTGATCGCGACGAAGCCGCGGAAGAAGCCGTCGCCGCCGAGGCCGAAGAGCCACCGGTCAGCGCGCTTCCGGGCGAAGAACTTCTTtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-12"><title>Fragment 12 : <italic>zitP<sup>1-133W35I</sup></italic> (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>)</title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaacatATGATCCTGACGTGCCCCGAATGCGCCTCGCGTTATTTTGTGGATGATTCCAAGGTCGGTCCCGATGGTCGTGTGGTCCGTTGTGCCAGCTGTGGTAATCGTATCACGGCCTTTAAGGATGAAGCGGAAGAACTGCTGGATCTGTTTGAAGAACCGGCGGCGGCCAGCGCCCGTAGCCAAGGTGATCGTGATGAAGCGGCGGAAGAAGCGGTGGCCGCCGAAGCGGAAGAACCGCCGGTCAGCGCCCTGCCCGGTGAAGAACTGCCCAAGGTCTTTCGCGCGCGTGCGGATGCCGAACGTCGTCTGCGTGCGGCGACCGCCACCGGCGTGATCTGGGCCGGTATGGCGGCCGCCATGGCGGTCGTCGTCGTGGCGGCCCTGATCTTTCGTATCGATTGAATTCtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-13"><title>Fragment 13 : <italic>zitP<sup>1-132malF</sup></italic> (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>)</title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaaCATATGATTCTGACCTGTCCGGAATGTGCATCTCGCTACTTTGTTGACGACAGCAAGGTTGGCCCGGACGGTCGTGTTGTACGTTGTGCGTCTTGTGGCAACCGTTGGACCGCTTTCAAAGACGAAGCAGAAGAACTGCTGGATCTGTTTGAGGAGCCGGCTGCTGCATCCGCGCGTAGCCAGGGCGATCGTGACGAAGCTGCGGAAGAAGCTGTAGCGGCAGAAGCGGAAGAGCCGCCGGTTAGCGCGCTGCCGGGTGAAGAACTGCCGAAGGTGTTCCGTGCCCGCGCTGATGCGGAACGCCGTCTGCGTGCGGCTCTGAAATGGTCCGTACTGGGTCTGCTGGGCCTGCTGGTTGGTTACCTGGTTGTTCTGATGTACGCCTGAATTCtctagaatatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-14"><title>Fragment 14 : <italic>HMPREF0185_02600</italic><sup>1-121WT</sup> (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>)</title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaaCATATGATCCTGACGTGTCCGGCGTGTGCGACCTCGTATTTTGTCCCGGATGAAGCCATCGGTCCCAATGGTCGTCGTGTCCGTTGTAAGACCTGTGGTCATGATTGGCGTGCCTCGCTGGAAGATGCCCCGCTGGAACTGGAACCCGCGACCGAAGGTCTGAGCCCGGCGGCCGATCCGGCGAGCGAAACCCTCCCCGAATCCCTGGCCGAAACCCCGGCCCCCGAACTGCCGCGTGCCTTTCGTGCCCGTGCCGAACGTAAGCGTCGTACCCGTCAAGCTGCTGCTGCTGGTGCTGCTTGGGCTGCTGCTGCTGCCGTCGTTTTGGGTTTGATTACGGGTGGTGTTTTGTTTCGTGAAGAATGAATTCtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-15"><title>Fragment 15 : <italic>RMB_01390</italic><sup>1-102WT</sup> (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>)</title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaaCATATGTACATCACCTGTCCGAACTGCCAGACCCGCTTCATCGTCACGTCGAATCAGATCGGCATCAACGGCCGTCGCGTGAAGTGCTCGAAGTGCTCCCATCTGTGGTATCAGAAGCTCGATTACAATACGAGCACCCTGAACGACTTCAAGGACAAGGTCAACACGGGCACCATCAAGACGCCGATCAAGAATCACTATAACGCGAACGTCCCGGTCATCCTGCCGTACATGCCCCCGAAGAAGAAGTATAACATCTTTCCGATCCTGTGGACCTCGTTCATCATCTTCTGCCTCGTGATCCTGCTGATCGACTGAattctatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-16"><title>Fragment 16 : <italic>popZ</italic> (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>)</title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaacatCATATGTCTGATCAAAGCCAAGAGCCCACGATGGAGGAAATCCTTGCGAGCATTCGTCGCATCATCTCTGAAGATGATGCCCCCGCGGAACCAGCCGCTGAAGCGGCCCCACCTCCTCCTCCTGAGCCGGAACCTGAACCGGTTTCGTTTGACGACGAAGTGCTGGAACTGACTGACCCGATTGCACCTGAACCGGAGCTGCCGCCGCTTGAAACCGTAGGCGACATTGATGTTTACTCTCCCCCGGAACCGGAATCTGAACCGGCGTATACCCCGCCGCCTGCGGCTCCTGTGTTCGACCGTGATGAAGTGGCGGAACAACTGGTTGGCGTATCAGCTGCGTCTGCAGCGGCGAGTGCGTTTGGCTCTTTGTCGAGTGCATTACTGATGCCTAAGGACGGCCGTACCTTAGAAGACGTAGTGCGCGAACTGCTTCGCCCCCTGCTGAAAGAATGGCTGGATCAGAACTTGCCGCGTATTGTGGAGACGAAAGTTGAAGAAGAAGTCCAGCGCATTTCTCGCGGCCGTGGCGCCCTCGAGtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-17"><title>Fragment 17 : <italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-90</sup> (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>)</title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaacatCATATGATCCTGACTTGTCCGGAATGTGCCAGCCGTTATTTCGTCGACGACTCTAAAGTTGGTCCGGATGGCCGTGTTGTCCGTTGCGCGTCTTGCGGTAACCGCTGGACGGCATTCAAAGATGAAGCTGAAGAACTGCTGGATCTGTTTGAGGAACCGGCTGCTGCTTCTGCACGTTCCCAAGGTGATCGTGATGAAGCGGCGGAAGAGGCCGTTGCTGCAGAAGCCGAAGAGCCGCCGGTTTCTGCTCTGCCAGGCGAAGAACTGCCGAAACTCGAGtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-18"><title>Fragment 18 :<italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43R27Q/W35I(Rs)</sup></title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaacatGAGCTCTGATGCGTCTGATCTGCCCGAACTGCGACGCTCAGTACGAAGTTTCTGACGACGCTATCCCGCCGGAAGGTCGTGACGTTCGTTGCTCTAACTGCGGTCACGGTatcTTCCAGCGTCCGGTTTCTCTGGCTTGAGAATTCtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-19"><title>Fragment 19 : <italic>zitP</italic><sup>1-43W35I</sup> (codon optimized for <italic>E. coli</italic>)</title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaaCATATGATCCTGACTTGTCCGGAATGTGCCAGCCGTTATTTCGTCGACGACTCTAAAGTTGGTCCGGATGGCCGTGTTGTCCGTTGCGCGTCTTGCGGTAACCGCATTACGGCATTCAAAGATGAAGCTGAACTCGAGtatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-20"><title>Fragment 20 : <italic>agmX</italic><sup>1-90</sup></title><p>gccgaccgactgagacgctcacaagagctcTGATGCGCTTTGTCTGTGATAGCTGCCGCGCCCAGTATATGATCTCGGACGACAAGATCGGCCCGAAGGGCGTCAAGGTCCGTTGCAAGAAGTGCGGCCATACCATCACCGTCCGGCCCGCCGGCGCGACCGCGGCCAAGGATTCCGCGTCGGAAAGCAGCACCTCGGAGGCCTCGGCGTCGACCGACGTCGGCAAGGGCTCGGATGCGTCCGCCGCGACGATGCCGGCGACCCTGGGCACCtgaattctatagtgagtcgtattaattt</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Lucy Shapiro for materials and Antonio Frandi for help with ChIP-Seq analyses. Funding support is from the Swiss National Science Foundation (to PHV, to FHA and to SM) and the Novartis Consumer Health Foundation (to MB).</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf1"><p>The authors declare that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>MB, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article, Contributed unpublished essential data or reagents</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>SC, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article, Contributed unpublished essential data or reagents</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>JM, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article, Contributed unpublished essential data or reagents</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>SH, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Contributed unpublished essential data or reagents</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>LT, Acquisition of data, Contributed unpublished essential data or reagents</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>SM, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>FH-TA, Conception and design, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>PHV, Conception and design, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="SD1-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.016</object-id><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>NMR and refinement statistics of ZitP<sup>(1-43)</sup>.</title><p>Data used to derive the NMR solution structure.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.016">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.016</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-supp1-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SD2-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.017</object-id><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>List of strains, plasmids and oligonucleotides.</title><p>Details on strain and plasmid constructions and the oligonucleotides that were used.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.017">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.017</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-20640-supp2-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material><sec id="s7" sec-type="datasets"><title>Major datasets</title><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><related-object content-type="generated-dataset" id="data-ro1" source-id="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE79918" source-id-type="uri"><collab>Matthieu Bergé</collab><x>,</x> <collab>Patrick H Viollier</collab><x>,</x> <year>2016</year><x>,</x><source>ChIP-Seq</source><x>,</x> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE79918">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE79918</ext-link><x>,</x> <comment>Publicly available at the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (accession no. GSE79918)</comment></related-object></p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson-Furgeson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zupan</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Grangeon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zambryski</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Loss of PodJ in agrobacterium tumefaciens leads to ectopic polar growth, branching, and reduced cell division</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>198</volume><fpage>1883</fpage><lpage>1991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00198-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27137498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zomorodipour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Sicheritz-Pontén</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsmark</surname><given-names>UC</given-names></name><name><surname>Podowski</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Näslund</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurland</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>The genome sequence of rickettsia prowazekii and the origin of mitochondria</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>396</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/24094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9823893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Betzig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sougrat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindwasser</surname><given-names>OW</given-names></name><name><surname>Olenych</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonifacino</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippincott-Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Imaging intracellular fluorescent proteins at nanometer resolution</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>313</volume><fpage>1642</fpage><lpage>1645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1127344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16902090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biteen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Goley</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moerner</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Three-dimensional super-resolution imaging of the midplane protein FtsZ in live Caulobacter crescentus cells using astigmatism</article-title><source>ChemPhysChem</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1007</fpage><lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cphc.201100686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Comolli</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaietta</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellisman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Caulobacter PopZ forms a polar subdomain dictating sequential changes in pole composition and function</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07088.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20149103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Comolli</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moerner</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Earnest</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>A polymeric protein anchors the chromosomal origin/ParB complex at a bacterial cell pole</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>945</fpage><lpage>955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18805088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ptacin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ighodaro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Folta-Stogniew</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Comolli</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Oligomerization and higher-order assembly contribute to sub-cellular localization of a bacterial scaffold</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>776</fpage><lpage>795</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.12398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24102805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brilli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fondi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazzicalupo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Biondi</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The diversity and evolution of cell cycle regulation in alpha-proteobacteria: a comparative genomic analysis</article-title><source>BMC Systems Biology</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>52</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-4-52</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20426835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Pedro</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kysela</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Henst</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bolle</surname><suffix>X</suffix></name><name><surname>Fuqua</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Polar growth in the alphaproteobacterial order rhizobiales</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>1697</fpage><lpage>1701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1114476109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22307633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Viollier</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>A membrane metalloprotease participates in the sequential degradation of a Caulobacter polarity determinant</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>1085</fpage><lpage>1103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04443.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15686556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Abeliuk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalogeraki</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Passarelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Coller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fero</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>The essential genome of a bacterium</article-title><source>Molecular Systems Biology</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>528</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb.2011.58</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21878915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beusch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bösch</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerletti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores-Tinoco</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Medico</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Christen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Quantitative selection analysis of bacteriophage φcbk susceptibility in caulobacter crescentus</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source><volume>428</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2015.11.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26593064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Getting in the loop: regulation of development in caulobacter crescentus</article-title><source>Microbiology and Molecular Biology Reviews</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00040-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20197497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Identification of essential alphaproteobacterial genes reveals operational variability in conserved developmental and cell cycle systems</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>93</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.12686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24975755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldor</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Establishing polar identity in gram-negative rods</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Microbiology</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2013.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24029491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Siervo</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Homola</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1980">1980</year><article-title>Analysis of caulobacter crescentus lipids</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>143</volume><fpage>1215</fpage><lpage>1222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7410318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Siervo</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1985">1985</year><article-title>High levels of glycolipid and low levels of phospholipid in a marine caulobacter</article-title><source>Journal of bacteriology</source><volume>164</volume><fpage>684</fpage><lpage>688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4055697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deghelt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sternon</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Laloux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dotreppe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Henst</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs-Wagner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Letesson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bolle</surname><suffix>X</suffix></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>G1-arrested newborn cells are the predominant infectious form of the pathogen brucella abortus</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>5366</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms5366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25006695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebersbach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Briegel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs-Wagner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>A self-associating protein critical for chromosome attachment, division, and polar organization in caulobacter</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>956</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.07.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18805089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ely</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Genetics of caulobacter crescentus</article-title><source>Methods in Enzymology</source><volume>204</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0076-6879(91)04019-k</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1658564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grangeon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zupan</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson-Furgeson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zambryski</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>PopZ identifies the new pole, and PodJ identifies the old pole during polar growth in agrobacterium tumefaciens</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>11666</fpage><lpage>11671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1515544112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26324921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Belin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Tight regulation, modulation, and high-level expression by vectors containing the arabinose PBAD promoter</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>177</volume><fpage>4121</fpage><lpage>4130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.177.14.4121-4130.1995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7608087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haglund</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Skau</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovar</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Rickettsia Sca2 is a bacterial formin-like mediator of actin-based motility</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1057</fpage><lpage>1063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20972427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hallez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellefontaine</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Letesson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bolle</surname><suffix>X</suffix></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Morphological and functional asymmetry in alpha-proteobacteria</article-title><source>Trends in Microbiology</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2004.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15276611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pengo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meibom</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez Fernandez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Manley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>High throughput 3d super-resolution microscopy reveals caulobacter crescentus in vivo Z-ring organization</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>4566</fpage><lpage>4571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1313368111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Follett</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Meadows</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title><italic>Caulobacter</italic> PopZ forms an intrinsically disordered hub in organizing bacterial cell poles</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>12490</fpage><lpage>12495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1602380113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><name><surname>Huitema</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Keiler</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>Viollier</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Protein localization and dynamics within a bacterial organelle</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>5599</fpage><lpage>5604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0909119107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20212131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huitema</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matteson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Viollier</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Bacterial birth scar proteins mark future flagellum assembly site</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>1025</fpage><lpage>1037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.01.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16530048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roop</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrand</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Broad-host-range expression vectors with tightly regulated promoters and their use to examine the influence of TraR and TraM expression on Ti plasmid quorum sensing</article-title><source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>5053</fpage><lpage>5062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01098-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18606801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Viollier</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Poles apart: prokaryotic polar organelles and their spatial regulation</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>a006809</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a006809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21084387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The discovery of zinc fingers and their applications in gene regulation and genome manipulation</article-title><source>Annual Review of Biochemistry</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-biochem-010909-095056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kornhaber</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moseley</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Montelione</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Identification of zinc-ligated cysteine residues based on 13calpha and 13cbeta chemical shift data</article-title><source>Journal of Biomolecular NMR</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10858-006-0027-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16645816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kühn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Briegel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mörschel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahnt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thanbichler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Bactofilins, a ubiquitous class of cytoskeletal proteins mediating polar localization of a cell wall synthase in Caulobacter crescentus</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2009.358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19959992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Koschwanez</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Evolutionary adaptation after crippling cell polarization follows reproducible trajectories</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e09638</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.09638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26426479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laloux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs-Wagner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Spatiotemporal control of PopZ localization through cell cycle-coupled multimerization</article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>201</volume><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201303036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23751494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schofield</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs-Wagner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>A landmark protein essential for establishing and perpetuating the polarity of a bacterial cell</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>1011</fpage><lpage>1023</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2005.12.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16530047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenarcic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Halbedel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Errington</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marenduzzo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamoen</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Localisation of DivIVA by targeting to negatively curved membranes</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>2272</fpage><lpage>2282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2009.129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19478798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Surovtsev</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltran</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bewersdorf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs-Wagner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Evidence for a DNA-relay mechanism in ParABS-mediated chromosome segregation</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e02758</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24859756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madasu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kast</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovar</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Rickettsia Sca2 has evolved formin-like activity through a different molecular mechanism</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>E2677</fpage><lpage>E2686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1307235110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro-Rojas</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Teiling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapatral</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Walunas</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The genetic basis of laboratory adaptation in caulobacter crescentus</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>192</volume><fpage>3678</fpage><lpage>3688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00255-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20472802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkowitz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Cell polarization in budding and fission yeasts</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiology Reviews</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6976.12055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24354645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mignolet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Panis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Eroglu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Theraulaz L</surname></name><name><surname>Manley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Viollier</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Functional dichotomy and distinct nanoscale assemblies of a cell cyclecontrolled bipolar zinc-finger regulator</article-title><source>eLife</source><elocation-id>e18647</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.18647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Khokhrina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Guilbride</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lisby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiebel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Compartment-specific aggregases direct distinct nuclear and cytoplasmic aggregate deposition</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>778</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201489524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25672362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohl</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gober</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Cell cycle-dependent polar localization of chromosome partitioning proteins in <italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81910-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9054507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauriello</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zusman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>A multi-protein complex from myxococcus xanthus required for bacterial gliding motility</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>1539</fpage><lpage>1554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07184.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20487265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ptacin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gahlmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>von Diezmann</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckart</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moerner</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Bacterial scaffold directs pole-specific centromere segregation</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>E2046</fpage><lpage>E2055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1405188111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24778223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ptacin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Comolli</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moerner</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>A spindle-like apparatus guides bacterial chromosome segregation</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20657594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramamurthi</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Losick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Negative membrane curvature as a cue for subcellular localization of a bacterial protein</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>13541</fpage><lpage>13545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0906851106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19666580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattoni</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rech</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmeggiani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nollmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouet</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Stochastic Self-Assembly of ParB proteins builds the bacterial DNA segregation apparatus</article-title><source>Cell Systems</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cels.2015.07.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27135801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schofield</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs-Wagner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Cell cycle coordination and regulation of bacterial chromosome segregation dynamics by polarly localized proteins</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>3068</fpage><lpage>3081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2010.207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20802464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Losick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Generating and exploiting polarity in bacteria</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>298</volume><fpage>1942</fpage><lpage>1946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1072163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>St Johnston</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahringer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Cell polarity in eggs and epithelia: parallels and diversity</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>141</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2010.05.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20510924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strahl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamoen</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Finding the corners in a cell</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Microbiology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2012.10.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23182676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thanbichler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iniesta</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>A comprehensive set of plasmids for vanillate- and xylose-inducible gene expression in Caulobacter crescentus</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>35</volume><elocation-id>e137</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17959646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thanbichler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>MipZ, a spatial regulator coordinating chromosome segregation with cell division in Caulobacter</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.05.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16839883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treuner-Lange</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Søgaard-Andersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Regulation of cell polarity in bacteria</article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>206</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201403136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25002676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viollier</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thanbichler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Meewan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Rapid and sequential movement of individual chromosomal loci to specific subcellular locations during bacterial DNA replication</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>9257</fpage><lpage>9262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0402606101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15178755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Structural insights into the interaction of the crenarchaeal chromatin protein Cren7 with DNA</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07136.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20345658</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="article-commentary" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.021</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Veening</surname><given-names>Jan Willem</given-names></name><aff id="aff5"><institution>University of Groningen</institution>, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Modularity and determinants of a (bi-)polarization control system from free-living and obligate intracellular bacteria&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by two peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Vivek Malhotra as the Senior Editor. The following individual involved in review of your submission has agreed to reveal his identity: Grant Bowman (Reviewer #3).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission</p><p>Summary:</p><p>The reviewers find that the identification and characterization of ZitP are highly interesting and contribute to our understanding of cell polarity in bacteria. The experiments are, in general, well-designed and the paper is clearly written. The very data rich paper demonstrates that ZitP is a factor that contributes to the positioning of PopZ. However, the conclusions on its role in origin segregation are less well supported and the authors make a few overinterpretations of their results, and these should be corrected before the manuscript is ready for publication. Some of these interpretations would be strengthened by additional supporting experiments, and others would be best left out of the manuscript.</p><p>Central conclusions:</p><p>1) The Zn-finger domain of ZitP is sufficient for interaction with PopZ, whereas its association with the membrane is critical for its function.</p><p>2) ZitP is found to associate, directly or indirectly, with sites flanking the PopZ/ParB-associated centromeric <italic>parS</italic> sites.</p><p>3) Deletion of ZitP or overexpression leads to defects in PopZ and ParB localization.</p><p>4) ZitP is able to mediate the redistribution of PopZ to both cell poles upon co-overexpression with PopZ in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> and in a heterologous <italic>E. coli</italic> system.</p><p>5) Similar properties are observed for ZitP homologues from various α-proteobacterial species, suggesting that the function of the protein is widely conserved in this lineage.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>The reviewers raise a number of concerns that must be adequately addressed before the paper can be accepted. Some of the required revisions will likely require further experimentation.</p><p>In general we propose to remove some of the data concerning the claim that ZitP affects chromosome segregation as the current data does not fully supports this. The manuscript says important things about PopZ and cell polarity, including issues related to chromosome segregation. Focusing the paper on the ZitP-PopZ part will also make the paper more accessible to non Caulobacter readers.</p><p>Thus, instead of doing the proposed experiments listed below, some of the points listed can be solved by either downplaying the claims made and/or removing the data.</p><p>1) The conclusion that ZitP has a role in origin segregation that goes beyond controlling PopZ localization is not supported by the data:</p><p>A) The ChIP-seq results may be explained by the fact that ZipP is associated with the membrane-proximal surface of the PopZ complex and, therefore, located in the vicinity of the DNA regions flanking the PopZ-associated ParB-<italic>parS</italic> complex. The results obtained for PopZ may reflect a similar situation: crosslinking to the <italic>parS</italic> region itself may be less efficient because it requires the isolation of a tripartite complex consisting of PopZ, ParB and <italic>parS</italic> DNA, whereas crosslinking to the flanking regions that are not covered by ParB but still in the immediate proximity of PopZ may be more effective. The experiment using the mCherry-PopZ strain and an anti-RFP antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, bottom row) should be performed in a strain lacking ZitP.</p><p>B) The synthetic effects caused by the deletion of zitP in the different popZ mutant backgrounds do not necessarily indicate a direct role of ZitP in ParAB regulation. All the defects in ParB localization observed are likely explained by the aberrant formation and localization of PopZ clusters, which in turn may affect the positioning of ParB-<italic>parS</italic> complexes or the localization/function of ParA and, thus, the control of cell division by the MipZ system. As shown by Ptacin et al. (2014), the mutant forms of PopZ are not fully defective in ParA/ParB binding but still show some affinity for the two proteins. Thus, the deletion of ZitP and the consequent changes in the efficiency/reliability of PopZ localization may simply aggravate the defects caused by the mutation of PopZ and thus enhance the segregation defects of the mutant strains. In agreement with this notion, the severity of the phenotype in all cases corresponds to the severity of the defect in PopZ localization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). Similarly, the effects of zitP overexpression (stalling of ParB movement, displacement of monomeric ParA) may all be explained by the strongly aberrant PopZ localization patterns induced in this condition and their effects on ParB localization and ParA function. In my eyes, there is no evidence for the statement that &quot;ZitP controls ParAB through a new mechanism that does not involved the known ParAB interaction sites in PopZ but unknown regions flanking the centromere&quot;.</p><p>2) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B</xref>: The elution profile for ZitP needs to be shown to allow a definitive conclusion on the interaction between PopZ and ZitP.</p><p>3) The main function of ZitP appears to be the attachment of PopZ to the membrane, which in turn helps to establish the bipolar PopZ localization pattern. Is PopZ in the <italic>C. crescentus</italic> Δ<italic>zitP</italic> mutant no longer membrane-associated (even though its subcellular distribution is largely unchanged)? This could be clarified by PALM analysis of suitable <italic>C. crescentus</italic> strains. Similarly, it would be interesting to see that in <italic>E. coli</italic>, PopZ clusters are cytoplasmic and no longer membrane-associated (as suggested in the subsection “ZitP imparts bipolarity upon PopZ in <italic>E. coli</italic>”, first paragraph).</p><p>4) The results shown for RpZitP and RpPopZ in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref> are not as clear as for those obtained for the <italic>C. crescentus</italic> proteins. The data obtained for the rickettsial proteins should be quantified.</p><p>5) From the evidence presented in this manuscript, it is clear that PopZ directs the localization of ZitP. However, the authors also strive to prove the reverse – that ZitP directs PopZ localization. They succeed in showing this under two circumstances – co-expression of proteins in <italic>E. coli</italic> and in the context of overproduction of ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> in Caulobacter. At times, the authors seem to be drawing too strong of a conclusion from these results, as the same might be expected of any protein that binds to PopZ. Thus, ZitP's role in directing PopZ may not be unique, especially if PopZ has many binding partners. The possibility of many binding partners may be inferred from the fact that nearly all ST proteins (in addition to the chromosome centromere and ParA/B are delocalized in a <italic>popZ</italic> knockout background (Bowman et al. 2010). To support the claim that ZitP has a physiological role in directing PopZ localization, they also show that zitP knockouts enhance the cell division phenotype in PopZ mutant backgrounds where PopZ cannot interact with ParA/B. This is a critical result that bears further exploration. First, the authors should determine whether interaction with PopZ is needed for rescue by testing the effects of rescuing the PopZ<sup>KE/KEP</sup> mutant with the W35I mutant of ZitP. Additionally, the authors should ask which parts of ZitP are critical for the rescuing effect by adding back different sections of ZitP into the PopZ<sup>KE</sup> and/or KEP background. If ZitP<sup>1-133</sup>is sufficient to rescue the phenotype and ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> is not, this suggests that membrane anchoring and not just interaction with PopZ is important for proper polar localization of PopZ. If full length ZitP is required, it suggests an important functional role for the C-terminal domain. If ZitP<sup>1-43</sup> is sufficient, the model that ZitP directs PopZ localization will likely require some adjustment.</p><p>6) Chromatin-IP starts with formaldehyde x-linking, which binds any near neighbors to DNA. Thus, interaction between ZitP and DNA may not be direct or even indirect in the formal sense. It is likely that indirect binding to DNA was observed for PopZ, as sequence-dependent association with DNA probably occurs through ParB/ParA. However, we also know that centromeres reside near poles in Caulobacter cells, and that the poles also have PopZ. Thus, some of the binding observed by ChIP-seq may have occurred merely because PopZ and the centromere are in proximity – not from a direct or even an indirect connection between protein and DNA. Similarly, it seems possible that ZitP is merely in the vicinity of centromere by virtue of its interaction with PopZ, and not indirectly binding to DNA. The conclusions would be strengthened if the authors could provide more compelling evidence that ZitP isn't interacting with sites near centromeric DNA because it is at the poles and happens to be near DNA that is not otherwise occluded by ParA/ParB/PopZ. If this is not possible, several of the authors' conclusions should be reworded, the issue should be raised in the main text of the manuscript, and mechanisms outside of ZitP-DNA interactions should be discussed.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.022</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p><italic>Essential revisions:</italic> </p><p><italic>The reviewers raise a number of concerns that must be adequately addressed before the paper can be accepted. Some of the required revisions will likely require further experimentation.</italic> </p><p><italic>In general we propose to remove some of the data concerning the claim that ZitP affects chromosome segregation as the current data does not fully supports this. The manuscript says important things about PopZ and cell polarity, including issues related to chromosome segregation. Focusing the paper on the ZitP-PopZ part will also make the paper more accessible to non Caulobacter readers.</italic></p><p><italic>Thus, instead of doing the proposed experiments listed below, some of the points listed can be solved by either downplaying the claims made and/or removing the data.</italic> </p><p><italic>1) The conclusion that ZitP has a role in origin segregation that goes beyond controlling PopZ localization is not supported by the data:</italic> </p><p><italic>A) The ChIP-seq results may be explained by the fact that ZipP is associated with the membrane-proximal surface of the PopZ complex and, therefore, located in the vicinity of the DNA regions flanking the PopZ-associated ParB-parS complex. The results obtained for PopZ may reflect a similar situation: crosslinking to the parS region itself may be less efficient because it requires the isolation of a tripartite complex consisting of PopZ, ParB and parS DNA, whereas crosslinking to the flanking regions that are not covered by ParB but still in the immediate proximity of PopZ may be more effective. The experiment using the mCherry-PopZ strain and an anti-RFP antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, bottom row) should be performed in a strain lacking ZitP.</italic></p><p>We agree and we now de-emphasize this aspect and just show that ZitP associates near <italic>parS</italic> and that this is dependent on PopZ and the N-terminal region that is required that is required for efficient binding of ParAB in <italic>popZ<sup>KE</sup></italic>cells and in <italic>popZ</italic>∆<sup>26</sup>cells. While we still summarize these findings briefly, they are just used as supporting evidence and therefore placed it in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>. We also determined that the association of PopZ with the <italic>parS</italic> region is not influenced by the Δ<italic>zitP</italic> mutation but chose to eliminate this from the manuscript.</p><p><italic>B) The synthetic effects caused by the deletion of zitP in the different popZ mutant backgrounds do not necessarily indicate a direct role of ZitP in ParAB regulation. All the defects in ParB localization observed are likely explained by the aberrant formation and localization of PopZ clusters, which in turn may affect the positioning of ParB-parS complexes or the localization/function of ParA and, thus, the control of cell division by the MipZ system. As shown by Ptacin et al. (2014), the mutant forms of PopZ are not fully defective in ParA/ParB binding but still show some affinity for the two proteins. Thus, the deletion of ZitP and the consequent changes in the efficiency/reliability of PopZ localization may simply aggravate the defects caused by the mutation of PopZ and thus enhance the segregation defects of the mutant strains. In agreement with this notion, the severity of the phenotype in all cases corresponds to the severity of the defect in PopZ localization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). Similarly, the effects of zitP overexpression (stalling of ParB movement, displacement of monomeric ParA) may all be explained by the strongly aberrant PopZ localization patterns induced in this condition and their effects on ParB localization and ParA function. In my eyes, there is no evidence for the statement that &quot;ZitP controls ParAB through a new mechanism that does not involved the known ParAB interaction sites in PopZ but unknown regions flanking the centromere&quot;.</italic> </p><p>We agree with this comment that the effect of ZitP on DNA segregation are mediated by its effect on PopZ localization and we modified the corresponding passage, concluding that ZitP is able to redirect PopZ localization via direct interaction between the two partners and ZitP membrane anchoring.</p><p><italic>2) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B</xref>: The elution profile for ZitP needs to be shown to allow a definitive conclusion on the interaction between PopZ and ZitP.</italic> </p><p>Agreed. This is fixed now and the omitted elution profile added to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B</xref> unambiguously that the two proteins co-elute together, indicative of a direct interaction that we further quantify by ITC in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>.</p><p><italic>3) The main function of ZitP appears to be the attachment of PopZ to the membrane, which in turn helps to establish the bipolar PopZ localization pattern. Is PopZ in the C. crescentus ΔzitP mutant no longer membrane-associated (even though its subcellular distribution is largely unchanged)? This could be clarified by PALM analysis of suitable C. crescentus strains. Similarly, it would be interesting to see that in E. coli, PopZ clusters are cytoplasmic and no longer membrane-associated (as suggested in the subsection “ZitP imparts bipolarity upon PopZ in E. coli”, first paragraph).</italic> </p><p>To address this question, we performed some fractionation experiment in <italic>E. coli</italic> as well as in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> to see if the presence of ZitP could influence the fractionation properties of PopZ in extracts. To do so, we separated extracts from the relevant under- and over-expression strains in soluble and insoluble fractions by centrifugation and then treated the insoluble fraction with different detergents to test if PopZ can be solubilized. Unfortunately, in the presence or absence of ZitP in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> as well as in <italic>E. coli</italic>, the PopZ fractionation profile did not reveal any difference as in all cases PopZ accumulates in the soluble fraction to the same extent. Perhaps PopZ interactions with its partners are labile and disrupted during extract preparation. As the blots were not revealing we did not include them in the manuscript, but we include the data for the fractionation done with proteins expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Author response image 1</xref> (labels are as for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1C</xref> where fractionation of ZitP is shown).<fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.20640.018</object-id><label>Author response image 1.</label><caption><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20640.018">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.20640.018</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="png" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-20640-resp-fig1-v1"/></fig></p><p>The suggested two-color PALM experiments in live cells that would be necessary to reveal the difference between polar membrane-localized PopZ versus polar membrane proximal PopZ could not be done for technical reasons. Additionally, we decided not to push hard to find a solution because it seemed unlikely that a difference would be visible even if the technical problems could be resolved. While it is certainly plausible that ZitP acts as membrane anchor for PopZ, it clearly does act as sole membrane anchor since there are other transmembrane proteins such as DivL and CckA as reported by the Bowman group that interact with PopZ directly and would likely mask the contribution (i.e. membrane association) by ZitP.</p><p><italic>4) The results shown for RpZitP and RpPopZ in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref> are not as clear as for those obtained for the C. crescentus proteins. The data obtained for the rickettsial proteins should be quantified.</italic> </p><p>We now show that membrane-anchored Rickettsial ZitP can induce the formation of bipolar plugs of <italic>C. crescentus</italic> PopZ in <italic>C. crescentus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>) and in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref>). Moreover, Dendra-tagged <italic>C. crescentus</italic> ZitP (full length) can also adopt a bipolar disposition when co-expressed with rickettsial PopZ in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6G</xref>, this is the same figure as shown before, whereas 6B and 6E are new panels).</p><p><italic>5) From the evidence presented in this manuscript, it is clear that PopZ directs the localization of ZitP. However, the authors also strive to prove the reverse – that ZitP directs PopZ localization. They succeed in showing this under two circumstances – co-expression of proteins in E. coli and in the context of overproduction of ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> in Caulobacter. At times, the authors seem to be drawing too strong of a conclusion from these results, as the same might be expected of any protein that binds to PopZ. Thus, ZitP's role in directing PopZ may not be unique, especially if PopZ has many binding partners. The possibility of many binding partners may be inferred from the fact that nearly all ST proteins (in addition to the chromosome centromere and ParA/B are delocalized in a popZ knockout background (Bowman et al. 2010). To support the claim that ZitP has a physiological role in directing PopZ localization, they also show that zitP knockouts enhance the cell division phenotype in PopZ mutant backgrounds where PopZ cannot interact with ParA/B. This is a critical result that bears further exploration. First, the authors should determine whether interaction with PopZ is needed for rescue by testing the effects of rescuing the PopZ KE / KEP mutant with the W35I mutant of ZitP. Additionally, the authors should ask which parts of ZitP are critical for the rescuing effect by adding back different sections of ZitP into the PopZ KE and/or KEP background. If ZitP</italic><sup><italic>1-133</italic></sup> <italic>is sufficient to rescue the phenotype and ZitP</italic><sup><italic>1-43</italic></sup> <italic>is not, this suggests that membrane anchoring and not just interaction with PopZ is important for proper polar localization of PopZ. If full length ZitP is required, it suggests an important functional role for the C-terminal domain. If ZitP</italic><sup><italic>1-43</italic></sup> <italic>is sufficient, the model that ZitP directs PopZ localization will likely require some adjustment.</italic> </p><p>The proposed experiment was done and the results (reported as growth curves) are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>. The figure shows complementation experiment with the different variants as Dendra-ZitP fusions expressed from the <italic>xylX</italic> locus (ZitP<sup>1-43</sup>, ZitP<sup>1-133</sup> and ZitP full-length) in the <italic>popZ<sup>KE</sup></italic>background. Only ZitP full-length and the ZitP anchored to the membrane (ZitP<sup>1-33</sup>) are able to promote growth of the mutant cells. By contrast, when ZitP can no longer interact with PopZ (i.e. the ZitP<sup>CS</sup> variant) or when only soluble (cytoplasmic) part of ZitP is expressed (ZitP<sup>1-43</sup>), cells grow poorly.</p><p>These results not only demonstrate that the direct interaction of ZitP with PopZ is required but also that the membrane anchoring is essential for ZitP to control PopZ.</p><p><italic>6) Chromatin-IP starts with formaldehyde x-linking, which binds any near neighbors to DNA. Thus, interaction between ZitP and DNA may not be direct or even indirect in the formal sense. It is likely that indirect binding to DNA was observed for PopZ, as sequence-dependent association with DNA probably occurs through ParB/ParA. However, we also know that centromeres reside near poles in Caulobacter cells, and that the poles also have PopZ. Thus, some of the binding observed by ChIP-seq may have occurred merely because PopZ and the centromere are in proximity – not from a direct or even an indirect connection between protein and DNA. Similarly, it seems possible that ZitP is merely in the vicinity of centromere by virtue of its interaction with PopZ, and not indirectly binding to DNA. The conclusions would be strengthened if the authors could provide more compelling evidence that ZitP isn't interacting with sites near centromeric DNA because it is at the poles and happens to be near DNA that is not otherwise occluded by ParA/ParB/PopZ. If this is not possible, several of the authors' conclusions should be reworded, the issue should be raised in the main text of the manuscript, and mechanisms outside of ZitP-DNA interactions should be discussed.</italic></p><p>With the new ChIP-seq data it is now clear that PopZ, but not ZitP, is required for binding of the PopZ complex at these two (<italic>parS</italic>-flanking) sites. Moreover, the interaction of PopZ with ParA/B (or other DNA binding proteins that might associate with PopZ N-terminal region) is clearly critical as well. However, because the binding is distinct from that of ParB it is possible that this mediated via ParAB binding to adjacent sites or by another (unknown) protein in the PopZ complex. The ChIP-seq results are de-emphasized in the modified Results section, but briefly mentioned in the revised Discussion.</p></body></sub-article></article>