<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="article-commentary" dtd-version="1.3"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">111563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.111563</article-id><article-version article-version-type="publication-state">version of record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Insight</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cell Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sub-display-channel"><subject>Auditory Hair Cells</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Examining the role of lipids in hearing</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Yein Christina</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5011-7421</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><bio><p><bold>Yein Christina Park</bold> is in the Section on Sensory Physiology and Biophysics, National Institute on Deafness and other Communication Disorders, Bethesda, United States, and the Graduate Program in Cell, Molecular, Developmental Biology &amp; Biophysics, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, United States</p></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ballesteros</surname><given-names>Angela</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5796-6875</contrib-id><email>Angela.Ballesteros@nih.gov</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><bio><p><bold>Angela Ballesteros</bold> is in the Section on Sensory Physiology and Biophysics, National Institute on Deafness and other Communication Disorders, Bethesda, United States</p></bio></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04mhx6838</institution-id><institution>Section on Sensory Physiology and Biophysics, National Institute on Deafness and other Communication Disorders</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Bethesda</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00za53h95</institution-id><institution>Graduate Program in Cell, Molecular, Developmental Biology and Biophysics, Johns Hopkins University</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Baltimore</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="publication"><day>13</day><month>05</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e111563</elocation-id><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article, free of all copyright, and may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. The work is made available under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons CC0 public domain dedication</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-111563-v1.pdf"/><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.110466" id="ra1"/><abstract><p>The asymmetry of lipid membranes is tightly regulated in eukaryotic cells, and auditory hair cells are no exception.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>auditory hair cells</kwd><kwd>lipid bilayers</kwd><kwd>membrane asymmetry</kwd><kwd>scramblase activity</kwd><kwd>ATP8B1-TMEM30B</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Mouse</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>The asymmetry of lipid membranes is tightly regulated in eukaryotic cells, and auditory hair cells are no exception.</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Template</meta-name><meta-value>1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text><p><bold>Related research article</bold> De Hoyos HN, Li S, Im JS, Luz-Ricca A, Szeto B, Jonas R, Kim E, Amin N, Shin JB. 2026. ATP8B1-TMEM30B flippase activity maintains stereocilia lipid asymmetry required for hearing. <italic>eLife</italic> <bold>15</bold>:RP110466. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.110466">10.7554/eLife.110466</ext-link>.</p></boxed-text><p>Why does our sense of hearing deteriorate with age or after repeated exposure to loud noise? Part of the answer to this question lies in the vulnerability of hair cells, the sensory cells in the inner ear that detect sound (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). Humans are born with about 15,000 hair cells in each ear, and once they are lost, they are not replaced, so losing them can lead to permanent hearing loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Wagner and Shin, 2019</xref>). But what determines whether the effect of stress on hair cells is reversible, such as the temporary ringing we experience in our ears after a loud concert, or if it will result in lasting hearing problems?</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Regulation of membrane asymmetry in auditory hair cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic illustration of the adult human ear, showing the cochlea (green), and the organ of Corti (pink). Within the organ of Corti are three rows of outer hair cells (blue) and one row of inner hair cells (also blue) which amplify sound and transmit signals to the auditory nerve (yellow), respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) Side view of an auditory hair cell, depicting the cylindrical organelles called stereocilia that project from its apical surface. The two shorter rows of stereocilia contain a mechanoelectrical transduction (MET) complex (red) at their tip. There are also protein links (brown) between the complexes on neighboring stereocilia. (<bold>C</bold>) When sound deflects the stereocilia, tension is applied to the MET complexes, causing an influx of ions (circles) into the hair cell. These ions produce the electrical signals that are sent from the auditory nerve (yellow) to the brain. (<bold>D</bold>) Three rows of stereocilia (center), and expanded views of the cell membrane at the stereocilia tip (left, oval) and base (right, rectangle). The cell membrane is made of two layers or leaflets of lipids (dark blue and white shapes), and in most cells the compositions of the inner and outer leaflets are different – a phenomenon known as membrane asymmetry. In hair cells, however, the scramblase activity of two proteins in the MET complex (red) – TMC1 and TMC2 – disrupt membrane asymmetry at the tip. De Hoyos et al. report that a ATP8B1-TMEM30B complex (purple) localizes at the base of the stereocilia, and that the flippase activity of this complex restores membrane asymmetry at the base by actively transporting specific lipids, such as phosphatidylserine and phosphatidylethanolamine (white shapes), to the inner leaflet.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-111563-fig1-v1.tif"/></fig><p>An essential feature of hair cells – and, indeed, of most eukaryotic cells – is an uneven distribution of lipids between the inner and outer leaflets of the cell membrane. This membrane asymmetry – which is critical for many cellular functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Sakuragi and Nagata, 2023</xref>) – is maintained by enzymes called flippases that move specific lipids to the inner leaflet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bhandari et al., 2025</xref>), and floppases, which move lipids to the outer leaflet. There are also enzymes called scramblases that can move lipids in both directions, disrupting the membrane asymmetry. Importantly, scramblases are tightly regulated because they can move a lipid called phosphatidylserine to the outer leaflet, which marks the cell for elimination via the process of apoptotic cell removal. Remarkably, in hair cells, this scramblase activity happens within the very protein complex that detects sound.</p><p>This protein complex, known as the mechanoelectrical transduction complex, converts sound into electrical signals to enable hearing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B, C</xref>). Existing evidence indicates that its core components, a pair of proteins called TMC1 and TMC2, function both as ion channels and lipid scramblases. As ion channels, they allow ions to enter the hair cells, initiating electrical signals that are sent to the brain; and as scramblases, they disrupt membrane asymmetry. One possible explanation for this dual function is that lipid reorganization by TMC1 and TMC2 alters membrane properties, thereby tuning the ion channel function of the complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">George and Ricci, 2026</xref>).</p><p>However, when left unchecked, scramblase activity can – via the movement of phosphatidylserine to the outer leaflet, and the formation of blebs on the membrane – lead to the death of hair cells in mutant TMC1 mouse models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Ballesteros and Swartz, 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Lee et al., 2025</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Peineau et al., 2025</xref>). These findings suggest that hair cells must tightly regulate membrane asymmetry by balancing scramblase, flippase, and floppase activities to preserve hearing. Now, in eLife, Jung-Bum Shin and colleagues at the University of Virginia – including Henry De Hoyos as first author – report that they have identified some of the key players involved in the regulation of membrane asymmetry in hair cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">De Hoyos et al., 2026</xref>).</p><p>De Hoyos et al. identified an ATPase called ATP8B1 as the predominant flippase in outer hair cells and determined its timeline of expression in mice. ATP8B1 protein expression is first detected in hair cells around postnatal day 11, coinciding with the onset of hearing, suggesting a potential role in auditory maturation. They also showed that ATP8B1 and its chaperone – a transmembrane protein called TMEM30B – were localized to the bases of stereocilia, which are cylindrical structures erected at the top of the hair cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). This finding supports a model in which the scramblase activity of TMC1 and TMC2 at the tips of the stereocilia is counterbalanced by the flippase activity of the ATP8B1–TMEM30B complex at the base, thus limiting the diffusion of externalized phosphatidylserine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>).</p><p>Building on these findings, De Hoyos et al. examined how the loss of ATP8B1 or TMEM30B affects outer hair cells. In mice lacking either protein, outer hair cells displayed disrupted membrane asymmetry, including phosphatidylserine externalization, stereocilia degeneration, and cell death. These defects were accompanied by significant hearing impairment compared to controls. Notably, when TMEM30B was absent, ATP8B1 mislocalized to the hair cell bodies, demostrating that proper localization of ATP8B1 is essential for the survival of outer hair cells and hearing. Finally, De Hoyos et al. found that in mutant mice lacking the gene for Cib2 – which encodes an essential component of the mechanoelectrical transduction complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Giese et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Liang et al., 2021</xref>) – ATP8B1 and TMEM30B were mislocalized to the body of the hair cells. This suggests that a working mechanoelectrical transduction complex is required for correct flippase localization.</p><p>This work marks an important step toward understanding the role of lipid flippases in hearing, and adds to growing evidence that membrane asymmetry is closely linked to the activity of the mechanoelectrical transduction complex and hair cell health. Although the details of the underlying mechanism remain unclear, it is evident that the activity of the complex – which is composed of multiple transmembrane proteins – simultaneously modulates, and is modulated by, its lipid environment. This regulation can be direct (through the scramblase activity of TMC1 and TMC2, or interactions between the complex and a lipid called PIP2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Caprara et al., 2025</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Cunningham et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Effertz et al., 2017</xref>), or indirect, through changes in the localization of other membrane regulatory proteins, such as ATP8B1 and TMEM30B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">De Hoyos et al., 2026</xref>).</p><p>Despite these advances, however, key questions remain. For example, it remains unclear whether additional flippases are localized near the mechanoelectrical transduction complex. The identity of the flippases that establish membrane asymmetry in inner hair cells are also unknown, and the role of floppases remains unexplored. Moreover, a particular mutation in ATP8B1 (called G308V) causes hearing loss in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Stapelbroek et al., 2009</xref>), but it is not clear if this reflects ATP8B1 G308V mislocalization or changes to the mechanoelectrical transduction complex. Addressing these gaps in knowledge will be critical for understanding how membrane asymmetry supports hair cell function and preserves hearing.</p><p><bold>Acknowledgement</bold>: This work was supported by the Division of Intramural Research of the National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders (NIDCD DIR DC000096 to AB) and by the Intramural Research Program of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). The contributions of the NIH author are considered Works of the United States Government. The findings and conclusions are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the NIH or the US Department of Health and Human Services.</p></body><back><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballesteros</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Regulation of membrane homeostasis by TMC1 mechanoelectrical transduction channels is essential for hearing</article-title><source>Science Advances</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>eabm5550</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abm5550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35921424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Traughber</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorkowski</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brubaker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ertugral</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kothapalli</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubyak</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulshan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year><article-title>ATP8B1 regulates PIP2 localization and cleavage of pyroptotic executioner Gasdermin D</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>122</volume><elocation-id>e2502798122</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2502798122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="preprint"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caprara</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year><article-title>PIP<sub>2</sub>-Tmie interactions drive mammalian hair cell slow adaptation independently of myosin motors</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.04.01.646713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>TMIE defines pore and gating properties of the mechanotransduction channel of mammalian cochlear hair cells</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2020.03.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32343945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Hoyos</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Im</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Luz-Ricca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Szeto</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2026">2026</year><article-title>ATP8B1-TMEM30B flippase activity maintains stereocilia lipid asymmetry required for hearing</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>RP110466</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.110466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Effertz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Phosphoinositol-4,5-bisphosphate regulates auditory hair-cell mechanotransduction-channel pore properties and fast adaptation</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>11632</fpage><lpage>11646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1351-17.2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29066559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2026">2026</year><article-title>Auditory hair cell mechanotransduction channels dynamically shape the mechanical properties of their membrane environment</article-title><source>Advanced Science</source><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e08268</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/advs.202508268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40908646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giese</surname><given-names>APJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowl</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldring</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SDM</given-names></name><name><surname>Riazuddin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fettiplace</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Frolenkov</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>CIB2 interacts with TMC1 and TMC2 and is essential for mechanotransduction in auditory hair cells</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>43</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-00061-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28663585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="preprint"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaraman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotomayor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballesteros</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year><article-title>TMC1 and TMC2 are cholesterol-dependent scramblases that regulate membrane homeostasis in auditory hair cells</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.07.03.663083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dionne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pucak</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>CIB2 and CIB3 are auxiliary subunits of the mechanotransduction channel of hair cells</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>2131</fpage><lpage>2149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2021.05.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34089643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peineau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcovich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballesteros</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year><article-title>Mammalian TMC1 or 2 are necessary for scramblase activity in auditory hair cells</article-title><source>Hearing Research</source><volume>460</volume><elocation-id>109229</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heares.2025.109229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40073458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakuragi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Regulation of phospholipid distribution in the lipid bilayer by flippases and scramblases</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-023-00604-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37106071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stapelbroek</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>van Beurden</surname><given-names>DHA</given-names></name><name><surname>Curfs</surname><given-names>JHAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Joosten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beynon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Velden</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Oude Elferink</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zanten</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klomp</surname><given-names>LWJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Houwen</surname><given-names>RHJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>ATP8B1 is essential for maintaining normal hearing</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>9709</fpage><lpage>9714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0807919106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19478059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Mechanisms of hair cell damage and repair</article-title><source>Trends in Neurosciences</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2019.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30992136</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>