<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">42908</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Structural Biology and Molecular Biophysics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular basis of signaling specificity between GIRK channels and GPCRs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-51407"><name><surname>Touhara</surname><given-names>Kouki K</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3167-9784</contrib-id><email>ktouhara@rockefeller.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-3903"><name><surname>MacKinnon</surname><given-names>Roderick</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7605-4679</contrib-id><email>mackinn@mail.rockefeller.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><institution content-type="dept">Laboratory of Molecular Neurobiology and Biophysics</institution><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, The Rockefeller University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">New York</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>Kenton Jon</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke, National Institutes of Health</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>The University of Texas at Austin</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e42908</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-10-16"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-12-08"><day>08</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018, Touhara and MacKinnon</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Touhara and MacKinnon</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-42908-v2.pdf"/><related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="ra1" related-article-type="commentary" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.44298"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.001</object-id><p>Stimulated muscarinic acetylcholine receptors (M2Rs) release Gβγ subunits, which slow heart rate by activating a G protein-gated K<sup>+</sup> channel (GIRK). Stimulated β2 adrenergic receptors (β2ARs) also release Gβγ subunits, but GIRK is not activated. This study addresses the mechanism underlying this specificity of GIRK activation by M2Rs. K<sup>+</sup> currents and bioluminescence resonance energy transfer between labelled G proteins and GIRK show that M2Rs catalyze Gβγ subunit release at higher rates than β2ARs, generating higher Gβγ concentrations that activate GIRK and regulate other targets of Gβγ. The higher rate of Gβγ release is attributable to a faster G protein coupled receptor – G protein trimer association rate in M2R compared to β2AR. Thus, a rate difference in a single kinetic step accounts for specificity.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>GIRK</kwd><kwd>GPCR</kwd><kwd>ion channel</kwd><kwd>G protein</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Human</kwd><kwd>Mouse</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>GM43949</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>MacKinnon</surname><given-names>Roderick</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>A single kinetic step in the G protein activation cycle determines whether a G protein-coupled receptor activates G protein-gated K<sup>+</sup> channels or not.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Heart rate is tightly regulated by the combined effects of the sympathetic and parasympathetic branches of the autonomic nervous system. These two branches control heart rate by stimulating different G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs), which in turn activate ion channels that modify the electrical properties of cardiac pacemaker cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">DiFrancesco, 1993</xref>). Sympathetic stimulation accelerates heart rate through activation of beta-adrenergic receptors (βARs) and the stimulatory G protein (Gα<sub>s</sub>) pathway, while parasympathetic stimulation slows heart rate through activation of the muscarinic acetylcholine receptor M<sub>2</sub> (M2Rs) of the inhibitory G protein (Gα<sub>i</sub>) pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Brodde and Michel, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Gordan et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>G protein-activated inward rectifier K<sup>+</sup> (GIRK) channels are targeted by the parasympathetic nervous system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Loewi, 1921</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Irisawa et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Schmitt et al., 2014</xref>). Upon stimulation, acetylcholine (ACh) released from the vagus nerve binds to and activates M2Rs in sinoatrial node (SAN) pacemaker cells, promoting the engagement of the GDP-bound G protein trimer (Gα<sub>i</sub>(GDP)βγ). The activated receptor catalyzes removal of GDP from the G protein alpha subunit (Gα<sub>i</sub>), which allows intracellular GTP to bind. The GTP-bound Gα (Gα<sub>i</sub>(GTP)) and the G protein beta-gamma subunit (Gβγ) then dissociate from the receptor and from each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Hilger et al., 2018</xref>). The Gβγ subunit, now free to diffuse on the intracellular membrane surface (attached by a lipid anchor), binds to GIRK and causes it to open (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Sakmann et al., 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Soejima and Noma, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Logothetis et al., 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Wickman et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Krapivinsky et al., 1995</xref>). Open GIRK channels hyperpolarize the cell membrane and thus lengthen the interval between cardiac action potentials (i.e. slow the heart rate) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">DiFrancesco, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Schmitt et al., 2014</xref>). The process is reversed by the alpha subunit, which hydrolyses GTP to GDP followed by reformation of the Gα<sub>i</sub>(GDP)βγ complex.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.002</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Gβγ specificity between GPCRs and GIRK channels.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A schematic representation of GPCR signal transduction and GIRK channel activation. Agonist binding promotes the formation of a GPCR-Gα(GDP)βγ complex. The activated GPCR then triggers the exchange of GDP to GTP on the Gα subunit. Gα(GTP) and Gβγ subunits subsequently dissociate from the GPCR. Dissociated Gβγ directly binds to and activates GIRK channels. Dissociated Gα(GTP) hydrolyzes GTP to GDP, which then reassociates with Gβγ to form Gα(GDP)βγ. (<bold>B</bold>) A representative current-clamp recording of spontaneous action potentials from an acutely isolated murine sinoatrial node (SAN) cell. 1 µM isoproterenol (Iso) or acetylcholine (ACh) was applied as indicated. (<bold>C</bold>) A representative voltage-clamp recording from the same SAN cell in (<bold>B</bold>). The membrane potential was held at −80 mV, and 1 µM Iso or ACh was applied as indicated. (<bold>D</bold>) Representative voltage-clamp recordings of HEK-293T cells transiently co-transfected with GIRK channels, and either M2Rs, β2ARs or β1ARs. The membrane potential was held at −80 mV. 10 µM ACh or Iso was applied as indicated. (<bold>E</bold>) Validation of the function of βARs. HEK-293T cells expressing βARs or untransfected HEK-293T cells (Ctrl) were treated with 10 µM propranolol (Pro) or isoprennaline (Iso), and intracellular cAMP levels were quantified (N = 3, ±SD). See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.003</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Gβγ specificity in heterologously expressed GIRK channels.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Endogenous M2Rs do not activate GIRK. HEK-293T cells were transiently transfected with GIRK channels. The membrane potential was held at −80 mV. 10 µM ACh was applied as indicated. (<bold>B</bold>) (<bold>C</bold>) Confocal images of HEK-293T cells expressing M2Rs or β2ARs. HEK2-93T cells were transiently transfected with (<bold>B</bold>) SNAP-M2Rs or (<bold>C</bold>) SNAP-β2ARs. Receptors were stained using Alexa Fluor 488 conjugate to a SNAP-ligand. Three representative images are shown for each receptor. (<bold>D</bold>) Representative voltage-clamp recordings of CHO cells transiently co-transfected with GIRK channels, and either M2Rs, β2ARs or β1ARs. The membrane potential was held at −80 mV. 10 µM ACh or Iso was applied as indicated. The function of βARs was validated by quantifying intracellular cAMP (N = 3, ±SD). (<bold>E</bold>) Representative voltage-clamp recordings of Sf9 cells co-infected with GIRK channels, and either M2Rs, β2ARs or β1ARs. The membrane potential was held at −80 mV. 10 µM ACh or Iso was applied as indicated. The function of βARs was validated by quantifying intracellular cAMP (N = 3, ±SD).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig1-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Sympathetic stimulation of βAR speeds heart rate by opening excitatory ion channels through the Gα<sub>s</sub> pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">DiFrancesco and Tortora, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Simonds, 1999</xref>). Important to balanced opposing effects of sympathetic and parasympathetic input, βAR stimulation does not open GIRK channels even though Gβγ subunits are released by this receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hein et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Digby et al., 2008</xref>). The reason why GIRK channel opening is specific to Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCR stimulation and not to Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled GPCR stimulation has remained a long-standing unsolved puzzle, which we refer to as the Gβγ specificity puzzle. One theory posited the existence of a macromolecular super-complex consisting of GIRK, G proteins and a Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCR, to endow specificity by proximity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Peleg et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Ivanina et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Clancy et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Riven et al., 2006</xref>). Another theory suggested that stimulated Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled receptors might generate insufficient quantities of free Gβγ if Gα<sub>s</sub>(GTP) binds to Gβγ with higher affinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Digby et al., 2008</xref>). None of these studies provided sufficient data to strongly support a solution. Here we present data that support a simple biochemical solution to this puzzle.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Gβγ specificity in native and heterologously expressed GIRK channels</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref> shows spontaneous action potentials recorded from current-clamped murine SAN cells isolated from adult mice. With application of isoproterenol (Iso), action potential (AP) frequency increased, and with ACh firing altogether ceased. Somewhat surprisingly, we could not find in the literature a demonstration of both autonomic responses in the same cell. Here we observe that both Gα<sub>i</sub>-associated (<italic>via</italic> ACh to slow heart rate) and Gα<sub>s</sub>-associated (<italic>via</italic> Iso to speed heart rate) pathways are indeed activated within a single pacemaker cell. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref> shows a voltage-clamp experiment performed on the very same cell shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>. ACh produces inward K<sup>+</sup> current through GIRK channels, which is the origin of action potential cessation in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>. Iso does not activate GIRK even though βAR stimulation is known to generate free Gβγ subunits.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref> shows voltage clamp experiments in human embryonic kidney 293T (HEK-293T) cells in which GIRK channels and GPCRs were heterologously expressed. M2R is a Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCR stimulated by ACh and beta 1-adrenergic receptor (β1AR) and beta 2-adrenergic receptor (β2AR) are both Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled GPCRs stimulated by Iso. In each experiment, agonist (ACh or Iso) is applied to reveal the level of stimulated K<sup>+</sup> current. Only M2R receptor stimulation activates GIRK to a large extent. This expression is not due to endogenous M2Rs in HEK-293T cells, as ACh fails to stimulate GIRK channels unless M2R is expressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>). A difference in surface expression levels of the GPCRs does not explain this result, as Alexa Fluor 488-labeled M2Rs and β2ARs show similar fluorescence intensity at the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B–1C</xref>). To ensure that expressed β1AR and β2AR are indeed functional in the cells and capable of initiating the Gα<sub>s</sub> pathway, the cAMP ELIZA assay was used to measure Iso-stimulated increases in cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) concentration, which is not observed in control cells and is thus dependent on the β1AR and β2AR expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>). Similar experiments were carried out in chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cells (also mammal-derived) and Spodoptera frugiperda (Sf9) cells (insect-derived) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1D–1E</xref>). In each cell line only M2R receptor stimulation activates GIRK channels. These data demonstrate that specificity persists across mammalian and insect cells and is therefore a robust property of these signaling pathways. The results also imply that GIRK activation does not depend on Gβγ subtypes, because different cell lines, particularly Sf9 cells, express subtypes of Gβγ that are distinct from those in mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Leopoldt et al., 1997</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Effect of artificially enforced GPCR-GIRK co-localization</title><p>To test whether the macromolecular supercomplex hypothesis can account for Gβγ specificity, we artificially enforced proximity by expressing GIRK linked to either M2R or β2AR within a single open reading frame, as shown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). When expressed and analyzed using a western blot, the linked GIRK channel and GPCR run on SDS-PAGE gels as either full-length GIRK-GPCR units or as dimers, trimers and tetramers of those units (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Therefore, when expressed, GIRK and the GPCR remain linked together. Because GIRK channels are tetramers under native conditions, expression of the GIRK-GPCR unit causes each channel to be surrounded by four GPCRs. Voltage-clamp experiments on HEK-293T cells transiently transfected with the M2R-GIRK construction showed GIRK activation in response to ACh stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). Iso stimulation with cells expressing the β2AR-GIRK construction did not activate GIRK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>), even though the β2AR is functional as evidenced by quantifying levels of stimulated cAMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>). These experiments do not support the macromolecular supercomplex hypothesis as an explanation for Gβγ specificity.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.004</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Effect of artificially enforced GPCR-GIRK co-localization.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A schematic representation of GPCR-GIRK concatemer constructs. GIRK was directly fused to the C-terminus of GPCRs. A cleavable signal peptide and a Halo tag were added to the N-terminus of each concatemer. Additionally, a SNAP tag was added to the C-terminus of each concatemer. (<bold>B</bold>) Western-Blot analysis of GPCR-GIRK concatemer constructs. HEK-293T cells were transiently transfected with either M2R-GIRK or β2AR-GIRK concatemers. The expected size of these concatemers is ~150 kDa. (<bold>C</bold>) (<bold>D</bold>) Representative voltage-clamp recordings of HEK-293T cells transiently transfected with M2R-GIRK concatemers or β2AR-GIRK concatemers. Membrane potential was held at −80 mV. 10 µM ACh or Iso was applied as indicated. (<bold>E</bold>) Validation of the function of β2AR-GIRK concatemers. HEK-293T cells expressing β2AR-GIRK concatemers were treated with 10 µM propranolol (Pro) or isoproterenol (Iso), and intracellular cAMP levels were quantified (N = 3, ±SD).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Influence of G protein levels on specificity</title><p>In the experiments described so far, activation of GIRK channels by GPCR stimulation was facilitated by endogenous levels of G proteins in the cells. We next ask what happens if the levels of G proteins available for mediating activation are altered? Using a cell line in which we established stable expression of GIRK channels and GPCRs, G protein levels were altered using transient transfection. In control experiments endogenous G protein levels support M2R stimulated GIRK channel activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>), as was observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>. Expression of additional Gα<sub>i1</sub> subunits suppressed the level of M2R-stimulated GIRK current, presumably because excess Gα<sub>i1</sub> subunits blunt the normal increase in Gβγ concentration (i.e. Gα<sub>i1</sub> can compete with the channel for available Gβγ). Expression of additional Gα<sub>i1</sub> and Gβγ subunits, however, leads to M2R-stimulated GIRK current that exceeds levels mediated by endogenous G proteins alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1A</xref>). This latter observation would seem to suggest that increased availability of Gα<sub>i</sub>(GDP)βγ substrate (upon which stimulated M2R acts to generate free Gβγ) leads to increased Gβγ levels following M2R stimulation. The question then naturally arises, if sufficiently high levels of Gα<sub>s</sub>(GDP)βγ substrate are provided, might the β2AR activate GIRK to a detectable extent? The answer is yes. Experiments using cells expressing GIRK channels and β2ARs show that excess Gα<sub>s</sub> and Gβγ subunits give rise to β2AR-stimulated GIRK current (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1B</xref>). This finding suggests that the specificity exhibited by Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCRs versus Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled GPCRs is somehow related to differences in the levels of Gβγ that they each are able to generate.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.005</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Influence of G protein levels on specificity.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) GIRK currents induced by M2R agonist ACh. Cells from a stable HEK-293T cell line expressing M2Rs and GIRK channels were transiently transfected with a vector expressing either GFP (Ctrl), Gα<sub>i1</sub>, or Gα<sub>i1</sub> and Gβγ. 10 µM ACh was applied, and the evoked inward current was normalized to the capacitance of the cell (±SEM). (<bold>B</bold>) GIRK currents induced by β2AR agonist Iso. Cells from a stable HEK-293T cell line expressing β2ARs and GIRK channels were transiently transfected with a control vector expressing either GFP, Gα<sub>s</sub>, or Gα<sub>s</sub> and Gβγ. 10 µM Iso was applied, and the evoked inward current was normalized to the capacitance of the cell (±SEM). (<bold>C</bold>) A schematic representation of the BRET assay. Upon agonist stimulation of a GPCR, Gβγ-Venus is released. Gβγ-Venus then binds to GIRK-NLuc, which increases the BRET signal. (<bold>D</bold>) (<bold>E</bold>) Representative changes in BRET signal upon stimulation of GPCRs. In (<bold>D</bold>), HEK-293T cells were transfected with M2Rs, Gβγ-Venus, GIRK-NLuc, and increasing amounts of Gα<sub>i1</sub>. In (<bold>E</bold>), HEK-293T cells were transfected with β2ARs, Gβγ-Venus, GIRK-NLuc, and increasing amounts of Gα<sub>s</sub>. Agonists were applied at t = 5 s. See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplements 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.006</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>β2ARs activate GIRK channels in the presence of over-expressed G protein trimers.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A representative voltage-clamp recording of HEK-293T cells stably expressing M2Rs and GIRK. The cells were transiently transfected with Gα<sub>i1</sub> and Gβγ. (<bold>B</bold>) A representative voltage-clamp recording of HEK-293T cells stably expressing β2ARs and GIRK. The cells were transiently transfected with Gα<sub>s</sub> and Gβγ. (<bold>C</bold>) A representative time-resolved BRET ratio curve from HEK-293T cells expressing M2Rs, Gα<sub>i1</sub>, Gβγ-Venus, and masGRK3ct-NLuc, which is known to interact with Gβγ. (<bold>D</bold>) A representative time-resolved BRET ratio curve from HEK-293T cells expressing M2Rs, Gα<sub>i1</sub>, Gβγ-Venus, and Kir2.2-NLuc, another inward-rectifier K<sup>+</sup> channel that is structurally similar to GIRK but does not bind to Gβγ. (<bold>E</bold>) Normalized changes in BRET signal upon stimulation of GPCRs. ΔBRET ratio was measured in the presence of different Gα expression levels and was normalized to that in the presence of 4 × Gα (N = 6–8, ±SEM).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig3-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.007</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Comparison of endogenous Gα levels in HEK-293T cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Evaluation of antibody specificity. Different Gα proteins were heterologously expressed, purified and analyzed by Western Blot. Anti-Gα<sub>i1</sub> antibody recognizes both Gα<sub>i1</sub> and Gα<sub>i3</sub>. Anti-Gα<sub>i2</sub>, Gα<sub>o</sub>, and Gα<sub>s</sub> antibodies specifically recognize their target Gα. (<bold>B</bold>) Comparison of endogenous Gα levels in HEK-293T cells. HEK-293T cells were lysed and analyzed by Western Blot. 5 ng of purified Gα was loaded as a reference.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig3-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Direct measurement of the Gβγ–GIRK interaction</title><p>We explored the influence of G protein levels further using a more direct measurement to estimate the Gβγ-GIRK interaction. After fusing the modified yellow fluorescent protein Venus to Gβγ and the bioluminescent protein Nano-Luciferase (NLuc) to GIRK (GIRK-NLuc) we monitored their proximity by measuring the bioluminescent resonance energy transfer (BRET) ratio (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Masuho et al., 2015</xref>). The idea is, following GPCR stimulation Gβγ-Venus separates from the GPCR-G protein complex and binds to GIRK, bringing Venus close to NLuc on the channel and thus increasing the BRET ratio (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>).</p><p>Two initial controls were carried out. First, we examined the binding of Gβγ-Venus to the membrane anchored C-terminal PH domain of GRK3 fused to NLuc (masGRK3ct-NLuc), which is known to bind to Gβγ with ~20 nM affinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Pitcher et al., 1992</xref>). This experiment produced a robust increase in the BRET signal following M2R stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1C</xref>). Second, we examined the binding of Gβγ-Venus to Kir2.2 fused to NLuc. Kir2.2 is structurally similar to GIRK but does not bind to Gβγ. No change in BRET signal occurred following M2R stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1D</xref>). These positive and negative controls imply that the BRET assay may be suitable for monitoring a specific interaction between GIRK and Gβγ subunits released following GPCR stimulation.</p><p>HEK-293T cells were transiently transfected with M2Rs, Gβγ-Venus, GIRK-NLuc, and varying concentrations of Gα<sub>i1</sub>. The BRET signal was then monitored over time following ACh stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1E</xref>). Even in the absence of additional Gα<sub>i1</sub>, the BRET signal showed a time-dependent increase, consistent with Gβγ-Venus being released from M2Rs and then binding to the GIRK channel. As the amount of Gα<sub>i1</sub> expression was increased the BRET signal increased further, consistent with more Gβγ-Venus being generated as a result of greater Gα<sub>i1</sub>(GDP)βγ-Venus substrate availability. Note that this result is not inconsistent with the reduced current generated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref> upon excess Gα<sub>i1</sub> expression because in the BRET experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>) Gβγ-Venus is also over-expressed. As the level of Gα<sub>i1</sub> expression is increased a maximum BRET signal is reached, suggesting that an aspect of this signaling pathway other than Gα<sub>i1</sub> availability eventually becomes limiting. When the same experiment was carried out with the β2AR only a very small change in the BRET signal was observed in the absence of Gα<sub>s</sub> transfection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1E</xref>), consistent with the failure of β2AR stimulation (in the absence of Gα<sub>s</sub> transfection) to activate GIRK channels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). In accord with the ability of Gα<sub>s</sub> and Gβγ over-expression to over-ride specificity and permit β2AR-stimulated GIRK current (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>), the BRET ratio increased with increased expression of Gα<sub>s</sub> (and Gβγ-Venus). The electrophysiological and BRET assays are in complete agreement with each other and suggest that specificity in Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCR signaling results from higher Gβγ concentrations achieved when Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptors are stimulated compared to Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled receptors.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Generalization of Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCR target specificity</title><p>If specificity results from higher levels of Gβγ generated when Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptors are stimulated rather than from a specific protein-protein interaction and localization of the receptor with GIRK, then other targets upon which Gβγ acts might also exhibit similar specificity. To test this idea, we carried out experiments using the transient receptor potential melastatin 3 (TRPM3) channel, which is inhibited by Gβγ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Badheka et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Quallo et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Dembla et al., 2017</xref>). TRPM3 channels and M2Rs were transiently transfected into HEK-293T cells and whole-cell voltage-clamp recordings were performed. TRPM3 channels were first activated by a chemical ligand, pregnenolone sulphate (PS), and then inhibited (85 ± 10%) by stimulating M2R with Ach (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B and C</xref>). Similar experiments with Iso-stimulated β2ARs showed only modest inhibition (17 ± 10%), consistent with some degree of specificity as a result of there being insufficient concentrations of Gβγ generated by the Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B and D</xref>). As in the GIRK experiments, specificity is lost when Gα<sub>s</sub> and Gβγ are over-expressed (inhibition 73 ± 14%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B–4F</xref>). These observations further strengthen the idea that Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptors generate higher concentrations of Gβγ in the setting of endogenous G protein concentrations and that these higher Gβγ levels account for Gβγ specificity. These observations also further reject the macromolecular supercomplex hypothesis as a tenable explanation, because similar Gβγ specificity is observed with a completely different protein target of the Gβγ pathway.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.008</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Generalization of Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCR target specificity.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A schematic representation of TRPM3 channel inhibition by Gβγ. Upon agonist stimulation, released Gβγ directly binds to and inhibits TRPM3 channels. (<bold>B</bold>) The amount of current blocked upon GPCR stimulation was normalized to the first peak current (±SEM). (<bold>C</bold>)-(<bold>F</bold>) Representative voltage-clamp recordings of HEK-293T cells transiently transfected with (<bold>C</bold>) TRPM3 and M2Rs (<bold>D</bold>) TRPM3 and β2ARs (<bold>E</bold>) TRPM3, β2ARs, and Gα<sub>s</sub>, or (<bold>F</bold>) TRPM3, β2ARs, Gα<sub>s</sub>, and Gβγ. A ramp protocol from −100 mV to +100 mV was applied to the cells every second. The currents at +100 mV were plotted. TRPM3 currents were evoked by 10 µM pregnenolone sulfate (PS). M2Rs and β2ARs were stimulated by 10 µM ACh and Iso, respectively.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Relative rates of Gβγ release by Gα<sub>i</sub> versus Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled receptors</title><p>By what mechanisms do M2Rs generate higher Gβγ concentrations than β2ARs? If Gα<sub>i</sub> subunits were more abundant in cells than Gα<sub>s</sub> subunits then higher rates of Gβγ generation would be expected. This explanation seems unlikely though, because the endogenous levels of Gα<sub>s</sub> in HEK-293T cells are actually higher than Gα<sub>i</sub> when we measure levels directly using a Western blot assay in the same cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>). Higher levels of Gα<sub>s</sub> in HEK-293T cells were also reported previously on the basis of RNA levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Atwood et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Alternatively, differences in the affinity of Gβγ for Gα<sub>s</sub>-GTP versus Gα<sub>i</sub>-GTP could potentially account for differences in the levels of free Gβγ generated during β2AR versus M2R stimulation. To test this possibility, we assessed the relative ability of Gα<sub>s</sub>-GTP versus Gα<sub>i1</sub>-GTP to bind to Gβγ. Because the affinity of GTP-bound forms of Gα for Gβγ are so low we contrived the experiment shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>. GIRK channels and Gβγ were reconstituted into planar lipid bilayers at a mass ratio of ~1:0.1. In the presence of 8 mM Na<sup>+</sup> and 32 µM C8-PIP<sub>2</sub> a fraction of GIRK channels are activated in the context of limiting Gβγ concentration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A</xref>). Under this condition, sufficiently high concentrations of Gα(GTP-γS) can inhibit GIRK activation through competition by binding to Gβγ. Thus, known amounts of Gα<sub>i1</sub>(GTP-γS) or Gα<sub>s</sub>(GTP-γS) were added by replacing the lipid tail with a His<sub>10</sub> tag and including in the bilayer 3% Ni-NTA lipids. After saturation of Ni-NTA lipids these conditions should yield a Gα(GTP-γS) concentration adjacent to the membrane ~3 mM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wang et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Touhara et al., 2016</xref>). Inhibition of GIRK current was observed, but with no significant difference between Gα<sub>i1</sub>(GTP-γS) and Gα<sub>s</sub>(GTP-γS), suggesting that their affinities for Gβγ are similar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B–5D</xref>). Thus, lower Gβγ concentrations following Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled receptor stimulation cannot be attributed to sequestration by Gα<sub>s</sub>(GTP).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.009</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Gα<sub>s</sub>(GTP-γS) and Gα<sub>i1</sub>(GTP-γS) do not differentially compete with GIRK channels for Gβγ.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A schematic representation of the competition assay between His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) and GIRK for Gβγ in a reconstituted planar lipid bilayer system. In these experiments, we controlled the amount of lipid-associated Gα(GTP-γS) to evaluate the competition quantitatively. We first incorporated a fixed amount of Ni-NTA-lipids into the lipid bilayer and applied enough His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) to saturate all the available Ni-NTA binding sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B–1D</xref>). Tethered His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) competes with GIRK for Gβγ and therefore inhibits GIRK. (<bold>B</bold>) Current inhibition by His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) was normalized to the initial current levels (N = 3, ±SD). (<bold>C</bold>) (<bold>D</bold>) Representative inward GIRK currents from lipid bilayers. GIRK was partially activated by PIP<sub>2</sub>, Na<sup>+</sup>, and a low concentration of Gβγ. Dashed lines represent the baseline current (0 pA). (<bold>C</bold>) His<sub>10</sub>-Gα<sub>i1</sub>(GTP-γS) or (<bold>D</bold>) His<sub>10</sub>-Gα<sub>s</sub>(GTP-γS) was directly perfused to the bilayer membrane several times followed by mixing the solutions in the bilayer chamber. The transient decrease in the current upon Gα(GTP-γS) application is an artifact due to the absence of Na<sup>+</sup> in His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) solution. See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.010</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Purified His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) binds to the GUV membrane containing Ni-NTA lipids.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) GIRK channels were partially activated by low amounts of Gβγ. Proteoliposomes containing GIRK and Gβγ at a ratio of 1:0.1 (wt:wt) were fused to the planar lipid bilayer membrane. GIRK was then activated by adding 32 µM C8-PIP<sub>2</sub> and 32 mM Na<sup>+</sup> to the bilayer chamber (left trace). Subsequently GIRK was fully activated by fusing Gβγ vesicles (right trace). The ~5 fold increase in the inward GIRK current suggests the partial activation of GIRK channels due to the presence of limiting amounts of Gβγ in the left trace. (<bold>B</bold>) Typical confocal images of the giant unilamellar vesicle (GUV) equator planes. The corresponding concentration of Alexa Fluor 488-labeled His<sub>10</sub>-Gα<sub>i1</sub>(GTP-γS) is indicated. (<bold>C</bold>) (<bold>D</bold>) Gα(GTP-γS) binding curves to GUVs. The fluorescence intensities measured at different protein concentrations were fitted using a 1:1 binding model.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig5-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Next, we tested the possibility that Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptors catalyze intrinsically faster Gβγ release. We developed an assay by attaching Venus to Gα, NLuc to Gβγ, and measured the BRET ratio change to monitor GPCR-mediated dissociation of Gβγ-NLuc from Gα-Venus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). We also expressed masGRK3ct in the same cells to sequester Gβγ-NLuc once it is released, thus reducing the extent to which Gβγ-NLuc will rebind to Gα-Venus. Two different Gα-Venus insertion constructs were made – into the αa-αb loop or into the αb-αc loop of Gα – to ensure that the observed behavior does not depend on the site of insertion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1A</xref>). Prior to GPCR stimulation, N-Luc intensity and BRET ratio were nearly constant and approximately similar in magnitude in all experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B–6C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). Following GPCR stimulation the BRET ratio change was small for the β2AR and comparatively large for M2R. Similar experiments were also carried out with the Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled dopamine receptor (D2R), which activates GIRK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2A</xref>), and the Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled β1AR, which does not. Again, we observe that Gβγ-dissociation from Gα is much greater for the Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D–6E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2C–2D</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). The small signal associated with βAR stimulation is not due to malfunctioning of the Venus-inserted Gα<sub>s</sub> constructs because Gβγ-NLuc dissociation from Gα<sub>s</sub>-Venus is observable in controls in which G proteins were over-expressed to higher levels (i.e. when BRET ratio prior to βAR stimulation was higher) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2B</xref>). We conclude from these experiments that the Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptors M2R and D2R generate more rapid Gβγ release than the Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled receptors β1AR and β2AR due to a higher intrinsic turnover rate.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.011</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Relative rates of Gβγ release by Gα<sub>i</sub> versus Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled receptors.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A schematic representation of the experiment that monitors Gβγ release by BRET. Upon agonist stimulation, GPCRs release Gα and Gβγ. The dissociation of Gα-Venus and Gβγ-NLuc results in a decrease of the BRET signal. Released Gβγ-NLuc was chelated by masGRK3ct, a fusion of the C-terminal PH domain of GRK3 and a myristic acid attachment peptide. (<bold>B</bold>)-(<bold>E</bold>) Representative time-resolved BRET ratio curves. In (<bold>B</bold>) and (<bold>C</bold>), M2Rs released more Gβγ than β2ARs did within the same time period, independent of which Gα-Venus construct was used. In (<bold>D</bold>) and (<bold>E</bold>), D2Rs released more Gβγ than β1ARs did within the same time period, independent of which Gα-Venus construct was used. See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplements 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig6-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.012</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>M2Rs catalyze release of Gβγ at higher rate compared to β2ARs.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Structural comparison between Gα<sub>s</sub> and Gα<sub>i1</sub>. Crystal structures of Gα<sub>s</sub> (Blue, PDB: 1AZT) and Gα<sub>i1</sub> (Red, PDB: 1GG2) were superimposed. The Venus insertion sites are indicated as arrows. The Cα atoms of residues Gα<sub>s</sub>-113 and 144, and Gα<sub>i1</sub>-91 and 121 are represented as spheres. (<bold>B</bold>) (<bold>C</bold>) Time-resolved BRET ratio curves from HEK-293T cells transiently transfected with different GPCRs and Gα-Venus constructs.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig6-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.013</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>D2Rs catalyze release of Gβγ at higher rate compared to β1ARs.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A representative voltage-clamp recording of a HEK-293T cell transiently transfected with GIRK channels and D2Rs. The membrane potential was held at −80 mV. 10 µM Dopamine (Dopa) was applied as indicated. (<bold>B</bold>) Validation of the function of Venus-inserted Gα<sub>s</sub>. Time-resolved BRET ratio curves from HEK-293T cells transiently transfected with β1ARs and different Gα-Venus constructs were shown. (<bold>C</bold>) (<bold>D</bold>) Time-resolved BRET ratio curves from HEK-293T cells transiently transfected with different GPCRs and Gα-Venus constructs.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig6-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.014</object-id><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Quantitative-BRET measurements of Gβγ release from different Gα constructs.</title><p>Averaged Nano-Luc intensity, basal BRET ratio, and ΔBRET ratio were summarized (N = 3–4, ±SD).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top"/><th valign="top">NLuc intensity </th><th valign="top">Basal BRET ratio</th><th valign="top">ΔBRET ratio</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">M2R-Gα<sub>i1</sub>(αa-αb)</td><td valign="top">(13.85 ± 0.36) x105</td><td valign="top">0.301 ± 0.003</td><td valign="top">0.031 ± 0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">β2AR- Gα<sub>s</sub>(αa-αb)</td><td valign="top">(11.91 ± 2.80) x105</td><td valign="top">0.310 ± 0.007</td><td valign="top">0.002 ± 0.006</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">M2R-Gα<sub>i1</sub>(αb-αc)</td><td valign="top">(8.08 ± 1.77) x105</td><td valign="top">0.310 ± 0.014</td><td valign="top">0.029 ± 0.006</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">β2AR- Gα<sub>s</sub>(αb-αc)</td><td valign="top">(8.64 ± 2.62) x105</td><td valign="top">0.311 ± 0.014</td><td valign="top">0.005 ± 0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">D2R-Gα<sub>i1</sub>(αa-αb)</td><td valign="top">(23.29 ± 1.46) x105</td><td valign="top">0.312 ± 0.005</td><td valign="top">0.028 ± 0.006</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">β1AR- Gα<sub>s</sub>(αa-αb)</td><td valign="top">(24.51 ± 1.09) x105</td><td valign="top">0.315 ± 0.007</td><td valign="top">0.007 ± 0.003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">D2R-Gα<sub>i1</sub>(αb-αc)</td><td valign="top">(5.58 ± 4.31) x105</td><td valign="top">0.287 ± 0.001</td><td valign="top">0.032 ± 0.004</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">β1AR- Gα<sub>s</sub>(αb-αc)</td><td valign="top">(7.77 ± 0.34) x105</td><td valign="top">0.279 ± 0.004</td><td valign="top">0.008 ± 0.003</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Kinetic model of Gβγ specificity</title><p>We developed a kinetic model for GIRK activation to test whether we could replicate Gβγ-specificity on the basis of differences in Gα<sub>i</sub> versus Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled receptor turnover rates. The model consists of a G protein turnover reaction cycle and a GIRK-Gβγ binding reaction that leads to channel activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). Numerous studies have provided estimates for rate constants in the reaction cycle (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2">Table 2</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Breitwieser and Szabo, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Sarvazyan et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>), and the GIRK-Gβγ binding reaction has been studied in detail, providing estimates for <italic>k<sub>56</sub></italic> and <italic>k<sub>65</sub></italic> as well as a cooperativity factor µ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Shea et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wang et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Touhara et al., 2016</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.015</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Kinetic model of Gβγ specificity.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Reaction scheme used to model GPCR activation of GIRK. <italic>k</italic><sub>xy</sub> are the rate constants of the reactions between two G protein states. Rate, equilibrium and cooperativity constants are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2">Table 2</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) ACh-stimulated GIRK currents from two different SAN cells are shown in grey. Calculated GIRK-βγ<sub>4</sub> concentration as a function of time for two different <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub> magnitudes are shown in black solid and dashed curves. (<bold>C</bold>) Calculated steady state GIRK-βγ<sub>4</sub> concentration as a function of <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub> magnitude. (<bold>D</bold>) Steady state two-dimensional Gβγ concentration profile (molecules µm<sup>−2</sup>; one molecule µm<sup>−2</sup> = 0.2 µM in a layer 80 Å thick below the membrane surface) surrounding a single GPCR generating 1 Gβγ sec<sup>−1</sup> with mean Gβγ lifetime 1 s and diffusion coefficient 0.2 µm<sup>2</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup>. (<bold>E</bold>) Steady state two-dimensional concentration profile of Gβγ in and surrounding a hotspot of radius 0.3 µm with a density of 50 GPCR µm<sup>−2</sup>. Gβγ lifetime and diffusion coefficient are the same as in (<bold>D</bold>). (<bold>F</bold>) Two dimensional cross sections of concentration profiles in (<bold>D</bold>) and (<bold>E</bold>). (<bold>G</bold>) Steady state Gβγ concentration at the center of hotspot as a function of hotspot radius. See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2">Table 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig7-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.016</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Simulation of GPCR-activation of GIRK.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Calculated receptor and G protein concentrations as a function of time (<italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub> = 1 µM<sup>−1</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup>). (<bold>B</bold>) Muscarinic partial agonists activate GIRK channels to a limited extent. Whole-cell voltage-clamp recordings were performed on stable HEK-293T cells expressing M2Rs and GIRK channels. The membrane potential was held at −80 mV. 10 µM ACh, 100 µM Oxotremorine (Oxo), or 100 µM Pilocarpine (Pilo) was applied as indicated. (<bold>C</bold>) Partial agonist-activated GIRK currents were normalized to ACh-activated GIRK currents (N = 5–6, ±SEM). (<bold>D</bold>) Representative changes in BRET signal upon stimulation of M2Rs with different agonists. HEK-293T cells were transfected with M2Rs, Gβγ-Venus, GIRK-NLuc, and increasing amounts of Gα<sub>i1</sub>. 5 µM acetylcholine (ACh), 50 µM oxotremorine (Oxo), or 50 µM pilocarpine (Pilo) was applied at t = 5 s.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-42908-fig7-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><table-wrap id="table2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.017</object-id><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Parameters used for simulation of GPCR-activation of GIRK.</title><p><italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub>: The rate of formation of the productive GPCR-G protein complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>). <italic>k</italic><sub>21</sub>: The rate of dissociation of the productive GPCR-G protein complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>). <italic>k</italic><sub>23</sub>: The rate of nucleotide exchange and subsequent dissociation of GPCRs, Gα(GTP), and Gβγ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>). <italic>k</italic><sub>32</sub>: The rate of the reverse reaction of nucleotide exchange and dissociation of GPCRs and G proteins. <italic>k</italic><sub>34</sub>: The rate of GTP hydrolysis, based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Breitwieser and Szabo, 1988</xref>. <italic>k</italic><sub>43</sub>: The rate of the reverse reaction of GTP hydrolysis. <italic>k</italic><sub>45</sub>: The on-rate between Gα(GDP) and Gβγ, adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Sarvazyan et al., 1998</xref>. <italic>k</italic><sub>54</sub>: The off-rate between Gα(GDP) and Gβγ, calculated based on <italic>k</italic><sub>45</sub> and K<sub>d</sub> = 3 nM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Sarvazyan et al., 1998</xref>). <italic>k</italic><sub>56</sub>: The on-rate between the GIRK and Gβγ is diffusion limited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wang et al., 2016</xref>). <italic>k</italic><sub>65</sub>: The off-rate between the GIRK and Gβγ were calculated based on <italic>k</italic><sub>56</sub> and our previous K<sub>d</sub> measurement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Shea et al., 1997</xref>).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Reaction</th><th>Forward-rate</th><th>Backward-rate</th><th>Note</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>R* + Gα(GDP)βγ ⇌ R*-Gα(GDP)βγ</td><td>1 µM<sup>−1</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup> (<italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub>)</td><td>1 sec<sup>−1</sup> (<italic>k</italic><sub>21</sub>)</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref></td></tr><tr><td>R*-Gα(GDP)βγ ⇌ R* + Gα(GTP) + Gβγ</td><td>1 sec<sup>−1</sup> (<italic>k</italic><sub>23</sub>)</td><td>0 M<sup>−2</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup> (<italic>k</italic><sub>32</sub>)</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Gα(GTP) ⇌ Gα(GDP) + P<sub>i</sub></td><td>2 sec<sup>−1</sup> (<italic>k</italic><sub>34</sub>)</td><td>0 M<sup>−1</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup> (<italic>k</italic><sub>43</sub>)</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Breitwieser and Szabo, 1988</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Gα(GDP) + Gβγ ⇌ Gα(GDP)βγ</td><td>0.7 × 10<sup>6</sup> M<sup>−1</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup> (<italic>k</italic><sub>45</sub>)</td><td>0.002 sec<sup>−1</sup> (<italic>k</italic><sub>54</sub>)</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Sarvazyan et al., 1998</xref></td></tr><tr><td>GIRK-βγ<sub>n-1</sub> + (5 - n)Gβγ ⇌ GIRK-βγ<sub>n</sub> + (4 - n)Gβγ</td><td>(5 - n) × 1 × 10<sup>7</sup> M<sup>−1</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup> <break/>((5 - n) × <italic>k</italic><sub>56</sub>)</td><td>n × µ<sup>n-1</sup> × 600 sec<sup>−1</sup> <break/>(n × µ<sup>n-1</sup> × <italic>k</italic><sub>65</sub>)</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Shea et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wang et al., 2016</xref> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The G protein reaction cycle models the conversion of Gα(GDP)βγ (the G protein trimer) into Gα(GTP) and Gβγ in two kinetic transitions. The first transition (<italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic>) describes the formation of a productive complex between the G protein trimer and an active (ligand-bound) GPCR (R*). The second (<italic>k<sub>23</sub></italic>) combines multiple reactions, including GDP/GTP exchange and Gα(GTP) and βγ dissociation. In our experiments, the observation that G protein over-expression increases levels of stimulated Gβγ in cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>) implies that the <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> transition is to some extent rate-limiting under physiological G protein conditions. A single molecule study of the α2 adrenergic receptor (α2AR; a Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCR) also concluded that complex formation between activated receptor and G protein trimer (i.e. the <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> transition) was rate-limiting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>). Furthermore, the same study found that <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> for the β2AR was ten times smaller than for the α2AR.</p><p>GPCR density over the entire membrane of atrial cardiac myocytes and in CHO cells is approximately 5 µm<sup>−2</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Nenasheva et al., 2013</xref>). However, G protein signaling occurs within ‘hotspots’ that we estimate to cover about 10% of the membrane surface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>). Thus, we assume the receptor density to be 50 µm<sup>−2</sup> within a hotspot and assume an initial Gα(GDP)βγ density of 100 µm<sup>−2</sup>. When the reaction is switched on (i.e. ligand stimulation) at t = 0 by changing <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub> from 0 to 0.2 µm<sup>2</sup> molecule<sup>−1</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>), Gβγ concentration increases (along with time-dependent concentration changes of other components) and GIRK channels activate to a steady state value within a few seconds following a time course similar to M2R stimulated GIRK currents in SAN cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1A</xref>). We note that time courses vary from cell to cell, but that the modeled time course falls within the experimental range.</p><p>To model the β2AR receptor we reduced <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> ten times, consistent with Sungkaworn et al, leaving all other quantities the same. Lower concentrations of Gβγ are predicted and along with significantly less GIRK activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref> displays in greater detail calculated GIRK-(Gβγ)<sub>4</sub> concentration (i.e. channel activation) as a function of <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub> magnitude. A steep dependence occurs right around the experimentally determined value for the Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptor turnover rate constant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>). Thus, the model predicts that higher rates of G protein turnover catalyzed by Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled compared to Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled GPCRs can account for Gβγ specificity.</p><p>Partial agonists by definition activate GPCRs with reduced efficacy compared to full agonists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">McKinney et al., 1991</xref>). The effects of two partial agonists, oxotremorine and pilocarpine, on M2R activation of GIRK are shown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B–1C</xref>). A study recently concluded that for the β2AR, the distinction between partial and full agonist action lies in the magnitude of <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub>, its value being smaller for partial agonists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Gregorio et al., 2017</xref>). We think this conclusion likely applies to M2R as well, based on the following observations. When the partial agonists oxotremorine (Oxo) and pilocarpine (Pilo) are used to stimulate M2R, reduced GIRK currents are associated with reduced BRET signals for Gβγ-Venus binding to GIRK-NLuc (blue symbols in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1D</xref>). Furthermore, when amounts of available Gα<sub>i1</sub> are increased (so that more Gα<sub>i1</sub>(GDP)βγ-Venus can form), the partial agonist Oxo gives rise to a BRET signal as strong as that of ACh (orange symbols in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1D</xref>). A similar effect was also observed with Pilo, although to a lesser extent. These results are explicable on the basis of the G protein trimer-GPCR on-rate determining the efficacy of different agonists. Thus, <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub> can explain the difference in agonists versus partial agonists as well as the fundamental difference between M2R and βARs with respect to their ability to activate GIRK channels. In the model we present, <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub>, is rate limiting under physiological G protein concentrations, and its magnitude determines differential rates of Gβγ generation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The essential conclusion of this study is that M2R catalyzes the generation of Gβγ at a higher rate than β2AR, thus achieving higher concentrations of Gβγ to activate GIRK. The concentrations of Gα<sub>s</sub>(GTP) generated by β2AR are obviously sufficient to stimulate the downstream-amplified Gα<sub>s</sub> pathway and speed heart rate, but the lower Gβγ levels generated are insufficient to activate GIRK to a great extent. The higher rate of Gβγ generation by M2R likely stems from an intrinsically higher rate of association with G protein trimer. This conclusion is most easily appreciated through careful inspection of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D and E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1E</xref>, where it is shown that endogenous levels of Gα (in the presence of expressed Gβγ-Venus to detect Gβγ binding to GIRK) permit Gβγ generation by M2R, but not by β2AR. Furthermore, over-expression of Gα and Gβγ increases the rate of Gβγ generation in both cases, but higher levels of Gα expression are needed for the β2AR to reach its maximum rate. Thus, Gβγ specificity is explicable on the basis of a difference in the rate at which M2R and β2AR associate with G protein trimer, M2R being faster.</p><p>The forward rate in the first step of the reaction cycle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>) is <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> [G protein trimer] [GPCR]. Therefore, a difference in the rate constant <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> or either reactant concentration will change the forward rate. We have four reasons to conclude that the difference lies primarily in a difference in <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic>. First, we have shown in HEK-293T cells that the endogenous concentration of Gα<sub>i</sub> does not exceed Gα<sub>s</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>) and therefore it is unlikely that Gα<sub>i</sub> trimer exceeds Gα<sub>s</sub> trimer. Moreover, we estimate the levels of GPCR density expressed in HEK-293T cells to be similar for M2R and β2AR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B and C</xref>). Second, given that endogenous levels of Gα<sub>i</sub> are not greater than Gα<sub>s</sub> in HEK-293T cells, the difference in the rate of Gβγ generation (mediated by M2R versus β2AR) as reported by the BRET assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1E</xref>) is explicable on the basis of a difference in <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic>. Third, the higher rate of Gβγ dissociation from Gα, mediated by M2R versus β2AR (and also D2R versus β1AR), is most simply explained by a difference in <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>). Fourth, the recent single molecule study showing an intrinsically larger <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> for α2AR (a Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCR) compared to β2AR is completely consistent with the three reasons enumerated above (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>). Therefore, we conclude that the basis of specificity we are describing here is explained by a difference in <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic>. It is possible that differences in Gα<sub>i</sub> versus Gα<sub>s</sub> concentrations in certain cell types could further contribute to specificity. However, a difference in <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> alone can explain specificity.</p><p>When G protein trimer associates with a GPCR, both Gα and receptor undergo a series of conformational changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Rasmussen et al., 2011</xref>). A chimera Gα subunit containing mostly Gα<sub>i1</sub> amino acids and only 13 C-terminal Gα<sub>s</sub> amino acids – that engage the receptor – is known to permit βAR activation of GIRK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Leaney et al., 2000</xref>). This observation suggests that the Gα conformational change, which involves the main body of the Gα subunit, might be more important in determining the rate of G protein trimer-GPCR association.</p><p>The M2R-GIRK signaling pathway is characterized by four key features: M2R density over the entire cell membrane is relatively low (~5 µm<sup>−2</sup>), M2R turnover rate (i.e. Gβγ generation rate) is slow (maximum rate <italic>k</italic><sub>23</sub> ~1 sec<sup>−1</sup>), Gβγ lifetime is short (~1 s), and the affinity of Gβγ for GIRK is not very high (1.9 mM for the first Gβγ and a cooperativity factor of 0.3 for each successive Gβγ). These features have important consequences. The expected steady state concentration profile of Gβγ surrounding an isolated M2R catalyzing even at its maximum rate (<italic>k</italic><sub>23</sub>) shows that Gβγ never reaches sufficient levels to activate GIRK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7D and F</xref>). This is because as Gβγ is generated it both diffuses away (diffusion coefficient, D ~ 0.2 µm<sup>2</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup>) and is re-sequestered by Gα(GDP) in approximately one second (k ~ 1 sec<sup>−1</sup>), causing the Gβγ concentration to decay over a characteristic distance (D/k)<sup>1/2</sup>. This circumstance explains why β2AR does not activate GIRK even when it is tethered to the channel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). And it implies that the macromolecular super-complex hypothesis can not work very well to activate GIRK or to explain Gβγ specificity. At a density of 5 µm<sup>−2</sup>, M2Rs are too far apart from each other to build up the Gβγ concentration. But at a density of 50 M2Rs µm<sup>−2</sup>, sufficiently high Gβγ concentrations can be reached: the expected concentration profile surrounding a disk-shaped ‘hotspot’ of radius 0.3 µm is shown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7E and F</xref>). In the middle of the hotspot, which contains about 14 M2Rs, Gβγ concentration reaches 12.5 µm<sup>−2</sup> (2.5 µM in a layer 80 Å thick beneath the membrane), which is enough to activate GIRK channels that happen to be located within the disk. At a fixed GPCR density (50 µm<sup>−2</sup>), the steady state Gβγ concentration depends on the size of the disk (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7G</xref>). It is notable that the predicted disk size – several hundred nm to 1 µm – required to achieve sufficiently high concentrations of Gβγ to activate GIRK matches well with G protein signaling hotspots observed in cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>In summary, Gβγ specificity is determined by more rapid Gα<sub>i</sub>(GDP)Gβγ association with M2R compared to Gα<sub>s</sub>(GDP)Gβγ association with β2AR. A sufficient density of GPCRs is required to achieve GIRK-activating concentrations of Gβγ. This is apparently achieved through the formation of hotspots of higher GPCR and G protein density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sungkaworn et al., 2017</xref>). But specificity is explained by the magnitude of a rate constant.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Reagent type (species) <break/>or resource</th><th valign="top">Designation</th><th valign="top">Source or reference</th><th valign="top">Identifiers</th><th valign="top">Additional <break/>information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Rabbit monoclonal anti Gα<sub>i1</sub></td><td valign="top">Abcam</td><td valign="top">Cat. #: ab140125</td><td valign="top">1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Rabbit monoclonal Anti Gα<sub>i2</sub></td><td valign="top">Abcam</td><td valign="top">Cat. #: ab157204</td><td valign="top">1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Mouse monoclonal anti Gα<sub>o</sub></td><td valign="top">Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td><td valign="top">Cat. #: sc-13532</td><td valign="top">1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Rabbit polyclonal anti Gα<sub>s/olf</sub></td><td valign="top">Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td><td valign="top">Cat. #: sc-383</td><td valign="top">1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Rabbit polyclonal anti SNAP tag</td><td valign="top">NEB</td><td valign="top">Cat. #: P9310S</td><td valign="top">1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Rabbit polyclonal anti Halo tag</td><td valign="top">Promega</td><td valign="top">Cat. #: G9281</td><td valign="top">1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">cAMP ELISA Detection Kit</td><td valign="top">GenScript</td><td valign="top">Cat. #: L00460</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">NLuc substrate</td><td valign="top">Promega</td><td valign="top">Cat. #: N1110</td><td valign="top">1:50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (Homo Sapiens)</td><td valign="top">Flp-In-T-REx-293</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher</td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_U427">CVCL_U427</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (Homo Sapiens)</td><td valign="top">HEK-293 tsA201</td><td valign="top">Sigma</td><td valign="top">RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_2737">CVCL_2737</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (Cricetulus griseus)</td><td valign="top">Chinese Hamster Ovary Cells</td><td valign="top">Sigma</td><td valign="top">RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_0213">CVCL_0213</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (Spodoptera frugiperda)</td><td valign="top">Sf9 cells</td><td valign="top">Sigma</td><td valign="top">RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_0549">CVCL_0549</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software</td><td valign="top">Mathematica</td><td valign="top">Wolfram</td><td valign="top">SCR_014448</td><td valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Experimental model and subject details</title><sec id="s4-1-1"><title>Animals</title><p>C57BL/6J (Jackson Labs) male and female adult mice (≥10 weeks old) were used. Animals were kept in cages with a 12:12 hr light/dark cycle and unrestricted access to food and water. All experimental procedures were carried out according to a protocol approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) of The Rockefeller University (Protocol #16864).</p></sec><sec id="s4-1-2"><title>Cell lines</title><p>HEK-293T tsA201 cells were obtained from Sigma and maintained in DMEM (Thermo Fisher) supplemented with 10% Fetal Bovine Serum (FBS, Thermo Fisher) and 1% L-glutamine (Thermo Fisher). Chinese Hamster Ovary cells were obtained from Sigma and maintained in DMEM/F12 (Thermo Fisher) supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% L-glutamine. Sf9 cells were obtained from Sigma and maintained in Grace’s Insect medium (Thermo Fisher) supplemented with 10% FBS and Pluronic<sup>TM</sup> F-68 (Thermo Fisher).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s4-2-1"><title>Sinoatrial node (SAN) isolation</title><p>Adult mice (≥10 weeks old) were anesthetized with 90–150 mg/kg ketamine and 7.5–16 mg/kg xylazine IP (Sigma-Aldrich). After 5–10 min, when mice stopped responding to tail/toe pinches they were secured in the supine position by gently fixing their forepaws and hindpaws to a pinnable work surface on an animal surgery tray. SAN isolation was performed according to a published procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Sharpe et al., 2016</xref>). A midline skin incision was made from the mid abdomen to the diaphragm with a surgical scissor. The heart was exposed after cutting the diaphragm and holding the sternum with curved serrated forceps. The heart was lifted and dissected out of the thoracic cavity as near as possible to the dorsal thoracic wall. The isolated heart was transferred to a petri dish containing Tyrode’s solution (140 mM NaCl, 5.4 mM KCl, 1.2 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 5.5 mM D-glucose, 1 mg/mL BSA, 5 mM HEPES-NaOH [pH 7.4]), and quickly washed several times to remove residual blood. The heart was dissected and the ventricles were removed. The atria were transferred to a silicone dissection dish and pinned through the inferior and superior vena cavae and the right and left atrial appendages. The interatrial septum was exposed by opening the anterior wall. Next, the right atrial appendage was removed and the SAN was isolated by cutting along the cristae terminals.</p><p>The isolated SAN was transferred to low-Ca<sup>2+</sup>/Mg<sup>2+</sup> Tyrode’s solution (140 mM NaCl, 5.4 mM KCl, 1.2 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 5.5 mM D-glucose, 50 mM Taurine, 1 mg/mL BSA, 5 mM HEPES-NaOH [pH 7.4]) and incubated for 5 min at 37°C. Next the SAN was washed with low-Ca<sup>2+</sup>/Mg<sup>2+</sup> Tyrode’s solution twice, transferred to low-Ca<sup>2+</sup>/Mg<sup>2+</sup> Tyrode’s solution with enzymes (0.5 mg/mL Elastase [Worthington], 1.0 mg/mL Type II Collagenase [Worthington], and 0.5 mg/mL Protease xiv [Sigma-Aldrich]), and incubated for 15–20 min at 37°C. Digested tissue was transferred to Kraftbrühe (KB) medium (100 mM K-glutamate, 10 mM K-aspartate, 25 mM KCl, 10 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 2 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 20 mM Taurine, 5 mM Creatine, 0.5 mM EGTA, 20 mM D-glucose, 1 mg/mL BSA, 5 mM HEPES-KOH [pH 7.2]), and gently washed. The tissue was washed two more times with KB medium and cells were dissociated by constant trituration at approximately 0.5–1 Hz for 5–10 min. CaCl<sub>2</sub> solution was added stepwise (200 µM, 400 µM, 600 µM, and 1 mM) every 5 min to reach to a final concentration of 1 mM. Subsequently an equal volume of Tyrode’s solution was gradually added to the KB solution with dissociated cells. Finally, dissociated cells were centrifuged for 3 min at 150 g, resuspended in Tyrode’s solution, and plated onto PDL/Laminin pre-coated glass bottom dishes for ~1 hr prior to electrophysiological recordings.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-2"><title>Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings on SAN cells</title><p>Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings were performed with an Axopatch 200B amplifier in whole-cell mode. The analog current signal was low-pass filtered at 1 kHz (Bessel) and digitized at 20 kHz with a Digidata 1440A digitizer. Digitized data were recorded using the software pClamp. Patch electrodes (resistance 2.0–4.0 MΩ) were pulled on a Sutter P-97 puller (Sutter Instrument Company, Novato, CA) from 1.5 mm outer diameter filamented borosilicate glass. Spontaneous action potential recordings were performed using the amphotericin perforated-patch technique in current-clamp mode without current injection. For voltage-clamp recordings membrane potential was held at −80 mV throughout the experiments and the extracellular solution was exchanged via local perfusion with a 100 µm diameter perfusion pencil positioned adjacent to the cell. The bath solution contained 140 mM NaCl, 5.4 mM KCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM D-glucose, 10 mM HEPES-NaOH (pH 7.4) (~290 mOsm). For the voltage-clamp recordings, the extracellular solution was exchanged to high K<sup>+</sup> solution containing 130 mM NaCl, 15.4 mM KCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM D-glucose, 10 mM HEPES-NaOH (pH7.4) (~290 mOsm). The pipette solution contained 9 mM NaCl, 140 mM K-gluconate, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.5 mM EGTA-K, 10 mM HEPES-KOH (pH7.4), 3 mM MgATP, 0.05 mM Na<sub>2</sub>GTP, 200 µM Amphotericin-B (Sigma-Aldrich) (~310 mOsm).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-3"><title>Establishment of the stable HEK-293T cell lines</title><p>A SNAP tag was fused to the C-terminus of the full-length GIRK4 channel. A serotonin 5-HT signal peptide and a Halo tag were fused to the N-terminus of human full-length M2R or β2AR. Both GIRK4-SNAP and Halo-M2R or Halo-β2AR were cloned into the pcDNA5/FRT/TO vector. An internal ribosome entry site (IRES) sequence was inserted between SNAP-GIRK4 and Halo-GPCR to allow for their simultaneous expression under the same promoter. Stable HEK-293T cell lines were produced using the Flp-In T-REx-293 System according to the manufacturer’s protocol (ThermoFisher).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-4"><title>Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings on HEK-293T and CHO cells expressing GIRK channels</title><p>Human M2R, β2AR, D2R, and mouse β1AR were cloned into a pCEH vector for mammalian expression. A serotonin 5-HT cleavable signal peptide and a SNAP tag were inserted into the N-terminus of each receptor (Sero-SNAP-GPCR). The C-terminal GFP-tagged GIRK4 (GIRK4-GFP) was cloned into a pCEH vector. Human G proteins (Gα<sub>i1</sub>, Gα<sub>s</sub>, and Gβ<sub>1</sub>-IRES-Gγ<sub>2</sub>) were also cloned into a pCEH vector. Sero-SNAP-GPCR and GIRK4-GFP were transiently transfected to HEK-293T or CHO cells, and cells were incubated at 37°C for 20–24 hr. Stable HEK-293T cell lines expressing Sero-Halo-GPCR and GIRK4-SNAP were seeded at 0.4 million cells/mL, and expression was induced with 1 µg/mL of doxycycline. At the same time, G proteins were transiently transfected and cells were incubated at 37°C for 20–24 hr. Cells were then dissociated and plated on PDL/Laminin-pre-coated glass coverslips for electrophysiological recordings. Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings were performed with the same setup, pipettes, and perfusion system as described above. The low potassium extracellular solution contained 150 mM NaCl, 5.4 mM KCl, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM D-glucose, 10 mM HEPES-NaOH (pH 7.4) (~290 mOsm). The extracellular solution was exchanged to high K<sup>+</sup> solution containing 53 mM NaCl, 100 mM KCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM D-glucose, 10 mM HEPES-NaOH (pH7.4) (~290 mOsm). The pipette solution contained 9 mM NaCl, 140 mM K-gluconate, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.5 mM EGTA-K, 10 mM HEPES-KOH (pH7.4), 3 mM MgATP, 0.05 mM Na<sub>2</sub>GTP (~310 mOsm).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-5"><title>Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings on Sf9 cell</title><p>The human M2R, β2AR, mouse β1AR, and human GIRK4 were cloned into a pFB vector for insect cell expression. A PreScission protease cleavage site, an enhanced green fluorescent protein (eGFP) and a deca-histidine tag were placed at the C-terminus of each construct. Sf9 cells were co-infected with P3 baculovirus with GPCRs and GIRK4 and incubated at 27°C for 40–48 hr. Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings were performed with the same system, pipettes, and perfusion system as described above. The low potassium extracellular solution contained 135 mM NaCl, 10 mM KCl, 4 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM MES-KOH (pH 6.4) (~320 mOsm). The high potassium extracellular solution contained 45 mM NaCl, 100 mM KCl, 4 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM HEPES-KOH (pH6.4) (~300 mOsm). The pipette solution contained 85 mM KCl, 60 mM KF, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 mM EGTA-K, 10 mM HEPES-KOH (pH7.2), 3 mM MgATP, 0.05 mM Na<sub>2</sub>GTP (~320 mOsm).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-6"><title>Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings on HEK-293T cells expressing GPCR-GIRK concatemers</title><p>Full-length human GIRK4 was fused to the C-terminus of full-length human M2R or β2AR. A serotonin 5-HT cleavable signal peptide and a Halo tag were fused to the N-terminus of each concatemer. Additionally, a SNAP tag was fused to the C-terminus of each concatemer. Concatemers were transiently transfected and cells were incubated at 37°C for 20–24 hr. Cells were then dissociated and plated on PDL/Laminin-pre-coated glass coverslips for electrophysiological recordings. Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings were performed with the same system, pipettes, perfusion system, and solutions as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-7"><title>Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings on HEK-293T cells expressing TRPM3 channels</title><p>Mouse TRPM3α2 was cloned into a pEG BacMam vector. A PreScission protease cleavage site, an enhanced green fluorescent protein (eGFP), and 1D4 peptide tag were placed at the C-terminus of the TRPM3 construct. TRPM3-eGFP, Sero-SNAP-GPCR, and G proteins were transiently transfected to HEK-293T cells and cells were incubated at 30°C for 48–72 hr. Cells were then dissociated and plated on PDL/Laminin-pre-coated glass coverslips for electrophysiological recordings. Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings were performed as described above. The currents were recorded using a ramp protocol from −100 mV to +100 mV, applied every second, and the currents at +100 mV were plotted. TRPM3 currents were evoked by 10 µM pregnenolone sulfate (PS) (Tocris).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-8"><title>Western blot</title><p>Untransfected HEK-293T cells or HEK-293T cells transiently transfected with GPCR-GIRK4 concatemers were centrifuged and mixed with an equal volume of loading buffer containing 4% SDS and 10% β-mercaptoethanol. Samples were then run using standard SDS-PAGE procedures on Invitrogen NuPAGE 4–12% Bis-Tris gels and transferred onto PVDF membranes. Western Blot was performed using an anti-SNAP-tag (NEB), anti-HaloTag (Promega), anti-Gα<sub>i1</sub> (abcam, ab140125), anti-Gα<sub>i2</sub> (abcam, ab157204), anti-Gα<sub>o</sub> (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, sc-13532), or anti-Gα<sub>s</sub> (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, sc-383).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-9"><title>cAMP quantification assay</title><p>Untransfected HEK-293T cells or HEK-293T cells transfected with βARs were cultured in 12-well plates for 20–24 hr. Sf9 cells infected with P3 baculovirus of βARs were cultured in 12-well plates for 40–48 hr. Cells were treated with either 10 µM isoprenaline or propranolol for 10 min and washed twice with PBS + 500 µM isobutylmethylxanthine (IBMX). Cells were collected in 200 µL PBS + IBMX, exposed to four freeze-thaw cycles, and centrifuged (14,000 rpm) for 10 min at 4°C. The supernatant was analyzed for cAMP content according to the manufacturer’s protocol (cAMP ELISA Detection Kit, GeneScript).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-10"><title>BRET sample preparation</title><p>pCEH plasmids encoding Sero-SNAP-M2R, Sero-SNAP-β2AR, Sero-SNAP-β1AR, and Sero-SNAP-D2R were used in BRET experiments. For Gα-Venus constructs, Venus was inserted to either the αa-αb loop (between residues 91 and 92 for Gα<sub>i1</sub> and 113 and 114 for Gα<sub>s</sub>) or the αb-αc loop (between residues 121 and 122 for Gα<sub>i1</sub> and 144 and 145 for Gα<sub>s</sub>) with flanking SGGGS linkers. Human Gα<sub>i1</sub>, Gα<sub>s</sub>, Gα<sub>i1</sub>(αa-αb)-Venus, Gα<sub>i1</sub>(αb-αc)-Venus, Gα<sub>s</sub>(αa-αb)-Venus, and Gα<sub>s</sub>(αb-αc)-Venus were cloned into a pCEH vector. Venus 156–239-Gβ<sub>1</sub> and Venus 1–155-Gγ<sub>2</sub> were cloned into a pCEH-IRES vector to allow for expression of Gβγ-Venus from a single plasmid. Nano Luciferase-Gβ<sub>1</sub> (NLuc-Gβ<sub>1</sub>) and Gγ<sub>2</sub> were cloned into a pCEH-IRES vector to allow for expression of Gβγ-NLuc from a single plasmid. masGRK3ct, masGRK3ct-NLuc, GIRK4-NLuc, and Kir2.2-NLuc were also cloned into a pCEH vector.</p><p>For the BRET measurements between Gβγ-Venus and GIRK4-NLuc, 0.35 million HEK-293T cells were plated in each well of 12-well plates and incubated overnight at 37°C. After overnight incubation, cells were transfected with Sero-SNAP-GPCR (90 ng), Gβγ-Venus (90 ng), GIRK4-NLuc (90 ng) and different amounts of Gα (90 ng × 0, 1, 2, and 4) using Lipofectamine 2000 (ThermoFisher). Transfected cells were incubated for 20–24 hr at 37°C and then used for BRET measurements. GIRK4-NLuc was replaced by masGRK3ct-NLuc or Kir2.2-NLuc for control samples.</p><p>For BRET measurements between Gα-Venus and Gβγ-NLuc, HEK-293T cells were transfected with Sero-SNAP-GPCR (90 ng), Gβγ-NLuc (90 ng), masGRK3ct (90 ng), and Gα-Venus (90–450 ng), and incubated for 20–24 hr at 30°C or 37°C. The measured light emitted by Gβγ-NLuc is proportional to the amount of Gβγ-NLuc in the sample, and the measured light emitted by Gα-Venus is proportional to the amount of G protein trimers in the sample. By having equal intensities for Gβγ-NLuc and Gα-Venus (i.e. NLuc intensity and basal BRET ratio), the rate of Gβγ release can be compared and contrasted for different GPCRs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). Therefore, samples of each GPCR were prepared with different transfected Gα-Venus-DNA amounts (90–450 ng) to carry out these experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-11"><title>BRET measurements</title><p>After 20–24 hr incubation, transfected HEK-293T cells were washed with PBS twice and detached by incubation in PBS + 5 mM EDTA for 5 min at room temperature. Cells were harvested by centrifugation at 300 g for 3 min and resuspended into 350 µL BRET buffer (PBS supplemented with 0.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 0.1% D-glucose). 25 µL of the suspension containing ~70,000 cells was transferred to each well in a 96-well flat-bottom white microplate (Greiner CELLSTAR). The NLuc substrate (Promega) was diluted into the BRET buffer according to the manufacturer’s protocol, and 25 µL of diluted NLuc substrate were added to the cells in 96-well plates. BRET measurements were made with a microplate reader (Synergy Neo, BioTek) equipped with two emission photomultiplier tubes. The BRET signal was determined by calculating the ratio of the light emitted by Venus (535 nm with a 30 nm band width) to the light emitted by NLuc (475 nm with a 30 nm bandwidth).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-12"><title>Expression and purification</title><p>Human full-length GIRK4 was cloned into a pEG BacMam vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Goehring et al., 2014</xref>). A PreScission protease cleavage site, an enhanced green fluorescent protein (eGFP) and a 1D4 peptide tag were placed for purification at the C-terminus of the GIRK4 construct. For overexpression and protein purification, HEK-293S GnTl<sup>-</sup> cells were grown in suspension, infected with P3 BacMam virus of the GIRK4-1D4 and incubated at 37°C. At 8–12 hr post-infection, 10 mM sodium butyrate was added to the culture, and cells were harvested 60 hr post-transduction. Cells were harvested by centrifugation, frozen in liquid N<sub>2</sub>, and stored at −80°C until needed. Frozen cells were solubilized in 50 mM HEPES (pH 7.35), 150 mM KCl, 4% (w/v) n-decyl-β-D-maltopyranoside (DM), and the protease inhibitor cocktail (0.1 mg/mL pepstatin, 1 mg/mL leupeptin, 1 mg/mL aprotinin, 0.1 mg/mL soy trypsin inhibitor, 1 mM benzamidine, and 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride). After 2 hr of solubilization, lysed cells were centrifuged at 36,000 g for 30 min and the supernatant was incubated with 1D4 affinity resin for 1 hr at 4°C with gentle mixing. The resin was loaded onto a column and washed with buffer A (50 mM HEPES [pH 7.0], 150 mM KCl, 0.4% [w/v] DM). 5 mM DTT and 1 mM EDTA were added, and eGFP and affinity tags were cut with PreScission protease overnight at 4°C. The cleaved protein was then concentrated and run on a Superose 6 10/300 GL gel filtration column in 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 150 mM KCl, 0.2% (w/v) DM, 20 mM DTT, and 1 mM EDTA.</p><p>Human lipid-anchored Gβ<sub>1</sub>γ<sub>2</sub>, and soluble Gβ<sub>1</sub>γ<sub>2</sub> were purified as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Wang et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Human full-length Gα<sub>i1</sub> Gα<sub>i2</sub>, Gα<sub>i3</sub>, Gα<sub>o</sub>, and Gα<sub>s</sub> were cloned into a pET28a vector. A PreScission protease cleavage (PPX) site followed by a deca-histidine tag was fused to the N-terminus of Gα. The His<sub>10</sub>-PPX-Gα-pET28a vector was transformed into BL21(DE3) <italic>E. coli</italic> cells and transformants were cultured in LB medium containing 50 µg/L of kanamycin at 37°C for 4 hr. Isopropyl-thio-β-D-galactopyranoside was added to a final concentration of 0.5 mM to induce protein expression. Following an additional incubation at 25°C for 12 hr, the cells were harvested by centrifugation and resuspended in buffer B (200 mM HEPES-NaOH [pH 7.5], 300 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 10 µM MgGDP) and a protease inhibitor cocktail. Cell extracts were obtained by sonication followed by centrifugation at 36,000 g for 30 min. The supernatant was incubated with Talon metal affinity resin (Clontech) for 1 hr at 4°C with gentle mixing. The resin was washed in batch with five column volumes of buffer B, then loaded onto a column and further washed with 10 column volumes of buffer B + 20 mM imidazole. The column was then eluted with buffer B + 200 mM imidazole.</p><p>For Western Blotting analysis, the eluted protein was concentrated and run on a Superdex 200 10/300 GL gel filtration column in 10 mM potassium phosphate (pH 7.4), 150 mM KCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 10 µM GDP.</p><p>For the planar lipid bilayer experiment, the eluted protein was concentrated and run on a Superdex 200 10/300 GL gel filtration column in 10 mM potassium phosphate (pH 7.4), 150 mM KCl, and 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. 1 mM GTP-γS was then added to ~1 mg/mL purified proteins and incubated at 37°C for 30 min to produce His<sub>10</sub>-PPX-Gα(GTP-γS). Residual amounts of His<sub>10</sub>-PPX-Gα(GDP) affect the results of the subsequent bilayer experiment described below. Therefore purified His<sub>10</sub>-PPX-Gα(GTP-γS) was mixed with soluble Gβγ at a ratio of 4:1 (molar:molar) to chelate all the possibly contaminating His<sub>10</sub>-PPX-Gα(GDP). This low concentration of Gβγ does not affect GIRK activity.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-13"><title>Reconstitution of proteoliposomes</title><p>All lipids were purchased from Avanti Polar Lipids (Alabaster, AL). Proteoliposomes were reconstituted as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Wang et al., 2014</xref>). In brief, 20 mg/mL of the lipid mixture (3:1 [wt:wt]=1-palmitoyl-2-oleyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphoethanolamine [POPE] : 1-palmitoyl-2-oleyl-sn-glycero-3-phospho-[1’-rac-glycerol] [POPG]) was dispersed by sonication and solubilized with 20 mM DM.</p><p>Purified GIRK4 channels and Gβγ were combined with lipid mixtures at a ratio of GIRK4:Gβγ:lipid (wt:wt)=1:0.1:10. The protein-lipid mixtures were then diluted into reconstitution buffer (10 mM potassium phosphate [pH 7.4], 150 mM KCl, 1 mM EDTA, and 3 mM DTT) to make 1 mg/mL GIRK4, 0.1 mg/mL Gβγ, and 10 mg/mL (lipid mixture). Detergent was removed by dialysis against the reconstitution buffer at 4°C for 4 days.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-14"><title>Planar lipid bilayer recordings</title><p>Bilayer membranes were made as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wang et al., 2016</xref>). In brief, 1,2-dioleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphoetanolamine (DOPE) and 1-palmitoyl-2-oleyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (POPC) were mixed at a 1:1 ratio (wt:wt) and doped with 3% DGS-NTA (mole fraction). A lipid solution at 20 mg/mL was then prepared using decane. This solution was painted over a ~ 120 µm hole on a piece of transparency film to form a lipid bilayer. The same recording buffer (10 mM potassium phosphate [pH 7.4], 150 mM KCl, and 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>) was used in both chambers. Voltage across the lipid bilayer was clamped using an Axopatch 200B amplifier (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA) in whole-cell mode. The analog current signal was low-pass filtered at 1 kHz (Bessel) and digitized at 20 kHz with a Digidata 1440A digitizer (Molecular Devices). Digitized data were recorded using the software pClamp (Molecular Devices).</p><p>After forming a lipid bilayer, proteoliposomes containing GIRK4 and Gβγ at a ratio of 1:0.1 (wt:wt) were applied to the bilayer multiple times until they fused to the bilayer. The channels were then activated by adding 32 µM C8-PIP<sub>2</sub> and 8 mM NaCl to the chamber. GIRK4 channels were partially activated in this condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A</xref>.). 300 µM GTP-γS and 2 µM soluble Gβγ were added to the chamber to chelate possible contamination of His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GDP). This low concentration of added Gβγ does not affect GIRK activity. 500 µM NiSO<sub>4</sub> was added directly to the bilayer twice to charge DGS-NTA lipids with Ni<sup>2+</sup>. A solution of 30 µM His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) supplemented with 32 µM C8-PIP<sub>2</sub> was then perfused directly to the bilayer membrane several times until no further blockage was observed. Given the affinity of His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) to the bilayer containing 3% DGS-NTA lipids is ~0.5 µM, 30 µM His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) was used to saturate DGS-NTA lipids in the bilayer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B–1D</xref>). The transient current decrease upon addition of His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) is due to the absence of Na<sup>+</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C and D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-15"><title>Confocal microscopy of HEK-293T cells</title><p>HEK-293T cells were transiently transfected with SNAP-M2R or SNAP-β2AR. After overnight incubation at 37°C, the cells were treated with 3 µM SNAP-Surface 488 (NEB) in DMEM/FBS for 30 min to stain the SNAP-tagged receptors. Cells were then washed several times with PBS, fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde, and imaged under a ZEISS inverted LSM 880 NLO laser scanning confocal microscope with an oil immersion 40 × objective (numerical aperture 1.40). Microscope and software settings were kept the same for all images acquired. The fluorophore was excited with a white light laser of 488 nm.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-16"><title>Confocal microscopy of giant unilamellar vesicles (GUVs)</title><p>DOPE:POPC 1:1 (wt:wt) lipid mixture with 3% DGS-NTA lipids was used to produce GUVs. GUVs were prepared according to a published protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Martinac et al., 2010</xref>). In short, the lipid mixture was dried under a stream of argon. 2 µL of water was added to dried lipids to hydrate the lipids. After 3 min, 1 mL of 0.4 M sucrose solution was added. The lipid solution was then moved to a water bath and incubated at 42°C for 3 hr to form GUVs. To monitor the interaction between GUVs and His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS), Alexa Fluor 488 labeled His<sub>10</sub>-Gα(GTP-γS) was prepared in a buffer containing 10 mM potassium phosphate pH 7.4, 150 mM KCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 2 nM NiSO<sub>4</sub>. This protein solution was then mixed with 1/50 vol of GUVs. The equator plane of GUVs was imaged using a ZEISS inverted LSM 880 NLO laser scanning confocal microscope with an oil immersion 100 × objective (numerical aperture 1.40). Microscope and software settings were kept the same for all images acquired. The fluorophore was excited with a white light laser of 488 nm. The fluorescence intensity at the edge of the GUVs was measured using the Zeiss ZEN two software.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-17"><title>Kinetic simulation</title><p>Mass balance equations were derived based on the model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). Rate constants used in the simulation are presented and referenced in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2">Table 2</xref>. The set of first order differential equations was solved using the NDSolve function in Mathematica (Wolfram).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-18"><title>Diffusion model</title><p>The graphs in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7D and F</xref> (dashed) were generated by solving for the concentration of Gβγ (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf1"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula>) analytically, using DSolve in Mathematica, the equation <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf2"><mml:mo>∇</mml:mo><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>∇</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> in polar coordinates with the near boundary condition set at the perimeter of an 0.01 µm radius circle corresponding to a flux of 15.9 Gβγ µm<sup>−1</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup> (which corresponds to a single GPCR inside the circle with a turnover rate of 1 Gβγ sec<sup>−1</sup>) and far boundary condition zero. <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf3"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the diffusion coefficient (0.2 µm<sup>2</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup>) and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf4"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the Gβγ decay constant (1 sec<sup>−1</sup>). To model a GPCR density of 5 µm<sup>−2</sup>, on average the small circle with a GPCR resides within a circle of radius ~ 0.25 µm. At 0.25 µm the Gβγ concentration has not decayed to zero and therefore neighboring GPCRs increase the Gβγ concentration slightly above what is shown for a lone GPCR in an essentially infinite membrane, but not enough to activate GIRK. The graphs in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7E and F</xref> (solid curve) were generated numerically, using NDSolve in Mathematica, the equation <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf5"><mml:mo>∇</mml:mo><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>∇</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, applying a circular finite element mesh with a zero concentration boundary condition at the perimeter, far from a smaller, central ‘hotspot’ circle. <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf6"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> refers to Gβγ generation (molecules µm<sup>−2</sup> sec<sup>−1</sup>) and is applied over the hotspot. The magnitude of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf7"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> was selected to be near the steady state value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf8"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> in the kinetic equations. At a radius 3.16 times the hotspot radius (i.e. corresponding to a circular area 10 times the hotspot area) the Gβγ concentration is not zero (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7F</xref>) and therefore in a cell with hotspots covering 10% of the membrane the Gβγ concentration will be slightly higher than shown for the case of a lone hotspot. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7G</xref> graphs the <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf9"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula> solution to equation<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf10"><mml:mo>∇</mml:mo><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>∇</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, solved as described.</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Catherine Proenza for sharing the unpublished murine SAN isolation protocol, and David C.Gadsby for advice on SAN isolation. We thank Andrew Siliciano for advice on BRET experiments and sharing BRET constructs, Stephan Philipp for sharing mTPRM3 constructs, Thomas P. Sakmar for sharing human Gα<sub>i2</sub> constructs, and staff of RU resource centers (the Bio-Imaging Resource Center, the High-Throughput Screening Resource Center, and the Comparative Bioscience Center). We thank David CGadsby and members of the MacKinnon and Chen laboratory, especially Weiwei Wang for helpful discussions and Christoph Haselwandter for advice on the finite element method. We thank Chia-Hsueh Lee, Ji Sun, Michael Oldham, Emily Brown, and James Chen for advice on the manuscript.</p><p>This work was supported in part by GM43949. RM is an investigator in the Howard Hughes Medical Institute.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Software, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Project administration, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Software, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Validation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Project administration, Writing—review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1"><p>Animal experimentation: C57BL/6J (Jackson Labs) male and female adult mice (at least 10 weeks old) were used. Animals were kept in cages with a 12:12 h light/dark cycle and unrestricted access to food and water. All experimental procedures were carried out according to a protocol approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) of The Rockefeller University (Protocol #16864).</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.018</object-id><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-42908-transrepform-v2.pdf"/></supplementary-material><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atwood</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wager-Miller</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackie</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Straiker</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Expression of G protein-coupled receptors and related proteins in HEK293, AtT20, BV2, and N18 cell lines as revealed by microarray analysis</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>14</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-12-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21214938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badheka</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yudin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Borbiro</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartle</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yazici</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirshahi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohacs</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Inhibition of Transient Receptor Potential Melastatin 3 ion channels by G-protein βγ subunits</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e26147</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.26147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28829742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breitwieser</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Szabo</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year><article-title>Mechanism of muscarinic receptor-induced K<sup>+</sup> channel activation as revealed by hydrolysis-resistant GTP analogues</article-title><source>The Journal of General Physiology</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.91.4.469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2455765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brodde</surname> <given-names>OE</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Adrenergic and muscarinic receptors in the human heart</article-title><source>Pharmacological Reviews</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10581327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clancy</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Finley</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suen</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrabit</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berton</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosaza</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Casey</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Slesinger</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Pertussis-toxin-sensitive Galpha subunits selectively bind to C-terminal domain of neuronal GIRK channels: evidence for a heterotrimeric G-protein-channel complex</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Neuroscience</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2004.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15691717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dembla</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Behrendt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohr</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Goecke</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sondermann</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stab</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Enzeroth</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leitner</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuñez-Badinez</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwenk</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nürnberg</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Philipp</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Greffrath</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bünemann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zakharian</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberwinkler</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Anti-nociceptive action of peripheral mu-opioid receptors by G-beta-gamma protein-mediated inhibition of TRPM3 channels</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e26280</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.26280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28826482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiFrancesco</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tortora</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Direct activation of cardiac pacemaker channels by intracellular cyclic AMP</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>351</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/351145a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1709448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiFrancesco</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>Pacemaker mechanisms in cardiac tissue</article-title><source>Annual Review of Physiology</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ph.55.030193.002323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7682045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Digby</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sethi</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Differential dissociation of G protein heterotrimers</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>586</volume><fpage>3325</fpage><lpage>3335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2008.153965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18499725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goehring</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Claxton</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Baconguis</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Althoff</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname> <given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouaux</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Screening and large-scale expression of membrane proteins in mammalian cells for structural studies</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>2574</fpage><lpage>2585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2014.173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25299155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwathmey</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Autonomic and endocrine control of cardiovascular function</article-title><source>World Journal of Cardiology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4330/wjc.v7.i4.204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25914789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregorio</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Masureel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Terry</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Juette</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Aguilar</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauge</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathiasen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Javitch</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Single-molecule analysis of ligand efficacy in β<sub>2</sub>AR-G-protein activation</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>547</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature22354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28607487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hein</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochais</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorsch</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname> <given-names>VO</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berlot</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bünemann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Gs activation is time-limiting in initiating receptor-mediated signaling</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>281</volume><fpage>33345</fpage><lpage>33351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M606713200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16963443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Masureel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Structure and dynamics of GPCR signaling complexes</article-title><source>Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41594-017-0011-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29323277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irisawa</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>Cardiac pacemaking in the sinoatrial node</article-title><source>Physiological Reviews</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.1993.73.1.197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8380502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivanina</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Varon</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peleg</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rishal</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Porozov</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dessauer</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Keren-Raifman</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dascal</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Galphai1 and Galphai3 differentially interact with, and regulate, the G protein-activated K<sup>+</sup> channel</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>17260</fpage><lpage>17268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M313425200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14963032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krapivinsky</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Krapivinsky</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickman</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapham</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>G beta gamma binds directly to the G protein-gated K<sup>+</sup> channel, IKACh</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>270</volume><fpage>29059</fpage><lpage>29062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.270.49.29059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7493925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leaney</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Milligan</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinker</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>The G protein alpha subunit has a key role in determining the specificity of coupling to, but not the activation of, G protein-gated inwardly rectifying K(+) channels</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>275</volume><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.2.921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10625628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leopoldt</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harteneck</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nürnberg</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>G proteins endogenously expressed in Sf 9 cells: interactions with mammalian histamine receptors</article-title><source>Naunyn-Schmiedeberg's Archives of Pharmacology</source><volume>356</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/PL00005044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9272728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loewi</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1921">1921</year><article-title>Über humorale übertragbarkeit der Herznervenwirkung</article-title><source>Pflügers Archiv Für Die Gesamte Physiologie Des Menschen Und Der Tiere</source><volume>189</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01738910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Logothetis</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurachi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Galper</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Neer</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapham</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1987">1987</year><article-title>The beta gamma subunits of GTP-binding proteins activate the muscarinic K<sup>+</sup> channel in heart</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>325</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/325321a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2433589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinac</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Battle</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrov</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pal</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Foo</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Vásquez</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Huynh</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloda</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Studying mechanosensitive ion channels using liposomes</article-title><source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source><volume>606</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-60761-447-0_4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20013388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masuho</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostrovskaya</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Martemyanov</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Distinct profiles of functional discrimination among G proteins determine the actions of G protein-coupled receptors</article-title><source>Science Signaling</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>ra123</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.aab4068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26628681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKinney</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nickelson</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Aksoy</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Interactions of agonists with M2 and M4 muscarinic receptor subtypes mediating cyclic AMP inhibition</article-title><source>Molecular Pharmacology</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>1014</fpage><lpage>1022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1722002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nenasheva</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neary</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mashanov</surname> <given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Birdsall</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Breckenridge</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Molloy</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Abundance, distribution, mobility and oligomeric state of M₂ muscarinic acetylcholine receptors in live cardiac muscle</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular and Cellular Cardiology</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yjmcc.2013.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23357106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peleg</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Varon</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanina</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dessauer</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dascal</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>G(alpha)(<sub>i</sub>) controls the <sup>gating</sup> of the G protein-activated K<sup>(+)</sup> channel, GIRK</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(01)00567-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11779482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitcher</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Inglese</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Arriza</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Casey</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Benovic</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwatra</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>Role of beta gamma subunits of G proteins in targeting the beta-adrenergic receptor kinase to membrane-bound receptors</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>257</volume><fpage>1264</fpage><lpage>1267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1325672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1325672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quallo</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkhatib</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentry</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>G protein βγ subunits inhibit TRPM3 ion channels in sensory neurons</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e26138</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.26138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28826490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>DeVree</surname> <given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruse</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname> <given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thian</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chae</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Calinski</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathiesen</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Caffrey</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gellman</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Steyaert</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Skiniotis</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname> <given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunahara</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Crystal structure of the β2 adrenergic receptor-Gs protein complex</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>477</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21772288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riven</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwanir</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuveny</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>GIRK channel activation involves a local rearrangement of a preformed G protein channel complex</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2006.08.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16950155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakmann</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Noma</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautwein</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1983">1983</year><article-title>Acetylcholine activation of single muscarinic K<sup>+</sup> channels in isolated pacemaker cells of the mammalian heart</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>303</volume><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/303250a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6302520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarvazyan</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ann</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Determinants of Gα<sub>i1</sub> and βγ binding</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>273</volume><fpage>7934</fpage><lpage>7940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.14.7934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitt</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunnet</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Olesen</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Cardiac potassium channel subtypes: new roles in repolarization and arrhythmia</article-title><source>Physiological Reviews</source><volume>94</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00022.2013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24692356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharpe</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>St. Clair</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Proenza</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Methods for the Isolation, Culture, and Functional Characterization of Sinoatrial Node Myocytes from Adult Mice</article-title><source>Journal of Visualized Experiments</source><volume>116</volume><elocation-id>e54555</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/54555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shea</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Omann</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Linderman</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Calculation of diffusion-limited kinetics for the reactions in collision coupling and receptor cross-linking</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>2949</fpage><lpage>2959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(97)78323-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9414209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simonds</surname> <given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>G protein regulation of adenylate cyclase</article-title><source>Trends in Pharmacological Sciences</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-6147(99)01307-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10101967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soejima</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Noma</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1984">1984</year><article-title>Mode of regulation of the ACh-sensitive K-channel by the muscarinic receptor in rabbit atrial cells</article-title><source>Pflügers Archiv European Journal of Physiology</source><volume>400</volume><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00587544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sungkaworn</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jobin</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnecki</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Weron</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Calebiro</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Single-molecule imaging reveals receptor-G protein interactions at cell surface hot spots</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>550</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature24264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29045395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Touhara</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKinnon</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>The GIRK1 subunit potentiates G protein activation of cardiac GIRK1/4 hetero-tetramers</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e15750</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.15750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27074664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Whorton</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKinnon</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Quantitative analysis of mammalian GIRK2 channel regulation by G proteins, the signaling lipid PIP2 and Na+ in a reconstituted system</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e03671</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.03671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25049222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Touhara</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Weir</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bean</surname> <given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKinnon</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Cooperative regulation by G proteins and Na<sup>(+)</sup> of neuronal GIRK2 K<sup>(+)</sup> channels</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e15751</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.15751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27074662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickman</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Iñiguez-Lluhl</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davenport</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taussig</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Krapivinsky</surname> <given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Linder</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilman</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapham</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Recombinant G-protein beta gamma-subunits activate the muscarinic-gated atrial potassium channel</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>368</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/368255a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8145826</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.020</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>Kenton Jon</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke, National Institutes of Health</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Molecular basis of signaling specificity between GIRK channels and GPCRs&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, including Kenton Jon Swartz as the Reviewing Editor and Reviewer #1, and the evaluation has been overseen by Richard Aldrich as the Senior Editor.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>This is a fascinating manuscript exploring why Gα<sub>i</sub> coupled GPCRs like M2R activate GIRK channels while Gα<sub>s</sub>coupled receptors like β2AR do not, even though both liberate the same Gβγ subunits that ultimately bind to and activate the GIRK channel. This is a systematic study by all measures, including testing a wide range of conditions, expression systems, approaches (both experimental and computational) to look at each step in the pathway to arrive at the simple and elegant solutions that the receptors that can activate GIRK channels must liberate Gβγ at faster rates and therefore achieve higher concentrations of the active subunits. The authors were also able to push the Gα<sub>s</sub>system to observe GIRK activation under non-physiological experimental conditions, which we found particularly satisfying. The additional controls with TRPM3 are beyond what we would have expected from a study such as this and they recapitulate the core conclusion. The modeling adds considerably by illustrating the conditions required for selective activation of GIRK channels. The authors are to be commended for putting together an unusually complete and conclusive story on a topic of fundamental biological importance. The presentation also fully takes advantage of the <italic>eLife</italic> format to concisely yet thoroughly present a large body of work.</p><p>Suggested revisions:</p><p>1) One point of comment is that conformational changes in both G protein and receptor proteins are required for their stable association (the <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> step in Figure 7A). This seems to imply that one of these conformational changes may be the rate-limiting component of the <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> receptor/G protein association step. In the second paragraph of the Discussion, data are discussed supporting this idea, identifying conformational change in the G protein, rather than receptor, as the limiting factor for receptor/G protein association. In our view this is quite a remarkable result, and it could be more strongly emphasized and discussed given its implications. For example, if conformational change in the Gα protein is the true rate-limiting step, this implies that selectivity of GIRK activation is independent of receptor expression levels, since active-state G protein subunits and not activated receptor molecules are limiting. It also means that GIRK activation should still not occur even if several Gα<sub>s</sub>-coupled receptors are activated simultaneously. This could be a useful biological feature of the system given the rich collection of GPCRs expressed in the heart and the nervous system.</p><p>2) Our only criticism would be that the manuscript contains a somewhat cursory treatment of the literature, and a corresponding lack of discussion of potentially alternative theories and modifying aspects. For example:</p><p>a) G-protein subunit specificities were a big story in the late 1980's and the 1990's. Some functional experiments showed remarkable subtype specificities, while biochemical experiments showed very little (with the exception of the retinal β<sub>1</sub>γ<sub>1</sub> pair). This is not at all discussed and (unless we overlooked this) the authors don't even tell us which Gβγ they are using.</p><p>b) Paul Insel's lab did a thorough determination of the stoichiometries of the receptor/G-protein/cyclase signaling chains in the heart. Although, to our knowledge, they did not attempt an analysis in sinoatrial node cells, they did report an excess of Gα<sub>i</sub> over Gα<sub>s</sub> that may explain the authors' findings similarly well. Furthermore, several labs, notably Al Gilman's, determined quantities of various G proteins in various tissues, and usually found very little Gα<sub>s</sub>.</p><p>c) FRET and BRET experiments done in the mid-2000s have yielded controversial results whether Gα and Gβγ dissociate or just re-arrange during activation. Particularly for Gα<sub>i</sub> variants, several labs reported that they do not (or do not need to) dissociate in intact cells (which appears be different in cell membrane experiments). How would such a finding affect the authors’ model and conclusions?</p><p>3) A final remark concerns the choice of reaction parameters in Table 2, which are all taken from the indicated references. However, the GTP hydrolysis rate (Breitwieser and Szabo, 1988) is very high compared with turnover numbers reported from biochemical experiments by many labs (which are on the order of 2-4/min).</p><p>4) The authors do a nice job of documenting population responses for most experiments, except for the BRET responses. Would there be a simple way to analyze the results from the most important experiments to provide population data?</p><p>5) In the Results, the authors might specifically mention the cAMP ELISA used to measure the concentration of the nucleotide simply to orient the reader without going to the methods.</p><p>6) Subsection “Direct measure of the Gβγ-GIRK interaction”, last paragraph, suggest modifying &quot;no change&quot; to &quot;only very small changes&quot;.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.42908.021</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Suggested revisions:</p><p>1) One point of comment is that conformational changes in both G protein and receptor proteins are required for their stable association (the k<sub>12</sub> step in Figure 7A). This seems to imply that one of these conformational changes may be the rate-limiting component of the k<sub>12</sub> receptor/G protein association step. In the second paragraph of the Discussion, data are discussed supporting this idea, identifying conformational change in the G protein, rather than receptor, as the limiting factor for receptor/G protein association. In our view this is quite a remarkable result, and it could be more strongly emphasized and discussed given its implications. For example, if conformational change in the Gα protein is the true rate-limiting step, this implies that selectivity of GIRK activation is independent of receptor expression levels, since active-state G protein subunits and not activated receptor molecules are limiting. It also means that GIRK activation should still not occur even if several Gαs -coupled receptors are activated simultaneously. This could be a useful biological feature of the system given the rich collection of GPCRs expressed in the heart and the nervous system.</p></disp-quote><p>The fundamental conclusion here is that the second order rate constant <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> is intrinsically faster for M2R than for the βARs and this accounts for specificity. We do not know whether this intrinsic difference is related to differences in conformational changes in the G protein trimer or the GPCR or both. However, in light of our findings, the observations of Leaney et al. suggest that rate differences are mainly ‘encoded’ by the Gα subunits. We put this idea forth only as a suggestion. This is definitely an area worth further investigation.</p><p>To the dependence of GIRK activation on receptor expression levels, our data support the conclusion that under physiological G protein concentrations, when receptors are activated by ligand they are generally not saturated with G protein trimer, especially in the case of the βARs owing to a smaller <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic>. This can be appreciated from the BRET data in Figure 3D and 3E and in a new figure supplement (Figure 3—figure supplement 1E), which provides the requested statistical information from multiple experiments (see below). Increasing the GPCR concentration will still increase the rate of Gβγ generation (because the forward rate of formation of activated receptor is <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> [G protein trimer] [GPCR]), but a very high density of βARs would be required.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) Our only criticism would be that the manuscript contains a somewhat cursory treatment of the literature, and a corresponding lack of discussion of potentially alternative theories and modifying aspects. For example:</p><p>a) G-protein subunit specificities were a big story in the late 1980's and the 1990's. Some functional experiments showed remarkable subtype specificities, while biochemical experiments showed very little (with the exception of the retinal β<sub>1</sub>γ<sub>1</sub> pair). This is not at all discussed and (unless we overlooked this) the authors don't even tell us which Gβγ they are using.</p></disp-quote><p>We present in the Materials and methods that we used human Gβ<sub>1</sub> and Gγ<sub>2</sub> (subsection “Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings on HEK293T and CHO cells expressing GIRK channel”, subsection “BRET sample preparation” and subsection “Expression and purification”, second paragraph). In Figure 1 and in Figure 1—figure supplement 1 we show that GPCR-GIRK signaling specificity persists in cells derived from species ranging from mammals to insects. Because G protein conservation between insects and mammals is very low compared to conservation between mammalian subtypes, it is extremely unlikely that Gβγ subtype affects signaling. We now include this point in the discussion on Gβγ subtype specificities (subsection “Gβγ specificity in native and heterologously expressed GIRK channels”, last paragraph).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>b) Paul Insel's lab did a thorough determination of the stoichiometries of the receptor/G-protein/cyclase signaling chains in the heart. Although, to our knowledge, they did not attempt an analysis in sinoatrial node cells, they did report an excess of Gαi over Gαs that may explain the authors' findings similarly well. Furthermore, several labs, notably Al Gilman's, determined quantities of various G proteins in various tissues, and usually found very little Gαs.</p></disp-quote><p>In this study we have demonstrated that expression levels of Gα<sub>i</sub> and Gα<sub>s</sub> are similar in HEK cells (Figure 3—figure supplement 2), where we still observe signaling specificity (Figure 1D). Thus, given the mechanism of specificity based on an intrinsically larger <italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic> for the Gα<sub>i</sub>-coupled GPCR, higher levels of Gα<sub>i</sub> (compared to Gα<sub>s</sub>) are not required for specificity. If the concentration of Gα<sub>i</sub> were to be greater than Gα<sub>s</sub> in certain cell types then this would also contribute to specificity, but it is not a requirement. This is such an important point raised by the reviewers that we have added a paragraph to the Discussion (second paragraph) to address it.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>c) FRET and BRET experiments done in the mid-2000s have yielded controversial results whether Gαand Gβγ dissociate or just re-arrange during activation. Particularly for Gαivariants, several labs reported that they do not (or do not need to) dissociate in intact cells (which appears be different in cell membrane experiments). How would such a finding affect the authors' model and conclusions?</p></disp-quote><p>As pointed out, a FRET study by Bünemann et al. suggested that Gα<sub>i</sub> and Gβγ undergo subunit rearrangement rather than dissociation during G protein activation (Bünemann et al., 2003). However, in our BRET experiments we observed robust apparent dissociation of Gα and Gβγ using two different Gα-Venus constructs (Figure 6). Furthermore, and perhaps more importantly, our previous studies using reconstitution clearly demonstrate that free Gβγ activates GIRK and that Gα<sub>i</sub>(GDP) inhibits the channel by removing Gβγ from GIRK through equilibrium-mass action (Wang et al., 2014). Furthermore, our atomic structural studies also demonstrate that the GIRK binding site on Gβγ overlaps with the Gα binding site (Whorton and MacKinnon, 2013). Given these data, the necessity of G protein subunit dissociation seems an inescapable fact.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) A final remark concerns the choice of reaction parameters in Table 2, which are all taken from the indicated references. However, the GTP hydrolysis rate (Breitwieser and Szabo, 1988) is very high compared with turnover numbers reported from biochemical experiments by many labs (which are on the order of 2-4/min).</p></disp-quote><p>Intrinsic GTPase activity of Gα is known to be 2-4 min<sup>-1</sup>. However, under physiological conditions GTPase-activating proteins (GAPs) accelerate the rate by ~10-1000 fold (Sprang, 2016). Breitwieser and Szabo measured the GTP hydrolysis rates in isolated atrial myocytes where endogenous GAPs were most likely present, as in our experiments.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) The authors do a nice job of documenting population responses for most experiments, except for the BRET responses. Would there be a simple way to analyze the results from the most important experiments to provide population data?</p></disp-quote><p>We added Figure 3—figure supplement 1E to provide population data for BRET experiments in Figure 3.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) In the Results, the authors might specifically mention the cAMP ELISA used to measure the concentration of the nucleotide simply to orient the reader without going to the methods.</p></disp-quote><p>We added the information to the manuscript (subsection “Gβγ specificity in native and heterologously expressed GIRK channels”, last paragraph).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>6) Subsection “Direct measure of the Gβγ-GIRK interaction”, last paragraph, suggest modifying &quot;no change&quot; to &quot;only very small changes&quot;.</p></disp-quote><p>We made this change.</p></body></sub-article></article>