<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">eLife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13503</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Tools and Resources</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Mammalian enhancer trap resource for discovering and manipulating neuronal cell types</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-3237"><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>Yasuyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-3236"><name><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>Ken</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-47415"><name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>Chris Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-47416"><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>Masami</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-47417"><name><surname>Taneja</surname><given-names>Praveen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-47418"><name><surname>Bullis</surname><given-names>James B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-47419"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>Sonam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-42099"><name><surname>Lois</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-1149"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>Sacha B</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0108-8599</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-2"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con9"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Biology and National Center for Behavioral Genomics</institution>, <institution>Brandeis University</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Waltham</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Janelia Research Campus, Howard Hughes Medical Institute</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Ashburn</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Division of Biology and Biological Engineering, Beckman Institute</institution>, <institution>California Institute of Technology</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Pasadena</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Liqun</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff4"><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Stanford University</institution>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><email>nelson@brandeis.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa1"><label>†</label><p>Galenea Corporation, Wakefield, United States</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>21</day><month>03</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e13503</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>03</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016, Shima et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Shima et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-13503-v3.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.001</object-id><p>There is a continuing need for driver strains to enable cell-type-specific manipulation in the nervous system. Each cell type expresses a unique set of genes, and recapitulating expression of marker genes by BAC transgenesis or knock-in has generated useful transgenic mouse lines. However, since genes are often expressed in many cell types, many of these lines have relatively broad expression patterns. We report an alternative transgenic approach capturing distal enhancers for more focused expression. We identified an enhancer trap probe often producing restricted reporter expression and developed efficient enhancer trap screening with the PiggyBac transposon. We established more than 200 lines and found many lines that label small subsets of neurons in brain substructures, including known and novel cell types. Images and other information about each line are available online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://enhancertrap.bio.brandeis.edu/">enhancertrap.bio.brandeis.edu</ext-link>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.001">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.001</ext-link></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>Scientists can track and even alter the activity of different kinds of neurons, as well as the connections between neurons, by manipulating their genes. However, most genes are active in many different kinds of cells in many different places in the brain, making it difficult to track or target only a particular neuron or brain area.</p><p>Enhancers are sections of DNA that can regulate the activity of nearby genes so that they are only active in very specific cell types, and an “enhancer trap” is a genetic approach that essentially hijacks enhancers to express artificial genes in those same cell types. The technique relies on inserting a genetic marker, which can be easily tracked, into random locations in the genome. If this marker then interacts with an enhancer, it is activated and the effect of the enhancer on gene expression can be assessed.</p><p>This method has been used in fruit flies and fish to identify enhancers that specifically restrict gene expression to a small subset of cells. Now, Shima et al. show that enhancer traps can be used successfully in mammals too. The experiments produced over 200 different strains of mice, many with the fluorescent marker only in specific brain areas or in specific kinds of brain cells. Some of the types of brain cells uncovered by these experiments are new, and the labelling of specific brain cells and brain areas in different strains makes these mice a useful resource for future work. Furthermore, it will be relatively straightforward to produce many more strains of these mice, because it would simply involve crossbreeding mice. It is likely that some of these to-be-discovered strains will be useful tools for research as well.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.002">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.002</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Author Keywords</title><kwd>enhancer trap</kwd><kwd>cell type</kwd><kwd>transgenic animals</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research Organism</title><kwd>Mouse</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="par-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000053</institution-id><institution>National Eye Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>EY022360</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>Sacha B</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000025</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Mental Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MH105949</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>Sacha B</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000065</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NS075007</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>Sacha B</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-4"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100004412</institution-id><institution>Human Frontier Science Program</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>LT00151</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>Yasuyuki</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>elife-xml-version</meta-name><meta-value>2.5</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>A novel transposon-based enhancer trap screen in mice permits high throughput development of highly restricted driver strains targeting specific neuronal cell types.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The mammalian brain is likely comprised of thousands of distinct neuronal cell types. The ability to distinguish these cell types and to understand their roles in circuit activity and behavior is enhanced by an increasing variety of new genetic technologies in mice. Conditional transgenes like fluorescent reporters or alleles that sense or modify neuronal activity can be turned on in cells of interest through the use of 'driver' strains selectively expressing Cre recombinase or the tet transactivator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Huang and Zeng, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Luo et al., 2008</xref>). Most techniques for producing these driver strains rely on recapitulating endogenous patterns of gene expression. However, selective expression patterns often depend both on elements within the proximal promoter, and on enhancers and other regulatory elements that can be located quite distally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Visel et al., 2009</xref>). Recapitulating endogenous expression requires either a knock-in approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Taniguchi et al., 2011</xref>), or making transgenics from very large genomic fragments containing both the promoter and distal control elements (e.g. BAC transgenics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Gong et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Yang et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>One limitation of recapitulating endogenous expression patterns is that they are often broader than would be optimal for selective control. For example, the Pvalb-cre driver strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hippenmeyer et al., 2005</xref>) can be used to target Pvalb-positive fast-spiking interneurons in the neocortex; however, Pvalb is also expressed in cerebellum (Purkinje cells), dorsal root ganglia, thalamus, and many other brain structures, as well as in skeletal muscle. Even in the neocortex, Pvalb-positive cells consist of at least two distinct interneuron subtypes (basket cells and chandelier cells) and some layer 5 pyramidal neurons. Limitations on cell type specificity are common, since most genes are expressed in many different cell types throughout many different brain regions and tissues. Although combinatorial approaches can enhance specificity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Madisen et al., 2015</xref>), this comes at the cost of increasing the number of alleles that must be created and bred. Furthermore, this approach requires initial knowledge about co-expression patterns that may be lacking for some cell types.</p><p>Here, we take an alternative approach that relies on the fact that some minimal promoters can, when randomly inserted into the genome, interact with local enhancers and regulatory elements to produce patterns of expression that can be more restricted. This approach, termed enhancer detection or enhancer trapping, has a long history in <italic>Drosophila</italic> where it has been pursued primarily using the Gal4-UAS system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bellen et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Brand and Perrimon, 1993</xref>). More recently, this system and others have been used for enhancer trapping in zebrafish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Balciunas et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Scott et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Urasaki et al., 2008</xref>), but the approach has been less widely used in mice (though see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gossler et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kothary et al., 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Soininen et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Stanford et al., 2001</xref>). A large-scale enhancer trap screen was performed using the SleepingBeauty transposon system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Ruf et al., 2011</xref>) but was focused on enhancers active during embryonic development, rather than those that regulate cell-type-specific expression in the adult. Kelsch et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kelsch et al., 2012</xref>) conducted a mouse enhancer trap screen for transgenic animals with specific patterns of neural expression. Their lentiviral enhancer probe successfully generated transgenic lines with expression in neuronal subsets, however, the number of lines generated was small and most lines had expression in many cell types. Thus, this approach, while promising, has not yet reached its full potential, both in terms of specificity and in terms of the efficiency with which new lines can be generated.</p><p>Here, we report on an efficient enhancer trap screen to generate lines with specific expression patterns in the brain. First, using lentiviral transgenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lois et al., 2002</xref>), we discovered a tet-transactivator-dependent enhancer probe capable of generating transgenic lines with highly restricted expression patterns. Next, we incorporated this tet-enhancer probe into the PiggyBac transposon system and developed a simple and efficient system for producing mouse lines with different PiggyBac insertion sites. The majority of these lines have brain expression and many have highly restricted expression patterns in known or novel neuronal cell types. Finally, a critical consideration in using the enhancer trap approach in the CNS of any species is the question of whether trapped neurons represent specific cell types or more random subsets of largely unrelated cells. To address this, we performed more detailed anatomical and physiological characterization in a subset of lines. These experiments revealed that the neuronal populations are not random assortments of unrelated cells, but represent highly specific, previously recognized, as well as novel, neuronal cell types. In addition, quantitative comparison with a recently annotated collection of knock-in and BAC-cre driver strains revealed that expression is, on average, far more restricted in the enhancer trap lines. Hence enhancer trapping is a viable strategy for producing driver strains that complement those generated through other genetic approaches. This resource provides a platform for genetic control of a wide variety of neuronal cell types, as well as for discovering new subtypes of known neuronal cell types.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Lentivirus transgenesis</title><p>Our initial enhancer trap screen employed lentiviral vectors because their highly efficient transduction of transgenes to the germ line minimized the number of injections needed to sample enough founders and their random single copy insertion permitted a broad survey of genomic sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lois et al., 2002</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref> for transgenesis scheme). Our enhancer probe constructs employed the tet-off genetic driver system and incorporated a tet-responsive element (TRE; we used TREtight, the second-generation TRE) driving the fluorescent reporter mCitrine, so that we could examine expression patterns in driver lines without crossing to separate reporter lines. We initially tried constructs with the minimal promoter from the mouse heat-shock protein 1A (Hspa1a) gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bevilacqua et al., 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>). We also incorporated other promoter sequences that had been used to generate transgenic animals with neuronal subset expression and enhancer candidate sequence from evolutionally conserved elements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Visel et al., 2007</xref>). We found a construct containing the minimal HSP promoter most efficiently generated lines with specific expression patterns in brain (28.8%, see <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>) and see supplemental note and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref> for details of other constructs tried.<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.003</object-id><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Efficiency of transgenesis. The numbers of lines dissected and the number of lines with brain expression are shown separately for each construct used.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.003">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.003</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>construct</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>analyzed</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>with expression</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p><bold>lentivirus</bold></p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><italic>HSP-tet</italic></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> HSP-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>132</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>38</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> hsp-tet2</p></td><td valign="top"><p>7</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>4</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> hsp-tet3</p></td><td valign="top"><p>12</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p><italic>promoter-tet</italic></p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> CamKII-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>18</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>4</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> minCamKN-te</p></td><td valign="top"><p>17</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>7</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> Thy1-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>15</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> minThy1-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>11</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> Gad1-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>9</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> Slc-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>6</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p><italic>enhancer-tet</italic></p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> 119-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>13</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>1</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> 121-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> 122-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>15</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> 170-tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>1</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p><bold>PiggyBac</bold></p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><italic>HSP-tet</italic></td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> tet</p></td><td valign="top"><p>101</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>81</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> tet-Cre</p></td><td valign="top"><p>57</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>43</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>Throughout the rest of the paper, we use the admittedly imperfect term 'cell type' to refer to cell populations defined operationally as the group of neurons labeled in a particular brain region of a transgenic line. We imagine neuronal cell types as nodes in a hierarchical tree-like structure with the terminal branches ('leaves') corresponding to 'atomic' cell types which are homogeneous and cannot be further divided based on projections, morphology, gene expression etc. The 'operational' cell types defined here are not necessarily 'atomic' in that further characterization may reveal that they are composed of subtypes, but they offer a useful starting point for subsequent identification of 'atomic cell types' based on uniformity of morphology, connections, physiology, and gene expression.</p><p>Although only a minority of lentiviral tet lines had reporter expression, the majority of lines with brain expression had highly restricted expression patterns. Some lines had expression only in restricted cell types, including medial prefrontal cortex layer 5 neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>), retinal ganglion cells projecting axons to superior colliculus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>), and Cajal-Retzius cells in cerebral cortex and dentate gyrus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). We had two lines with distinctive expression in cortical layer 4 neurons; TCGS in primary sensory cortices (including primary visual, somatosensory and auditory cortices; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>) and TCFQ which was devoid of expression in primary sensory cortices but expressed in associative cortices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>). We also obtained lines labeling specific cell types, such as thalamocortical projection neurons in the dorsal part of the lateral geniculate complex (LGd; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref>), anatomically clustered subsets of cerebellar granule cells, semilunar cells and a subset of superficial pyramidal neurons in piriform cortex, and a subtype of cortico-thalamic pyramidal neurons in layer 6 of neocortex (see below). Tet reporter expression could be turned off and on by administration of doxycycline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>). For a summary of expression patterns in all lines, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Supplementary file 1</xref>.<fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.004</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Example Lentiviral lines.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) 48L has expression in limbic cortex (A1, coronal section) layer 5 pyramidal cells (A2, magnified image in limbic cortex). (<bold>B</bold>) Superior colliculus (SC) of TCBV has columnar axons from retina. B1: sagittal section, B2: magnified image of superior colliculus. (<bold>C</bold>) 52L has expression in piriform cortex (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>) and Cajal-Retzius cells in dentate gyrus (DG, C2) and cerebral cortex (C3, inset: magnified image of a Cajal-Retzius cell). (<bold>D</bold>) TCGS has expression in layer 4 neurons of primary sensory cortices (primary somatosensory area: SSp and primary visual area:VISp in D3). (<bold>E</bold>) TCFQ has nearly complimentary layer 4 expression excluding primary sensory cortices. D1 and E1: sagittal sections, D2 and E2: confocal images of cortex, D3 and E3: dorsal view of whole brains. (<bold>F</bold>) TCJD has expression in dorsal part of lateral geniculate nucleus (LGd, F1), which projects to primary visual cortex (VISp). F1: sagittal section, F2: higher magnification of LGd, F3: higher magnification of axons in layers 1, 4, and 6 of VISp. Scale bars are 50 μm in A2, B2, C2, F2 and 500 μm in others.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.004">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.004</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.005</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Transgenesis.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Lentiviral transgenesis. Lentivirus encoding an enhancer probe is injected into the perivitelline space between the single cell embryo and the zona pellucida. Infected embryos are transferred to foster mothers. Founders are genotyped by PCR and transgene copy number is estimated by southern blot or quantitative PCR and additional rounds of breeding and quantitative genotyping are carried out (not shown) to produce single copy founders. (<bold>B</bold>) PiggyBac (PB) transgenesis. Plasmid DNA for a PB enhancer probe and PB transposase (PBase) mRNA are injected into the cytosol of single cell embryos. Copy numbers of PB probes are examined as for lentiviral founders. Animals with single copy PB are selected as seed lines for PB transgenesis. Seed lines (<bold>P</bold>) are crossed with PBase animals, and their children (<bold>F1</bold>) carrying both PB and PBase are mated with wild-type (WT) animals. PB hops only in F1 PB;PBase mice, and animals with new PB insertion sites are generated in the following generation (<bold>F2</bold>). Among F2 animals, animals with hopped PB but without PBase are founders of new transgenic lines. PB; prm-PBase females can also be founders since prm-PBase will not be expressed in the female germ line.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.005">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.005</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig1-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.006</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Constructs for transgenesis.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Lentiviral constructs. Viral sequences were inserted into the lentiviral backbone plasmid. The five variants listed are described in the text. (<bold>B</bold>) PiggyBac constructs containing tTA or tTA and Cre. Except for hsp-tet3, transcripts from lentiviral constructs use 3’ long terminal repeat (△U3-R–U5 in the backbone plasmid) as poly adenylation signal. In all constructs, tTA and mCitrine share poly adenylation signal sequences. HSPmp: minimal promoter from Hspa1a, tTA: tet transactivator, TRE: tet response element, WPRE: woodchuck hepatitis virus post-transcriptional regulatory element, 2A: FMDV-2A sequence, BGHpA: poly-adenylation signal from bovine growth hormone, HS4ins: insulator sequence from DNase hyper sensitive site in the chicken β-globin gene, PB- 5’ITR and PB-3’ITR: PiggyBac inverted terminal repeat.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.006">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.006</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig1-figsupp2-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.007</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Transgene regulation by Doxycycline (Dox).</title><p>Pregnant 48L females received water with Dox (0.2 mg/ml) or regular water (control) (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>B</bold>) <bold>P21</bold> (<bold>A</bold>) and P42 (<bold>B</bold>) images from 48L animals receiving water lacking Dox. (<bold>C</bold>–<bold>I</bold>) Images from 48L animals receiving Dox. Regular water (<bold>D</bold>–<bold>F</bold>, second row) and doxycycline water (<bold>G</bold>–<bold>I</bold>, third row) were used for 3 weeks from when pups were weaned at <bold>P21</bold>. Siblings are dissected at <bold>P21</bold> (<bold>C</bold>), <bold>P28</bold> (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>G</bold>), <bold>P35</bold> (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) and <bold>P42</bold> (<bold>F</bold> and <bold>I</bold>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.007">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.007</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig1-figsupp3-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Although lentiviral transgenesis successfully generated lines with highly restricted expression patterns, screening was difficult to scale up effectively. Generation of each new founder requires viral injection into single cell embryos and transfer of that embryo to a foster mother (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>). Tracking and segregating multiple alleles in order to identify the allele responsible for reporter expression in the case of founders having multiple insertions was especially time consuming. Moreover, we found four lines in which expression in the founder and early progeny was lost in later generations, implying possible silencing of lentiviral transgenes over generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Hofmann et al., 2006</xref>). We tried to incorporate insulator sequences (see below) to prevent silencing, but viruses with insulator sequences had 100 times lower titer (about 1 x 10<sup>7</sup> infection unit/ml) and were not usable for transgenesis.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>PiggyBac transgenesis</title><p>In order to develop a more efficient and scalable transgenesis platform, we made use of the PiggyBac (PB) transposon system as a means of delivering tet enhancer trap probes. The PB system has been widely used in mammalian genetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Ding et al., 2005</xref>) for insertional mutagenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Rad et al., 2010</xref>) and stable transgene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Woodard and Wilson, 2015</xref>). Unlike the SleepingBeauty transposon, PiggyBac has a weaker tendency to undergo local hops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Liang et al., 2009</xref>, but see supplemental note), making it more suitable for screens that target the whole genome. To simplify the process of establishing and tracking new transgenic alleles, we established lines of animals carrying a single-copy PB integration and additional lines expressing the PiggyBac transposase (PBase). PB hops only in animals with both the PB and PBase alleles, allowing us to generate transgenic animals with different PB insertion sites simply by mating wild type and PB;PBase animals (see the mating scheme in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>). We used the same tTA-reporter system used in the lentiviral probes (PB tet, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref>). We also created a probe designed to produce both tTA and Cre expression (PB tet-cre, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref>). In order to prevent the silencing seen in some lentiviral lines, we incorporated barrier insulator sequences from the chicken β-globin gene (see 'Materials and methods' for detail).</p><p>DNA plasmids encoding our PB enhancer probe and mRNA encoding a hyperactive PBase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Yusa et al., 2011</xref>) were co-injected into single cell embryos. Among 28 PB-positive animals, five had single-copy insertions confirmed by quantitative PCR and ligation-mediated PCR. These five served as seed lines for subsequent rounds of piggyBac transgenesis.</p><p>We used two PBase lines: 1) a Rosa-PBase line generated by Allan Bradley and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Rad et al., 2010</xref>) having nearly ubiquitous expression of PBase from the Rosa-26 locus and 2) a Prm-PBase line that we generated having spermatid-specific expression of hyper-active PBase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Yusa et al., 2011</xref>) under the protamine-1 promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">Zambrowicz et al., 1993</xref>). PiggyBac seed lines were crossed with PBase mice, and PB;PBase double hemizygous animals (P1 generation) were selected and crossed with wild-type animals (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>). P2 generation animals were genotyped for PB alleles (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.008</object-id><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Transposition efficiency PB;PBase double hemizygous animals (PB/+; PBase/+) were crossed with wild type animals and genotypes of pups from the mating were examined (see the mating scheme in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Numbers of animals are shown in parentheses. PB transmission rate: number of PB+ animals / total number of animals, PB transposition rate: number of PB in new sites / number of animals tested for transposition. (Note: we did not test transposition for PB/+;Rosa-PBase/+ and PB/+;Prm1-PBase/+ males because transgenes might not be stably transmitted to the next generation in these animals). New line production efficiency: number of animals with new insertion site / total number of animals born. *: All PB+ animals were female.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.008">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.008</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>Seed line</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>PBase line</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>PB transmission rate</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Transposition efficiency</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Efficiency of new line production</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>PBAG</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Rosa</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>28.6% (54/189)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>41.4 % (12/29)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>6.4 % (12/189)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> </p> <p> </p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Prm1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>29.2% (21/72)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>56.3 % (9/16)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>12.5% ( 9/72)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>PBAW</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Rosa</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>21.56% (80/371)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>62.2 % (23/37)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>6.2 % (23/371)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> </p> <p> </p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Prm1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>33.0 % (97/294) *</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>67.4 % (62/92)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>21.1% ( 62/294)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>PBAS</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Rosa</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>30.8 % (33/107)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>25.0 % (3/12)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>3.3 % ( 3/97)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> </p> <p> </p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Prm1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>35.6 % (130/365)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>41.9 % (39/93)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>10.7 % (39/365)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>PBAU</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Rosa</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>22.2 % (30/135)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>38.9 % (7/18)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>5.2 % (7/135)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> </p> <p> </p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Prm1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>34.3 % (46/134)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>57.1 % (20/35)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>14.9 % (20/134)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>PBAQ</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Rosa</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>37.5 % (6/16)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0 % (0/3)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0 % (0/16)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> </p> <p> </p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Prm1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>60.0 % (9/15)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>12.5 %( 1/8)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>6.6 % (1/15)</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>Animals carrying the PB allele were further tested to ensure transposition had occurred. We found that the PB allele transmission rate was significantly lower than the expected Mendelian ratio, implying that a substantial fraction of excised PB failed to re-insert into the host genome (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). The PB alleles derived from each of the single-copy seed lines jumped at similar transposition rates, except for those from the PBAQ seed line that rarely translocated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). We found that Prm-PBase produced founders more efficiently than Rosa-PBase (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). See supplemental note and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">4</xref> for further details of transposition frequency.<table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.009</object-id><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Numbers of insertion events occurring in genes and intergenic regions.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.009">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.009</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>Insertion Sites</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Number of lines</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>gene</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>60</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> coding exon</p></td><td valign="top"><p>1</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> 3'UTR</p></td><td valign="top"><p>4</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p> intron</p></td><td valign="top"><p>55</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>intergenic</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>81</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>repetitive sequence</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>26</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.010</object-id><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Rates of inter-chromosomal, intrachromosomal and local (within 2 Mb) transposition events. Some insertions were not located due to insertion in repetitive sequences.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.010">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.010</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>line</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>number of lines</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>inter-chromosomal hop</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>intra-chromosomal hop</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>local (&lt;2 Mb) hop</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>not located</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>PBAW</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>69</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>46 (66.7 %)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>11(15.9 %)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>8(11.6 %)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>12 (17.4 %)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>PBAS</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>46</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>26 (56.5 %)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>18 (39.1%)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>9 (19.6%)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2 (4.3 %)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>PBAU</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>26</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>13 (50.0 %)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>8 (30.8 %)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2 (7.7%)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>5 (19.2 %)</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>Total</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>141</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>85 (60.2 %)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>37 (26.2 %)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>19 (13.4%)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>19 (13.4 %)</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>PB line expression patterns</title><p>We established more than 200 independent lines and examined expression patterns from more than 130 lines (210 and 135 as of October 2015, respectively; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Supplementary file 1</xref> for line expression summary and insertion sites). We occasionally encountered termination of lines for infertility (20 lines; cf. the productive mating rate of the mouse strain C57Bl6/j is 84% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Silver, 1995</xref>]) or death mainly due to maternal complications at birth (5 lines). Because of the difficulties associated with managing a large number of colonies, some (4 lines) were accidentally lost before cryopreservation.</p><p>The rate of obtaining lines with brain expression in the PB screen (78.5% ) was more than twice that obtained with lentiviral transgenesis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Lines generated by local hop of PB (within ~100 Kb) had similar expression patterns to that of the original line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>), probably because shared local enhancers regulated expression of the reporter. In most of lines, we did not find clear resemblance between reporter expression patterns and those of genes near insertion sites (see supplemental note). Some lines had dominant expression in a single anatomical structure, such as deep entorhinal cortex (P038, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>), subiculum (P141, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), retrosplenial cortex (P099, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>), or dorsal hindbrain (P108, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). Many lines had expression in multiple regions but with unique cell types in each area. For example, P008 has broad expression in striatum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E1</xref>) but has restricted expression in the most medial part of the hippocampus (fasciola cinereum, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E2</xref>). P057 had cortical layer 5 expression and restricted expression in anterior-lateral caudate putamen (CP; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2H</xref>). Interestingly, the mCitrine-positive CP cells appeared to be part of the direct pathway; the cells projected axons to a limited area in substantia nigra pars reticulata (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2H2</xref> inset) but not to the globus pallidus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2H1</xref> arrow; compare the GP projection of P008 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E1</xref>). Lines with broad expression, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2J</xref>), those labeling few cells, and those closely resembling existing lines were terminated (48 lines). Most lines with 'broad expression' had strong mCitrine expression restricted to forebrain and founders carrying multiple PB copies also had strong forebrain expression.<fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.011</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Example PiggyBac lines.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) Examples of lines that appear to label a single cell type. (d) P038 has expression in entorhinal cortex medial part (ENTm) layer 6 neurons (A1: sagittal) that send axons to lateral dorsal nucleus of thalamus (LD in A2: coronal). (<bold>B</bold>) P141 has expression in a restricted area in subiculum (SUB, B1: sagittal, B2: coronal). (<bold>C</bold>) Retrosplenial cortex (RSP) expression in P099 (C1: sagittal, C2: coronal). (<bold>D</bold>) Dorsal hindbrain expression in P108 (D1: sagittal, D2: coronal at hindbrain). (<bold>E</bold>–<bold>H</bold>) Examples of lines with regionally distinctive cell type labeling. (<bold>E</bold>) P008 has expression in striatum (STR) broadly (E1: sagittal) but its hippocampal expression is restricted to the most medial part (fasciola cinereum: FC, E2 inset) (<bold>F</bold>) P122 has scattered expression in hippocampus and strong expression in cortical amygdalar area. F1: sagittal, F2: coronal sections. (<bold>G</bold>) P134 has broad expression in cortical interneurons and cerebellar Lugaro cells (G1: sagittal). Its expression in midbrain is restricted to subnuclei (G2, superior olivary complex: SOC and presumably pedunculopontine nucleus: PPN). (<bold>H</bold>) P057 (H1:coronal, H2, sagittal section) has expression in layer 5 pyramidal cells in the cortex. Expression in caudate putamen (CP) is restricted to lateral-most areas (arrows in H1). H2 inset: coronal section at the level of the dotted line. The striatal neurons project to a small area in the reticular part of the substantia nigra, reticular part (SNr, dotted area in H2 inset) but not to globus pallidus (H2 arrow). (<bold>J</bold>) Lines with broad expressions. Scale bar: 500 μm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.011">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.011</ext-link></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD1-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.012</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Viral reporter expression counting data One or two animals per line were injected with TRE3G –myristorylsted mCherry HA.</title><p>The numbers of cells (mCitirne+, mCherry+, mCitrine+;mCherry+, and mCitrine-:mCherry+) infection rate (mCitrine+;mCherry+/ mCitirne +) were counted from confocal image stacks from sections near injection sites (5 - 9 sections/line). Infection rates (mCherry+;mCitrine+ /mCitrine) and 'off-target' expression rate (mCherry+;mCitirne-/mCherry+) are shown in average ± SEM.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.012">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.012</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig2-data1-v3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig2-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.013</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Similar expression patterns in lines with nearby insertions.</title><p>Insertion sites and expression patterns of a founder PBAS and lines generated from PBAS by local hop are shown. Lines inserted near original PBAS site have scattered expression in Purkinje cells in cerebellum. Many lines have axonal projections in dentate gyrus from entorhinal cortex. P103 and P136 have insertion sites more than 300 kb away from the origin and their expression patterns are quite different from PBAS.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.013">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.013</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig2-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.014</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Developmental dynamics in P162 expression patterns.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) sections from P10 (<bold>A</bold>) and mature (<bold>B</bold>) animals. Parafascicular nucleus of thalamus had expression at P10 but not in mature animal (arrowheads). (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) P10 (<bold>C</bold>) animal expressed reporter in pontine gray (arrowhead) but matured animal (<bold>D</bold>) did not. (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>) Subiculum expression was not seen at P10 (<bold>E</bold>) but was present in mature (<bold>F</bold>) animals (arrowheads). (<bold>G</bold>) Higher magnification of parafascicular nucleus in <bold>A</bold>. Asterisk: fasciculus retroflexus. (<bold>H</bold>) Higher magnification of pontine gray. (<bold>I</bold>) Cerebellum receives axons from pontine gray. (<bold>J</bold>) High magnification of cerebellum. Mossy terminals were labeled.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.014">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.014</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig2-figsupp2-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.015</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Examples of virus injection.</title><p>AAV–TRE3G- myristoylated mCherry-HA was injected to the brain. Wide field images (1) and confocal images (2, rectangle areas in 1) of injection sites. Note that myristoylated mCherry strongly labels axons and dendrites. (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) Injection to retrosplenial cortex. P160 labels layer 2/3 (<bold>A</bold>), P136 in layer 5 (<bold>B</bold>), and P160 in layer 6 (<bold>C</bold>). In P160, virus spread to entire cortex (see infected cells in deep layer (arrows in A2) but viral reporter expression is restricted to mCtirine positive cells. (<bold>D</bold>) Hippocampal CA1 injection to P160. (<bold>E–F</bold>) Examples of 'off-target' expression. Primary somatosensory cortex injection in P057 (<bold>E</bold>) and subiculum injection in P113 (<bold>F</bold>). Arrowheads: cells with viral reporter without visible mCitrine expression. Blue: DAPI, Green: anti-GFP, Red: anti-HA.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.015">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.015</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig2-figsupp3-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.016</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>tet reporter expression in cultured cell lines.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>I</bold>) Induction of tet reporter constructs was tested with 293T cells. Cells were transfected without (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>I</bold>, first panels) or with (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>I</bold>, second panels) CMV-tTA plasmid. Some constructs had strong tTA-independent 'leak' expression (ex. <bold>A1</bold>, <bold>E1</bold>, and <bold>F1</bold>). GBP-split Cre had the strongest expression of Cre reporter in the presence of GFP (<bold>I3</bold>) but could activate the reporter expression without GFP expression (<bold>I2</bold>). See Supplemental note for further details.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.016">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.016</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig2-figsupp4-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s5" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.017</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 5.</label><caption><title>Specificity of tet reporter expression in vivo.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) AAV–TREtight-myrmCherry expression in 56L. mCherry expression was restricted to mCitrine positive cells (mCitrine+ cells/ mCherry+ cells: 152/152). (<bold>A2</bold>) higher magnification of injection site. (<bold>B</bold>) Co-infection of AAV–TRE3G–Cre and AAV–CAG–Flex-myrmCherry HAnsulator sequence from. There was strong non-specific mCherry expression near injection site (<bold>B2</bold>). (<bold>C</bold>) TRE3G–Split Cre had specific expression of reporter without apparent leak. (<bold>D</bold>) TRE3G–Flpe had non-specific expression in a few cells (<bold>D2</bold>, arrows) (<bold>E</bold>) TRE3G split Cre had non-specific expression from Ai14 reporter allele in P113 subiculum. (<bold>F</bold>) TRE3G-nanobody Split Cre had specific expression (mCitrine+ cells/mCherry + cells: 64/64). (<bold>F2</bold>) higher magnification of the injection site. (<bold>G</bold>) Specific expression of AAV Cre repoter by TRE3G-nanobody split Cre in 56L.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.017">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.017</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig2-figsupp5-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>We compared reporter expression patterns with those observed in BAC-Cre and knock in –Cre lines. Harris and her colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Harris et al., 2014</xref>) manually evaluated the density of reporter-positive cells in 295 brain structures for each of 135 BAC- and knock in-Cre lines into six categories (widespread, scattered, sparse, enriched, restricted/Laminar, and restricted but sparse). We employed the same expression categories to annotate expression patterns in PB lines (see 'Materials and methods' and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>; annotation data is summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3-data">Supplementary file 2</xref>). We found that, on average, more than three times fewer structures were labeled in PB lines (33) than in the Cre lines (107) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A and B</xref>). The numbers of structures with enriched/restricted expressions were also lower in PB lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). We count the number of lines with expression in 12 major subclass of brain structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Harris et al., 2014</xref>). Cre lines had relatively homogenous expression rates (70–83% ) in any brain regions, whereas PB lines had expression bias to forebrain structures such as the isocortex, olfactory bulb, and hippocampus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.018</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>PB lines have more restricted expression than Cre lines.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>) Histograms of the number of brain regions (x axis) with expression per line. Bac-Cre/Cre knock in –lines (<bold>A</bold>) have expression in more areas than PB enhancer trap lines (<bold>B</bold>). Arrows: averages. (<bold>C</bold>) Histogram of number of brain structures with enriched or restricted expression. Red: Cre lines, Green: PB lines. (<bold>D</bold>) Fraction of lines with expression in brain subregions. Iso: Isocortex, Olf: olfactory areas, Hip: hippocampal formation, Cor: cortical subplate, Str: striatum, Pal: pallidum, Tha: thal amus, Hyp: hypothalamus, Mid: midbrain, Pon: Pons, Med: medulla, Cer: cerebellum. Red: Cre lines, Green: PB lines.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.018">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.018</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig3-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.019</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Categories of regional expression patterns.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Criteria used to delineate expression categories. (<bold>B</bold>–<bold>H</bold>) Examples of expression categories (<bold>B</bold>: widespread, <bold>C</bold>: scattered, <bold>D</bold>: sparse, <bold>E</bold>: enriched, <bold>F</bold>: restricted, <bold>G</bold>: restricted sparse). Areas with less than 10 mCitrine-expressing cells/mm<sup>2</sup> were ignored (<bold>H</bold>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.019">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.019</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig3-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Although our screen was focused on brain expression, we also performed a brief screen of the rest of the body and found that some lines (24/135) also had expression in tissues other than the brain, including skin (8), bone (5), viscera (9), and brown (1) and white (3) adipocytes. Although we occasionally observed expression, in retinal ganglion cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>), and spinal cord (P032, P105), we did not systematically examine the retina, spinal cord, or peripheral nervous system. Non-brain expression patterns are summarized at the enhancer trap web site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://enhancertrap.bio.brandeis.edu/data/">enhancertrap.bio.brandeis.edu/data/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Expression stability in PB lines</title><p>Except for lines that were lost or terminated early, we examined expression patterns of multiple animals from each transgenic line (73 lines). Nearly all had consistent expression patterns over multiple generations. A few lines showed variable expression patterns in individual animals. P039 had stable expression in subiculum, but its expression in cortex varied, and two lines (P027 and P197) had expression that was left-right asymmetric. P139 heterozygous animals had consistent expression in cortico-thalamic L6 cells in lateral cerebral cortex (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10</xref>), but the number of labeled cells varied across animals and sometimes across hemispheres (data not shown). Since P139 homozygous animals had stable expression patterns, subthreshold-level tTA expression might have caused stochastic reporter expression.</p><p>In the brain, most enhancers display developmental dynamics visible, for example, in the state of an active enhancer marker H3K27Ace (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Nord et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">2015</xref>). Many lines showed different reporter expression patterns at different ages, likely reflecting the developmental dynamics of the trapped enhancers. Screening was primarily carried out in young adults (P20-30). We examined adult (P50 or later) expression in 34 lines. Mature expression was reduced in 12 of these lines, but was retained in the remaining 22 lines. Some lines showed complex spatiotemporal expression patterns. For example, young postnatal animals (P10-12) from line P162 had expression in primary sensory cortices, the parafascicular nucleus of the thalamus and pontine grey, but more mature (3 weeks or older) animals lost thalamic and pontine expression and gained subiculum expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>), suggesting the probe trapped enhancer(s) activated in different structures at different developmental stages. Unlike some lentiviral lines, silencing of PB transgenes over generations was not observed; even lines losing expression late in adulthood had pups that regained reporter expression.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Transgene expression in tet lines</title><p>We examined whether our tet lines could drive transgenes other than the mCitrine encoded in the probes. TRE promoters are known to have weak, tTA-independent ('leak') expression that can be substantial when many copies of the TRE-Cre constructs are delivered virally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Mizuno et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">Zhu et al., 2007</xref>). We injected adenoassociated virus (AAV) encoding TRE-driven transgenes into multiple areas in different lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10</xref>. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1-data">Figure 2—source data 1</xref> for counts). We found mCherry reporter was expressed specifically expressed in mCitrine-positive cells in most of cases. For example, three lines with expression in different layers of retrosplenial cortex had specific virus expression in different layers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3A–C</xref>). Infection efficiency varied from 36.5% (CA1 pyramidal cells in P066, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4D</xref>) to nearly 100% (layer 6 pyramidal cells in 56L, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10R and T</xref>), probably due to AAV serotype preference. In some lines, as reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Choy, 2015</xref>), we found a few viral reporter-positive but mCitrine-negative cells in the same layer/positions with those of mCitrine-positive cells (arrowheads in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3E and F</xref>; 0.7% +/- 0.7% of infected cells, n=6 injections in 5 strains), but never in ectopic positions lacking mCitrine positive cells. We speculate this 'off-target' expression might be a result of competition over tTA proteins between single copy TRE of mCitrine in the genome and many copies of TRE from virus. Myristoylated mCherry driven by a second-generation TRE (TREtight-myrmCherry-HA) was expressed only in mCitrine-positive cells and could be used to map their axonal projections (see below). Similarly, tet-dependent channelrhodopsin virus (TREtight-ChR2H134R-mCherry) had specific expression only in mCitrine-positive cells and could drive action potentials upon blue light stimulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Choy, 2015</xref>).</p><p>Because of the widespread utility of recombinase systems such as Cre and Flp, we made significant efforts to make reagents allowing either a) TRE-dependent recombinase expression or b) expression of Cre directly from the enhancer probe. Nearly all these attempts were unsuccessful (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s5">5</xref>) due first to low level leak of all versions of the TRE promoter tried, combined with the high sensitivity of cre-dependent recombination. Expression of Cre from the enhancer probe may have suffered from this problem in some cases as well as the additional problem of more widespread developmental expression. We were able to obtain specific Cre-reporter expression restricted to mCitrine-positive cells, using an implementation of the GFP nanobody-split Cre virus (developed independently from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Tang et al., 2015</xref>). The GFP nanobody-split Cre also had specific reporter expression from Ai14 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Madisen et al., 2010</xref>) TdTomato Cre reporter allele (supplemental note, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s5">5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>A catalog of neuronal cell types</title><p>By screening a large number of lines, we were able to identify strains that target both classically distinguished neuronal cell types and subtypes of these cell types including some previously unrecognized subtypes. In this section, we focus on seven major brain structures. Our anatomical and physiological characterizations are necessarily incomplete, but we expect that others with scientific interests in the relevant structures will contribute to more detailed characterization.</p><sec id="s2-6-1"><title>Neocortex</title><p>Many lines have regional and/or laminar expression in the neocortex. For examples, P172 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>) had layer 4 expression in three primary sensory cortices (primary somatosensory area: SSp, primary visual area: VISp, and primary auditory area: AUDp) while P063 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>), and P160 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>) has expression in only in AUDp and VISp layer 4 neurons respectively. Layer 5 pyramidal neurons are categorized by their axonal projection patterns and somatodendritic morphologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hattox and Nelson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Molyneaux et al., 2007</xref>): callosal neurons (projecting to contralateral cortex) have thinner apical dendrites and smaller somata, whereas corticofugal (subcereberal) projection neurons have thick tufted dendrites and larger somata. Both main types of L5 neurons also project to the striatum. Corticofugal cells can be further divided based on their projection targets. P136 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>) has expression in callosal thin tufted pyramidal neurons located in upper layer 5 (layer 5a) and projecting to the entire caudoputamen. P161 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>) has expression in callosal projecting thin-tufted cells forming a thin layer above layer 6. P074 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F</xref>) has expression in callosal projecting pyramidal neurons in anterior (motor and somatosensory) cortex with axonal projections that are biased to lateral caudoputamen. Thick tufted cortico-tectal neuronal lines (P081 and P084, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4G and H</xref>) and cortico-spinal lines (P149 and P135, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4I and J</xref>) also showed differences in regional expression patterns (P081: strong in somatomotor (MO) and supplemental somatomoter area (SSs), P084: only in SSp, P149: strong in MO and SSs, P135: SSp and VISp). We also obtained multiple layer 6 lines with different thalamic projection patterns (discussed below).<fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.020</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>PB Lines labeling neocortical cell types.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>J</bold>) Images of lines with layer-specific expression. Sagittal (top rows), coronal (middle rows), and high-magnification coronal images (bottom rows) are shown. Arrowheads (<bold>D</bold>,<bold>E”</bold>): callosal projections. Asterisks (<bold>I</bold>,<bold>J”</bold>): corticospinal projections. Scale bars: 500 μm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.020">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.020</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig4-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.021</object-id><label>FIgure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Retrosplenial cortex lines.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) RSPv Layer 2 expression in P160. (<bold>B</bold>) P099 has expression in upper RSPv layer 2/3 with callosal projection (arrowhead). (<bold>C</bold>) RSPv layer 2/3 expression in P136. (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>E</bold>) RSPv layer 6 expression. (<bold>F</bold>) P107 has expression in RSPd layer2/3 and layer6 in RSPd. (<bold>G</bold>) P012 has layer 2 expression in RSPv. (<bold>H</bold>) P122 has expression in posterior RSPv. (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>H1</bold>) coronal, (<bold>H2</bold>) sagittal sections.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.021">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.021</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig4-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Layer-specific expression patterns were distinctive in retrosplenial cortex (RSP, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">FIgure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). P160, P099, and P136 have expression in distinctive layers of ventral part (RSPv) but not in dorsal part (RSPd). P160 has expression in layer 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>), in P099 mCitrine cells form a thin layer immediately under layer 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref>), and P136 has expression in layer 2/3. P099 and P136 are strikingly different in their presence or absence of callosal projection (arrowhead). We also observed several lines with RSP layer 6 expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1D–F</xref>), RSPd expression (P012, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1G</xref>) and posterior RSPv expression (P122, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1H</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-6-2"><title>Olfactory bulb and related structures</title><p>The main olfactory bulb is a laminated structure that contains multiple cell types with different morphologies in each layer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Nagayama et al., 2014</xref>). P152 and P110 have expression in the glomerular layer of the main olfactory bulb (MOBgl). mCitrine-positive cells’ dendrites point toward the centers of glomeruli in P152 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>), but dendrites are mainly confined to glomerulus walls in P110 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). These morphological differences are characteristic of periglomerular cells and superficial short axon cells, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Nagayama et al., 2014</xref>). There are several lines with expression in the outer plexiform layer (MOBopl). Many of these lines have an even distribution of labeled cell bodies within the MOBopl (P118 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>) but P157 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>) has mCitrine-positive cells confined to the basal half of the layer. We also found lines targeting granule cells in the main olfactory bulb (MOBgr, P074, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>) and accessory olfactory bulb (AOBgr, P099, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref>). We found lines with expression in the anterior olfactory nucleus. P135 has mCitrine-positive cell bodies in the outer layer (anterior olfactory nucleus layer 1, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5G</xref>), whereas those of P113 are located in the ventral inner layer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5H</xref>). P074 has widespread expression in the inner layer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5I</xref>). We obtained three subtypes of piriform cortex layer II neurons (see below) and lines with expression in the cortical amygdalar area (COA, P055, and P122, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>). We also had lines with expression in tenia tecta (ex. P064, data not shown).<fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.022</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>PB lines labeling olfactory bulb cell types.</title><p>Coronal sections of main olfactory bulb (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>E</bold>), accessory olfactory bulb (<bold>F</bold>), and anterior olfactory nucleus (<bold>G</bold>–<bold>I</bold>). AOBgr: accessory olfactory bulb, granule layer, MOBgl: main olfactory bulb, glomerular layer, MOBgr: main olfactory bulb, granule layer MOBopl: main olfactory bulb, outer plexiform layer. Scale bars in <bold>A</bold>–<bold>E</bold>: 100 μm, others: 500 μm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.022">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.022</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig5-v3.tif"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s2-6-3"><title>Hippocampal formation</title><p>The entorhinal cortex, hippocampus, and subiculum are interconnected by complex loops with reciprocal connections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Ding, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Witter et al., 2014</xref>). Many (92) lines have expression in subregions of the hippocampal formation. CA1 is one of major input source of the subiculum, which sends axons to the entorhinal cortex through the presubiculum (PRE) and parasubiculum (PAR). Labeled cells proximal to CA1 in three lines, P162 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>), P139 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>), and P141 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>), do not project to PRE but the distal subiculum population labeled in P157 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>) does. P066, which has expression in the whole subiculum, also has PRE projections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref>). P162, P139, and P141 have expression in adjacent positions (cells in P162 and P139 are in nearly the same positions and P141 cells are located posterior to them, (see distal ends of CA1 marked by arrowheads in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A–C</xref>) but have different axonal projections. P162 has dense mCitrine-positive axons in the reuniens nucleus (RE) and dorsal and ventral submedial nucleus (SMT) but there are few axons in the corresponding areas in P139 and P141 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1A–F</xref>). Injection of tet –dependent virus (AAV-Tre3G-myristylated mCherry-HA) into the subiculum in P162 confirmed that axons in RE and SMT were coming from the subiculum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1G–I</xref>). P160 has expression in PRE and PAR and dense axonal projections to entorhinal cortex, medial part (ENTm, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref>). P149 has expression in ENTm layer 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6H</xref>). P084 also has expression in the same region, but the expression is restricted to the most medial part of ENTm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6G</xref>). 56L had broad expression in deep layer 6 of neocortex, but its expression in ENTm was observed in upper layer 6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6J</xref>). P038 occupied ENTm deep layer 6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6I</xref>). We also obtained lines with ENTm layer 2/3 (PBAS, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6K</xref>) and entorhinal cortex, lateral part (ENTl) layer 2/3 (P126, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6L</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.023</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Lines with expression in the hippocampal formation.</title><p>Horizontal sections through the hippocampal formation. (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>B</bold>) Expression closer to CA1 (P162, <bold>A</bold>) and to subiculum (P139, <bold>B</bold>) at the region of their border. CA1: Ammon’s horn, field CA1, SUB: subiculum, PRE: presubiculum, PAR: parasubiculum, ENTm: entorhinal cortex, medial part, ENTl: entorhinal cortex, lateral part. Arrowheads in (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) distal end of CA1 pyramidal layer. (<bold>C</bold>–<bold>E</bold>) Subiculum expression in P141(<bold>C</bold>), P157 (<bold>D</bold>) and P066 (<bold>E</bold>). (<bold>F</bold>) Presubiculum expression in P160. (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) Expression in medial entorhinal cortex layer 5 in P084 (<bold>G</bold>) and P149 (<bold>H</bold>). (<bold>I</bold> and <bold>J</bold>) medial entorhinal cortex layer6 expression in P038 (<bold>I</bold>) and 56L (<bold>J</bold>). (<bold>K</bold> and <bold>L</bold>) medial entorhinal (PBAS, <bold>K</bold>) and lateral entorhinal (P126, <bold>L</bold>).layer 2 expression. Scale bar: 500 μm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.023">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.023</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig6-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.024</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>P162 subiculum neurons project to thalamus.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>F</bold>) Axonal projection in nucleus of reunions (RE), dorsal (dSMT), and ventral (vSMT) submedial nuclei are prominent in P162 (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>B</bold>) but are weak or absent in p139 (<bold>C</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) and P141 (<bold>E</bold>–<bold>F</bold>). <bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold>, and <bold>F</bold> magnified images of areas shown <bold>A</bold>, <bold>C</bold>, and <bold>E</bold>, respectively. (<bold>G–I</bold>) TRE3G-myrmCherryHA injection to P162. (<bold>G</bold>) the injection site. (<bold>H</bold>) axons in RE. (<bold>I</bold>) axons in RE and vSMT.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.024">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.024</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig6-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group></p></sec><sec id="s2-6-4"><title>Cortical subplate (claustrum, endopiriform, amygdala) and nuclei (striatum and pallidum)</title><p>We identified lines separately labeling endopiriform nucleus (P138, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>) and claustrum (P018, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>). P170 has expression in the anterior part of the basolateral amygdalar nucelus (BLA, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref>) and P113 shows complementally expression in lateral and basomedial amygdalar nuclei (BLA and BMA, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7D</xref>).<fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.025</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Lines labeling cortical subplate, mesencephalic, and diencephalic cell types.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Endopiriform nucleus (EP) expression in P138 near anterior olfactory nucleus (left) and claustrum (asterisk). Note claustrum does not express mCitrine. (<bold>B</bold>) Claustrum (CLA) expression in P018. (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) Amygdalar nucleus expression in P170 (<bold>C</bold>, BLA:basolateral) and P113 (<bold>D</bold>, LA: lateral and BMA: basomedial). (<bold>E</bold>) Central amygdalar nucleus (CEA) expression in P189. (<bold>F</bold>) Expression in P161 lateral septum (LS) (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) Striosome expression in P172 (<bold>G</bold>) and P118 (<bold>H</bold>). GPe: globus pallidus, external part, SNr: substantia nigra, reticular part. (<bold>I</bold>) Anterior medial nucleus (AM) expression in P084. I2: close up of the rectangle area in I1. AD: anterior dorsal, AV: anterior ventral, RE: nucleus of reunions (<bold>J</bold>) Expression in ventral lateral geniculate nucleus in P138. J2: close up of the rectangle area in J1. LGd: dorsal lateral geniculate nucleus. (<bold>K</bold>) Dorsal submedius nucleus expression in P136. Inset: close-up of the rectangle. Sub: submedius nucleus, Rh: rhomboid nucleus. (<bold>L</bold>) Paraventricular nucleus (PVT) expression in P006 (<bold>M</bold>) P170 displayed sexually dimorphic expression (M1:male, M2: female) in medial preoptic area (MPO). (<bold>N</bold>) Superior colliculus (SC) expression in PBAU (<bold>O</bold>) Inferior colliculus (IC) expression in P118. (<bold>P</bold> and <bold>Q</bold>) Expression in subnuclei in interpeduncular nucleus (IPN) in P118 (<bold>P</bold>) and P025 (<bold>Q</bold>) (<bold>R</bold>) Inferior olivary complex (IO) expression in P066. (<bold>S</bold>) Nucleus of solitary tract (NTS) expression in P161. (<bold>T</bold>) Dorsal column nucle (DCN) expression in P118. (<bold>U</bold>) Expression in dorsal spinal cord in P108. Scale bars: 500 μm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.025">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.025</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig7-v3.tif"/></fig></p><p>There are 29 lines with expression in striatum and related structures. P189 had expression in the central amygdalar nucleus (CEA, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7E</xref>) and P161 had expression in the lateral septum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7F</xref>). Some lines have regional expression in caudoputamen. For example, P057 has expression only in lateral caudoputamen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2H</xref>) and P172 has expression in the striasomes in dorsal caudoputamen projecting to both globus pallidus, external part (GPe) and substantia nigra, reticular part (SNr) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7G</xref>). Striatal mCitrine-expressing cells in P118 are biased toward the anterior caudoputamen and appear to consist mainly of indirect pathway cells projecting to GPe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7H</xref>). Additional patterns of regional expression in the striatum include lateral (P055, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2H</xref>), and dorsal striosomes of both direct (projecting to substantia nigra pars reticulata) and indirect (projecting to globus pallidus) pathways (P172, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7G</xref>), as well as to striasomes restricted mainly to the indirect pathway (P118, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7H</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-6-5"><title>Thalamus and hypothalamus</title><p>We obtained lines with expression in specific thalamic and hypothalamic nuclei, including anterior medial nucleus (P084, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7I</xref>), ventral lateral geniculate nucleus (P138, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7J</xref>), submedius nucleus of thalamus (P136, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7K</xref>) and a part of the paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus (PVT, P006, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7L</xref>). P170 had sexually dimorphic expression; males (Figure 7M1) but not females (Figure 7M2) had expression in the medial preoptic area (MPO) and bed nuclei of stria terminalis (data not shown). Since both structures are larger in males than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Cooke et al., 1998</xref>) further work will be needed to determine if the neurons themselves or only their reporter expression are sexually dimorphic. The animals of both sexes had the same expression in other areas.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6-6"><title>Midbrain and hindbrain</title><p>We observed lines with expression in superior colliculus (SC, PBAU, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7N</xref>), inferior colliculus (IC, P118, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7O</xref>). P118 also has expression in the lateral part of the interpeduncular nucleus (IPN, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7P</xref>) and dorsal medulla, presumably a part of the parasolitary nucleus. In the interpeduncular nucleus, two lines label the dorsal (P025, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7Q</xref>) and central parts, respectively (P161, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://enahancertrap.bio.brandeis.edu/P161/coronal/029/5652/4481/25/">http://enahancertrap.bio.brandeis.edu/P161/coronal/029/5652/4481/25/</ext-link>). P066 has expression in neurons of the inferior olivary complex (IO), which send climbing fibers to the cerebellum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7R</xref>). P161 has expression in the solitary nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7S</xref>). P118 shows dorsal column nuclei (DCN) expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7T</xref>). P108 has expression in the dorsal part of the spinal nucleus of trigeminal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D2</xref>) and dorsal spinal cord (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7U</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-6-7"><title>Cerebellum</title><p>In the cerebellum, we found many lines with Purkinje cell and granule cell expression. Some lines have broad expression in these cell types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A and D</xref>), and others have sparser expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8B and E</xref>, see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Huang et al., 2013</xref>]). Expression in Purkinje cells in P014 was restricted to a small subset occupying a stripe-like pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8C</xref>) that is consistent across individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8C</xref> inset). P033 has restricted expression in granule cells that project to the basal half of the molecular layer. We also found lines with expression in Bergman glia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8G</xref>), basket cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8H</xref>), and stellate cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8I</xref>). There were two lines (P134 and P159) that have cell bodies directly beneath the Purkinje cell layer and extend dendrites into the molecular layer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8J–L</xref>). From their cell body positions and morphology, they appear to be Lugaro cells.<fig id="fig8" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.026</object-id><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>Lines labeling cerebellar cell types.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) Purkinje cells labeled densely (<bold>A</bold>, P034), sparsely (<bold>B</bold>, P096), and in restricted regions (<bold>C</bold>, P014). <bold>C</bold> inset: dorsal views of cerebellums from two different individuals. (<bold>D</bold>–<bold>F</bold>) Granule cells labeled densely (<bold>D</bold>, P012), sparsely (<bold>E</bold>, TCGC), and in a population projecting axons to the basal half of the molecular layer (<bold>F</bold>, P033). (<bold>G</bold>) Bergman glia labeling in TCFQ. (<bold>H</bold>) P102 has sparse labeling in basket cells. (<bold>I</bold>) P034 has expression in basket cells and stellate cells. (<bold>J</bold>–<bold>K</bold>) Lugaro cell like expression in P134 (<bold>J</bold> and <bold>K</bold>) and P159 (<bold>L</bold>). Scale bar in <bold>A</bold>–<bold>F</bold>: 500 μm, others: 100 μm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.026">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.026</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig8-v3.tif"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Finding a new cell type in piriform cortex</title><p>We found three lines (48L, 52L, P113) with distinctive expression patterns in the cell-dense layer (layer II) of the piriform cortex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9A–C</xref>). Two broad categories of layer II glutamatergic neurons have previously been described; semilunar (SL) cells, which lack well-defined basal dendrites and are located in the upper sublayer of layer II, and superficial pyramidal (SP) cells, which, like most pyramids, possess distinct basal and apical dendrites and are located deeper in layer II (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Suzuki and Bekkers, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">2011</xref>). 48L cells were recently shown to be a subset of SL cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Choy, 2015</xref>). Based on their cell body positions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9D</xref>) and dendritic morphology, the labeled cells in P113 appear to be typical SP cells. 52L cells were GABA-negative (data not shown) but do not clearly match the anatomical and physiological properties of either subtype of previously described pyramidal neurons.<fig id="fig9" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.027</object-id><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><title>Piriform cortex cell types.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) Expression in three distinct populations within piriform cortex. (<bold>D</bold>) Cell body distributions in layer 2. (<bold>E</bold>–<bold>K</bold>) 52L labels a previously undistinguished cell type. Firing patterns (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>G</bold>) and morphologies (<bold>F</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) of labeled (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>) and non-labeled (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) cells in 52L piriform cortex. Arrows: initial burst present in labeled, but not unlabeled cells’ arrowheads: AHP at the end of train present in unlabeled but not labeled cells. Average <bold>F</bold>–<bold>I</bold> curves (<bold>I</bold>), AHP amplitude (<bold>J</bold>), and instantaneous firing frequency (<bold>K</bold>) for labeled cells (red) and non-labeled cells (black) were significantly different (asterisks): mean firing frequencies (averaged over 400–500 pA current injection, 11 ± 5 Hz and 28 ± 5 Hz, p = 0.025), AHP amplitude (-1.2 ± 0.3 mV and -3.4 ± 0.6 mV, p=0.0073, labeled and non-labeled cells, respectively), and in instantaneous firing frequencies (131 ± 12 Hz and 58 ± 10 Hz, p = 0.00019). n= 10 for each; line. Scale bars: 500 μm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.027">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.027</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig9-v3.tif"/></fig></p><p>We recorded the physiological properties of mCitrine-labeled cells and non-labeled cells in 52L piriform cortex. Like SP cells, they responded to depolarizing current with an initial high frequency burst of action potentials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Suzuki and Bekkers, 2006</xref>) as did nearby non-labeled cells (arrows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8G</xref>). However, labeled cells (but not unlabeled cells) differed from the previously described SP neurons in that they exhibit a stuttering firing pattern and their firing inactivates at higher currents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9I</xref>). Labeled and non-labeled neurons also differ in their afterhyperpolarizations (arrowheads in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9E and G</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9J</xref>). While the labeled neurons could not sustain prolonged firing at high-current injections, their instantaneous firing frequency was higher in the beginning of spike train (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9E and G</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9K</xref>). Morphologically, the non-labeled neurons resemble previously described SP cells since they possessed distinct basal and apical dendrites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9H</xref>). Labeled neurons also possessed basal dendrites (unlike SL cells) but do not have a distinct apical dendrite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9F</xref>). Taken together, our anatomical and physiological results suggest that 52L cells are a distinct subset of SP cells that differ phenotypically from other, unlabeled SP cells.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>An altered classification of layer 6 cortico-thalamic pyramidal neurons</title><p>Cerebral cortex and thalamus have dense reciprocal connections and layer 6 of the cortex is the major source of the cortico-thalamic (CT) projection. Single cell tracing has shown that there are two types of L6 CT projecting pyramidal neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Thomson, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Zhang and Deschenes, 1997</xref>); primary sensory CT pyramidal neurons send axons to primary sensory thalamic nuclei (ex. ventro-posterior medial:VPm, lateral geniculate dorsal nucleus: LGd). Non-primary CT neurons send weaker projections to primary sensory nuclei, but also project to secondary sensory nuclei; for example, in primary somatosensory cortex, they send axons to VPM, posterior thalamic nuclei (Po), and intralaminar thalamic nucleus. Primary CT neurons are located in upper layer 6 and non-primary CT neurons in lower layer 6. Primary CT neurons also project to the thalamic reticular nucleus (RTN), whereas non-primary CT neurons do not. Primary CT neurons and non-primary CT neurons also have different morphologies. Primary CT neurons extend apical dendrites to layer 4 while dendrites of non-primary CT neurons do not reach to layer 4. Layer 6 also contains corticocortical pyramidal cells, which have long collateral projections within layer 6.</p><p>We obtained three lines with expression in layer 6 cortical pyramidal neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10</xref>). P162 has mCitrine-positive cells in primary somatosensory area (SSp), primary visual area (VISp), and retrosplenical cortex and axonal projection in VPm and LGd (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10G–J</xref>). P139 has expression in lateral cortex including supplemental somatosensory area (SSs) and gustatory cortex and projection in Po (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10M–P</xref>). There are topological projection patterns in RTN; dorsally located P162 cells project to dorsal RTN and laterally located P139 cells project to ventral RTN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s1">Figure 10—figure supplement 1B and C</xref>). The third line, 56L, has broad expression across neocortex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10A–D</xref>). 56L neurons have projection to both primary and secondary nuclei but not to RTN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s1">Figure 10—figure supplement 1A</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig10" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.028</object-id><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><title>Projections of layer 6 corticothalamic (CT) neurons.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) Coronal images from 56L. (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>) confocal images from SSp (<bold>E</bold>) and VISp (<bold>F</bold>) from 56L. (<bold>G</bold>–<bold>J</bold>) Coronal sections from P162. (<bold>K</bold> and <bold>L</bold>) Confocal images from SSp (<bold>K</bold>) and VISp (<bold>L</bold>) from P162. (<bold>M</bold>–<bold>P</bold>) Coronal images from P139. (<bold>Q</bold>) Confocal image from P139 SSs. Sections were taken from 0.7 mm (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>G</bold>, and <bold>M</bold>), 1.7 mm (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold>, <bold>H</bold>, <bold>J</bold>, <bold>N</bold>, and <bold>P</bold>), 2.3 mm (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>I</bold>, and <bold>O</bold>) caudal from bregma. (<bold>R</bold>–<bold>W</bold>) tet-reporter virus injection into 56L SSp (<bold>R</bold>), 56L SSs (<bold>T</bold>), P162 SSp (<bold>V</bold>), and P139 SSs (<bold>X</bold>) and their projection to thalamus (<bold>S</bold>, <bold>U</bold>, <bold>W</bold>, and <bold>Y</bold>, respectively). (<bold>Z</bold>) Schematic view of projections in layer 6 lines. ILM: interlaminar nucleus, Po: posterior complex, VPM: ventral posteomedial nucleus. Scale bars: 500 μm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.028">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.028</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig10-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig10s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.029</object-id><label>Figure 10—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Projections to the reticular nucleus of the thalamus (RT) (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) DAPI (blue), anti-GFP (green), and anti-Parvalbumin (PV, red) staining for thalamus of 56L (<bold>A</bold>), P162 (<bold>B</bold>), and P139 (<bold>C</bold>).</title><p>Few or no mCitrine-positive axons from 56L (<bold>A</bold>) project to the PV-positive RT. P162 (<bold>B</bold>) axons project only to the dorsal (d) part of RT, whereas the ventral (v) part receives axons from P139 (<bold>C</bold>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.029">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.029</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig10-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig10s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.030</object-id><label>Figure 10—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Sublaminar location and intrinsic physiology of layer 6 neurons.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Positions of mCitrine-positive cell bodies in Layer 5–6 are plotted. (<bold>A</bold>) P162 (green) and 56L (blue) in SSp. (<bold>B</bold>) P139 (green) and 56L (blue) in SSs. Dotted lines: averaged borders between layers 5 and 6. (<bold>C</bold>) Current clamp responses of P162, 56L SSp, P139, 56L SSs to 100 pA current injections. Input resistance (<bold>D</bold>) whole cell capacitance (<bold>E</bold>) of layer 6 cells. Asterisks: p&lt;0.05 with Turkey-Kremer’s post hoc test. (<bold>F</bold> and <bold>G</bold>) Current clamp responses of labeled (<bold>F</bold>) and nearby non-labeled (<bold>G</bold>) neurons in 56L layer 6 during current injection. (<bold>H</bold>) Firing frequency – current injection plot for labeled and non-labeled neurons in 56L layer 6. n = 16–20.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.030">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.030</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig10-figsupp2-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig10s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.031</object-id><label>Figure 10—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>56L axonal projection from VISp to thalamus.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Injection site. (<bold>B</bold>) High magnification of injection site. (<bold>C</bold>) Axonal projections to thalamus avoid the dorsal leteral geniculate nuceus (LGd).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.031">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.031</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig10-figsupp3-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig10s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.032</object-id><label>Figure 10—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Long lateral projections in 56L and P139 AA<bold>V</bold>–<bold>T</bold>RE3GmCherryHA was injected to 56L.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) and P139 (<bold>D</bold>–<bold>F</bold>). <bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold> high magnification of designated area in <bold>A</bold>. <bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold> high magnification of designated area in <bold>D</bold>. 56L had callosal projections (arrowhead in <bold>A</bold>) but these were not seen in P139 (arrowhead in <bold>C</bold>). Red: anti-HA, Green: anti-GFP, Blue: DAPI. Images in <bold>D</bold>–<bold>F</bold> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10X</xref> were taken from the same section.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.032">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.032</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig10-figsupp4-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>The labeled CT neurons also differ morphologically and in their laminar locations. Cell bodies of P162 and P139 are located in upper layer 6, but those of 56L are in lower layer 6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s2">Figure 10—figure supplement 2A and B</xref>). P162 and P139 have apical dendrites reaching to layer 4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10K, L and Q</xref>); some apical dendrites even extended to layer 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10K</xref>). Apical dendrites to layer 1 were more frequently seen in P162 VISp and P139 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10L and Q</xref>). On the other hand, 56L dendrites in SSp did not step in to layer 4. In VISp, some neurons extended dendrites to layer 1. From their cell body locations and projection patterns, P162 and P139 appeared to be primary-CT type pyramidal neurons in different cortical areas.</p><p>We also recorded the physiological properties of layer 6 cells. 56L cells have larger whole cell capacitances than P162 and P139 cells and tended to have correspondingly lower input resistances. All mCitrine-positive cells fired tonically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s2">Figure 10—figure supplement 2C and D</xref>). In the 56L recordings, we found that most mCitrine-negative cells recorded near mCitrine-positive cells fired more phasically and at lower rates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s2">Figure 10—figure supplement 2F–H</xref>) reminiscent of the firing previously described for CC cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mercer et al., 2005</xref>).</p><p>We compared axonal projection patterns to thalamus by injecting AAV-TRE3GmyrCherryHA virus in layer 6. P162 SSp cells projected to the dorsal part of VPM and P139 SSs neurons projected to Po (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10V–Y</xref>). In contrast, labeled axons from 56L SSp cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10R and S</xref>) were found in Po, VPM, and the intralaminar nucleus (ILM), consistent with previously described projections of non-primary CT cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Zhang and Deschenes, 1997</xref>). Axons from 56L SSs were enriched in ventral VPM and Po (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10T and U</xref>) and those from VISp mainly projected to the lateral posterior nucleus, not to LGd (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s3">Figure 10—figure supplement 3</xref>). We also found that 56L had long lateral axonal projections that even reached to the contralateral hemisphere, whereas P162 and P139 cells had local lateral axonal projections within the cerebral cortex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s4">Figure 10—figure supplement 4</xref>).</p><p>In order to complement our phenotypic analyses of differences between subtypes of L6 corticothalamic neurons, we also analyzed their RNAseq profiles and compared them to VISp layer 6 pyramidal neurons from the Ntsr1-Cre line, which is also known to have layer 6 specific expression in the cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Gong et al., 2007</xref>). Ntsr1-Cre labels virtually all primary CT neurons in layer 6 and also has projection to RTN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bortone et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Olsen et al., 2012</xref>). Clustering samples by correlations between gene expression vectors revealed two main clusters: those from 56L and all others (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11">Figure 11A</xref>). Samples from P162 and P139 are intermingled in the cluster, implying they have quite similar RNA expression profiles. Analysis of differentially expressed genes also showed clear differences between the two main groups. There were 1869 genes differentially expressed among all sample groups (false discovery rate (FDR) &lt; 0.01), and most differentially expressed genes showed bimodal patterns; high expressions in one group and low expressions in the other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11">Figure 11B and C</xref>). We also examined the expression of previously identified layer 6 marker genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Molyneaux et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">Zeisel et al., 2015</xref>) and of genes used to generate BAC-Cre lines having layer 6 expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Harris et al., 2014</xref>). Most of these known layer 6 markers are expressed both in the Ntsr1-cre group and in 56L (including the Ntsr1 gene itself) or were present only in the Ntsr1-cre lines. None were reliable markers for the 56L population (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11s1">Figure 11—figure supplement 1</xref> and supplemental Note). We also examined expression profile of entorhinal cortical layer 6 cells from P038 in addition to isocortical layer 6 cells. Based on RNAseq expression profiles, P038 cells belonged to the Ntsr1-cre group but expressed unique set of genes (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11s2">Figure 11—figure supplement 2</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig11" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.033</object-id><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><title>Two main subtypes of L6 CT neurons distinguished by gene expression .</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Clustering of L6 CT neuron samples based on correlations (color scale) between expression profiles. (<bold>B</bold>) Heat map of normalized gene expression (TPM) of 50 genes with lowest ANOVA p-values. Except for Plcxd2 (asterisk), the genes had dominant expression in either Ntsr1/P162/P139 or 56L. (<bold>C</bold>) Coverage histograms of differentially expressed genes. Examples of genes expressed in P162/P139 (Tle4 and Rgs4), 56L (Nptxr and Cacna1g), P139 (Atp1b2), and P162 (Ifitm2). Scale bars: 100 counts. (<bold>D–F</bold>) In situ hybridization for Tle4 (red) and Bmp3 (green) in wild type P10 animal SSp. (<bold>E</bold>) high-magnification image. (<bold>F</bold>) Proportion of cells expressing Tle4 and Bmp3 in SSp layer 6. (<bold>G</bold>–<bold>O</bold>) In situ hybridization for mCitrine and Tle4 (<bold>G</bold>, <bold>J</bold>, and <bold>M</bold>) or Bmp3 (<bold>H</bold>, <bold>K</bold> and <bold>N</bold>) in P162 SSp (<bold>G</bold> and H), P139 SSs (<bold>J</bold> and <bold>K</bold>) and P56 SSp (<bold>M</bold> and <bold>N</bold>). (<bold>I</bold>, <bold>L</bold>, <bold>O</bold>) Proportions of mCitrine<sup>+</sup> cells that expressTle4 or Bmp3 and converse proportions of cells expressing the dominant marker (Tle4 for I,L Bmp3 for <bold>O</bold>) that are mCitrine<sup>+</sup> from P162 (<bold>I</bold>), P139 (<bold>L</bold>) and 56L (<bold>O</bold>). Colors in bar graphs represent in situ signal patterns (Red: cells with marker gene but not mCitrine, Green: cells with mCitrine signal but not marker gene, and Yellow: cells with both marker and mCitrine signals). Scale bar in D: 500 μm, in E: 50 μm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.033">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.033</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig11-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig11s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.034</object-id><label>Figure 11—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Expression of known L6 marker genes.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Expression levels of known layer 6 marker genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Molyneaux et al., 2007</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) Expression levels of genes used to make BAC transgenic lines with layer 6 expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Harris et al., 2014</xref>). (<bold>C</bold>) Layer 6 marker genes found by single cell RNAseq (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">Zeisel et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.034">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.034</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig11-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig11s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.035</object-id><label>Figure 11—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>P038 entorhinal cortex layer 6 neurons are a distinct population.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Sample clustering (<bold>B</bold>) Heat map for top 100 genes with lowest ANOVA p-values. Arrows: genes shown in C. (<bold>C</bold>) Example of genes uniquely expressed in P038 (Nr4a2 and Parm1), Ntsr1 group and 56L markers (Tle4 and Bmp3), and selectively not expressed in P038 (Pcdh7 and Mef2c). y-axes: TPM.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.035">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.035</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-13503-fig11-figsupp2-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>We confirmed the expression of Tle4 (which is expressed strongly in Ntsr1-cre) and Bmp3 (expressed in 56L) by dual-color in situ hybridization. Tle4 and Bmp3 have essentially non-overlapping expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11">Figure 11D–F</xref>). mCitrine-positive cells in P162 and P139 dominantly express Tle4 with only a few Bmp3-positive cells, whereas 56L cells are mostly Bmp3-positive but Tle4-negative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11">Figure 11G–O</xref>). In all lines, the majority of marker (Tle4 or Bmp3)-positive cells do not express mCitrine, suggesting the three lines label subsets of these marker-positive cells. We also analyzed Tle4 expression in the Ntsr1-Cre animal (Nstr1-Cre;Ai14 Rosa-TdTomato) from dual-fluorescent in situ images (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://connectivity.brain-map.org/transgenic/experiment/100147520">http://connectivity.brain-map.org/transgenic/experiment/100147520</ext-link>) and found Ntsr1-Cre cells co-expressed Tle4; 100% (333/333) of Tdtomato<sup>+</sup> cells were Tle4<sup>+</sup> and 77.8% (333/428) of Tle4<sup>+</sup> cells were TdTomato<sup>+</sup>. These results support the view that P162 and P139 are subsets of the Ntsr1-cre population and that 56L cells are a distinct population of L6 CT neurons.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We have developed a highly efficient method of enhancer trapping in the mouse and have used it to generate a resource of lines that allow targeting of a wide range of known and novel neuronal cell types. The enhancer trap approach produces more focused labeling than commonly used approaches that attempt to recapitulate known patterns of endogenous gene expression. Using this approach, we have identified dozens of new subtypes of previously identified neuronal cell types and have clarified the classification of pyramidal neurons within the piriform cortex and within layer 6 of neocortex. The approach is readily scalable since new lines can be generated simply by additional rounds of breeding. We also develop the enhancer trap line web browser to search lines of interests and to share images and detailed information about lines. The web site can serve as a useful open resource for wide range of researcher in mouse genetics and neuroscience.</p><p>Cell-type-specific patterns of gene expression are thought to reflect interactions between regulatory sequences within the proximal promoter, and at other far more distal sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Nathanson et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Pennacchio et al., 2006</xref>). Viral reporter was mostly expressed only in mCitrine-positive cells, and we did not see major ectopic reporter expression, which supports that cell-type specific tTA expression, but not regional TRE silencing, mainly contributes to highly restricted expression patterns. Single genes often have multiple enhancer modules each of which regulates expression in different regional or developmental contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Dickel et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Visel et al., 2009</xref>). By harnessing these distal enhancers, BAC-transgenic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Gong et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">2007</xref>) and knock-in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Taniguchi et al., 2011</xref>) approaches have been used to generate lines that copy expression patterns of targeted genes with high-fidelity, but many of these are quite broadly expressed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Harris et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Madisen et al., 2015</xref>). On the other hand, lines with more limited expression patterns have been generated by unintentional positional effects arising from transgene insertion sites. Restricted expression patterns in the series of Thy1 lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Feng et al., 2000</xref>) and CA1-specific Cre mouse with a CamKII-promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Tsien et al., 1996</xref>) are notable examples. Because of these positional effects, even BAC transgenic lines occasionally have more restricted expression patterns that differ from those of the targeted genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Huang and Zeng, 2013</xref>). Although positional effects can restrict expression to specific populations, the population targeted is not predictable because the enhancer code that directs expression to specific cell types is not well understood. To circumvent this limitation, a useful enhancer trap requires screening a large number of individual strains. This has previously been done using transposable element mobilization in flies and fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Balciunas et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bellen et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Brand and Perrimon, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Scott et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Urasaki et al., 2008</xref>). However, since pronuclear-injection produces a rather low efficiency of transgenesis, this approach has not frequently been used in mouse genetics.</p><p>Hopping from single copy PB enabled fast identification of insertion sites without the laborious and time-consuming steps of tracking and segregating multiple transgene alleles. In fact, since we have made both single copy PB insertion lines and a line carrying PBase in the male germ line freely available, other laboratories can now screen for additional lines of interest without needing to isolate or inject embryos. Our strategy of including a mCitrine reporter on the probe enables fast expression screening without crossing to a separate reporter line, and including tTA enables inducible genetic manipulation in specifically labeled populations.</p><p>Although our enhancer trap lines were generated by random insertion, most lines maintain consistent expression over generations. In addition, lines generated by local hopping have similar expression patterns. These facts support the conclusion that the expression patterns are not generated randomly, but instead are tightly linked to transgenes’ insertion sites. PB translocation sites were widely distributed over the genome and lines with insertions far away from known genes often exhibited specific expression presumably by trapping distal enhancers. Distal enhancers are known to regulate tissue specific expression of genes, especially in the forebrain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Nord et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Visel et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">2013</xref>) and to regulate activity-dependent gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2010</xref>). Our results suggest that enhancers are also involved in the fine-grained specification of cell types, and that trapping them can cause very restricted expression patterns. Indeed, drivers restricted to major cell types and layers in laminated structures are already available, but drivers that pick out cell types in specific cortical regions, or thalamic nuclei are quite rare with gene-based strategies but were more common with our enhancer trap strategy.</p><p>The cell types accessed genetically in these and other driver strains are best thought of as operational cell types defined by the intersection of a driver strain and an anatomical region. This permits reproducibility but does not define the full set of 'atomic' cell types that comprise the nervous system. Like brain regions, cell types may be arranged hierarchically into tree-like taxonomies. Most operational cell types represent branches or nodes that can be further subdivided. This subdivision occurs when properties such as morphology, physiology, projections and gene expression are found to vary discontinuously. Eventually, those that cannot be further subdivided may be thought as terminal branches or 'atomic cell types'. For a few of the cell types identified in our enhancer trap strains (e.g. subsets of corticothalamic neurons or piriform cortex neurons) further characterization demonstrates functional distinctions between closely related subtypes. In other cases, the trapped neurons correspond to well-characterized subtypes of a larger class (e.g. LGN thalamic projection neurons), while in many other cases additional characterization will be needed to determine how trapped subtypes differ functionally from other cells in the same class. The anatomical distinctiveness of, for example, Purkinje cells restricted to particular folia or granule cells sending their axons to particular sublaminae are suggestive, but whether these neurons differ from other Purkinje cells and granule cells in other aspects of their anatomy, physiology and gene expression remains to be seen. Efforts to enhance the aggregation of such phenotypic data are needed to better refine the definition of cell types within the vertebrate nervous system. Hopefully, additional iterations of our enhancer trap database will benefit from enhanced informatic efforts to improve usability and interoperability with other databases and to make it easier for the community to contribute data that will help parse operational cell types into atomic cell types.</p><p>In addition to positional effects, the nature of our enhancer probe might have contributed to producing restricted expression patterns. We obtained lines with specific expression more frequently than those of previous enhancer screening with minimal HSP promoter-lacZ and thy1 promoter-Cre lines, although they employed the same random insertion method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kelsch et al., 2012</xref>). Some PB lines with intronic insertions expressed the reporter in neurons in which the inserted genes were strongly expressed. From these facts, we speculate our enhancer probes may require a certain level of transcriptional activity to drive the reporter expression, and this thresholding effect may limit the expression of the reporter. The use of a transactivator system, rather than a recombinase system, may also have contributed to generating specific reporter expression. Cre-dependent reporter expression will be present regardless of whether cre continues to be expressed, or whether it was only expressed in the labeled cells or their progenitors earlier in development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Harris et al., 2014</xref>), while tet reporters will be expressed only when tTA protein continues to be expressed.</p><p>Our screen revealed two major subtypes of corticothalamic pyramidal neurons in layer 6: primary CT neurons and non-primary CT neurons. The two cell types differ in distribution within layer 6 and have distinctive axonal projection patterns in the thalamus. They also have distinct RNA expression profiles identifying marker genes that display almost non-overlapping patterns in layer 6. Genetic labeling of primary CT cells by Ntsrt1-Cre (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Gong et al., 2007</xref>) has greatly advanced understandings of functions of layer 6 primary CT in cortical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bortone et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Olsen et al., 2012</xref>) and thalamic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Crandall et al., 2015</xref>) circuits. Perhaps since Ntsr1-Cre labels nearly all (92.7% in SSp and 95–100% in VISp :<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bortone et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2014</xref>) primary thalamic nuclei projecting CT neurons, and since a selective driver for non-primary CT layer 6 neurons was not previously available, the role of this second CT pathway from L6 has not been taken into consideration in previous functional studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bortone et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Watakabe et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Yamawaki and Shepherd, 2015</xref>). We found that 56L cells in SSp had projection to multiple nuclei (VPM, Po and ILM) as originally described by Zhang and Deschenes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Zhang and Deschenes, 1997</xref>). 56L in SSs has strong projections to VPM, which implies there are previously unidentified sources of CT feedback from higher order cortical regions to primary sensory thalamic nuclei (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Sherman, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Thomson, 2010</xref>). We also found that 56L cells have long collateral projections like those previously described for CC neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Zhang and Deschenes, 1997</xref>). Thomson and colleagues found that the most of cells with CC-like morphologies fired phasically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mercer et al., 2005</xref>). We speculate that 56L-like cells are the minor population of layer 6 pyramidal neurons which fire tonically like primary CT neurons but which possess large collateral projections and other morphological features associated with CC cells. Since mCitrine-negative cells in 56L were phasically firing, we speculate that these are CC cells labeled by neither Ntsr1-Cre nor 56L. For example, many of the Bmp3-positive cells not labeled by 56L could be CC-cells lacking a projection to thalamus.</p><p>Although we have shown the ability of the tet enhancer trap system to label highly restricted specific cell types, further technical improvements may enhance the utility of the approach. Replacing the HSP promoter with other (minimal) promoters may change the forebrain bias (see <bold>PB line expression patterns</bold> above) to permit better exploration of cell types in other major brain regions. Developments of additional molecular genetic tools, such as optogenetic tools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Choy et al., 2015</xref> is an example), voltage- or calcium sensors, and viral vectors targeted to synapses or other subcellular structures,or functionalized for retrograde or transynaptic transport may enhance analysis of the connectivity of trapped cell types. Finally, enhancer trap lines may be useful for analyzing the function of candidate enhancers near the insertion sites in order to better understand how distal enhancers contribute to the specification and maintenance of cell-type-specific gene expression in the mammalian nervous system.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Lentiviral transgenesis</title><p>Lentiral constructs were made using a backbone from pSico (Addgene, Cambridge, MA #11578). Lentiviruses were prepared and injected into single cell embryos as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lois et al., 2002</xref>) using virus solutions at 10<sup>9</sup> infection unit/ml. Candidate forebrain enhancer sequences were chosen using the VISTA enhancer browser (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://enhancer.lbl.gov">http://enhancer.lbl.gov</ext-link>). The four selected sequences (hs119, hs121, hs122, and hs170) were amplified from C57Bl6/J genomic DNA.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>PiggyBac transgenesis</title><p>pPB-UbC.eGFP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Yusa et al., 2009</xref>) was used as the backbone for PB plasmids. Prior work has distinguished two functional types of insulators: ‘barrier’ insulators, which prevent the spread of DNA methylation and silencing, and ‘blocking’ insulators, which limit promoter-enhancer interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Gaszner and Felsenfeld, 2006</xref>). Most vertebrate insulators with barrier activity also have blocking activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">West et al., 2002</xref>). The cHS4 site from the chicken β-globin locus is a well-characterized insulator known to have separate sequences that mediate its blocking and barrier insulator functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Dickson et al., 2010</xref>). To prevent silencing but not enhancer effects, we synthesized cHS4 sequence without the region responsible for the blocking activity (the CTCF-binding site). Tandem copies of the insulator sequences were inserted into each 5’ and 3’ ends of PB constructs (HS4 ins, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref>).</p><p>The Rosa-PBase line was provided by Ronald Rad and Allan Bradley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Rad et al., 2010</xref>). In order to establish the Protamine1 promoter-hyPBase line, the 848 bp mouse Protamine1 promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">Zambrowicz et al., 1993</xref>) was amplified by PCR from C57Bl6/J genomic DNA and fused with a hyperactive PiggyBac transposase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Yusa et al., 2011</xref>) and the SV40 polyadenylation signal. The linearized DNA was injected to pronuclei of single-cell embryos. PiggyBac seed lines were generated by pronuclear or cytosolic injection of a PiggyBac plasmid (2 ng/μl) and hyPBase mRNA (50 ng/μl) that was synthesized with mMESSAGE mMACHINE T7 Ultra Kit (Life Technologies) and purified with MEGAClear (Life Technologies).</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Amplification of insertion sites by ligation mediated (LM)-PCR</title><p>was performed as described by Wu et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Wu et al., 2003</xref>). We used the same adaptors and primers to amplify lentiviral and PB insertion sites. In addition to the adaptors, the following primers were used for PiggyBac lines; PB5'LMPCR: 5’-CGGATTCGCGCTATTTAGAA-3’, PB5'LMPCRnested: 5’-TCAAGAATGCATGCGTCAAT-3’, PB3'LMPCR: 5’-CCGATAAAACACATGCGTCA-3’, PB3'LMPCRnested: 5’-CGTCAATTTTACGCATGATTATCT-3’. After nested PCR, amplified products were isolated by agarose gel electrophoresis, and then reamplified by PCR to remove non-specific products. The final PCR products were used as templates for direct sequencing with the nested primers. Insertion sites were mapped on C57Bl6/j genome (GRCm38/mm10) with blat (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/cgi-bin/hgBlat">http://genome.ucsc.edu/cgi-bin/hgBlat</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>AAV preparation</title><p>For nanobody-split Cre construction, GBP1 and GBP6 (Addgene #50791 and #50796, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Tang et al., 2013</xref>) were fused with NCre and CCre from split Cre (gifts from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hirrlinger et al., 2009</xref>). AAV purification was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88">Zolotukhin et al., 1999</xref>). Since AAV serotypes can show tropism for specific cell types, we used a cocktail of 4 serotypes (2/1, 2/5, 2/8, 2/9). After iodixanol step gradient, the virus solution was dialyzed and concentrated with Amicon Ultra 100k Da filters (EMD Millipore, Billerica, MA) with lactated Ringer. Virus copy number was quantified with real-time PCR. Virus titers were in the range of 10<sup>12-14</sup> gene counts/ml.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Stereotaxic injection</title><p>We followed surgical procedures previously described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cetin et al., 2006</xref>). For each injection, 30-50 nl virus solutions were injected to the target sites with a custom-made injector.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Physiology</title><p>Whole cell recordings from visually identified neurons were obtained as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Miller et al., 2008</xref>). We recorded from four or more animals for each condition. We used t-test for statistical analyses if not stated.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Histology</title><p>After being deeply anesthetized with Ketamine and Xylazine, mice were perfused with phosphate buffer saline (PBS) and 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS. Brains were post-fixed overnight with 4%A PFA/PBS, embedded in 2% agarose /PBS, and then sectioned at 50 μm with a vibratome (Leica, Buffalo Grove, IL VT1000S). The following antibodies were used for immunohistochemistry: anti-GFP rabbit (Life Technologies, Thermo Fisher, Waltham, MA A-11122), anti-GFP chicken (Aves labs, Tigard, OR GFP-1020), anti-HA rat (Roche diagnostics, Indianapolis, IN clone 3F10). Whole slide images were taken with a microscope with 5x objective and XY-stage controlled by μManger (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://micro-manager.org">https://micro-manager.org</ext-link>). Grid/Collection stitching Fiji plugin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Preibisch et al., 2009</xref>) was used for image assembly. We followed the dual-color in situ protocol described in BraInSitu web site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nibb.ac.jp/brish/indexE.html">http://www.nibb.ac.jp/brish/indexE.html</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Watakabe et al., 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Evaluation of expression</title><p>The anatomy structure model in Allen reference mouse atlas (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mouse.brain-map.org/static/atlas">http://mouse.brain-map.org/static/atlas</ext-link>) was used to annotate expression areas. To compare the expression areas with Cre lines, 228 structures used in annotation commonly with sagittal and coronal sections in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Harris et al., 2014</xref> were applied. All lines were annotated by three observers independently and the unions of annotations were used. Expression levels were determined by the level of localization in anatomical structures and density of mCitrine-positive cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). Cell densities were determined by counting cells in most zoomed images in the web viewer (the window size is 600 x 400 px, 768 x 500 μm with images taken with a x5 objective). Structures with more than 10 cells/mm<sup>2</sup> (4 or more cells in the window) were annotated.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>RNA-seq</title><p>Manual sorting of fluorescent-labeled cells from transgenic animals was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Sugino et al., 2006</xref>). Total RNA was extracted from manually sorted cells (&lt;200) with Picopure RNA isolation kit (Thermo Fisher), and RNA-seq libraries were made with Ovation RNASeq System V2 and Encore kit (NuGEN, San Carlos, CA). Three or four biological duplicates were made for each sample. Illumina (San Diego, CA) HiSeq2500 was used for sequencing. rna-STAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Dobin et al., 2012</xref>) and cufflinks 2.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Trapnell et al., 2010</xref>) were used for mapping reads to reference mouse genome GRCm38 and for transcriptome assembly and quantification, respectively. Gene counts data generated with HT-seq {<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anders, 2015</xref> #103} was used for differentially expressed gene analysis by edgeR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Zhou et al., 2014</xref>). Custom-written Python programs using numpy and scipy were used for analysis. The accession number of RNAseq data is GSE75229.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Web page</title><p>Following programs were used to build the web site; Python 3.4 (programming language), Django 1.8 (web application framework), mySQL 5.6 (relational database), haystack-2.3.1 (search module for Django), elasticsearch-1.4.4 (search engine), uwsgi-2.0.10 (WSGI application server), and nginx-1.8 (web server).</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Supplemental note</title><sec id="s4-11-1"><title>Lentiviral constructs</title><p>The tet transactivator (tTA) was driven by the minimal promoter from the mouse heat shock protein 1A (Hspa1a) gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bevilacqua et al., 1995</xref>), which has previously been used for enhancer trapping in fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bayer and Campos-Ortega, 1992</xref>) and mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kelsch et al., 2012</xref>). Among the constructs tested, the hsp construct (hsp-tet) was most efficient at generating lines with brain expression (28.8%, see <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>) and many had restricted expression patterns (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Supplementary file 1</xref> for detail). We also tested hsp-probes with a spacer between tTA and TRE (hsp-tet2) and with inverted orientation (hsp-tet3). All hsp-tet2 animals had either broad or no brain expression and hsp-tet3 did not generate any lines with brain expression.</p><p>We also attempted to bias expression patterns by including candidate enhancers from highly-conserved sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Pennacchio et al., 2006</xref>) or by using promoters of genes known to have more restricted expression patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>). Specifically, we tested four ultra conserved, non-coding sequences found to have forebrain enhancer activity in an embryonic screen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Visel et al., 2007</xref>) and four promoters—CamKII (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Tsien et al., 1996</xref>), Gad1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Chattopadhyaya et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Szabo et al., 1996</xref>), Thy1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Feng et al., 2000</xref>), and Slc32a (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Ebihara et al., 2003</xref>) — previously used to establish cell-type specific transgenic lines. Most of these enhancer and promoter lentiviral probes had lower rates of brain expression rate than the hsp-tet probe (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). The CamKII promoter probe had comparable efficiency to hsp-tet but most lines had broad expression in the cerebral cortex (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-2"><title>PB Translocation</title><p>Previous studies have shown that piggyBac preferentially integrates into genes and other regions of active chromatin, and has a much weaker tendency hop locally than SleepingBeauty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Li et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Liang et al., 2009</xref>). We analyzed the patterns of translocation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Supplementary file 1</xref> for insertion sites of each line). The proportion of insertions into genes (60/167, 35.9% ) was comparable to that expected by chance (33.3% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Liang et al., 2009</xref>). We expected that prm-PBase may allow integration into a wider range of target locations than Rosa-PB because PB is expressed during histone-to-protamine transition that occurs in spermatogenesis. But Rosa-PBase (15:29) and prm-PBase (45:78) had similar gene-intergenic translocation ratios. Except for local hops, there were no particular genomic regions enriched for insertions and there were no insertions into previously described hot spots for PB translocation in mouse ES cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Li et al., 2013</xref>). The frequencies of local hopping and reinsertion within the same chromosome (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>) were comparable to the rates previously observed with SleepingBeauty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Ruf et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>We found that Prm-PBase generated founders more efficiently than Rosa-PBase (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). Prm-PBase conferred higher transposition rates than Rosa-PBase. In addition, the restriction of PBase to the male germ line meant that more founders could be established from Prm-PBase than from Rosa-PBase. Females of PB;PrmPBase did not have PBase activity and therefore could be founders of new lines whereas both sexes of PB;Rosa-PBase would not be able to transmit PB alleles stably (see differences in efficiency of new line production rate in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). We also found that all PB + founders from PBAW/Y;Prm-PBase/+ were females even though PB jumped to many other chromosomes. This showed tight regulation of Prm1 promoter only in meiosis II where sex chromosomes were already segregated. P2 animals with Prm-PBase allele and those without the allele had similar PB transposition efficiency, implying PB translocation occurred in sperm that did not carry the Prm-PBase gene. As suggested for Prm-SleepingBeuty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Ruf et al., 2011</xref>), PBase proteins may be supplied from Prm-PBase-positive sperms through cytoplasmic bridges among spermatids.</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-3"><title>PB insertion sites and reporter expression patterns</title><p>In order to determine if the reporter expression patterns reflected those of genes near the insertion sites, we examined the expression patterns of nearby genes using available databases (Allen Brain Atlas: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mouse.brain-map.org">http://mouse.brain-map.org</ext-link> and gene expression database: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.informatics.jax.org/expression.shtml">http://www.informatics.jax.org/expression.shtml</ext-link>). In most cases, in situ signals were broad and/or weak and were not strongly correlated with reporter expression. We often found clear correlation of expression patterns in the lines with intronic insertions. P103, for example, had strong reporter expression in hippocampus and local expression in a subset of Purkinje cells, whereas the inserted gene Gria1 has enriched expression in the hippocampus and nearly all Purkinje cells in the cerebellum. P062 has insertion in Slc9a2 intron and both P062 and Slc9a2 have strong expression in CA1.</p></sec><sec id="s4-11-4"><title>Viral reporter expression and 'leak' from tet promoters</title><p>We devoted significant effort to developing reagents that would allow us to 'convert' tet to cre expression in our driver strains. We first checked the expression of tet reporters in 293T cells. We found that TREtight-myrmCherry (myristoylated mCherry) had strong tTA-independent (leak) expression (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3A1 and A2</xref>). The leak expression from TRE3G (a third generation TRE with reduced leak expression) was hardly detectable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4A and B</xref>). We also evaluated leak in vivo. We injected AAV constructs containing the tTA reporter into the brains of our tet lines and did not observed leak expression (i.e. there was no reporter expression in mCitrine negative cells). Reporter driven by a second-generation TRE (TREtight-myrmCherry-HA) was expressed only in mCitrine positive cells and could be used to map their axonal projections (ex, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11">Figure 11</xref>). Presumably, the lower leak in vivo reflected a lower copy number of the TRE construct than achieved in cell culture. However, attempts to use TRE to drive recombinase expression revealed leak expression not visible with the tet reporter. Leak expression from TREtight-Cre and TRE3G-Cre were both strong enough to drive the Cre reporter, FLEX-mCherry in mCitrine negative cells both in culture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4E and F</xref>) and in vivo, where co-injection of TREtight-Cre and Cre reporter (AAV-Flex-mCherry) had non-specific expression in the brain.</p><p>We next tried a split-Cre construct, in which the Cre coding sequence is divided into N-terminus (NCre) and C-terminus (CCre) parts and their dimerization via a leucine zipper re-forms the functional enzyme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hirrlinger et al., 2009</xref>). Tre3G split Cre AAV (TRE3G-NCre and TRE3G-CCre) did not have detectable leak expression in 293T cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4G</xref>) or in the brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s5">Figure 2—figure supplement 5C</xref>). We also made a TRE3G flippase (TRE3G-Flpe) and and an FRT reporter construct (AAV-fDIO-myrmCherryHA). The Flippase had no leak expression in cultured cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4H</xref>). In the brain, reporter was primarily expressed in mCitrine-positive neurons; however, there were a few mCitrine-negative but FRT-reporter-positive cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s5">Figure 2—figure supplement 5D</xref>) indicating low-level leak.</p><p>We tested whether the TRE3G-split Cre could drive expression of a floxed reporter. We found that TRE3G splitCre had strong non-specific reporter expression in P113; Ai14 (TdTomato Cre reporter allele) animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s5">Figure 2—figure supplement 5D</xref>) indicating that this construct also had an unacceptable level of leak when used with a chromosomal reporter, even though it appeared not to leak when used with a viral reporter.</p><p>Finally, we applied GFP-nanobodies to split-Cre (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Tang et al., 2013</xref>). We made fusion protein constructs with GFP-binding proteins (GBP) and NCre or CCre so that functional Cre enzymes would be formed on GFP proteins. Co-expression of GFP-nanobody NCre (TRE3G-GBP1-NCre) and CCre (TRE3G-GBP6-CCre) had tTA independent reporter recombination in cultured cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4I</xref>), probably due to GFP-independent alpha-complementation of Cre protein. However, Tre3G-GBPsplit-Cre had specific expression in P113; Ai14 brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s5">Figure 2—figure supplement 5F</xref>). In addition, co-injection of TRE3G-GBP-splitCre AAV with Cre reporter AAV had restricted expression only in mCitrine+ cells in 56L (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s5">Figure 2—figure supplement 5G</xref>). Hence using split cre with GFP nanobodies can produce specific cre reporter expression without leak in vivo using both viral and chromosomal reporters.</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The transgenic lines were generated at the Brandies University transgenic mouse facility. We are grateful to Frank Sangiorgi and Zhe Meng for transgenesis; Serena David and Rajani Shelke for virus production; Roman Pavlyuk, Hao Fan, Sumana Setty, Alexander Cristofalo, Sarah Pizzano, and Emi Kullberg for assistance in histology; Prakhar Sahay for developing scripts for the web site. This work was supported by the Human Frontier Science Program Long Term Fellowship to Y.S., the David and Lucile Packard Foundation to C.L., and EY022360, NS075007 and MH105949 to S.N.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf2"><p>SBN: Reviewing editor, <italic>eLife</italic></p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf1"><p>The other authors declare that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>YS, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>KS, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>CMH, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>MS, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>PT, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>JBB, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>SM, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>CL, Conception and design, Drafting or revising the article, Contributed unpublished essential data or reagents</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con9"><p>SBN, Conception and design, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Animal experimentation: This study was performed in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. All of the animals were handled according to approved institutional animal care and use committee (IACUC) protocols (#14004) of Brandeis University. All surgery was performed under ketamine and xylazine anesthesia, and every effort was made to minimize suffering.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="SD2-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.036</object-id><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Enhancer trap line data List of lines generated in this study.</title><p>Line names beginning with the letter P are PiggyBac lines, others are lentiviral. Insertion sites and brief description of expression patterns are shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.036">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.036</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-13503-supp1-v3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SD3-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.037</object-id><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>Annotations of line expression Expression evaluation of the PB lines.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.13503.037">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.13503.037</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-13503-supp2-v3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><sec id="s7" sec-type="datasets"><title>Major datasets</title><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><related-object content-type="generated-dataset" id="NaN" source-id="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?token=yvmnuueudrgblwn&amp;acc=GSE75229" source-id-type="uri"><collab>Sugino K</collab>, <collab>Shima Y</collab>, <collab>Nelson S</collab><x>,</x> <year>2016</year><x>,</x><source>A Mammalian Enhancer trap Resource for Discovering and Manipulating Neuronal Cell Types</source><x>,</x> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?token=yvmnuueudrgblwn&amp;acc=GSE75229">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?token=yvmnuueudrgblwn&amp;acc=GSE75229</ext-link><x>,</x> <comment>Publicly available at the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (Accession no: GSE75229).</comment></related-object></p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyl</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>HTSeq--a Python framework to work with high-throughput sequencing data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balciunas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivasubbu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermanson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Welle</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekker</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Enhancer trapping in zebrafish using the sleeping beauty transposon</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>62</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-5-62</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos-Ortega</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>A transgene containing lacZ is expressed in primary sensory neurons in zebrafish</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>426</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Kane</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1989">1989</year><article-title>P-element-mediated enhancer detection: a versatile method to study development in Drosophila</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>1288</fpage><lpage>1300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.3.9.1288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bevilacqua</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinnunen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevilacqua</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Stage-specific regulation of murine Hsp68 gene promoter in preimplantation mouse embryos</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>170</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/dbio.1995.1230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bortone</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanziani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Translaminar inhibitory cells recruited by layer 6 corticothalamic neurons suppress visual cortex</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>474</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.02.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>Targeted gene expression as a means of altering cell fates and generating dominant phenotypes</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>415</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cetin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Komai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliava</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeburg</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Osten</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Stereotaxic gene delivery in the rodent brain</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>3166</fpage><lpage>3173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2006.450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chattopadhyaya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Cristo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Knott</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhlman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Welker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Experience and activity-dependent maturation of perisomatic GABAergic innervation in primary visual cortex during a postnatal critical period</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>9598</fpage><lpage>9611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1851-04.2004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Budisantoso</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bekkers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Optogenetic mapping of intracortical circuits originating from semilunar cells in the piriform cortex</article-title><source>Cerebral Cortex</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhv258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegstrom</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Villeneuve</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Breedlove</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Sexual differentiation of the vertebrate brain: principles and mechanisms</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neuroendocrinology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/frne.1998.0171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crandall</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruikshank</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Connors</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A corticothalamic switch: controlling the thalamus with dynamic synapses</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>768</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.03.040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dickel</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennacchio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Functional anatomy of distant-acting mammalian enhancers</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological Sciences</source><volume>368</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2012.0359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gowher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Strogantsev</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaszner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Felsenfeld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>VEZF1 elements mediate protection from DNA methylation</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e1000804</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Efficient transposition of the piggyBac (PB) transposon in mammalian cells and mice</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>122</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2005.07.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Comparative anatomy of the prosubiculum, subiculum, presubiculum, postsubiculum, and parasubiculum in human, monkey, and rodent</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>521</volume><fpage>4145</fpage><lpage>4162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.23416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Drenkow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaleski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Batut</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaisson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gingeras</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebihara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Obata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Mouse vesicular GABA transporter gene: genomic organization, transcriptional regulation and chromosomal localization</article-title><source>Brain Research. Molecular Brain Research</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0169-328x(02)00648-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellor</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller-Peck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>QT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nerbonne</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Imaging neuronal subsets in transgenic mice expressing multiple spectral variants of GFP</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0896-6273(00)00084-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaszner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Felsenfeld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Insulators: exploiting transcriptional and epigenetic mechanisms</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Genetics</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg1925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Doughty</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Losos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Didkovsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schambra</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leblanc</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatten</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Heintz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>A gene expression atlas of the central nervous system based on bacterial artificial chromosomes</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>425</volume><fpage>917</fpage><lpage>925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Doughty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harbaugh</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatten</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Heintz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerfen</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Targeting Cre recombinase to specific neuron populations with bacterial artificial chromosome constructs</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>9817</fpage><lpage>9823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2707-07.2007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gossler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyner</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Skarnes</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1989">1989</year><article-title>Mouse embryonic stem cells and reporter constructs to detect developmentally regulated genes</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>244</volume><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.2497519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirokawa</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortrud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouellette</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Madisen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Anatomical characterization of Cre driver mice for neural circuit mapping and manipulation</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neural Circuits</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>76</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncir.2014.00076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hattox</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Layer V neurons in mouse cortex projecting to different targets have distinct physiological properties</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>3330</fpage><lpage>3340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00397.2007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hippenmeyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrieseling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigrist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Portmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Laengle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladle</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Arber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>A developmental switch in the response of DRG neurons to ETS transcription factor signaling</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e159</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirrlinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirrlinger</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehr</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goebbels</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichenbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprengel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossner</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Split-cre complementation indicates coincident activity of different genes in vivo</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e4286</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewerling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabermann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brem</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Epigenetic regulation of lentiviral transgene vectors in a large animal model</article-title><source>Molecular Therapy</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymthe.2005.07.685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mensh</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hantman</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Convergence of pontine and proprioceptive streams onto multimodal cerebellar granule cells</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e00400</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/elife.00400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Genetic approaches to neural circuits in the mouse</article-title><source>Annual Review of Neuroscience</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-neuro-062012-170307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelsch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolfi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lois</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Genetic labeling of neuronal subsets through enhancer trapping in mice</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e38593</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laptewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbara-Haley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuersten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Markenscoff-Papadimitriou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Worley</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreiman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Widespread transcription at neuronal activity-regulated enhancers</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>465</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matney</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blankenship</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hestrin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Layer 6 corticothalamic neurons activate a cortical output layer, layer 5a</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>9656</fpage><lpage>9664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1325-14.2014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kothary</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year><article-title>A transgene containing lacZ inserted into the dystonia locus is expressed in neural tube</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>335</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/335435a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettitt</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadiñanos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The piggyBac transposon displays local and distant reintegration preferences and can cause mutations at noncanonical integration sites</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Biology</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>1317</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.00670-12</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stalker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Chromosomal mobilization and reintegration of Sleeping Beauty and PiggyBac transposons</article-title><source>Genesis</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvg.20508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lois</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pease</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltimore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Germline transmission and tissue-specific expression of transgenes delivered by lentiviral vectors</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>295</volume><fpage>868</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1067081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Genetic dissection of neural circuits</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2008.01.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madisen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwingman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunkin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zariwala</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmiter</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawrylycz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lein</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>A robust and high-throughput Cre reporting and characterization system for the whole mouse brain</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madisen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimaoka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuong</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Klapoetke</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Bourg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Niino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Egolf</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Monetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunkin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Benucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyawaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmchen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Empson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Knöpfel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyden</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carandini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Transgenic mice for intersectional targeting of neural sensors and effectors with high specificity and performance</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>85</volume><fpage>942</fpage><lpage>958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.02.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchhecker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerkhoff</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Excitatory connections made by presynaptic cortico-cortical pyramidal cells in layer 6 of the neocortex</article-title><source>Cerebral Cortex</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>1485</fpage><lpage>1496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhi027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Okaty</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Region-specific spike-frequency acceleration in layer 5 pyramidal neurons mediated by Kv1 subunits</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>13716</fpage><lpage>13726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2940-08.2008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarusawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Itohara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>NMDAR-regulated dynamics of layer 4 neuronal dendrites during thalamocortical reorganization in neonates</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.02.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molyneaux</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arlotta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Macklis</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Neuronal subtype specification in the cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Neuroscience</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothganger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Warrender</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Trumbo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Aimone</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>N2A: a computational tool for modeling from neurons to algorithms</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neural Circuits</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncir.2014.00001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nathanson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jappelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheeff</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Obata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Short promoters in viral vectors drive selective expression in mammalian inhibitory neurons, but do not restrict activity to specific inhibitory cell-types</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neural Circuits</source><volume>3</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/neuro.04.019.2009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nord</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Attanasio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Phouanenavong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Plajzer-Frick</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoukry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Afzal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennacchio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Rapid and pervasive changes in genome-wide enhancer usage during mammalian development</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>155</volume><fpage>1521</fpage><lpage>1531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.11.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nord</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattabiraman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Genomic perspectives of transcriptional regulation in forebrain development</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>85</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.11.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bortone</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Adesnik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanziani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Gain control by layer six in cortical circuits of vision</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>483</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pennacchio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahituv</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhakar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobrega</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoukry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Minovitsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubchak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Plajzer-Frick</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Val</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Afzal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Couronne</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>In vivo enhancer analysis of human conserved non-coding sequences</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>444</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preibisch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saalfeld</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomancak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Globally optimal stitching of tiled 3D microscopic image acquisitions</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>1463</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadinanos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassiliou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Rosa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>PiggyBac transposon mutagenesis: a tool for cancer gene discovery in mice</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>330</volume><fpage>1104</fpage><lpage>1107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1193004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Symmons</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Uslu</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ettwiller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Spitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Large-scale analysis of the regulatory architecture of the mouse genome with a transposon-associated sensor</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrenberg</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziv</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosse</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Targeting neural circuitry in zebrafish using GAL4 enhancer trapping</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth1033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Thalamocortical interactions</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2012.03.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><chapter-title>Mouse Genetics: Concepts and Applications</chapter-title><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soininen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Henseling</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Tepe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisters-Woike</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gossler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>The mouse Enhancer trap locus 1 (Etl-1): a novel mammalian gene related to Drosophila and yeast transcriptional regulator genes</article-title><source>Mechanisms of Development</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0925-4773(92)90030-n</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanford</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordes</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Gene-trap mutagenesis: past, present and beyond</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Genetics</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>756</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35093548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattox</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Molecular taxonomy of major neuronal classes in the adult mouse forebrain</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn1618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bekkers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Neural coding by two classes of principal cells in the mouse piriform cortex</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>11938</fpage><lpage>11947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3473-06.2006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bekkers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Two layers of synaptic processing by principal neurons in piriform cortex</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>2156</fpage><lpage>2166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5430-10.2011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szabó</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Katarova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Körtvély</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenspan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbán</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Structure and the promoter region of the mouse gene encoding the 67-kD form of glutamic acid decarboxylase</article-title><source>DNA and Cell Biology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>1081</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/dna.1996.15.1081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Szikra</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozorovitskiy</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixiera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cepko</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>A nanobody-based system using fluorescent proteins as scaffolds for cell-specific gene manipulation</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>154</volume><fpage>928</fpage><lpage>939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.07.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhande</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraira</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapan</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Drokhlyansky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Huberman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Regehr</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cepko</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Cell type-specific manipulation with GFP-dependent Cre recombinase</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kvitsiani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kvitsani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fishell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>A resource of Cre driver lines for genetic targeting of GABAergic neurons in cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>71</volume><fpage>995</fpage><lpage>1013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.07.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Neocortical layer 6, a review</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neuroanatomy</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>13</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnana.2010.00013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>van Baren</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonegawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Subregion- and cell type-restricted gene knockout in mouse brain</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>1317</fpage><lpage>1326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81826-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urasaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Efficient transposition of the Tol2 transposable element from a single-copy donor in zebrafish</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>19827</fpage><lpage>19832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0810380105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minovitsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubchak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennacchio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>VISTA enhancer browser--a database of tissue-specific human enhancers</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>D88</fpage><lpage>D92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennacchio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Genomic views of distant-acting enhancers</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>461</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Taher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Girgis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Golonzhka</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>McKinsey</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattabiraman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Silberberg</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Nord</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Phouanenavong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Plajzer-Frick</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoukry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Afzal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriegstein</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ovcharenko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennacchio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>A high-resolution enhancer atlas of the developing telencephalon</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>152</volume><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.12.041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watakabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohsawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Binding and complementary expression patterns of semaphorin 3E and plexin D1 in the mature neocortices of mice and monkeys</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>499</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.21106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watakabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takaji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizukami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohsawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Simultaneous visualization of extrinsic and intrinsic axon collaterals in Golgi-like detail for mouse corticothalamic and corticocortical cells: a double viral infection method</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neural Circuits</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>110</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncir.2014.00110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaszner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Felsenfeld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Insulators: many functions, many mechanisms</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.954702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witter</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Canto</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Couey</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Koganezawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Architecture of spatial circuits in the hippocampal region</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><volume>369</volume><elocation-id>20120515</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2012.0515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodard</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>piggyBac-ing models and new therapeutic strategies</article-title><source>Trends in Biotechnology</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2015.06.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Crise</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Transcription start regions in the human genome are favored targets for MLV integration</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>300</volume><fpage>1749</fpage><lpage>1751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1083413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamawaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Synaptic circuit organization of motor corticothalamic neurons</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>2293</fpage><lpage>2307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4023-14.2015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><name><surname>Model</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heintz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Homologous recombination based modification in Escherichia coli and germline transmission in transgenic mice of a bacterial artificial chromosome</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt0997-859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Generation of transgene-free induced pluripotent mouse stem cells by the piggyBac transposon</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>A hyperactive piggyBac transposase for mammalian applications</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>1531</fpage><lpage>1536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1008322108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zambrowicz</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harendza</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinster</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmiter</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>Analysis of the mouse protamine 1 promoter in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>5071</fpage><lpage>5075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.90.11.5071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeisel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz-Manchado</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Codeluppi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonnerberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>La Manno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jureus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Munguba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Betsholtz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Brain structure</article-title><source>Cell Types in the Mouse Cortex and Hippocampus Revealed by Single-Cell RNA-Seq. Science</source><volume>347</volume><fpage>1138</fpage><lpage>1142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaa1934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschênes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Intracortical axonal projections of lamina VI cells of the primary somatosensory cortex in the rat: a single-cell labeling study</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>6365</fpage><lpage>6379</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Robustly detecting differential expression in RNA sequencing data using observation weights</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>42</volume><elocation-id>e91</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Aller</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambridge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bausen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Herb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawinski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cetin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Osten</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Silencing and un-silencing of tetracycline-controlled genes in neurons</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e533</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zolotukhin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zolotukhin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chesnut</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Summerford</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Samulski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzyczka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Recombinant adeno-associated virus purification using novel methods improves infectious titer and yield</article-title><source>Gene Therapy</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>973</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.gt.3300938</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="article-commentary" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.040</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Liqun</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff5"><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Stanford University</institution>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your work entitled &quot;A Mammalian Enhancer trap Resource for Discovering and Manipulating Neuronal Cell Types&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been favorably evaluated by a Senior editor and two reviewers, one of whom is a member of our Board of Reviewing Editors.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>Although enhancer trap has been used in other genetic model organism for transgene expression (notably <italic>Drosophila</italic>), it has not been widely used in mice despite previous attempts. This is mostly because previous efforts have not produced large enough scale, detailed enough characterization of expression patterns, and strong enough expression levels. Here, Shima and colleagues used the powerful tTA/TRE system and tested basal promoter, construct variants, and methods of transgene production, and produced a large collection of tTA enhancer trap lines that are expressed in highly restricted patterns in the brain. The authors have carefully characterized these expression patterns so that they can be immediately useful for many users. The authors have further followed up a few lines that led them to identify a new cell type in the piriform cortex and access a new subpopulation of thalamus-projecting layer 6 cortical neurons. The data are of high quality and the paper is well written. In addition, the authors are to be complimented for describing many technical details-including optimization procedure and failed experiments, which will be very valuable for the field. Both reviewers are enthusiastic in support the publication, assuming that the authors will address the points raised by the review below:</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) Does the restricted expression of the mCitrine reporter, which is used to characterize enhancer trap for most experiments, caused by enhancer trapping of tTA alone, or could TRE also contribute (i.e., the genomic TRE is partially silenced due to insertion site)? This is important; if the latter is the case, then when TRE transgene is expressed from a virus, the transgenes may be expressed with less specificity because the tTA pattern is actually broader than the bi-cistronic enhancer reporter (I presume that in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>, tTA and TRE are independent transcription units with their own polyAs, which should be added to avoid confusion). The authors should definitely discuss this possibility, and perform additional experiments to test, using highly restricted lines such as those described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8C and F</xref>, to validate that TRE-transgenes from AAV is expressed in the same restricted patterns as mCitrine.</p><p>2) It is unclear whether the authors have mapped their piggyBac insertions to specific genomic regions. Data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref> (local hopping) seems to suggest that authors know the insertion sites. If so, they should report all the insertion sites in a supplemental table, which will be very valuable.</p><p>3) In general, the figures can benefit from more annotations of the anatomical structures, which can help readers to appreciate the specificity and educate them about brain anatomy.</p><p>4) Please be careful in the use of &quot;cell type&quot;.</p><p>5) It can be helpful for the authors to perform in a limited cases retrograde tracing to further define &quot;cell type&quot;. We consider this to be optional, and the authors can determine the number of lines and which sites to perform these experiments.</p><p>6) Please unify anatomical nomenclature in the text and figures to be consistent with a single atlas (Allen Brain Atlas is recommended).</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.13503.041</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) Does the restricted expression of the mCitrine reporter, which is used to characterize enhancer trap for most experiments, caused by enhancer trapping of tTA alone, or could TRE also contribute (i.e., the genomic TRE is partially silenced due to insertion site)? This is important; if the latter is the case, then when TRE transgene is expressed from a virus, the transgenes may be expressed with less specificity because the tTA pattern is actually broader than the bi-cistronic enhancer reporter (I presume that in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>, tTA and TRE are independent transcription units with their own polyAs, which should be added to avoid confusion). The authors should definitely discuss this possibility, and perform additional experiments to test, using highly restricted lines such as those described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8C and F</xref>, to validate that TRE-transgenes from AAV is expressed in the same restricted patterns as mCitrine.</p><p>To answer to this concern, we examined the possibility of TRE silencing using viral reporter injections, as the reviewers suggested. We injected TRE-myristoylated-mCherry-HA virus into several available lines and the results are shown as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3</xref>. We quantified the number of infected cells at the injection sites, the numbers of mCitrine positive neurons at the injection sites, the numbers of double-labeled cells and the number of cells expressing the viral mCherry that did not express mCitrine. The infection rate was 55+/-6% (fraction of mCitrine cells at the site positive for mCherry) and the off target expression rate was 0.7% +/- 0.7% (fraction of mCherry cells negative for mCitrine). The cell counts are provided as supplemental data and described in the first paragraph of the subsection “Transgene expression in tet lines”.</p><p>The specific expression in mCitrine-labeled cells and the minimal off-target expression supports the view that specific reporter expression is due to specific tTA expression rather than TRE silencing in other cells. Occasionally, we observed a few cells without visible mCitrine expression but with viral reporter expression (arrows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3E and F</xref>). Since those “off-target” expressing cells had similar morphologies and anatomical location to those of mCitrine positive cells, it is possible that this “off-target” expression could result from competition over tTA proteins between a single copy TRE of mCitrine in the genome and many copies of TRE from virus, but low levels of TRE silencing cannot be entirely ruled out.</p><p>We also tried two other methods to assess TRE silencing: we attempted to examine colocalization of mCitrine reporter and tTA by dual-color in situ hybridization and by immunohistochemistry. However, neither method gave high-quality tTA signals. From sequencing results, tTA expression levels (TPM) are 5 to 10% of that of mCitrine, perhaps contributing to the difficulty in detection.</p><p>(I presume that in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>, tTA and TRE are independent transcription units with their own polyAs, which should be added to avoid confusion).</p><p>In all the enhancer trap probes tTA and mCitrine share polyA signals. Lentiviral constructs usually use the 3’ LTR as polyA signal and do not contain additional poly A signals because a poly A signal in the middle of the construct would terminate lentiviral RNA genome transcription and thus lower the yield of virus. We used a unidirectional polyA signal from bGH in hsp-tet3 to encode transcripts in the opposite direction, and the polyA signal did not interfere with virus production. We added an explanation of this strategy to the legend of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>.</p><p>2) It is unclear whether the authors have mapped their piggyBac insertions to specific genomic regions. Data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref> (local hopping) seems to suggest that authors know the insertion sites. If so, they should report all the insertion sites in a supplemental table, which will be very valuable.</p><p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Supplementary file 1</xref> has all of the insertion site information. We modified the text (subsection “PB line expression patterns”, first paragraph) to state this more clearly. The insertion site information is also available via the enhancer trap website.</p><p><italic>3) In general, the figures can benefit from more annotations of the anatomical structures, which can help readers to appreciate the specificity and educate them about brain anatomy.</italic> </p><p>Annotations are added to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>.</p><p> <italic>4) Please be careful in the use of &quot;cell type&quot;.</italic> </p><p>As the reviewers correctly point out, a clear consensus on the terms and methods used to define neuronal cell types is still lacking. In response to this issue, we have tried to clarify our terminology, although we of course fall short of solving this enduring problem. Specifically, we have adopted the term “operational cell type” to refer to a population of neurons that appear to share phenotypic features and that can be defined in terms of the intersection of a transgenic strain and a brain region (see subsection “Lentivirus transgenesis”, second paragraph and Discussion, fifth paragraph). We imagine cell types organized in a tree-like taxonomy and note that operational cell types may refer to any node or branch in this tree-like structure. We distinguish this more general term from “atomic” cell types lying at the terminal branches (“leaves”) of this tree of cell types, and which are presumed indivisible in terms of their phenotypic properties. For convenience we use the term “cell type” to refer to the broader concept of “operational cell type.” A major point of the paper is to demonstrate a “proof of principle” in the case of Piriform cortex cells and layer 6 corticothalamic projection neurons, that the more specific populations labeled in our enhancer trap lines can, with further characterization, be shown to be at least closer to “atomic” cell types than previously appreciated for these populations. However, carrying this program forward is going to be a large and presumably distributed effort involving many laboratories and many approaches.</p><p> <italic>5) It can be helpful for the authors to perform in a limited cases retrograde tracing to further define &quot;cell type&quot;. We consider this to be optional, and the authors can determine the number of lines and which sites to perform these experiments.</italic> </p><p>This is related to essential revision point #4. As noted above, further analyses will be needed to examine if the labeled cells are atomic cell types or can be further subdivided based not only on projections, but also based on morphology, physiology and gene expression. In some cases (e.g. LGd neurons projecting to VISp) retrograde labeling is unlikely to reveal further details, while in many other cases such experiments will help clarify whether one or two or more than two closely related atomic cell types are targeted. We feel that further experiments of this sort are beyond the scope of the current paper but they represent a major goal for future work. We have been sharing our lines with several laboratories and hope these and future collaborations will contribute to further characterization of cell types.</p><p> <italic>6) Please unify anatomical nomenclature in the text and figures to be consistent with a single atlas (Allen Brain Atlas is recommended).</italic></p><p>Throughout the text we unified anatomical nomenclature to those of the Allen Brain Atlas.</p></body></sub-article></article>