<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.2" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">72883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.72883</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Tools and Resources</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Developmental Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Developmental single-cell transcriptomics of hypothalamic POMC neurons reveal the genetic trajectories of multiple neuropeptidergic phenotypes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-248849"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5249-0193</contrib-id><email>huiyuz@umich.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-119271"><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>Marcelo</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7500-7771</contrib-id><email>mrubins@dna.uba.ar</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-45820"><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>Malcolm J</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9900-3708</contrib-id><email>mjlow@umich.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Molecular and Integrative Physiology, University of Michigan Medical School</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Ann Arbor</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Instituto de Investigaciones en Ingeniería Genética y Biología Molecular, Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Buenos Aires</named-content></addr-line><country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Departamento de Fisiología, Biología Molecular y Celular, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Buenos Aires</named-content></addr-line><country>Argentina</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>Joel K</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Bronner</surname><given-names>Marianne E</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>California Institute of Technology</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>19</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e72883</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2021-08-07"><day>07</day><month>08</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2022-01-18"><day>18</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a preprint at .</event-desc><date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2021-05-13"><day>13</day><month>05</month><year>2021</year></date><self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443898"/></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2022, Yu et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yu et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-72883-v2.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="figures-pdf" xlink:href="elife-72883-figures-v2.pdf"/><abstract><p>Proopiomelanocortin (POMC) neurons of the hypothalamic arcuate nucleus are essential to regulate food intake and energy balance. However, the ontogenetic transcriptional programs that specify the identity and functioning of these neurons are poorly understood. Here, we use single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) to define the transcriptomes characterizing <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing cells in the developing hypothalamus and translating ribosome affinity purification with RNA-sequencing (TRAP-seq) to analyze the subsequent translatomes of mature POMC neurons. Our data showed that <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing neurons give rise to multiple developmental pathways expressing different levels of <italic>Pomc</italic> and unique combinations of transcription factors. The predominant cluster, featured by high levels of <italic>Pomc</italic> and <italic>Prdm12</italic> transcripts, represents the canonical arcuate POMC neurons. Additional cell clusters expressing medium or low levels of <italic>Pomc</italic> mature into different neuronal phenotypes featured by distinct sets of transcription factors, neuropeptides, processing enzymes, cell surface, and nuclear receptors. We conclude that the genetic programs specifying the identity and differentiation of arcuate POMC neurons are diverse and generate a heterogeneous repertoire of neuronal phenotypes early in development that continue to mature postnatally.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>POMC</kwd><kwd>development</kwd><kwd>single-cell transcriptomics</kwd><kwd>hypothalamus</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Mouse</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000062</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>DK068400</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>Malcolm J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>Marcelo</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Single-cell transcriptomic analyses of hypothalamic POMC neurons performed at seven developmental ages revealed marked cellular heterogeneity and divergent developmental pathways into alternative neuronal phenotypes that lack POMC.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>Proopiomelanocortin (POMC</italic>)-expressing neurons located in the arcuate nucleus of the hypothalamus play an essential role in the regulation of food intake by maintaining a melanocortin-dependent anorexigenic tone. The critical importance of hypothalamic melanocortins is apparent in mice lacking <italic>Pomc</italic> that develop hyperphagia and early-onset extreme obesity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bumaschny et al., 2012</xref>). This phenotype is closely mirrored in humans carrying biallelic null mutations in <italic>POMC</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Krude et al., 1998</xref>). In addition, arcuate POMC neurons release the <italic>Pomc</italic>-encoded opioid peptide β-endorphin, which is critical in mediating normal food intake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Appleyard et al., 2003</xref>) and stress-induced analgesia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Rubinstein et al., 1996</xref>).</p><p>Postmitotic POMC neurons acquire their phenotypic identity in the developing hypothalamus days earlier than any other peptidergic neurons born in the presumptive arcuate nucleus (e.g. NPY/AGRP, GHRH, SST, KISSPEPTIN). <italic>Pomc</italic> mRNA is initially observed in the tuberal portion of the prospective mouse hypothalamus of E10.5 embryos, following the concurrent advent of the essential transcription factors (TFs) ISL1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Nasif et al., 2015</xref>), NKX2-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Orquera et al., 2019</xref>), and PRDM12 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hael et al., 2020</xref>) that act together in a combinatorial manner. In fact, the early ablation of either <italic>Isl1</italic>, <italic>Nkx2-1</italic>, or <italic>Prdm12</italic> disrupts the onset of hypothalamic <italic>Pomc</italic> expression in conditional mutant mouse embryos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Nasif et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Orquera et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hael et al., 2020</xref>). Given that the number of arcuate neurons co-expressing <italic>Nkx2-1</italic>, <italic>Isl1</italic>, and <italic>Prdm12</italic> greatly exceeds that of POMC neurons in this area, it is expected that additional and still unknown TFs integrate a core regulatory complex completing the genetic program that specifies the identity of POMC neurons.</p><p>Other molecular markers of arcuate POMC neurons such as transporters, receptors, channels, and co-transmitters exhibit great variability indicating that a heterogeneous pool of diverse subpopulations of these neurons are involved in multiple circuits and functions. In fact, previous studies have suggested that subsets of arcuate <italic>Pomc-</italic>expressing neurons may act as precursors of terminally differentiated neurons of alternative neuropeptidergic phenotypes such as NPY/AGRP and KISSPEPTIN/NEUROKININ-B/DYNORPHIN (KNDY) neurons in the adult hypothalamus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Padilla et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sanz et al., 2015</xref>). Initial attempts to characterize the transcriptome of adult POMC neurons at the single-cell level confirmed the heterogeneous nature of arcuate POMC neurons and revealed the existence of distinct clusters including those co-expressing the aforementioned neuropeptide genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Campbell et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Chen et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lam et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Huisman et al., 2020</xref>). However, the molecular signatures of the various hypothalamic <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing lineages are still lacking.</p><p>Here, we track the origin and maturation of arcuate POMC neurons in the developing and early postnatal hypothalamus by performing single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) transcriptomics of fluorescently labeled cells taken from <italic>Pomc-TdDiscomaRed-Sv40PolyA</italic> (<italic>Pomc-TdDsRed</italic>) transgenic mice at different embryonic (E11.5, E13.5, E15.5, and E17.5) and early postnatal (P5 and P12) ages. Our data indicate that POMC neurons give rise to distinct transcriptional trajectories and show that a heterogeneous population of <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing neurons is established early in the developing arcuate nucleus. Combining translating ribosome affinity purification with RNA-sequencing (TRAP-seq) of <italic>Pomc-eGFPL10a</italic> transgenic mice at P12 and P60, we identified transcriptional programs that emerge from distinct populations of early embryonic POMC neurons that later mature into fully functional POMC neurons. We believe that these datasets provide a valuable resource for comprehensively understanding the genetic bases underlying the ontogeny and development of POMC neurons as well as for the rational design of further functional studies of brain circuits involving POMC neurons.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Cluster analysis of gene expression in POMC positive hypothalamic cells integrated across six development ages</title><p>We captured the single-cell transcriptomes of hypothalamic <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing cells at four embryonic days (E11.5, E13.5, E15.5, and E17.5) and two early postnatal days (P5 and P12) when the maturing neurons already develop axons and innervate key target nuclei distal to the Arc (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bouret, 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bouret et al., 2004b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bouret et al., 2012</xref>). Medial basal hypothalami from mice that express the reporter transgene <italic>Pomc-TdDsRed</italic> selectively in POMC cells were pooled from multiple embryos or postnatal pups at the indicated ages. Dissociated single-cell suspensions were sorted for DsRed fluorescence and used for library preparation with the 10× Genomics platform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). After a rigorous screening procedure to remove substandard scRNA-seq data (see Materials and methods), we used a combination of computational platforms to analyze the transcriptomes of 13,962 cells that had <italic>Pomc</italic> counts of ≥1 unique molecular identifiers (UMIs).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Single-cell sequencing of <italic>Pomc<sup>DsRed</sup></italic> cells from developing mouse hypothalami at E11.5, E13.5, E15.5, E17.5, P5, and P12 reveals eight distinct neuronal clusters and three non-neuronal clusters.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic diagram showing the overall experimental procedure. (<bold>B</bold>) UMAP (Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection) plot showing the distribution of major cell clusters and their corresponding numbers of cells at each developmental stage. (<bold>C</bold>) Violin plots showing the expression of three signature genes and <italic>Pomc</italic> for each cluster. (<bold>D</bold>) UMAP plots showing the enrichment of feature genes in each cluster. Genes representing each cluster were colored and highlighted to show the cluster-specific enrichment. The color intensity corresponds to the normalized gene expression from Seurat analysis, where gene expression for each cell was normalized by the total expression, multiplied by a scale factor of 10,000, and then log-transformed. VLMC, vascular leptomeningeal cell.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata1"><label>Figure 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Average gene expression obtained from the Seurat analysis of each of the 11 proopiomelanocortin (<italic>Pomc</italic>) clusters integrated across all six developmental stages (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig1-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata2"><label>Figure 1—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Feature genes that define each of the 11 proopiomelanocortin (<italic>Pomc</italic>) clusters (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>) integrated across all six developmental stages.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig1-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Heatmap showing the expression of the top 30 marker genes defining each cluster from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>.</title><p>M: microglia; V: vascular and leptomeningeal cells; A: astrocytes.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig1-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Analysis of proopiomelanocortin (POMC) cells with <italic>DsRed</italic> transcripts reveals nine distinct cell clusters.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) plot showing the distribution of major cell clusters. (<bold>B</bold>) Violin plots showing signature gene expression in each cell type. Three feature genes were chosen to represent each cell type. (<bold>C</bold>) UMAP plots showing the enrichment of feature genes in each cluster. Genes representative of each cluster were colored and highlighted to show the cluster-specific enrichment. The color intensity corresponds to the normalized gene expression from Seurat analysis. (<bold>D</bold>) Identification of similar cell clusters between POMC cells with <italic>DsRed</italic> transcripts and POMC cell clusters. Red: POMC cell clusters are from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>. Blue: POMC cells with <italic>DsRed</italic> transcripts from <bold>A-F</bold>. (<bold>E</bold>) Venn diagram showing the number of cells expressing <italic>Pomc</italic> transcripts, <italic>DsRed</italic> transcripts or both <italic>Pomc</italic> and <italic>DsRed</italic> transcripts. Pie chart showing the percentage of POMC cells expressing <italic>DsRed</italic> transcripts at each developmental stage. (<bold>F</bold>) Vertical bar-chart showing the percentage of cells with <italic>DsRed</italic> transcripts projected to corresponding POMC cell clusters. VLMC, vascular and leptomeningeal cell.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s2sdata1"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Average gene expression obtained from the Seurat analysis of each of the nine DsRed clusters integrated across all six developmental stages (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig1-figsupp2-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig1-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Overview of cell clusters from proopiomelanocortin (POMC) cells with <italic>DsRed</italic> transcripts.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) plot showing the distribution of major cell clusters and their corresponding number of cells from each developmental stage. (<bold>B</bold>) UMAP plots showing the number of cells at each developmental stage. (<bold>C</bold>) UMAP plots showing the splitting of clusters by developmental stages.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s3sdata1"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Feature genes that define each of the nine DsRed clusters integrated across all six developmental stages (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig1-figsupp3-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig1-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>A Seurat analysis of all cells integrated across the six time points revealed 11 distinct cell clusters projected onto a UMAP plot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). The same data are represented in a heatmap corresponding to the top 30 expressed genes per cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>). Clusters 1–8 (10,828 cells) were all highly enriched for a panel of three neuronal marker gene transcripts. The embedded table in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref> lists the number of neurons of each cluster at each developmental age. The other three clusters (3134 cells) were enriched in transcripts characteristic of either microglia, vascular leptomeningeal cells (VLMC), or astrocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). Gene ontology analyses for biological processes further confirmed the neuronal or non-neuronal identities of the 11 individual clusters (data not shown).</p><p>By definition, all cells in the neuronal and non-neuronal clusters contained <italic>Pomc</italic> transcripts (UMI ≥1), however there were significant differences in the average expression levels per cluster, ranging from 1.3 to 33.8 [exp(<italic>log Normalized</italic> counts) –1]. Nomenclature of the eight neuronal clusters is based on a combination of relatively high (&gt;20), medium (5–20), or low (&lt;5) <italic>Pomc</italic> levels and high expression of one differential key feature gene as follows: no. 1, <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic>; no. 2 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic>; no. 3, <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic>; no. 4, <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic>; no. 5, <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)<italic>/</italic></sup><italic>Tac2</italic>; no. 6, <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Dlx5</italic>; no. 7, <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Prdm13</italic>; and no. 8, <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Pitx2</italic>. The cluster distribution and relative expression of those feature genes are represented by individual UMAP plots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). Average expression levels of all genes, including <italic>Pomc</italic>, in the 11 clusters and complete lists of all feature genes that define the individual clusters are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata1">Figure 1—source data 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata2">Figure 1—source data 2</xref>, respectively.</p><p>In order to validate our experimental approach of isolating <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing cells from the developing hypothalamus by fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) for the transgenic surrogate marker <italic>Pomc-TdDsRed</italic>, we performed an independent unsupervised cluster analysis of the transcriptomes from the 5724 cells that had <italic>DsRed</italic> counts of ≥1 UMI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A-C</xref> and ). A projection analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2D-F</xref>) of the differentially expressed feature genes defined nine DsRed clusterswhich closely corresponded to 9 of the 11 clusters based on <italic>Pomc</italic> counts of ≥1 UMI. The two exceptions were the smallest clusters 7. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Prdm13</italic> and astrocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3D-F</xref>). Furthermore, the number of cells at each developmental age from the corresponding neuronal clusters was remarkably similar in the <italic>Pomc</italic> UMI ≥ 1 dataset compared to the <italic>DsRed</italic> UMI ≥ 1 dataset (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A</xref>). The different population of DsRed fluorescent sorted cells showing UMI ≥ 1 for <italic>Pomc</italic> (13,962) or <italic>DsRed</italic> (5724) may be due to differential half-lives of the fluorescent protein DSRED used during cell sorting and its transcript used for barcoding the RNA-seq libraries.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Temporal gene expression analysis of the eight neuronal clusters at individual developmental stages</title><p>Next, we analyzed temporal gene expression patterns for each of the eight neuronal clusters at the six distinct developmental ages (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata1">Figure 2—source data 1</xref>). The progressive changes in feature genes across time are responsible for the observed within cluster heterogeneity on the heatmap in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>.</p><sec id="s2-2-1"><title>Cluster 1</title><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> cells were the most abundant among the eight neuronal clusters and consistently had the highest levels of <italic>Pomc</italic> expression at all six developmental ages. We consider them to be the cell lineage that matures into the canonical POMC neurons in the adult hypothalamus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A–C</xref>). Other feature genes included a set of four TFs known to be critical for the initiation and/or maintenance of Arc <italic>Pomc</italic> expression, <italic>Isl1</italic>, <italic>Nkx2-1</italic>, <italic>Prdm12</italic>, and <italic>Tbx3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Nasif et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Orquera et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Quarta et al., 2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hael et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). They were expressed in similar developmental patterns to each other, with the exception of <italic>Tbx3</italic> that was significantly expressed only from day E15.5. Notably, there was a lack of the pituitary-specific <italic>Tbx19</italic> TF, confirming that no pituitary tissue was included in the hypothalamic dissections. Two homologues of the <italic>Drosophila sine oculus</italic> homeobox gene, <italic>Six3</italic> and <italic>Six6,</italic> which have not been described previously in the context of Arc POMC neuron development, were also expressed robustly at all six time points (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). Co-expression of their mRNAs with <italic>Pomc</italic> by RNAScope at ages E12.5 and E16.5 confirmed the scRNA-seq analysis, although the two TFs were expressed in additional hypothalamic domains and the pituitary gland (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). <italic>Vim1</italic>, <italic>Sox1</italic>, -<italic>2, -3</italic>, and -<italic>14,</italic> and <italic>Myc</italic>, whose expression is typically associated with neuronal precursors or immature neurons, tended to have higher expression at the earlier embryonic ages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). The nuclear receptor gene <italic>Nr5a1</italic>, also known as steroidogenic factor 1 (<italic>Sf1</italic>), was a key feature gene expressed almost exclusively at age E11.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>), but only minimally expressed at later embryonic time points when NR5A1 is critically involved in the development of the hypothalamic ventromedial nucleus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Ikeda et al., 1995</xref>). This differential spatio-temporal presence of NR5A1 within or outside POMC neurons was confirmed by immunofluorescence on hypothalamic sections taken from E11.5 and E17.5 mouse embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Interestingly, <italic>Nr5a1</italic>, <italic>Nr0b1</italic> (<italic>Dax1</italic>), and <italic>Shh</italic> transcripts were also present in cluster 1 at the two earliest ages, and are factors known to interact with the <italic>Wnt/</italic>β-catenin signaling pathway in early cell fate determination in the adrenal and pituitary glands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Luo et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Meeks et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Mizusaki et al., 2003</xref>). A combination of pseudotime and gene ontology analyses for the top expressed genes (Log2FoldChange &gt; 0.25, p &lt; 0.05) in cluster 1 revealed that the genes expressed at the beginning of pseudotime function in the organization of cell projections, axonogenesis, and the regulation of cellular component size, whereas genes expressed at the middle and end of the pseudotime function are related to neuron maturation and neuron-specified functions such as the formation of myelin sheath and regulation of synaptic vesicle cycling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Temporal gene expression patterns of the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> cluster and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> clusters.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) Violin plots showing the expression of signature genes at each developmental stage in the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> cluster and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> cluster, respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) Fluorescence in situ hybridization showing the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Six6</italic> (red), the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Six3</italic> (red) at indicated developmental stages. Immunofluorescence showing the co-localization TDTOMATO (red) NR5A1 (green) at the indicated developmental stages. (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>F</bold>) Heatmaps showing the gene ontology analysis based on the top marker genes in the order of pseudotime in <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> cluster and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> cluster, respectively. (<bold>E</bold>) Fluorescence in situ hybridization showing the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Ebf1</italic> (red) at E11.5. (<bold>G</bold>) Reclustering cells from the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> cluster reveals two subclusters denoted as 2–1 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup> and 2–2 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup>. Violin plots showing the signature gene expression in 2–1 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup> and 2–2 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup> clusters. Insets are magnified views of the indicated boxes. Arrows indicate co-expressing neurons in the merged panels. Scale bar: 50 µm. Image orientation: left, posterior(P); right, anterior(A). RP: Rathke’s pouch; Pit: pituitary gland. Arc: arcuate nucleus; VMH: ventromedial hypothalamus; V: ventricular zone; Mes: mesenchyme.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata1"><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Average gene expression obtained from the Seurat analysis of six developmental stages of each cluster (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, and their linked <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig2-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata2"><label>Figure 2—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Average gene expression obtained from the Seurat analysis of the two subclusters 3–1 and 3–2 derived from reclustering of cluster 3.</title><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic> and the two subclusters 2–1 and 2–2 derived from reclustering of cluster 2. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2G</xref>, cluster 2 and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>, cluster 3).</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig2-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata3"><label>Figure 2—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Feature genes that define each of the two subclusters 3–1 and 3–2 derived from reclustering of cluster 3.</title><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic> and the two subclusters 2–1 and 2–2 derived from reclustering of cluster 2. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1 Ebf1</italic> (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2G</xref>, cluster 2 and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>, cluster 3).</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig2-data3-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Fluorescence in situ hybridization showing the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Ebf1</italic> (red) at E13.5 (<bold>A</bold>) and at E17.5 (<bold>B</bold>) and the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Pou4f1</italic> (red) at E13.5 (<bold>C</bold>) and at E17.5 (<bold>D</bold>), respectively.</title><p>Scale bar: 50 µm. Image orientation: left, posterior (P); right, anterior (A); Pit: pituitary gland; Mes: mesenchyme.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig2-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Temporal gene expression patterns of the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Pitx2</italic> clusters.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Violin plots showing the expression of signature genes in the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic> cluster at each developmental stage. (<bold>B</bold>) Fluorescence in situ hybridization showing the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Nr4a2</italic> (red). (<bold>C</bold>) Reclustering cells from the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic> cluster reveals two subclusters denoted as 3–1 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup> and 3–2 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup> clusters. Violin plot showing the signature gene expression in 3–1 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup> and 3–2 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup> clusters. (<bold>D</bold>) Violin plots showing the expression of signature genes at each developmental stage in the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Pitx2</italic> cluster. (<bold>E</bold>) Fluorescence in situ hybridization showing the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Pitx2</italic> (red). Scale bar: 50 µm. Insets are magnified views of the indicated boxes. Arrows indicate co-expressing neurons in the merged panels. Scale bar: 50 µm. Image orientation: left, posterior (P); right, anterior (A). RP: Rathke’s pouch; Pit: pituitary gland.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig2-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-2-2"><title>Cluster 2</title><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> neurons made up the second highest abundance cluster of POMC neurons, particularly at E11.5 and E13.5. After these time points, the fraction of all neurons constituting cluster 2 dropped by approximately two-thirds from ages E15.5 through P12. In contrast, the number of neurons in clusters 3–8 increased over time with peaks at different embryonic ages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Cluster 2 neurons, on average, had medium levels of <italic>Pomc</italic> transcripts that were divided distinctly from their lowest at ages E11.5–E13.5 to highest at later embryonic and postnatal ages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata1">Figure 2—source data 1</xref>). Major cluster 2 feature markers included members of the non-basic helix-loop-helix early B-cell TF family EBF (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata2">Figure 1—source data 2</xref>). <italic>Ebf1</italic> is typically co-expressed with either <italic>Ebf2</italic> or <italic>Ebf3</italic> and pairs of these factors were shared not only in cluster 2, but also in clusters 3 and 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>). Dual RNAScope in situ hybridization showed overlapping co-expression of <italic>Ebf1</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic> mRNAs in the ventricular zone of the developing hypothalamus at an early embryonic stage (E11.5) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>). However, transcript levels of <italic>Ebf1</italic> are much lower than what was found in other areas of the same sections, such as the mesenchyme (MES) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>). <italic>Ebf1</italic> mRNA was also detected in <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing cells at E13.5, and then was barely detectable at E17.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A and B</xref>). A similar expression pattern was found with another cluster 2 featured gene, <italic>Pou4f1 (POU Class 4 Homeobox 1</italic>). Dual RNAScope in situ hybridization confirmed the overlap of <italic>Pou4f1</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic> mRNAs at E13.5, but not at E17.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1C and D</xref>). These results, together, suggest that <italic>Pomc</italic> mRNA levels peak only after expression of both <italic>Ebf1</italic> and <italic>Pou4f1</italic> decrease. Two other prominent feature genes in cluster 2 were <italic>Crabp1</italic> and <italic>Crabp2</italic>, which encode cellular retinoic acid binding proteins. A majority of the marker genes for cluster 2 are predicted to be expressed at the beginning of pseudotime and the main functions are associated with the maintenance of basic cell biological processes such as nucleosome organization, axonogenesis, microtubule transport, and intracellular transport (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>). The genes ordered in the middle and end of pseudotime function for the regulation of synapse structure and activities.</p><p>Visual examination of the UMAP plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref> suggested that cluster 2 was composed of two compartments, one with high and one with low <italic>Pomc</italic> abundance. Unsupervised reclustering of the differentially expressed genes from integrated cluster 2 confirmed the existence of two subclusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2G</xref>). Subcluster 2–1 contained two-thirds of the neurons, which were <italic>POMC</italic><sup>(high)</sup> whereas subcluster 2–2 contained the other one-third of cluster 2 neurons, which in contrast, were <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>, subcluster 2–2 contains cells mainly from the early developmental stages E11.5 to E15.5, whereas, subcluster 2–1 contains cells from E17.5 to P12. Consistently, known activating TFs for <italic>Pomc</italic> expression such as <italic>Nkx2-1</italic>, <italic>Isl1</italic>, and <italic>Tbx3</italic> were limited to subcluster 2–1 while relatively high levels of <italic>Ebf</italic> and <italic>Crabp</italic> transcripts were characteristic of subcluster 2–2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata2">Figure 2—source data 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata3">Figure 2—source data 3</xref>). Another distinctive feature of cells in cluster 2 (both subclusters) is the absence of <italic>Prdm12</italic> transcripts, one main component of cluster 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A and D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-3"><title>Cluster 3</title><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic> neurons displayed high expression of its major feature gene <italic>Nr4a2</italic> (Nuclear Receptor Subfamily 4 Group A Member 2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>). <italic>Nr4a2</italic> mRNA was also expressed at relatively high levels in clusters 2. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> and 8. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Pitx2. Nr4a2</italic> (<italic>Nurr1</italic>) has been implicated in the regulation of <italic>Pomc</italic> expression in the pituitary corticotropic cell line AtT20 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kovalovsky et al., 2002</xref>). Furthermore, <italic>Nr4a2</italic> is a pioneer transcriptional regulator important for the differentiation and maintenance of meso-diencephalic dopaminergic (mdDA) neurons during development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Perlmann and Wallén-Mackenzie, 2004</xref>). It is crucial for expression of a set of genes including <italic>Slc6a3</italic> (plasma membrane dopamine transporter, DAT), <italic>Slc18a2</italic> (synaptic vesicular monoamine transporter, VMAT), <italic>Th</italic> (tyrosine hydroxylase), <italic>Foxa1</italic> and <italic>Foxa2</italic> (forkhead family TFs), and <italic>Drd2</italic> (dopamine receptor 2) that together define the dopaminergic neuronal phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Hong et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jankovic et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Saucedo-Cardenas et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smits et al., 2003</xref>). An additional key factor involved in the generation and maintenance of mdDA neurons, <italic>Lmx1a</italic> (Lim- and homeodomain factor 1a) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Andersson et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Hong et al., 2014</xref>), was also a key feature gene of clusters 3 and 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2A and D</xref>) suggesting that POMC and DA neurons share at least part of their genetic differentiation programs.</p><p>Similar to cluster 2, reclustering of the differentially expressed genes from cluster 3 revealed two subclusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2C</xref>). Subcluster 3–1 constituted 72% of the main cluster 3 and was characterized by <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup> neurons with strong <italic>Nr4a2</italic> expression at all developmental ages. Feature genes for subcluster 3–1 also included <italic>Lmx1a</italic>, <italic>Slc6a3</italic>, <italic>Slc18a2, Foxa2</italic>, and <italic>Th</italic>, all feature genes for developmental subclusters E13.5–10 and E15.5–11 derived from cluster 3 indicating that a fraction of cluster 3 neurons were dopaminergic and existed transiently during a 3-day developmental window (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata2">Figure 1—source data 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata1">Figure 2—source data 1</xref>). In contrast, subcluster 3–2 neurons were <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup> together with characteristic expression of the known <italic>Pomc</italic> transcriptional activator genes and were present only at ages P5 and P12. The dissociation of high <italic>Pomc</italic> expression with low <italic>Nr4a2</italic> expression in subcluster 3–2 suggests that the latter is not necessary for hypothalamic <italic>Pomc</italic> expression, unlike its role in pituitary corticotrophs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Murphy and Conneely, 1997</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-4"><title>Cluster 8</title><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Pitx2</italic> is more closely related to clusters 2. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> and 3. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic> than to any of the others (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2D</xref>). In addition to <italic>Pitx2,</italic> major feature genes were <italic>Barhl1, Foxa1, Foxp2, Lmx1a/b,</italic> and <italic>Tac1</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata2">Figure 1—source data 2</xref>). Intriguingly, virtually all of the top cluster 8 defining genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata2">Figure 1—source data 2</xref>) are identical to those that characterize both the mesencephalic dopamine neurons and glutamatergic, non-dopaminergic, subthalamic nucleus neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Kee et al., 2017</xref>). Dual RNAscope in situ hybridization for <italic>Pitx2</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic> showed limited overlap at E12.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2E</xref>). Cluster 8 is the only cluster with the neuropeptide <italic>Cck</italic> as a feature gene at developmental ages P5 and P12 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata1">Figure 1—source data 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata1">Figure 2—source data 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-5"><title>Cluster 4</title><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> cells uniquely expressed <italic>Otp</italic> at all developmental ages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). <italic>Pomc</italic> expression was moderate at E11.5 and then dropped to consistently lower levels through age P12 despite continued expression of <italic>Isl1, Nkx2-1,</italic> and <italic>Tbx3</italic>. Interestingly, expression of the other transcriptional modulator important for <italic>Pomc</italic> expression, <italic>Prdm12</italic>, was detected only at E11.5. Other characteristic features of cluster 4 were increasing gradients of <italic>Agrp, Npy,</italic> and <italic>Calcr</italic> expression over the course of development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). Minimal co-expression of <italic>Pomc</italic> and <italic>Npy</italic> was confirmed by fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) at age E15.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). <italic>Sst</italic> was highly expressed in this cluster at ages E13.5, P5, and P12 with a temporary drop off at E15.5 and E17.5. Altogether, these patterns of gene expression indicate that a subpopulation of POMC neurons expressing <italic>Otp</italic> further differentiates into AGRP/NPY neurons as suggested previously by studies based on transgenic lineage tracing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Padilla et al., 2010</xref>). Most of the top enriched genes of this cluster are expressed in the middle and end portions of pseudotime prediction highlighting functions such as regulation of inhibitory synapses, ribosomal biogenesis, and synaptic vesicle cytoskeletal transport (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). A map of gene expression in individual cells within the cluster 4 UMAP plot demonstrated that <italic>Npy</italic> was expressed in virtually all <italic>Agrp</italic> neurons, but few <italic>Sst</italic> neurons. <italic>Sst</italic> and <italic>Agrp</italic> neurons were essentially separate cell populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>). The GABAergic marker <italic>Slc32a1</italic> encoding the vesicular inhibitory amino acid transporter was expressed at the second highest level in cluster 4 relative to all other clusters (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata1">Figure 1—source data 1</xref>), consistent with the GABAergic phenotype of mature AGRP/NPY neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Temporal gene expression patterns of the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> cluster and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Tac2</italic> cluster.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold> and <bold>E</bold>) Violin plots showing the expression of signature genes at each developmental stage in <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> cluster and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Tac2</italic> cluster, respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) Fluorescence in situ hybridization showing the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Npy</italic> (red) at E15.5. (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>G</bold>) Heatmaps showing the gene ontology analysis based on the top marker genes in the order of pseudotime in <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> cluster and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Tac2</italic> cluster, respectively. (<bold>D</bold>) Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) plots showing cells in the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> cluster expressing <italic>Sst</italic>, <italic>Agrp</italic>, <italic>Npy</italic>, <italic>Sst</italic>/<italic>Agrp</italic>, <italic>Sst</italic>/ <italic>Npy,</italic> or <italic>Agrp/Npy</italic>. Cells expressing <italic>Sst</italic> and cells expressing both <italic>Agrp</italic>/<italic>Npy</italic> are from two distinct cell populations. (<bold>F</bold>) Fluorescence in situ hybridization showing the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Tac2</italic> (red), the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Tacr3</italic> (red), and the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Sox14</italic> (red) at the indicated developmental stages. Immunofluorescence showing the co-localization of TDTOMATO (red) and ESR1 (green) at the indicated developmental stages. Insets are magnified views of the indicated boxes. Arrows indicate co-expressing neurons in the merged panels. Scale bar: 50 µm. Image orientation: left, posterior; right, anterior; Pit: pituitary gland, RP: Rathke’s pouch.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Distribution of GABAergic and glutamatergic neurons in POMC<sup>DsRed</sup> cell clusters.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) plots showing the distribution of cells with <italic>Gad1</italic> or <italic>Vglut2</italic> gene expression. (<bold>B</bold>) Violin plots showing expression of the GABAergic or glutamatergic marker genes in each neuronal cluster.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig3-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Temporal gene expression patterns of the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Dlx5</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup>/<italic>Prdm13</italic> clusters.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Violin plots showing the expression of signature genes at each developmental stage in the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Dlx5</italic> cluster. (<bold>B</bold>) Fluorescence in situ hybridization showing the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Dlx5</italic> (red). (<bold>C</bold>) Violin plots showing the expression of signature genes at each developmental stage in the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Prdm13</italic> cluster. (<bold>D</bold>) Fluorescence in situ hybridization showing the co-localization of <italic>Pomc</italic> (green) and <italic>Prdm13</italic> (red). Insets are magnified views of the indicated boxes. Arrows indicate co-expressing neurons in the merged panels. Scale bar: 50 µm. Image orientation: left, posterior; right, anterior; Pit: pituitary gland.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig3-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-2-6"><title>Cluster 5</title><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Tac2</italic> represents a distinct neuronal population from cluster 1 in its patterns of TFs associated with the development of mature POMC neurons and its low level of <italic>Pomc</italic> transcripts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). In particular, <italic>Isl1</italic> was highly expressed only at E11.5 and <italic>Prdm12</italic> at E11.5 and E13.5 in cluster 5. Starting from E15.5 through P12 there was a gradual onset of expression for a set of genes including <italic>Tac2, Ar, Esr1, Tacr3, Prlr, Pdyn,</italic> and <italic>Kiss1/Gm28040</italic> isoforms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). Confirmations of co-expression for <italic>Pomc</italic> with either <italic>Tac2, Tacr3</italic> and <italic>Sox14</italic> or TDTOMATO with ESR1 at several embryonic ages are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>. Interestingly, <italic>Sox14</italic> has been reported to be necessary for expression of <italic>Kiss1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Huisman et al., 2019</xref>). Most of the top enriched genes for this cluster are inferred to be expressed at the middle to end portions of the pseudotime prediction, and their functions are related to reproduction, synapse assembly/organization, pre/post-synaptic specialization, and neuron migration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3G</xref>). Taken together, this ensemble of genes is characteristic of adult Arc KNDY neurons that play an essential role in the control of reproductive physiology. A previous publication based on transgene lineage tracing also concluded that a significant subpopulation of KNDY neurons is derived from POMC progenitor cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sanz et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>A prominent and unique characteristic of cluster 6. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)<italic>/</italic></sup><italic>Dlx5</italic> neurons was the expression of members of the <italic>Dlx</italic> family of homeobox TFs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2A and B</xref>). The six family members are usually expressed in three linked pairs of isoforms: 1 and 2, 3 and 4, or 5 and 6. Cluster 6 was enriched in <italic>Dlx1/2,</italic> and <italic>Dlx5/6</italic> together with <italic>Dlxos1</italic>. The <italic>Dlx1/2</italic> pair is known to activate expression of <italic>Ghrh</italic> in the mouse Arc (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2018</xref>). However, there were no transcripts for <italic>Ghrh</italic> expressed in cluster 6 or any of the other <italic>Pomc</italic> neuronal clusters suggesting that <italic>Dlx1/2</italic> are not sufficient to induce <italic>Ghrh</italic> expression. Moreover, it has been recently shown that <italic>Dlx1/2</italic> binding to <italic>Otp</italic> regulatory elements inhibits OTP production, subsequently reducing downstream <italic>Agrp</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2018</xref>). Cluster 6 had the highest expression of the opioid prepronociceptin (<italic>Pnoc</italic>) compared to the other integrated clusters, but low levels of preprodynorphin (<italic>Pdyn</italic>), similar to cluster 5 KNDY neurons.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-7"><title>Cluster 6</title><p>It had the highest <italic>Gad1</italic>, <italic>Gad2,</italic> and <italic>Slc32a1</italic> (<italic>Vgat,</italic> vesicular inhibitory amino acid transporter) expression density of all clusters with virtually no <italic>Slc17a6</italic> (<italic>Vglut2,</italic> vesicular glutamate transporter 2) expression, suggesting that these differentiating neurons were exclusively GABAergic. A comparison of GABAergic and glutamatergic markers among the eight neuronal clusters is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>. Cluster 4 neurons were also uniformly GABAergic. Cluster 1 neurons contained a mixture of glutamatergic and GABAergic markers with the exception of undetectable <italic>Slc32a1</italic>. However, they did express low levels of <italic>Slc18a2</italic> (<italic>Vmat2</italic>, vesicular monoamine transporter 2), which possibly functions as an alternative vesicular GABA transporter in some dopamine neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">German et al., 2015</xref>). This combination of mixed glutamatergic and GABAergic features in cluster 1 is characteristic of postnatal POMC neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Wittmann et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jones et al., 2019</xref>) and was also present to a limited extent in cluster 2. The remaining neuronal clusters 3, 5, 7, and 8 were all uniformly glutamatergic.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-8"><title>Cluster 7</title><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Prdm13</italic> contained the smallest number of cells among the eight neuronal clusters, and the cells were primarily limited to developmental ages E13.5–E17.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Feature genes included <italic>Prdm13, Nr5a1, Adcypap1, Cnr1, Fam19a1, Rbp1,</italic> and <italic>Pdyn</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2C</xref>). <italic>Prdm13</italic> was reported recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chen et al., 2020</xref>) to be highly expressed in E15.5 POMC cells.</p><p>We further analyzed all of the neurons and non-neuronal cells by reclustering them based on their individual developmental ages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>) rather than for their gene expression profiles integrated across all ages. Average gene expression levels for each of these developmental subclusters are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata1">Figure 4—source data 1</xref> and the feature genes defining the developmental subclusters are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata2">Figure 4—source data 2</xref>. Based on these data, it was then possible to trace the temporal continuity between developmental subclusters from age E11.5 to P12 relative to the original integrated cell cluster identities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). These data are important because they connected the dynamic nature of gene expression profiles at each embryonic stage leading to the eventual transcriptomes present in the postnatal time points.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) plots showing the distribution of major cell clusters at each developmental stage.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) E11.5, (<bold>B</bold>) E13.5, (<bold>C</bold>) E15.5, (<bold>D</bold>) E17.5, (<bold>E</bold>) P5, and (<bold>F</bold>) P12. The developmental subclusters derived from each primary cluster are colored to corresponding cells in the UMAP plot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata1"><label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Average gene expression obtained from the Seurat analysis of each subcluster unique to the six developmental stages (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig4-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata2"><label>Figure 4—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Feature genes that define each subcluster at each of the six developmental stages (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig4-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>POMC<sup>DsRed</sup> developmental cell subclusters shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> are projected to the original integrated cell clusters from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>.</title><p>The projections were based on the Seurat analysis and manual comparisons of feature genes in each subcluster (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata2">Figure 1—source data 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata2">Figure 4—source data 2</xref>). The clusters from individual stages leading to the same final integrated clusters are labeled with the same color. Question marks indicate uncertainties of individual projections.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig4-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Overview of neuropeptide, secretory granule, and processing enzyme gene expression patterns across clusters and developmental ages.</title><p>The size of dots indicates the percentage of cells expressing the specific transcripts. The color intensity corresponds to the levels of normalized gene expression.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig4-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Overview of G-protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) gene expression patterns across clusters and developmental ages.</title><p>The size of dots indicates the percentage of cells expressing the specific transcripts. The color intensity corresponds to the levels of normalized gene expression. The list of genes was acquired from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/targets.jsp">https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/targets.jsp</ext-link> and Gene Ontology (GO:0005576).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig4-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Comparison of transcriptional profiles for neuropeptides, neuropeptide processing enzymes, neuroendocrine secretory proteins, and GPCRs in the eight neuronal POMC clusters at each developmental age</title><p>We identified 19 unique neuropeptide prohormone genes that were clearly differentially expressed features in at least one of the neuronal clusters at one or more developmental ages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata1">Figure 2—source data 1</xref>). In addition to the neuropeptide genes already mentioned as characteristic features of certain clusters, additional neuropeptides were featured in other clusters primarily at postnatal ages P5 and P12. Notable examples are <italic>Gal, Tac1, Adcyap1, Cartpt,</italic> and <italic>Pthlh</italic>. Unlike the mosaic of neuropeptide gene expression profiles across clusters and developmental ages, the neuroendocrine secretory proteins, characteristic of dense core granules, were expressed ubiquitously in all eight neuronal clusters with similar gradients across all developmental ages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>). These included members of the chromogranin (<italic>Chga</italic> and <italic>Chgb</italic>) and secretogranin (<italic>Scg2, Scg3,</italic> and <italic>Scg5</italic>) families. Among the prohormone processing enzymes, <italic>Pcsk1</italic> was prominently expressed only at P5 and P12 in most neuronal clusters while <italic>Pcsk2</italic> was expressed at both embryonic and postnatal ages in the same clusters as <italic>Pcsk1. Pam</italic> was expressed in the same cluster/developmental age pattern as <italic>Pcsk1</italic>. Only <italic>Cpe</italic> was expressed in virtually all neurons at all developmental ages.</p><p>Split plots of G-protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) gene expression revealed a wide range of cluster- and age-specific patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s3">Figure 4—figure supplement 3</xref>). <italic>Cnr1</italic> (cannabinoid receptor 1) was an important feature primarily of cluster 7 and the two interrelated clusters 3 and 8. The two metabotropic GABA receptors <italic>Gabbr1</italic> and <italic>Gabbr2</italic> were strongly expressed in all eight neuronal clusters but differed in their developmental gradients. <italic>Gabbr1</italic> was expressed at all developmental ages while <italic>Gabbr2</italic> transcripts were largely present only in more mature neurons at postnatal ages P5 and P12. The opioid receptor <italic>Oprl1</italic> that is selectively activated by nociception/orphanin FQ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Toll et al., 2016</xref>) stood out for its consistently strong expression in all eight neuronal clusters, particularly at postnatal days P5 and P12.</p><p>The prokineticin receptor 1 (<italic>Prokr1</italic>) was selectively expressed together with the GPCR accessory protein gene <italic>Mrap2</italic> in cluster 1 <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> neurons. Although MRAP2 was initially identified as an activating modulator of melanocortin receptor signaling, consequently reducing food intake, it was subsequently shown to be promiscuous in its interaction with additional GPCRs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Srisai et al., 2017</xref>). Unlike its action on MC4R signaling, MRAP2 inhibits PROKR1 signaling to promote food intake in mice independently of its interaction with MC4R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Chaly et al., 2016</xref>). Therefore, the co-expression of <italic>Prokr1</italic> and <italic>Mrap2</italic> in anorexigenic POMC neurons suggests an additional mechanism for PROKR1’s regulation of energy homeostasis by modulating the release of melanocortins from POMC neurons. Finally, the high expression of <italic>Npy2r</italic> (neuropeptide Y receptor 2) in both clusters 1 and 4 matches well with its expression in adult anorexigenic POMC neurons and orexigenic AGRP/NPY neurons, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>TRAP-seq analysis of POMC-expressing cells at P12 and P60</title><p>To define the important genetic programs that direct the transition from early postnatal to adulthood and to compare the differences of the transcriptional programs that guide embryonic vs. postnatal/adult development, we performed Translating Ribosome Affinity Purification TRAP-seq using compound <italic>Pomc-CreERT2; Rosa26-eGFPL10a</italic> transgenic mice where POMC neurons are labeled with a <italic>eGFPL10a</italic> tag after tamoxifen administration at specific developmental stages. Colocalization of POMC and GFP immunoreactivity confirms the expression of <italic>eGFPL10a</italic> in Arc POMC neurons upon tamoxifen injection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). Anti-GFP-conjugated beads were used to pull down actively translating RNAs bound to the eGFPL10a ribosomes from hypothalamic extracts. Both the pull-down mRNA samples and the resultant supernatant mRNA samples were subjected to RNA sequencing. Principal component (PC) analysis shows distinct separation of pull-down and supernatant samples at both ages P12 and P60 from three independent experiments, suggesting good quality of these samples and the intrinsic differences between pull-down and supernatant samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). Both <italic>Pomc</italic> and <italic>GFP</italic> were highly expressed in TRAP pull-down samples relative to the supernatants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>), further validating the specificity of the TRAP-seq method. Gene enrichment analysis identified 1143 and 1047 highly enriched genes (p &lt; 0.05) from <italic>Pomc- eGFPL10a</italic> P12 and P60 TRAP-seq pull-downs, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata1">Figure 5—source data 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata2">Figure 5—source data 2</xref>), from which 653 genes expressed in both datasets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>). We hypothesize that the commonly expressed genes may be associated with the maintenance of POMC functional identity, whereas the uniquely expressed genes at P12 or P60 may be related to distinct age-dependent biological phenomena. To test this hypothesis, we performed gene ontology analysis on the 653 co-expressed genes, 394 P60 specifically expressed genes and 490 P12 specifically expressed genes. The results demonstrate that the commonly expressed genes are associated with the establishment and maintenance of neuron structure and basic neuronal functions. The top three functional annotations include the organization of synapses, regulation of neuron differentiation, and cytoskeleton-dependent intracellular transport. The ontology annotations on the uniquely expressed genes from P12 and P60 are dramatically different from each other. The functions of P12 uniquely enriched genes emphasize basic cellular metabolism, cellular modeling, and biochemical changes, whereas, the P60 enriched genes are related to the maturation of POMC neurons such as neurotransmitter development and POMC-specific function establishment including the responses to nutrient, and the construction of feeding behavioral circuits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref>). We next compared the TRAP-seq commonly expressed genes to our developmental scRNA-seq data to examine their expression levels in each cluster and each age. Approximately one-third (241) of the genes shown in the heatmaps on the left are abundantly expressing in the scRNA-seq dataset across all the clusters. Notably, compared to the four embryonic stages, a constantly higher transcript abundance was observed at both P5 and P12 ages (gray outlined boxes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5G</xref>), indicating great genetic similarities between P5 and P12. Intriguingly, the patterns of expression levels are very similar in both the P12 and P60 TRAP-seq datasets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5G</xref>, right heatmaps). To gain a better visualization of the distribution of TRAP-seq common genes expression at a single-cell level, we grouped the 241 genes as one module, calculated module scores based on the normalized counts and projected the scores to a UMAP plot of the eight neuronal clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5H</xref>). Most cells from cluster 1 (<italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic>), cluster 5 (<italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)<italic>/</italic></sup><italic>Tac2</italic>), cluster 3 (<italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic>), and a subcluster of cluster 2 (<italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic>) present a higher module score (high gene expression levels). Assessment together with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref> confirms that most of the high scoring cells are derived from the two postnatal stages (P5 and P12).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Translating ribosome affinity purification with RNA-sequencing (TRAP-seq) showing gene enrichment and gene expression profiles at P12 and P60.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic diagram showing the generation of <italic>Pomc-CreERT2; ROSA26<sup>eGFP-L10a</sup></italic> mice for TRAP-seq experiment. Immunofluorescence validated the co-localization of proopiomelanocortin (POMC) and eGFP. (<bold>B</bold>) Principal component analysis showing the separation of the RNA sequencing data from beads pull-down vs. supernatant at P12 (purple) and P60 (green), respectively. (<bold>C</bold>) Heatmap showing both <italic>Pomc</italic> and eGFP were highly expressed in beads pull-down samples. Rows are the biological replicates of each sample. Sup: Supernatant samples; PD: pull-down samples. Data were presented as scaled counts per million (CPM). (<bold>D</bold>) Gene enrichment plots showing 1143 genes and 1047 genes were significantly expressed in beads pull-down samples at P12 and P60, respectively (p &lt; 0.05). (<bold>E</bold>) Venn diagram showing the number of genes highly enriched in both P12 (purple) and P60 (green) beads pull-down samples. (<bold>F</bold>) Gene ontology analysis showing the top 15 biological processes that were represented in P12 and P60 co-expressed genes, P12 uniquely expressed genes and P60 uniquely expressed genes. (<bold>G</bold>) Expression profile of the top enriched genes from both P12 and P60 TRAP-seq datasets across eight neuronal clusters; gray boxes indicate the higher expression of these genes in the two postnatal stages. The two heatmaps (right) indicating the top genes expression in P12 and P60 TRAP-seq datasets. (<bold>H</bold>) Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) plot showing the distribution of the top enriched genes from both P12 and P60 TRAP-seq datasets in eight neuronal cell clusters. CPM: counts per million; org.: organization; reg.: regulation; pos.:positive; neg.: negative.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata1"><label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Differentially expressed genes by RNA translating ribosome affinity purification with RNA-sequencing (TRAP-seq) between pull-down vs. supernatant at age P12 (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig5-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata2"><label>Figure 5—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Differentially expressed genes by RNA translating ribosome affinity purification with RNA-sequencing (TRAP-seq) between pull-down vs. supernatant at age P60 (corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig5-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>RNA velocity and diffusion maps analyses illustrating the developmental trajectories of hypothalamic neuronal clusters.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) RNA velocity analysis showing the multiple origins of embryonic proopiomelanocortin (POMC) cells in eight neuronal clusters according to Seurat analysis cell embedding. (<bold>B</bold>) RNA velocity analysis showing the multiple origins of POMC cells correspond to the early embryonic stages. (<bold>C–D</bold>) Diffusion map showing the cell lineages of POMC neurons during embryogenesis. Cells are colored on the basis of their developmental stage (<bold>C</bold>) or based on their previously defined clusters (<bold>D</bold>). (<bold>E</bold>) Diffusion maps showing the expression of selected genes according to previous characterization of the feature genes representing each cluster. The color intensity corresponds to the normalized gene expression from Seurat analysis.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig6-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Overview of neuronal clusters split by developmental stages.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) plots showing the splitting of neuronal clusters by developmental stages. Clusters were dash-dot circled to show the emerging/evolving progress through development. (<bold>B</bold>) RNA velocity analysis showing the multiple origins of proopiomelanocortin (POMC) cells are mainly from 1. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> and 2. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> clusters and are mainly from E11.5 and E13.5. (<bold>C</bold>) RNA velocity analysis on neurons from three late embryonic stages (E13.5, E15.5, and E17.5) showing two origins of POMC cells from 1. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> and 2. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> clusters at E13.5.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-72883-fig6-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Developmental relationships of gene expression patterns in the eight neuronal POMC clusters at four embryonic ages</title><p>To investigate the gene expression trajectories of developing POMC neurons, we performed an RNA velocity analysis of cells from the eight neuronal clusters focusing on the four embryonic stages. This RNA velocity analysis revealed a major origin of POMC neurons captured by the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> cluster and a minor origin depicted by the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A and B</xref>), which is consistent with the early appearance of these two clusters at E11.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>). Further investigation of cells from E13.5, E15.5, and E17.5 also suggest a dual origin from <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> or <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>To further validate the hypothesis of a dual origins of POMC neurons and to better visualize cell trajectories in three-dimensional Euclidean space, we constructed diffusion maps of all neurons from the four embryonic stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). The image depicts a triangular beveled star polygon with rays 1 and 2 derived primarily from distinct groups of neurons at ages E11.5 and E13.5, a center vertex containing individual neurons from the intermediate ages E13.5 and E15.5 and a third ray with neurons from ages E15.5 and E17.5. The same data are alternatively color-coded for each neuron’s cluster identity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>) showing that ray 1 is primarily derived from cluster 2, ray 2 from cluster 1, the center vertex from a convergence of all clusters 1–8 and ray 3 from clusters 1, 2, 4, 5, and 6. Compared to ray 2, cells in ray 1 are not continuously ordered, but instead show an abrupt transition at the junction of cells from E11.5 and E13.5.</p><p>We then overlaid the geometric location of each neuron with the expression levels of selected feature genes from each of the eight clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref>). Consistent with the diffusion maps analyses, the more granular data for individual genes and neurons illustrates the essentially identical patterns of high <italic>Pomc</italic> expression with the two originally discovered cognate transactivating factors <italic>Isl1</italic> and <italic>Nkx2-1</italic> across embryonic development (rays 2 and 3). However, <italic>Isl1</italic> was also expressed in numerous <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup> neurons at E11.5 and E13.5 (ray 1). <italic>Prdm12</italic> and <italic>Tbx3</italic> exhibited complementary temporal patterns of high expression at early (ray 2) vs. late (ray 3) embryonic ages, respectively. The combined developmental and geometric patterns of <italic>Six3, Six6,</italic> and <italic>Sox14</italic> expression were all very similar to both <italic>Pomc</italic> and <italic>Nkx2-1</italic>, suggesting that all four of these TF genes might be necessary to define the cell fate of a subpopulation of hypothalamic neuronal progenitors into mature differentiated POMC neurons.</p><p>In contrast to those genes with expression patterns that defined the continuum of neuronal identity from ray 2 to ray 3, another set of genes including <italic>Ebf1, Pou4f1,</italic> and <italic>Nr4a2</italic> was similarly highly expressed only at the two earliest embryonic ages in neurons constituting ray 1. The expression of <italic>Pitx2</italic>, which characterizes cluster 8 and a portion of cluster 3, was high in ray 1 as it merges into the center vertex and was mostly derived from age E13.5. Finally, the temporal and geometric patterns of high expression levels for <italic>Otp, Prdm13, Tac2,</italic> and <italic>Dlx5</italic> were distinct from each other and the aforementioned genes, consistent with their ontogeny into the distinct differentiated cell fates of cluster 4. AGRP/NPY/GABA, cluster 5. KNDY, and cluster 6. GABA/PNOC neurons, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we tracked the genetic programs that give rise to <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing neurons in the developing hypothalamus and followed their progression into terminally differentiated POMC neurons and alternative phenotypic destinies. To this end, we performed an scRNA-seq study specifically of <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing neurons present in developing mouse hypothalami at four embryonic time points (E11.5, E13.5, E15.5, E17.5) and two early postnatal days (P5 and P12). We also performed a complementary TRAP-seq study on affinity purified translating RNAs derived from hypothalamic POMC cells obtained at ages P12 and P60. These developmental stages were selected based on the ontogeny of <italic>Pomc</italic> expression in the presumptive hypothalamus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Japón et al., 1994</xref>), peak of neurogenesis of POMC neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Nasif et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Orquera et al., 2019</xref>), subsequent developmental maturation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Padilla et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sanz et al., 2015</xref>), and terminal differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Quarta et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Our study revealed the existence of a major group of POMC neurons (cluster 1. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)<italic>/</italic></sup><italic>Prdm12</italic>) that showed by far the highest levels of <italic>Pomc</italic> UMIs relative to all other neuronal clusters at all ages. We believe that this cluster constitutes the canonical POMC neurons that further mature and integrate into functional circuits in the postnatal hypothalamus. Cluster 1 is featured by a unique combinatorial set of TFs that includes <italic>Isl1</italic>, <italic>Nkx2-1,</italic> and <italic>Prdm12</italic>. In the last few years, our laboratories demonstrated that these three TFs are present in neurons that start expressing <italic>Pomc</italic> in the developing arcuate nucleus at E10.5, and their expression continues at later developmental ages and adulthood in hypothalamic POMC neurons. Indeed, we showed that ISL1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Nasif et al., 2015</xref>), NKX2-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Orquera et al., 2019</xref>), and PRDM12 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hael et al., 2020</xref>) are absolutely necessary to specify the identity of POMC neurons. Moreover, we also demonstrated previously that adult mice lacking any of these three TFs exclusively from POMC cells display greatly reduced levels of hypothalamic <italic>Pomc</italic> mRNA together with increased adiposity and body weight. However, our results also indicated that the sole presence of ISL1<italic>,</italic> NKX2-1, and PRDM12 at E10.5–E11.5 is insufficient to determine the early identity of hypothalamic POMC neurons, suggesting that the combinatorial set of TFs necessary for neuronal-specific <italic>Pomc</italic> expression has additional early components, yet to be discovered. In this regard, our scRNA-seq study revealed several novel candidates in cluster 1 cells including <italic>Six3</italic>, <italic>Six6, Sox1/2/3, Sox14,</italic> and other TFs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). Future molecular and functional genetic studies will be needed to assess their potential contribution to Arc <italic>Pomc</italic> expression and the functioning of POMC neurons.</p><p><italic>Six3</italic> and <italic>Six6</italic> are two evolutionarily related TF genes known to play critical roles in the development of the eyes, forebrain, and pituitary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Liu and Cvekl, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Liu et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Suh et al., 2010</xref>). The expression patterns of <italic>Six3</italic> and <italic>Six6</italic> highly overlap during early embryogenesis but segregate into different territories during late embryonic development, indicating possible distinct postnatal functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Geng et al., 2008</xref>). Indeed, <italic>Six3</italic> knockout mice die at birth whereas mice lacking <italic>Six6</italic> exhibit decreased numbers of GNRH neurons and impaired fertility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Larder et al., 2011</xref>). Although <italic>Six3</italic> and <italic>Six6</italic> are abundantly expressed in Arc POMC neurons across all examined developmental stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>), their participation in the control of <italic>Pomc</italic> expression and the patterning and function of POMC neurons requires further investigation. Regarding Sox genes, a family of TFs known to regulate cell fate by transactivating cell-specific genes, in silico analysis of conserved SOX protein binding motifs suggests the potential binding of SOX proteins including SOX1, SOX2, SOX3, and SOX14 to <italic><underline>Pomc</underline></italic> neuronal enhancers nPE1 and nPE2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chen et al., 2020</xref>). All four of these <italic>Sox</italic> genes were highly enriched in <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> cluster 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata2">Figure 1—source data 2</xref>) as well as in <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Tac2</italic> cluster 5 and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Prdm13</italic> cluster 7. Furthermore, mice lacking <italic>Sox14</italic> exhibit a great reduction in KNDY neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Huisman et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>A particular feature gene present in cluster 1 was <italic>Tbx3</italic>, a T-box TF that has been recently reported to play a key role in Arc <italic>Pomc</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Quarta et al., 2019</xref>). Unlike <italic>Isl1</italic>, <italic>Nkx2.1,</italic> and <italic>Prdm12</italic>, which are all strictly required at the onset of <italic>Pomc</italic> expression (E10.5), <italic>Tbx3</italic> expression commences several days later (E15.5) in the Arc and, therefore, apparently does not participate in the early specification of POMC neurons. However, <italic>Tbx3</italic> plays an important role in the functional maturation of these neurons as a transcriptional booster of arcuate <italic>Pomc</italic> expression. It was recently demonstrated in mice specifically lacking <italic>Tbx3</italic> from POMC neurons that <italic>Pomc</italic> expression was diminished leading to hyperphagia and obesity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Quarta et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>The TRAP-seq results add another layer to our understanding of the genetic machinery that leads to mature functional POMC neurons. Genes that are uniquely enriched at P12 are associated with the basic cellular biology process and cell metabolism whereas genes specifically expressed at P60 are involved in the establishment of POMC neuronal functions. The co-expressed genes from TRAP-seq are highly expressed at P5 and P12 in the single-cell sequencing datasets, suggesting that the genetic programs that dominate embryonic POMC neuronal development are substantially different from the programs that guide postnatal POMC neuronal differentiation. Although only 1 week apart, the cells at P5 share more genetic similarities to the cells at P12 rather than the cells at E17.5.</p><p>An unanticipated finding of our study is the discovery of an early population of Arc <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing neurons characterized by the expression of the TF <italic>Ebf1</italic> and <italic>Pou4f1</italic>, in the absence of <italic>Prdm12</italic> transcripts. The expression profile of cluster 2. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Ebf1</italic> differs from cluster 1. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> most particularly at the earliest developmental ages E11.5–E15.5 and may both represent alternative genetic routes leading to mature arcuate neurons. The early expression of <italic>Ebf1</italic> suggests that this TF may regulate the migration of differentiating neurons out of the ventricular zone to the mantle, as has been reported in the developing striatum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Garel et al., 1999</xref>). Further studies are needed to understand the functional significance of the non-canonical population of <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing neurons captured by cluster 2 cells.</p><p>Another main finding of our study is the identification of multiple subpopulations of <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing neurons that originate in the developing arcuate nucleus. In addition to the previously characterized fertility-regulating KNDY neurons (<italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Tac2</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sanz et al., 2015</xref>) and orexigenic AGRP/NPY neurons (<italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Padilla et al., 2010</xref>), our data indicated that, as early as E11.5, <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing neurons may also give rise to four other less characterized neuronal populations noted as <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2, Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Pitx2, Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Dlx5,</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Prdm13</italic>. Moreover, subclustering cells from E11.5 revealed a distinct cell population featured by <italic>Otp</italic> expression (E11.5–9 cluster in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>), suggesting that the presence of <italic>Otp</italic> transcripts at E11.5 may already be dictating the differentiation pathway of this neuronal cluster toward an AGRP phenotype, a hypothesis that requires further investigation. In addition, RNA-velocity developmental trajectory analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1B</xref>) suggested that the early cells in <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup>/<italic>Prdm12</italic> cluster project to <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup>/<italic>Otp</italic> cluster.</p><p><italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Pitx2</italic> are related clusters sharing 20% of their top 150 feature genes being one of the most salient differences the presence of neuropeptide <italic>Cck</italic> transcripts only in the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Pitx2</italic> cluster. Comparing our dataset with a previous one obtained using FACS from adult hypothalami of POMC-EGFP mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lam et al., 2017</xref>) in which <italic>Nr4a2</italic> showed to be expressed in 18.5% of cells in cluster 4, it is likely that embryonic <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(med)</sup><italic>/Nr4a2</italic> cells captured by our study keep their identity through adulthood. Similarly, signature genes for the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Dlx5</italic> cluster including <italic>Dlx1, Dlx2, Dlx5</italic>, and <italic>Dlx6</italic> were also found to be highly enriched and specific for cluster 1 in Lam et al.’s study, suggesting that the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Dlx5</italic> cluster detected in our study becomes a subset of adult POMC neurons. Finally, our identification of the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Prdm13</italic> cluster matches with a recent study showing that <italic>Prdm13</italic> is highly enriched in FACS cells from E15.5 POMC-EGFP embryos analyzed by whole transcriptome RNA sequencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chen et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>It is worth mentioning that despite some extent of similarities between embryonic and adult POMC cells, the majority of embryonic and early postnatal cells profiled in our study are distantly related to mature adult POMC neurons, indicating that terminal differentiation of POMC neurons is a long-lasting maturation process that proceeds along multiple life stages. For example, most adult POMC cells express proprotein convertase PC1/3 (<italic>Pcsk1</italic>) and leptin receptor (<italic>Lepr</italic>), whereas only 22% and 2.7% of cells from our datasets express the two genes, respectively, suggesting critical functional changes in the transcriptome of POMC neurons during postnatal maturation after early postnatal ages.</p><p>Due to the limitations of the scRNA-seq techniques, some interesting questions cannot be answered from our study at the functional level. For example, are all TFs present in cluster 1. <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(high)</sup><italic>/Prdm12</italic> at E11.5 critical for dictating the identity of the cannonical POMC neurons? what TFs are critical for maintaining POMC neuron identity throughout lifetime? Is <italic>Otp</italic> the only critical gene that determines the transition of <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing cells into AGRP/NPY neurons? Which are the TFs that give rise to the lineage of KNDY neurons during development? We believe that our study provides a valuable resource to tackle these and many other questions aimed at a better understanding of the regulation and functioning of POMC and other related neurons in the mammalian arcuate nucleus of the hypothalamus.</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>Concluding remarks</title><p>In summary, this study is the first to comprehensively characterize the transcriptomes of Arc hypothalamic POMC cells during embryonic and early postnatal development. This dataset extends our understanding of the diversification of early POMC cells and provides a valuable resource for further elucidating the regulatory mechanism for <italic>Pomc</italic> expression and neuronal maturation. The identification of new marker genes in each subpopulation from scRNA-seq and uniquely expressed genes at P12 or P60 from the TRAP-seq study will potentially lead to new directions for future functional studies of POMC neurons.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">Reagent type (species) or resource</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Designation</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Source or reference</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Identifiers</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Genetic reagent (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Pomc -TdDsRed</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PMID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19864580/">19864580</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Dr Malcolm Low (University of Michigan)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Genetic reagent (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Pomc-CreERT2</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PMID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24177424/">24177424</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:MGI:5569339">MGI:5569339</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Genetic reagent (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rosa26<sup>eGFP-L10a</sup></italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Jackson Laboratory</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Stock # 024750;RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:IMSR_JAX:024750">IMSR_JAX:024750</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Anti-Nr5a1(Rabbit Polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Dr Gary Hammer, University of Michigan</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:750–1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Anti-td-Tomato [16D7] (Rat Monoclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Kerafast</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # EST203;RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2732803">AB_2732803</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:750)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Anti-Pomc (Rabbit Polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Phoenix Pharmaceuticals</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # H-029–30;RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2307442">AB_2307442</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF(1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Anti-Rabbit Alexa 488 (Goat polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Invitrogen</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # A-11034;RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2576217">AB_2576217</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF(1:500–1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Anti-Rat Alexa Fluor 555 (Goat polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Invitrogen</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # A-21434;RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2535855">AB_2535855</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF(1:500–1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Anti-Esr1 (Rabbit Polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Dr Sue Moenter, University of Michigan</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF(1:10000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Anti-GFP (Chicken polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Abcam</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # ab13970;RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_300798">AB_300798</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF(1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Papain Dissociation System</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Worthington Biochemical Corporation</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">LK003178</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">DNase</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Worthington Biochemical Corporation</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">LK003172</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R Project for Statistical Computing</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Seurat 3.1.5</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Satija Lab</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://satijalab.org/seurat/articles/install.html">https://satijalab.org/seurat/articles/install.html</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Monocle 2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cole-trapnell lab</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cole-trapnell-lab.github.io/monocle-release/docs/">http://cole-trapnell-lab.github.io/monocle-release/docs/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Destiny 2.14.0</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Carsten Marr &amp; Florian Buettner lab</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://theislab.github.io/destiny/">https://theislab.github.io/destiny/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RNAscope Multiplex Fluorescent V2 Assay</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ACDbio</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 323110</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Six3</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 412941-C3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Six6</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 574291</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Tac2</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 446391-C3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Npy</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 313321</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Ebf1</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 433411</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Pou4f1</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 414671-C3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Pomc</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 314081-C2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Sox14</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 516411</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Prdm13</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 543551-C2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Tacr3</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 481671</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Dlx5</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 478151</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Pitx2</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 412841</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-<italic>Pomc</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 314081</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-Positive Control Probe</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 320881</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mm-Negative Control Probe</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 320871</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sequence-based reagent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RNAscope Probe Diluent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Advanced Cell Diagnostics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 300041</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Opal 520 Reagent Pack</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">AKOYA Biosciences</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # NC1601877</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1:750–1:1500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Opal 620 Reagent Pack</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">AKOYA Biosciences</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # NC1612059</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1:750–1:1500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Opal 690 Reagent Pack</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">AKOYA Biosciences</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # NC1605064</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1:750–1:1500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Other</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">DAPI</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">BD Biosciences</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat # 564907</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">FACS (500–1000 ng/mL)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Other</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ProLong Gold Antifade Mountant</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ThermoFisher</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">P36930</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Other</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Earle’s Balanced Salts</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">E2888</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Mice</title><p>All procedures were performed in accordance with the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) at the University of Michigan and followed the Public Health Service guidelines for the humane care and use of experimental animals. Mice were housed in ventilated cages under controlled temperature and photoperiod (12 hr light/12 hr dark cycle, lights on from 6:00 AM to 6:00 PM), with free access to tap water and laboratory chow (5L0D, LabDiet). Breeding mice were fed with the breeder chow diet (5008, LabDiet). Transgenic mice expressing the fluorescent protein Tdimer-Discosoma red (TdDsRed) in POMC neurons were generated previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hael et al., 2020</xref>). The vast majority of <italic>Pomc-TdDsRed</italic> cells were validated as authentic POMC neurons based on co-localization of ACTH immunostaining with the TdDsRed fluorophore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hentges et al., 2009</xref>) <italic>Pomc-CreERT2</italic> and <italic>Rosa26<sup>eGFP-L10a</sup></italic> (Stock no. 024750, The Jackson Laboratory) mice were generated as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Liu et al., 2014</xref>). To induce POMC neurons-specific expression of eGFP-L10a at P12 or P60, tamoxifen (50 mg/kg) was injected intraperitoneally for 5 constitutive days from P6 to P10 or P50 to P54.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Generation of single-cell suspension for scRNA-seq</title><p>Adult male <italic>Pomc-TdDsRed/+</italic> mice were bred with female <italic>Pomc-TdDsRed/+</italic> mice and the day of copulation plug detection was counted as embryonic day 0.5 (E0.5). Embryonic hypothalami were dissected at E11.5, E13.5, E15.5, and E17.5. Postnatal hypothalami were isolated from pups at postnatal day 5 (P5) and P12. In each dissection, hypothalami from at least six pups were pooled together to acquire enough cells for FACS. Pooled tissue samples were digested in papain solution supplemented with DNAse for 20 min (E11.5 and E13.5), 30 min (E15.5), 40 min (E17.5), or 1 hr (P5 and P12) with gentle agitation based on a published protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Garel et al., 1999</xref>). The isolated cells were stained with DAPI as an indicator for cell viability and sorted by FACS for the transgenic red fluorophore. The collected cells were counted and subjected to scRNA-seq library preparation and sequencing (10× Genomics).</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>scRNA-seq data processing</title><p>A total of 37,053 single cells (E11.5: 5329, E13.5: 7051, E15.5: 5148, E17.5: 2488, P5: 7551, and P12: 9486) from six different developmental stages were processed using the 10× Genomics Chromium system. The libraries were sequenced on Illumina HiSeq 4000 and NovaSeq platforms. We obtained a total of over 2.6 billion reads with an average of 70,7896 reads per cell. Over 85% of reads mapped confidently to the mouse genome across all six developmental stages. Raw reads were processed with Cell Ranger (v.2.2 and v.3.0). Seurat package (v.3.1.5) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Butler et al., 2018</xref>) was used for downstream analysis. Since the number of genes and UMI counts varied across developmental stage, we applied different criteria at each stage to filter out possible doublets and low-quality cells. Specifically, at E11.5, we removed outlier cells that had UMI counts &lt;5000 or &gt;60,000 and gene counts &lt;1000 or &gt;8000 (determined by the visualization of UMI counts and gene count distributions). At E13.5, we removed outlier cells that had UMI counts &lt;2500 or &gt;30,000 and gene counts &gt;1500. At E15.5, we removed outlier cells that had UMI counts &gt;40,000 and gene counts &lt;1000 or &gt;6000. At E17.5, we removed outlier cells that had UMI counts &gt;25,000 and gene counts &lt;1000 or &gt; 5000. At P5, we removed outlier cells that had UMI counts &lt;1500 or &gt;60,000 and gene counts &lt;1500 or &gt;8000. At P12, we removed outlier cells that had UMI counts &lt;2000 or &gt;60,000 and gene counts &lt;1500 or &gt;8000. Moreover, cells with high proportions of mitochondrial genes (&gt;10%) or hemoglobin genes (&gt;10%) were filtered out. Finally, we removed all the cells without any <italic>Pomc</italic> transcript UMI counts. A total of 13,953 cells passed the criteria (E11.5: 1498, E13.5: 1796, E15.5: 2078, E17.5: 1139, P5: 3909 and P12: 3533) for downstream analysis.</p><p>The gene expression level for each cell was normalized by the total expression, multiplied by a scaling factor of 10,000 followed by log-transformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Butler et al., 2018</xref>). The top 2000 most variable genes were selected from each age and 60 integration anchors were used to combine all the datasets together. After scaling and centering the integrated dataset, we performed PCs analysis on the data matrix and the top 50 PCs were selected based on JackStraw and Elbow plots from Seurat package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hentges et al., 2009</xref>) for data visualization using Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) technique. We next constructed a shared nearest neighbor (SNN) graph by setting an expected number of neighbors to 50. In order to cluster the cells, an SNN modularity optimization technique within a function FindClusters was used to group cells together with a resolution parameter 0.1. The identity for each cluster was assigned based on the level of <italic>Pomc</italic> transcripts and prior knowledge of marker genes. The similar analysis was applied to define <italic>TdDsRed</italic> cell clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>). In addition to the above criteria applied to remove unwanted cells, we chose cells with at least one <italic>TdDsRed</italic> transcript UMI count and used the top 2000 highly variable genes for PCs analysis. The top 30 PCs were selected for unsupervised clustering with a resolution of 0.3.</p><p>Unsupervised cell clustering from each developmental age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>) was conducting using the following PC numbers (E11.5: 25; E13.5: 24, E15.5: 26, E17.5: 19, P5: 40, P12: 34) with their corresponding resolutions (E11.5: 0.2; E13.5: 0.6, E15.5: 0.5, E17.5: 0.5, P5: 0.5, P12: 0.5). The UMAP plots, violin plots, feature plots, and dot plots were all generated in the Seurat package. The average expression levels for each gene within each developmental subcluster (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata1">Figure 4—source data 1</xref>) were obtained from Seurat and calculated by the average of [<italic>exp(logNormalized counts)–1</italic>]. The differentially expressed genes in each identified cluster was identified by the comparison of gene expression levels in a specific cluster to all the other clusters.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Cluster identity comparisons</title><p>To compare cluster identities between POMC cells and DSRED cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>), we normalized the DSRED cells data and acquired the top 2000 most variable genes. We then use the standard datasets integration method from Seurat packages with the top 50 anchors for data integration and top 50 anchors to transfer cell identities from POMC cells to DSRED cells. We also applied this approach to conduct age-pairwise comparisons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>) with default setting from Seurat V3.1.5 package.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Cell lineage construction</title><p>For RNA velocity analysis, spliced and unspliced matrices of reads were summarized using velocyto (v.0.17.16) with default parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">La Manno et al., 2018</xref>). Low complexity and repeat regions were downloaded from the UCSC browser (rmsk table from mm10). scVelo was performed for RNA velocity analysis (v.0.2.2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bergen et al., 2020</xref>). The cell embedding information was acquired from Seurat analysis. The top 4000 genes, the top 20 PCs, and the top 20 neighbors under stochastic mode were used to generate velocity graph.</p><p>Cell lineage was constructed using the Destiny (v.2.14.0) package, which implements the formulation of diffusion maps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Angerer et al., 2016</xref>). Diffusion maps are a spectral method for non-linear dimension reduction, which is especially suitable for analyzing single-cell gene expression data from different time-courses. We removed VLMC, glial cells, and astrocytes (clusters 9, 10, and 11 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>) and kept only neurons at embryonic stages (E11.5, E13.5, E15.5, and E17.5), resulting in a total of 6005 cells for this analysis. The log-transformed normalized data from Seurat data slot and the corresponding annotation information were imported to construct an expression matrix. The diffusion maps were constructed under the default setting for the Gaussian kernel width sigma (σ) and 300 nearest neighbors. The first two diffusion components (DCs) were used to visualize the results. The 3D plots were produced using rgl package (v.0.100.50) with the top three DCs.</p><p>To perform pseudotime gene expression analysis, cells from cluster 1, cluster 2, cluster 4, and cluster 5 were extracted from the Seurat object, respectively. Raw counts were acquired to construct Monocle (v.2.4.0) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Qiu et al., 2017a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Trapnell et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Qiu et al., 2017b</xref>) datasets. Cells were ordered along the pseudotime by setting E11.5 as the root state. Differentially expressed genes (Log2FoldChange &gt; 0.25 and p &lt; 0.05) in each cluster from the Seurat analysis were plotted along the pseudotime using ‘plot_pseudotime_heatmap’ function. Gene ontology analysis (Biological Process) was performed using ClusterProfiler (v.3.18.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Yu et al., 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>TRAP-seq analysis</title><p>Mice (<italic>Pomc-CreERT2</italic>; ROSA26<sup>eGFP-L10a</sup>) were euthanized and decapitated. The brain was removed from the skull and the arcuate nucleus was isolated from 2 mm thick coronal slices using a brain matrix. Tissues were then homogenized and the subsequent tissue lysate was subjected to immunopurification steps according to the previous protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Heiman et al., 2014</xref>). The ribo-depletion kit (RiboGone, Takara, CA) and SMARTer Stranded total RNA sample prep kit were used to remove excess ribosomal RNA and synthesize cDNA library. Samples were sequenced on a 50-cycle single end run on a HiSeq 4000 (Illumina) according to manufacturer’s protocols.</p><p>Raw sequencing data was processed at the University of Michigan Bioinformatics core. Briefly, the quality of the raw reads data was checked using FastQC (v.0.11.3) and the filtered reads were aligned to reference genome (UCSC mm10) using TopHat (v.2.0.13) and Bowtie2 (v.2.2.1) with default parameters. The HTSeq/DEseq2 method was used for differential expression analysis with paired-samples and treatment (pull-down vs. supernatant) as the main effects.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Tissue collection and immunofluorescence staining</title><p>Depending on developmental stage, embryos at E10.5–E17.5 were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde in phosphate buffer solution (PBS) at 4°C for a various period of time. Specifically, embryos at E10.5–E12.5 were fixed for 1 hr; heads from embryos at E15.5–E16.6 and E17.5 were fixed for 2 and 4 hr, respectively. Tissues were stabilized in 10% sucrose/10% gelatin in PBS at 37°C for 30 min prior to embedding in OCT compound as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Butler et al., 2018</xref>). Embryonic brains were sectioned sagittally on a cryostat (Leica CM1950) at 20 μm thickness. For dual immunofluorescence, after washing excess OCT compound with PBS, a heat-induced antigen retrieval process was performed using citrate buffer (10 mM anhydrous citric acid and 0.05% Tween-20, pH 6.0) at 80°C for 30 min followed by two washes in PBS. Sections were then blocked with 3% normal goat serum and 0.1% Triton X-100 for 1 hr and incubated with primary antibodies at room temperature overnight. After PBS washes, sections were incubated with goat secondary antibodies for 2 hr at room temperature. Nuclei were stained with DAPI (1 mg/L) for 10 min and the slides washed five times with PBS before mounting with ProLong Gold Antifade Mountant (ThermoFisher). Sections were imaged on a Nikon 90i fluorescence microscope with NIS-Elements software. Information on the sources and dilution of antibodies are listed in Key resources table.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>In situ hybridization</title><p>FISH was performed using RNAscope Multiplex Fluorescent V2 Assay (Advanced Cell Diagnostics) according to the manufacturer’s instructions with slight modifications. Specifically, after washing with PBS, sections were post-fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 20 min, and dehydrated in a series of ethanol solutions (50%, 70%, and 100%). After drying, dehydrated sections were incubated in RNAscope Hydrogen Peroxide solution for 10 min followed by the protease treatment using RNAscope Protease IV for 20 min. Sections were then hybridized to target RNA probes for 2 hr in the HybEZ II hybridization oven. Hybridized probes were amplified using a cascade of signal amplification solutions (AMP 1–3) followed by standard signal developing protocol as described in the manufacturer’s brochure. Detailed information on RNA probes and dilutions are listed in Key resources table. Confocal images were obtained using a Nikon Instruments A1 Confocal Laser Microscope with NIS-Elements software.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Supervision, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Resources, Supervision, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>All procedures were performed in accordance with the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) protocol (PRO00008570) at the University of Michigan and followed the Public Health Service guidelines for the humane care and use of experimental animals.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-72883-transrepform1-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All raw data have been deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus under accession numbers GSE154153 and GSE181539.</p><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><element-citation id="dataset1" publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcelo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Malcolm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><data-title>Single cell RNA-seq of the developing mouse hypothalamus</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE154153">GSE154153</pub-id></element-citation></p><p><element-citation id="dataset2" publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcelo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Malcolm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><data-title>Developmental single-cell transcriptomics of hypothalamic POMC progenitors reveal the genetic trajectories of multiple neuropeptidergic phenotypes</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE181539">GSE181539</pub-id></element-citation></p></sec><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr Graham L Jones, Dr Zoe Thompson, and Charles Keane for their assistance in animal dissection, tissue sectioning, and data analysis, Dr Joshua Welch and Tongyu Liu for advice on data analysis, the Flow Cytometry Core, the Advanced Genomics Core, the Bioinformatics Core and the Microscopy, Imaging and Cellular Physiology Core (supported by NIH Grant: P30DK020572) and the University of Michigan Center for Gastrointestinal Research (supported by NIH grant: P30DK034933) at University of Michigan for data collection. Funding: This study was supported by NIH grant DK068400 (MJL and MR)</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tryggvason</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Friling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alekseenko</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ericson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Identification of intrinsic determinants of midbrain dopamine neurons</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2005.10.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angerer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Haghverdi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Büttner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Theis</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Buettner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>destiny: diffusion maps for large-scale single-cell data in R</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26668002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Appleyard</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>A role for the endogenous opioid beta-endorphin in energy homeostasis</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>144</volume><fpage>1753</fpage><lpage>1760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.2002-221096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12697680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peidli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Theis</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Generalizing RNA velocity to transient cell states through dynamical modeling</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>1408</fpage><lpage>1414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-020-0591-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32747759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouret</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004a</year><article-title>Formation of Projection Pathways from the Arcuate Nucleus of the Hypothalamus to Hypothalamic Regions Implicated in the Neural Control of Feeding Behavior in Mice</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>2797</fpage><lpage>2805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5369-03.2004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouret</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Simerly</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004b</year><article-title>Trophic Action of Leptin on Hypothalamic Neurons That Regulate Feeding</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>304</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1095004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouret</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>MG</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Simerly</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Distinct roles for specific leptin receptor signals in the development of hypothalamic feeding circuits</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>1244</fpage><lpage>1252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2277-11.2012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22279209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bumaschny</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casas-Cordero</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Otero-Corchón</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>FSJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Obesity-programmed mice are rescued by early genetic intervention</article-title><source>The Journal of Clinical Investigation</source><volume>122</volume><fpage>4203</fpage><lpage>4212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI62543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23093774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Smibert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Papalexi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Satija</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Integrating single-cell transcriptomic data across different conditions, technologies, and species</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.4096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29608179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Macosko</surname><given-names>EZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenselau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pers</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyubetskaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstegen</surname><given-names>AMJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Resch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarroll</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowell</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>A molecular census of arcuate hypothalamus and median eminence cell types</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28166221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaly</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Srisai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebag</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>The Melanocortin Receptor Accessory Protein 2 promotes food intake through inhibition of the Prokineticin Receptor-1</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e12397</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26829592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Single-Cell RNA-Seq Reveals Hypothalamic Cell Diversity</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>3227</fpage><lpage>3241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2017.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28355573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyler</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Landy</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Comparative Transcriptomic Analyses of Developing Melanocortin Neurons Reveal New Regulators for the Anorexigenic Neuron Identity</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>3165</fpage><lpage>3177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0155-20.2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32213554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marín</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosschedl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Charnay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Ebf1 controls early cell differentiation in the embryonic striatum</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>5285</fpage><lpage>5294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.126.23.5285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10556054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Speirs</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagutin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Inbal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Solnica-Krezel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Haploinsufficiency of Six3 fails to activate Sonic hedgehog expression in the ventral forebrain and causes holoprosencephaly</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2008.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18694563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>German</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Baladi</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleckenstein</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Regulation of the Dopamine and Vesicular Monoamine Transporters: Pharmacological Targets and Implications for Disease</article-title><source>Pharmacological Reviews</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/pr.114.010397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26408528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hael</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Orquera</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>The transcriptional regulator PRDM12 is critical for Pomc expression in the mouse hypothalamus and controlling food intake, adiposity, and body weight</article-title><source>Molecular Metabolism</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molmet.2020.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32180559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heiman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulicke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenster</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Greengard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heintz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Cell type-specific mRNA purification by translating ribosome affinity purification (TRAP)</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>1282</fpage><lpage>1291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2014.085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24810037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hentges</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Otero-Corchon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennock</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Proopiomelanocortin expression in both GABA and glutamate neurons</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>13684</fpage><lpage>13690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3770-09.2009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19864580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K-S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Functional roles of Nurr1, Pitx3, and Lmx1a in neurogenesis and phenotype specification of dopamine neurons during in vitro differentiation of embryonic stem cells</article-title><source>Stem Cells and Development</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/scd.2013.0406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24172139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Delogu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Single cell transcriptome analysis of developing arcuate nucleus neurons uncovers their key developmental regulators</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>3696</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-11667-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31420539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Delogu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Author Correction: Single cell transcriptome analysis of developing arcuate nucleus neurons uncovers their key developmental regulators</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1359</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-14964-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32157096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>The nuclear receptor steroidogenic factor 1 is essential for the formation of the ventromedial hypothalamic nucleus</article-title><source>Molecular Endocrinology</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/mend.9.4.7659091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7659091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jankovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>The role of Nurr1 in the development of dopaminergic neurons and Parkinson’s disease</article-title><source>Progress in Neurobiology</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2005.09.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16243425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Japón</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>In situ hybridization analysis of anterior pituitary hormone gene expression during fetal mouse development</article-title><source>The Journal of Histochemistry and Cytochemistry</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/42.8.8027530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8027530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokosawa</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lechan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Selective Restoration of Pomc Expression in Glutamatergic POMC Neurons: Evidence for a Dynamic Hypothalamic Neurotransmitter Network</article-title><source>ENeuro</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>2019</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/ENEURO.0400-18.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30957016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Volakakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkeby</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Storvall</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolbrant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Björklund</surname><given-names>ÅK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Joodmardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Single-Cell Analysis Reveals a Close Relationship between Differentiating Dopamine and Subthalamic Nucleus Neuronal Lineages</article-title><source>Cell Stem Cell</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2016.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28094018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovalovsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Refojo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberman</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochbaum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereda</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Coso</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stalla</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Holsboer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Arzt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Activation and induction of NUR77/NURR1 in corticotrophs by CRH/cAMP: involvement of calcium, protein kinase A, and MAPK pathways</article-title><source>Molecular Endocrinology</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1638</fpage><lpage>1651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/mend.16.7.0863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12089357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krude</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Biebermann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Luck</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brabant</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Grüters</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Severe early-onset obesity, adrenal insufficiency and red hair pigmentation caused by POMC mutations in humans</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9620771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>La Manno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Soldatov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeisel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochgerner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Petukhov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lidschreiber</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kastriti</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Lönnerberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Borm</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>van Bruggen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundström</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Castelo-Branco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Adameyko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Linnarsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kharchenko</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>RNA velocity of single cells</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>560</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0414-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30089906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>BYH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cimino</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Polex-Wolf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicole Kohnke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimmington</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyemere</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Heeley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulte</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Saraiva</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Blouet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Rahilly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>GSH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Heterogeneity of hypothalamic pro-opiomelanocortin-expressing neurons revealed by single-cell RNA sequencing</article-title><source>Molecular Metabolism</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molmet.2017.02.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28462073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>NLG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellon</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Hypothalamic dysregulation and infertility in mice lacking the homeodomain protein Six6</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1688-10.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21228153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Raber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Dlx1/2 and Otp coordinate the production of hypothalamic GHRH- and AgRP-neurons</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>2026</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-04377-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29795232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagutin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Swindell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Neuroretina specification in mouse embryos requires Six3-mediated suppression of Wnt8b in the anterior neural plate</article-title><source>The Journal of Clinical Investigation</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>3568</fpage><lpage>3577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI43219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20890044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Krautzberger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Baetscher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grgic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hide</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Cell-specific translational profiling in acute kidney injury</article-title><source>The Journal of Clinical Investigation</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>1242</fpage><lpage>1254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI72126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24569379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cvekl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Six3 in a small population of progenitors at E8.5 is required for neuroretinal specification via regulating cell signaling and survival in mice</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>428</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2017.05.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28579317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>A cell-specific nuclear receptor is essential for adrenal and gonadal development and sexual differentiation</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(94)90211-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8187173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jameson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Dax1 is required for testis determination</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12679814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizusaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ariyoshi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morohashi</surname><given-names>K-I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Dax-1 (dosage-sensitive sex reversal-adrenal hypoplasia congenita critical region on the X chromosome, gene 1) gene transcription is regulated by wnt4 in the female developing gonad</article-title><source>Molecular Endocrinology</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/me.2002-0362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12554773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Conneely</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Neuroendocrine regulation of the hypothalamic pituitary adrenal axis by the nurr1/nur77 subfamily of nuclear receptors</article-title><source>Molecular Endocrinology</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/mend.11.1.9874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8994186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nasif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>FSJ</given-names></name><name><surname>González</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orquera</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Islet 1 specifies the identity of hypothalamic melanocortin neurons and is critical for normal food intake and adiposity in adulthood</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>E1861</fpage><lpage>E1870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1500672112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25825735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orquera</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavella</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>FSJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>The Homeodomain Transcription Factor NKX2.1 Is Essential for the Early Specification of Melanocortin Neuron Identity and Activates Pomc Expression in the Developing Hypothalamus</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>4023</fpage><lpage>4035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2924-18.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30886014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padilla</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeltser</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Pomc-expressing progenitors give rise to antagonistic neuronal populations in hypothalamic feeding circuits</article-title><source>Nature Medicine</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.2126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20348924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perlmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallén-Mackenzie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Nurr1, an orphan nuclear receptor with essential functions in developing dopamine cells</article-title><source>Cell and Tissue Research</source><volume>318</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00441-004-0974-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15340833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017a</year><article-title>Single-cell mRNA quantification and differential analysis with Census</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28114287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chawla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pliner</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017b</year><article-title>Reversed graph embedding resolves complex single-cell trajectories</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quarta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisette</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Colldén</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Legutko</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>Y-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Reim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wierer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Rosa</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaus</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rausch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaker</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Strom</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Poher</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Thuc</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Cebrian-Serrano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellocchio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pflugfelder</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogueiras</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeltser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunwald Kadow</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>García-Cáceres</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Treier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Doege</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschöp</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Functional identity of hypothalamic melanocortin neurons depends on Tbx3</article-title><source>Nature Metabolism</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42255-018-0028-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32694784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogil</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Japón</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Absence of opioid stress-induced analgesia in mice lacking beta-endorphin by site-directed mutagenesis</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>93</volume><fpage>3995</fpage><lpage>4000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.9.3995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8633004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deem</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmiter</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>McKnight</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Fertility-regulating Kiss1 neurons arise from hypothalamic POMC-expressing progenitors</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>5549</fpage><lpage>5556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3614-14.2015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25855171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saucedo-Cardenas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintana-Hau</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smidt</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Mayo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Burbach</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Conneely</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Nurr1 is essential for the induction of the dopaminergic phenotype and the survival of ventral mesencephalic late dopaminergic precursor neurons</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>4013</fpage><lpage>4018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.7.4013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9520484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smits</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponnio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Conneely</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burbach</surname><given-names>JPH</given-names></name><name><surname>Smidt</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Involvement of Nurr1 in specifying the neurotransmitter identity of ventral midbrain dopaminergic neurons</article-title><source>European Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1731</fpage><lpage>1738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1460-9568.2003.02885.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srisai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouault</surname><given-names>AAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grobe</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebag</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>MRAP2 regulates ghrelin receptor signaling and hunger sensing</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>713</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-00747-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28959025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellingsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Austbø</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fjose</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Autoregulatory binding sites in the zebrafish six3a promoter region define a new recognition sequence for Six3 proteins</article-title><source>FEBS Journal</source><volume>277</volume><fpage>1761</fpage><lpage>1775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2010.07599.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toll</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruchas</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Calo’</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaveri</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Nociceptin/Orphanin FQ Receptor Structure, Signaling, Ligands, Functions, and Interactions with Opioid Systems</article-title><source>Pharmacological Reviews</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/pr.114.009209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26956246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cacchiarelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimsby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pokharel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lennon</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinn</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>The dynamics and regulators of cell fate decisions are revealed by pseudotemporal ordering of single cells</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24658644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hrabovszky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lechan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Distinct glutamatergic and GABAergic subsets of hypothalamic pro-opiomelanocortin neurons revealed by in situ hybridization in male rats and mice</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>521</volume><fpage>3287</fpage><lpage>3302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.23350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23640796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q-Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>clusterProfiler: an R package for comparing biological themes among gene clusters</article-title><source>Omics</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/omi.2011.0118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455463</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="sa0"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.72883.sa0</article-id><title-group><article-title>Editor's evaluation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>Joel K</given-names></name><role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><related-object id="sa0ro1" link-type="continued-by" object-id="10.1101/2021.05.12.443898" object-id-type="id" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2021.05.12.443898"/></front-stub><body><p>This study investigates the developmental origins of functionally distinct neuronal populations in the arcuate nucleus of the hypothalamus. This study reports the transcriptional program of develop of multiple subtypes of POMC neurons, which are important for multiple physiological and behavioral functions, including appetite. The paper uses cutting edge methods will be important for research studying the arcuate nucleus including regulating food intake and metabolism.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.72883.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>Joel K</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text id="box1"><p>Our editorial process produces two outputs: (i) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2021.05.12.443898">public reviews</ext-link> designed to be posted alongside <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.05.12.443898v3">the preprint</ext-link> for the benefit of readers; (ii) feedback on the manuscript for the authors, including requests for revisions, shown below. We also include an acceptance summary that explains what the editors found interesting or important about the work.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Developmental single-cell transcriptomics of hypothalamic POMC progenitors reveal the genetic trajectories of multiple neuropeptidergic phenotypes&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by 3 peer reviewers, one of whom is a member of our Board of Reviewing Editors, and the evaluation has been overseen by Marianne Bronner as the Senior Editor. The reviewers have opted to remain anonymous.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed their reviews with one another, and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) Showing in situ hybridization data for E11.5 markers in a coronal plane, where the ventricular and mantle layer can de distinguished, would help to resolve the question of whether Ebf-hi expression represents newly differentiated neurons that are in the process of migrating out of the ventricular zone. (This appears to be case from the E13.5 section in Figure 1F, but it is hard to tell.)</p><p>2) Addition of scRNA-seq data from earlier embryonic stages (i.e. E10.5 and/or E11.0) would help to identify the precursor to the population of immature POMC neurons that is captured by cluster 1.POMC-hi/Prdm12.</p><p>3) One question raised by these data are the presence of an inhibitory population of GABA releasing (ie Vgat-expressing) POMC neurons. This is controversial with some studies reporting this and others indicating that there are no GABAergic POMC neurons. Given the evidence for a developmental cluster that is evident even at P12, it is important to resolve this issue in the context of the authors report of a bona fide transcriptional cluster with these co-expression patterns. The authors should examine the colocalization of these Pomc/Vgat neurons using RNA-FISH and report their distribution across development.</p><p>4) Finally, several conclusions need to be tempered. Nonetheless, the paper will be an outstanding resource for the field. The discussion should be written to reflect the important resource of this data set.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>There seemed to be a substantial subset of microglia expressing Pomc (Figure 1), did the authors remove these from the dataset? How do they determine a bona fied Pomc neuron vs a neuron with Pomc mRNA contamination.</p><p>A supplemental model figure/cartoon integrating the various developmental trajectories with their defining transcriptional factors would be useful to visualize the key findings of the paper.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>• Showing in situ hybridization data for E11.5 markers in a coronal plane, where the ventricular and mantle layer can de distinguished, would help to resolve the question of whether Ebf-hi expression represents newly differentiated neurons that are in the process of migrating out of the ventricular zone. (This appears to be case from the E13.5 section in Figure 1F, but it is hard to tell.)</p><p>• Addition of scRNA-seq data from earlier embryonic stages (i.e. E10.5 and/or E11.0) would help to identify the precursor to the population of immature POMC neurons that is captured by cluster 1.POMC-hi/Prdm12.</p><p>• The number of total neurons changes dramatically across gestation, in large part because cells that adopt non-POMC fates turn off Pomc expression and are no longer captured by FACS. In Figure 1, reporting the absolute number of neurons in each cluster, instead expressing it as a percentage, would make it easier to interpret.</p><p>• Analyses shown in Figure 3 Supplemental Figures 3-4 are critical to resolve issues related to POMC progenitor heterogeneity. This information should be moved to the main figures. Maintaining a consistent color scheme between Figure 1 and Figure 3 Supplement 3 would make it much easier to interpret this data. The chart in Supplemental Figure 4 could then remain as a supplemental figure to reinforce this point.</p><p>• Trajectory analyses shown in Figure 5 should include separate analyses of 2.Pomc-med/Ebf1 and 3.Pomc-med/Nra2, as they appear to map onto different populations in the mature ARH (Supplemental Figure 15)</p><p>• There are discrepancies between the text (lines 489-497) and Supplementary file 14, which do not link 3.Pomc-med/Nr4a2 neurons to mature POMC populations and Supplementary file 15, which does, making it difficult to interpret these data.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #3 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>This manuscript by Yu et al. beautifully captures the transcriptional heterogeneity of mouse POMC neurons across hypothalamic development. This study unifies multiple other observations about the role for other neuron al cell types that express POMC transiently during development. The paper is an important contribution to understanding of the diversity of POMC neuron classes and their relationship to other cell types in the arcuate nucleus.</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were suggested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><p>Thank you for resubmitting your work entitled &quot;Developmental single-cell transcriptomics of hypothalamic POMC neurons reveal the genetic trajectories of multiple neuropeptidergic phenotypes&quot; for further consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your revised article has been reviewed by 2 peer reviewers and the evaluation has been overseen by Marianne Bronner as the Senior Editor, and a Reviewing Editor.</p><p>The revisions by the authors improved the manuscript. These data will be a valuable resource for the field. However, there are a few important points that should be corrected or clarified in a final version.</p><p>1. Characterization of Ebf1 expression</p><p>The claim that Ebf1 expression at E11.5 is localized to the mantle layer (line 201) and the labels in the accompanying Figure 1E are not accurate. Expression of Pomc and Ebf1 are located within the ventricular zone (VZ), albeit toward the lateral edge, as indicated by the dense DAPI stain. The mantle layer &quot;ML&quot; is label is not accurate; there is almost no &quot;mantle layer&quot; in the mediobasal hypothalamus at E11.5. Also, the differentiating zone indicated at the lateral edge of the VZ in Figure 1E is not striatal.</p><p>Note that Figure 2-Figure Suppl 1A shows co-expression of Pomc and Ebf1 at the border between the VZ and ML at E13.5. There appears to be more co-expression on the VZ side than the ML side. The expression pattern shown here is consistent with reports in other regions of the developing CNS, where EBFs have been implicated in regulating migration out of the VZ.</p><p>2. Lines 474-5 &quot;The diffusion maps analysis appears to confirm the multiple origins of POMC progenitor cells demonstrated by the RNA velocity study.&quot;</p><p>This is a confusing sentence because &quot;POMC progenitors&quot; is not the accurate terminology to use. It is easier to just eliminate this sentence.</p><p>3. Discussion of Ebf1+/cluster 2 neurons</p><p>Lines 614-6 &quot;The expression profile of cluster 2.Pomc<sup>(med)</sup>614 /Ebf1 differs from cluster 1.Pomc<sup>(high)</sup>615 /Prdm12 most particularly at the earliest developmental ages E11.5 to E15.5 and may both represent alternative genetic routes leading to mature POMC neurons.&quot;</p><p>There is no evidence that the Ebf1+/cluster 2 neurons develop into mature neurons of any sort. The analysis in Figure 6 depicts the Ebf1+/cluster 2 neurons as a dead end in Ray 1 (i.e. retains immature properties). Since the transcriptomics performed here relied on the expression of a Pomc-GFP transgene, it is possible that cluster 2 neurons differentiate into mature non-POMC cell types. The sentence should be corrected by swapping &quot;arcuate&quot; for &quot;POMC&quot;.</p><p>4. Discussion of developmental origins of NPY and KNDy neurons Lines 619-626 are confusing.</p><p>Timing question: With regard to NPY and KNDy neurons, which are known to derive from Pomc-expressing neurons, the authors argue that they arise &quot;earlier than expected &quot;(presumably at E11.5). And yet, according to the developmental clustering (Figure 4) and developmental trajectory analyses (Figure 6 supplement 1), meaningful numbers of Otp+/cluster 4 (future NPY) and Tac2+/cluster 5 (future KNDy) neuron precursors emerge at E13.5, consistent with reports in the literature.</p><p>Developmental lineage: These analyses also support the idea that Otp+/cluster 4 (future NPY) neurons share the same developmental trajectory as Prdm12+/cluster 1 (future POMC) neurons (Figure 6) as well as a common precursor (E13.5-4, Figure 4). This should be explicitly discussed. These studies do not provide clues into the origin of the Tac2+/cluster 5 (future KNDy) neurons.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.72883.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) Showing in situ hybridization data for E11.5 markers in a coronal plane, where the ventricular and mantle layer can de distinguished, would help to resolve the question of whether Ebf-hi expression represents newly differentiated neurons that are in the process of migrating out of the ventricular zone. (This appears to be case from the E13.5 section in Figure 1F, but it is hard to tell.)</p></disp-quote><p>As suggested by reviewer #2, we performed in situ hybridization studies using antisense RNAscope probes to simultaneously label <italic>Pomc</italic> and <italic>Ebf1</italic> expression in coronal sections of E11.5 embryos at the level of the developing basal hypothalamus. Using this additional embryonic time point and plane sectioning (in the original manuscript we had shown sagittal sections of E13.5 mouse embryos), we confirmed that <italic>Ebf1</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic> co-express in many cells located in the mantle zone of the developing hypothalamus, as can be observed in the newly submitted Figure 2E and Figure 2—figure supplement 1. The previously shown Figure 2F is now included in Figure 2—figure supplement 1. As a consequence of including this new supplement figure, the previous Figure 2—figure supplement 1 is now named Figure 2—figure supplement 2 and its reference changed in the Results section (line 184-195). It is worth mentioning that the level of <italic>Ebf1</italic> expression in the developing hypothalamus is much lower than that found in other areas of the same sections, such as the striatal differentiating zone (SDZ) and mesenchyme (MES) as clearly observed in Figure 2E. Our scRNA-seq study shows that the expression level of <italic>Ebf1</italic> in POMC cells is highest at E11.5, diminishes at E13.5, is even further reduced at E15.5 and completely disappears from E17.5 and beyond (Figure 2D). These results are confirmed by in situ hybridization (Figure 2E and Figure 2—figure supplement 1). Because <italic>Ebf1</italic> has been involved in the control of cell differentiation and migration of early neurons from the subventricular zone to the mantle in the developing striatum (Garel, Marin, Grosschedl, and Charnay, 1999), it is tempting to speculate that <italic>Ebf1</italic> plays a similar role in early <italic>Pomc</italic>-expressing hypothalamic cells. However, our data precludes us from making such a conclusion at this point and further studies will be necessary to evaluate the functional role of <italic>Ebf1</italic> during the ontogeny of hypothalamic POMC neurons.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) Addition of scRNA-seq data from earlier embryonic stages (i.e. E10.5 and/or E11.0) would help to identify the precursor to the population of immature POMC neurons that is captured by cluster 1.POMC-hi/Prdm12.</p></disp-quote><p>The reviewer points to a very interesting question which in our hands turned up to be technically more challenging than expected. At the initial design of this study, we sought to FACS cells from E10.5 developing hypothalami to capture the transcriptome at the onset of <italic>Pomc</italic> expression. However, the number of fluorescent cells in <italic>Pomc</italic>-dsRed transgenic E10.5 embryos was very small probably due to the existing delay between the onset of <italic>Pomc</italic>-driven transcription of the transgene and the translation of the early dsRed mRNAs into the fluorescent protein Tdimer2. In our hands, we need at least 17,000 cells to finally obtain 10,000 FACS cells for sequencing. In our current study, primary cells from POMC-TdDsRed/+ mice were first FACS sorted for the transgenic red fluorophore. The sorting percentage for POMC-TdDsRed cells is only 1-2%. Thus, it is very challenging to collect enough cells for FACS followed by scRNA-seq library preparation. We have previously reported using either an anti- ACTH antibody or anti-EGFP antibody in Pomc-EGFP E10.5 embryos that the number of cells expressing proteins from the <italic>Pomc</italic> gene or <italic>Pomc</italic> transgenes are very limited at this stage (Nasif et al., 2015, PNAS, Figure 1A and Hael et al., 2020 Mol Metab, Figure 1) (Hael, Rojo, Orquera, Low, and Rubinstein, 2020; Nasif et al., 2015).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) One question raised by these data are the presence of an inhibitory population of GABA releasing (ie Vgat-expressing) POMC neurons. This is controversial with some studies reporting this and others indicating that there are no GABAergic POMC neurons. Given the evidence for a developmental cluster that is evident even at P12, it is important to resolve this issue in the context of the authors report of a bona fide transcriptional cluster with these co-expression patterns. The authors should examine the colocalization of these Pomc/Vgat neurons using RNA-FISH and report their distribution across development.</p></disp-quote><p>Typically, neurons are classified as either glutamatergic based on their expression of one or more vesicular glutamate transporters VGLUT1, VGLUT2 and VGLUT3 mRNAs (<italic>Slc17a7, Slc17a6 and Slc17a8,</italic> respectively) or GABAergic based on their expression of the vesicular GABA and glycine transporter VGAT (<italic>Slc32a1</italic>). Alternatively, GABAergic neurons are identified by expression of the synthetic enzymes glutamate decarboxylase 1 or 2 (<italic>Gad67</italic> and <italic>Gad65</italic>, respectively). None of these three last mentioned markers can definitively identify a GABAergic neuron and we do not report the coexpression of <italic>Pomc</italic> and <italic>Slc32a1</italic> in our manuscript. Moreover, triple in situ hybridization studies have demonstrated that subpopulations of POMC neurons express both <italic>Slc17a6</italic> and <italic>Gad65</italic> and the proportions of these neurons change during early postnatal life in the mouse (Jones et al., 2019; Wittmann, Hrabovszky, and Lechan, 2013). Synaptic storage and release of GABA from neuronal terminals after appropriate stimulation is in our view the definitive means to identify a neuron as GABAergic. Several publications have shown by E-physiology that some subpopulations of POMC neurons induce ipsps that can be blocked by GABA receptor antagonists (Hentges, Otero-Corchon, Pennock, King, and Low, 2009). Although VGAT expression has indeed not been found in POMC neurons, they do express VMAT as shown in Figure 3—figure supplement 1 and VMAT can act as an alternative synaptic GABA vesicular transporter in dopamine neurons (German, Baladi, McFadden, Hanson, and Fleckenstein, 2015).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) Finally, several conclusions need to be tempered. Nonetheless, the paper will be an outstanding resource for the field. The discussion should be written to reflect the important resource of this data set.</p></disp-quote><p>As suggested by the reviewer we shortened some paragraphs of the Discussion to focus on the most important and less speculative matters. We have also tempered some conclusions and highlighted the importance and usefulness of this resource for future studies by many investigators worldwide. All changes in the revised Discussion are indicated in the revised manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>There seemed to be a substantial subset of microglia expressing Pomc (Figure 1), did the authors remove these from the dataset? How do they determine a bona fied Pomc neuron vs a neuron with Pomc mRNA contamination.</p></disp-quote><p>A general caveat of the scRNA sequencing technique is the potential contamination with RNA molecules from other cells present in the sample or even from the environment. Although this possibility can never be completely ruled out, in our study we used fluorescence assisted cell sorting from medial basal hypothalami collected from POMC-DsRed transgenic mice to enrich the population of cells to be analyzed at the single cell level. In addition, we took several levels of precaution to limit, monitor and discard potential cases of cross contamination events: (1) We applied stringent filtering criteria to exclude doublets and low quality cells as described in the Materials and methods section; (2) We performed an independent unsupervised analysis on cells expressing the transgenic red fluorophore (DsRed) while ignoring <italic>Pomc</italic> UMI criteria per cell (Figure1—figure supplement 2 and Figure 1—figure supplement 3) and we found similar clustering at each developmental age compared to clustering based on <italic>Pomc</italic> UMI criteria of &gt; = 1. (3) To validate each cluster, we performed dual RNAscope in situ hybridization to confirm the colocalization of <italic>Pomc</italic> and feature genes from each cluster (Figure 2, Figure 3 and their linked supplemental figures). The glial cell clusters in this study were defined by showing simultaneous expression of high levels of several marker genes selectively representing microglia, VLMC, or Astrocytes (Figure 1C), and the absence of neuronal markers whereas a reciprocal criterion was used to define neuronal clusters. Because the current study focuses on <italic>Pomc</italic> expressing neurons, we have only studied and reported neuronal clusters (1-8) in greater detail.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>A supplemental model figure/cartoon integrating the various developmental trajectories with their defining transcriptional factors would be useful to visualize the key findings of the paper.</p></disp-quote><p>The reviewer’s suggestion is a genuine interest we had for a long time. Unfortunately, we have been unable to capture in a single schematic the design and most meaningful results of this complex work without duplicating graphs already shown in Figures 1, 2, 3 and 6 of this manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>• Showing in situ hybridization data for E11.5 markers in a coronal plane, where the ventricular and mantle layer can de distinguished, would help to resolve the question of whether Ebf-hi expression represents newly differentiated neurons that are in the process of migrating out of the ventricular zone. (This appears to be case from the E13.5 section in Figure 1F, but it is hard to tell.)</p></disp-quote><p>This question was answered in the Essential Revision 1</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>• Addition of scRNA-seq data from earlier embryonic stages (i.e. E10.5 and/or E11.0) would help to identify the precursor to the population of immature POMC neurons that is captured by cluster 1.POMC-hi/Prdm12.</p></disp-quote><p>This question was answered in the Essential Revision 2.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>• The number of total neurons changes dramatically across gestation, in large part because cells that adopt non-POMC fates turn off Pomc expression and are no longer captured by FACS. In Figure 1, reporting the absolute number of neurons in each cluster, instead expressing it as a percentage, would make it easier to interpret.</p></disp-quote><p>We appreciate the reviewer’s suggestion and have edited Figure 1 accordingly.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>• Analyses shown in Figure 3 Supplemental Figures 3-4 are critical to resolve issues related to POMC progenitor heterogeneity. This information should be moved to the main figures. Maintaining a consistent color scheme between Figure 1 and Figure 3 Supplement 3 would make it much easier to interpret this data. The chart in Supplemental Figure 4 could then remain as a supplemental figure to reinforce this point.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer’s suggestion and have edited Figure 3 Supplemental Figure3-4 accordingly in this revised version of the manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>• Trajectory analyses shown in Figure 5 should include separate analyses of 2.Pomc-med/Ebf1 and 3.Pomc-med/Nra2, as they appear to map onto different populations in the mature ARH (Supplemental Figure 15).</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with the reviewer that the interpretation of original Supplementary Figure15 is not straightforward and may be misleading. Therefore, we decided to remove this comparative analysis from the Results section and its corresponding figures. Based on the reviewer’s comment, the original Figure 5 became Figure 6.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>• There are discrepancies between the text (lines 489-497) and Supplementary file 14, which do not link 3.Pomc-med/Nr4a2 neurons to mature POMC populations and Supplementary file 15, which does, making it difficult to interpret these data.</p></disp-quote><p>This part has been removed from the Results section.</p><p>References</p><p>Garel, S., Marin, F., Grosschedl, R., &amp; Charnay, P. (1999). Ebf1 controls early cell differentiation in the embryonic striatum. <italic>Development, 126</italic>(23), 5285-5294.</p><p>German, C. L., Baladi, M. G., McFadden, L. M., Hanson, G. R., &amp; Fleckenstein, A. E. (2015). Regulation of the Dopamine and Vesicular Monoamine Transporters: Pharmacological Targets and Implications for Disease. <italic>Pharmacol Rev, 67</italic>(4), 1005-1024. doi:10.1124/pr.114.010397</p><p>Hael, C. E., Rojo, D., Orquera, D. P., Low, M. J., &amp; Rubinstein, M. (2020). The transcriptional regulator PRDM12 is critical for Pomc expression in the mouse hypothalamus and controlling food intake, adiposity, and body weight. <italic>Mol Metab, 34</italic>, 43-53. doi:10.1016/j.molmet.2020.01.007</p><p>Hentges, S. T., Otero-Corchon, V., Pennock, R. L., King, C. M., &amp; Low, M. J. (2009). Proopiomelanocortin expression in both GABA and glutamate neurons. <italic>J Neurosci, 29</italic>(43), 13684-13690. doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3770-09.2009</p><p>Jones, G. L., Wittmann, G., Yokosawa, E. B., Yu, H., Mercer, A. J., Lechan, R. M., &amp; Low, M. J. (2019). Selective Restoration of Pomc Expression in Glutamatergic POMC Neurons: Evidence for a Dynamic Hypothalamic Neurotransmitter Network. <italic>eNeuro, 6</italic>(2). doi:10.1523/ENEURO.0400-18.2019</p><p>Nasif, S., de Souza, F. S., Gonzalez, L. E., Yamashita, M., Orquera, D. P., Low, M. J., &amp; Rubinstein, M. (2015). Islet 1 specifies the identity of hypothalamic melanocortin neurons and is critical for normal food intake and adiposity in adulthood. <italic>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, 112</italic>(15), E1861-1870. doi:10.1073/pnas.1500672112</p><p>Wittmann, G., Hrabovszky, E., &amp; Lechan, R. M. (2013). Distinct glutamatergic and GABAergic subsets of hypothalamic pro-opiomelanocortin neurons revealed by in situ hybridization in male rats and mice. <italic>J Comp Neurol, 521</italic>(14), 3287-3302. doi:10.1002/cne.23350</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were suggested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>The revisions by the authors improved the manuscript. These data will be a valuable resource for the field. However, there are a few important points that should be corrected or clarified in a final version.</p><p>1. Characterization of Ebf1 expression</p><p>The claim that Ebf1 expression at E11.5 is localized to the mantle layer (line 201) and the labels in the accompanying Figure 1E are not accurate. Expression of Pomc and Ebf1 are located within the ventricular zone (VZ), albeit toward the lateral edge, as indicated by the dense DAPI stain. The mantle layer &quot;ML&quot; is label is not accurate; there is almost no &quot;mantle layer&quot; in the mediobasal hypothalamus at E11.5. Also, the differentiating zone indicated at the lateral edge of the VZ in Figure 1E is not striatal.</p><p>Note that Figure 2-Figure Suppl 1A shows co-expression of Pomc and Ebf1 at the border between the VZ and ML at E13.5. There appears to be more co-expression on the VZ side than the ML side. The expression pattern shown here is consistent with reports in other regions of the developing CNS, where EBFs have been implicated in regulating migration out of the VZ.</p></disp-quote><p>In agreement with the reviewer’s comment, we have modified the sentence (line 186-189) indicating now that the co-expression of <italic>Ebf1</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic> occurs at the ventricular zone. Accordingly, we have modified the labels in Figure 2E. Concerning the reviewer’s suggestion that <italic>Ebf1</italic> may regulate cell migration out of the VZ during neuronal development, we have now include this hypothesis in the Discussion section (lines 514 – 517).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2. Lines 474-5 &quot;The diffusion maps analysis appears to confirm the multiple origins of POMC progenitor cells demonstrated by the RNA velocity study.&quot;</p><p>This is a confusing sentence because &quot;POMC progenitors&quot; is not the accurate terminology to use. It is easier to just eliminate this sentence.</p></disp-quote><p>Following the reviewer’s suggestion we have deleted this sentence in the newly revised manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3. Discussion of Ebf1+/cluster 2 neurons</p><p>Lines 614-6 &quot;The expression profile of cluster 2.Pomc<sup>(med)</sup>614 /Ebf1 differs from cluster 1.Pomc<sup>(high)</sup>615 /Prdm12 most particularly at the earliest developmental ages E11.5 to E15.5 and may both represent alternative genetic routes leading to mature POMC neurons.&quot;</p><p>There is no evidence that the Ebf1+/cluster 2 neurons develop into mature neurons of any sort. The analysis in Figure 6 depicts the Ebf1+/cluster 2 neurons as a dead end in Ray 1 (i.e. retains immature properties). Since the transcriptomics performed here relied on the expression of a Pomc-GFP transgene, it is possible that cluster 2 neurons differentiate into mature non-POMC cell types. The sentence should be corrected by swapping &quot;arcuate&quot; for &quot;POMC&quot;.</p></disp-quote><p>Following the reviewer’s suggestion, we have replaced “POMC” with “arcuate” in the newly revised manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4. Discussion of developmental origins of NPY and KNDy neurons Lines 619-626 are confusing.</p><p>Timing question: With regard to NPY and KNDy neurons, which are known to derive from Pomc-expressing neurons, the authors argue that they arise &quot;earlier than expected &quot;(presumably at E11.5). And yet, according to the developmental clustering (Figure 4) and developmental trajectory analyses (Figure 6 supplement 1), meaningful numbers of Otp+/cluster 4 (future NPY) and Tac2+/cluster 5 (future KNDy) neuron precursors emerge at E13.5, consistent with reports in the literature.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer’s constructive suggestion and have revised this sentence accordingly (lines 520 – 523).</p><p>We would like to remark that POMC cells from cluster 4 display relatively high levels of <italic>Ot</italic>p already at E11.5. Although <italic>Npy</italic> and <italic>Agrp</italic> transcripts only peak up days later, the early presence of <italic>Otp</italic> at E11.5 is likely an active marker for the differentiation pathway leading to the AGRP phenotype. We would also like to point out that developmental subclustering of POMC cells only at E11.5 revealed a small but distinct group of related cells (E11.5-9) featuring <italic>Otp</italic> (Figure 4-Source Data2). This subcluster shares high similarity to <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> cluster in regards to the gene expression profiles (comparing Figure 4-Source Data 2 to Figure 1-Source Data 2). In situ hybridization studies shown by the Allen Developmental Mouse Brain Atlas also confirmed the expression of <italic>Otp</italic> in the developing hypothalamus at E11.5 and it is likely these early <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> cells are the precursors of AGRP/NPY neurons at later embryonic stages, although this hypothesis requires further investigation.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Developmental lineage: These analyses also support the idea that Otp+/cluster 4 (future NPY) neurons share the same developmental trajectory as Prdm12+/cluster 1 (future POMC) neurons (Figure 6) as well as a common precursor (E13.5-4, Figure 4). This should be explicitly discussed. These studies do not provide clues into the origin of the Tac2+/cluster 5 (future KNDy) neurons.</p></disp-quote><p>We thoroughly examined our raw data. We agree that the <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> neurons share the common precursors as <italic>Pomc</italic> <sup>(high)</sup> / <italic>Prdm12</italic> cluster, as shown by the RNA-velocity trajectory analysis in Figure 6A and Figure 6—figure supplement 1B and by the transcriptomic analysis at individual developmental stages (Figure 4—figure supplement 1). We have now addressed this issue in the revised manuscript (Line 528-530).</p><p>The reviewer pointed out the existence of common precursor (E13.5-4, Figure 4), indicating the <italic>Otp+</italic>/cluster 4 (future NPY) neurons share the same developmental trajectory as <italic>Prdm12+</italic>/cluster 1 (future POMC) neurons. We have carefully re-examined the Figure 4 and its associated supplement figures and source data and confirmed that the gene profiles in E11.5-9 and E13.5-4 subclusters are highly similar to that of <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> cluster with the feature genes – <italic>Otp</italic>, <italic>Calcr</italic>, and <italic>Sst</italic>. We also found these two clusters share genes that are highly expressed in <italic>Pomc</italic> <sup>(high)</sup> / <italic>Prdm12,</italic> such as <italic>Dlk1, Six3, Six6, Cited1, Isl1 and Peg3</italic>. That’s why we consider E11.5-9 and E13.5-4 subclusters as the common origins for both <italic>Pomc</italic><sup>(low)</sup><italic>/Otp</italic> and <italic>Pomc</italic> <sup>(high)</sup> / <italic>Prdm12</italic> clusters (Figure 4—figure supplement 1). It worth noting that AGRP neurons share several similarities with POMC neurons in terms of transcription profiles although their physiological functions are opposite. For example, <italic>Tbx3</italic> is expressed in both AGRP and POMC neurons, although its role appears to be different in each cell type based on the phenotype observed in the individual conditional mouse mutants.</p></body></sub-article></article>