<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">27595</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Developmental Biology and Stem Cells</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fish larval recruitment to reefs is a thyroid hormone-mediated metamorphosis sensitive to the pesticide chlorpyrifos</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-85655"><name><surname>Holzer</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name><email>guillaume.holzer@ens-lyon.fr</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">†</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-85527"><name><surname>Besson</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3381-322X</contrib-id><email>marc.besson@ens-lyon.org</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">†</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-85656"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-85912"><name><surname>François</surname><given-names>Loïc</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-85658"><name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-85659"><name><surname>Gillet</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-85660"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>Sandrine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-85661"><name><surname>Piganeau</surname><given-names>Gwenaël</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-16860"><name><surname>Leulier</surname><given-names>Francois</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con9"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-98944"><name><surname>Viriot</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con10"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-44002"><name><surname>Lecchini</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib2">‡</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con11"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-85582"><name><surname>Laudet</surname><given-names>Vincent</given-names></name><email>vincent.laudet@obs-banyuls.fr</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib2">‡</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con12"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Institut de Génomique Fonctionnelle de Lyon</institution><institution>Université de Lyon, Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1, UMR CNRS 5242, Ecole Normale Supérieure de Lyon</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Lyon</named-content></addr-line><country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">CRIOBE USR3278 EPHE-UPVD-CNRS</institution><institution>PSL Research University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Moorea</named-content></addr-line><country>French Polynesia</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Observatoire Océanologique de Banyuls-sur-Mer</institution><institution>UMR CNRS 7232, Université Pierre et Marie Curie Paris</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Paris</named-content></addr-line><country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Laboratoire d'Excellence CORAIL</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Moorea</named-content></addr-line><country>French Polynesia</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor" id="author-1052"><name><surname>Bronner</surname><given-names>Marianne</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>California Institute of Technology</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="equal-contrib1"><label>†</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="equal-contrib2"><label>‡</label><p>These authors also contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e27595</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2017-04-07"><day>07</day><month>04</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2017-10-02"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2017, Holzer et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Holzer et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-27595-v1.pdf"/><related-object ext-link-type="url" xlink:href="https://elifesciences.org/articles/e27595v1"><date date-type="v1" iso-8601-date="2017-10-30"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date></related-object><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.001</object-id><p>Larval recruitment, the transition of pelagic larvae into reef-associated juveniles, is a critical step for the resilience of marine fish populations but its molecular control is unknown. Here, we investigate whether thyroid-hormones (TH) and their receptors (TR) coordinate the larval recruitment of the coral-reef-fish <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic>. We demonstrate an increase of TH-levels and <italic>TR</italic>-expressions in pelagic-larvae, followed by a decrease in recruiting juveniles. We generalize these observations in four other coral reef-fish species. Treatments with TH or TR-antagonist, as well as relocation to the open-ocean, disturb <italic>A. triostegus</italic> larvae transformation and grazing activity. Likewise, chlorpyrifos, a pesticide often encountered in coral-reefs, impairs <italic>A. triostegus</italic> TH-levels, transformation, and grazing activity, hence diminishing this herbivore’s ability to control the spread of reef-algae. Larval recruitment therefore corresponds to a TH-controlled metamorphosis, sensitive to endocrine disruption. This provides a framework to understand how larval recruitment, critical to reef-ecosystems maintenance, is altered by anthropogenic stressors.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>Many animals go through a larval phase before developing into an adult. This transformation is called metamorphosis, and it is regulated by hormones of the thyroid gland in vertebrates. For example, most fish found on coral reefs actually spend the first part of their life as free-swimming larvae out in the ocean. The larvae usually look very different from the juveniles and adults. When these fish become juveniles, the larvae undergo a range of physical and behavioral changes to prepare for their life on the reef. Yet, until now it was not known what hormones control metamorphosis in these fish.</p><p>To address this question, Holzer, Besson et al. studied the convict surgeonfish <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic>. This herbivorous coral-reef fish lives in the Indo-Pacific Ocean, and the results showed that thyroid hormones do indeed regulate the metamorphosis of its larvae. This includes changing how the larvae behave and how their adult features develop. Further, Holzer, Besson et al. found that this was also true for four other coral-reef fish, including the lagoon triggerfish and the raccoon butterflyfish. In <italic>A. triostegus</italic>, thyroid hormones controlled the changes that enabled the juveniles to efficiently graze on algae growing on the reef such as an elongated gut.</p><p>When the fish larvae were then exposed to a pesticide called chlorpyrifos, a well-known reef pollutant, their hormone production was disturbed. This in turn affected their grazing behavior and also their metamorphosis. These fish had shortened, underdeveloped guts and could not graze on algae as effectively.</p><p>Herbivorous fish such as <italic>A. triostegus</italic> play a major role in supporting coral reef ecosystems by reducing algal cover and therefore promoting coral recruitment. These new findings show that pollutants from human activities could disturb the metamorphosis of coral-reef fish and, as a consequence, their ability to maintain the reefs. A next step will be to test what other factors can disrupt the hormones in coral-reef fish and thus pose a threat for fish populations and the coral-reef ecosystem.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>Thyroid hormones</kwd><kwd>Metamorphosis</kwd><kwd>Coral reef fish</kwd><kwd>Chlorpyrifos</kwd><kwd>Acanthurus triostegus</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Other</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>No external funding was received for this work</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Coral reef fish larval recruitment is a metamorphosis that can be disturbed by reef pollutants, as it is under the influence of the environment through the direct control of thyroid hormone signaling.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Life history transitions are critical for many animal species and often correspond to concomitant developmental and ecological shifts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bishop et al., 2006</xref>). Unfortunately, little is known about how internal and external cues act in concert during these events. The life cycle of most teleost reef fish include a major developmental and ecological transition. Adults reproduce in the vicinity of the reef, emitting eggs that disperse and hatch in the ocean, where the larvae grow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Leis and McCormick, 2002</xref>). Larvae migrate back and enter reefs where they become juveniles, a step called larval recruitment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Leis and McCormick, 2002</xref>). This step involves the perception of environmental cues for larvae to localize and settle in the reef, and is accompanied by major morphological changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">McCormick et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lecchini et al., 2005b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">2005a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Lecchini et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Barth, 2015</xref>). This transition of pelagic larvae into reef-associated juveniles is often referred to as metamorphosis and is critical for the maintenance of reef fish populations, but its molecular control remains largely unknown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Dufour and Galzin, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Doherty, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Leis and McCormick, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">McCormick et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Dixson et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Barth, 2015</xref>). Since larval recruitment is an ecological event coupled to a morphological transformation, reminiscent of the situation in amphibians, it may correspond to a thyroid hormones (TH) controlled metamorphosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bishop et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brown and Cai, 2007</xref>).</p><p>TH and their receptors (TR) trigger and coordinate metamorphosis of many species such as <italic>Xenopus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brown and Cai, 2007</xref>) or flatfish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Solbakken et al., 1999</xref>). The thyroid gland produces mainly the thyroxine hormone (T4), which is peripherally transformed into triiodothyronine (T3), the active form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Chopra, 1996</xref>). The transformation of T4 into T3, and the degradation of T4 and T3 are controlled by a family of enzymes called deiodinases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bianco and Kim, 2006</xref>). TH levels peak at the climax of metamorphosis. Precocious treatment with TH triggers metamorphosis whereas goitrogen (TH synthesis inhibitors) treatment blocks it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Tata, 2006</xref>). Similar mechanisms have been described in several teleost fishes, but in contexts disconnected from the natural environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brown, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">de Jesus et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Yamano and Miwa, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kawakami et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Marchand et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">McMenamin and Parichy, 2013</xref>).</p><p>In the convict surgeonfish <italic>Acanthurus triostegus,</italic> larvae have a planktonic diet while juveniles and adults are herbivorous, and external morphological changes occurring at recruitment have been previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Randall, 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">McCormick, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">McCormick et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Frédérich et al., 2012</xref>). Interestingly, crest-captured larvae can delay their metamorphosis when relocated to the external slope of the reef (open ocean), showing an influence of the environment on their morphological transformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">McCormick, 1999</xref>). Nevertheless, again, the molecular mechanisms remain unknown.</p><p>Here we report that <italic>A. triostegus</italic> larval recruitment to the reefs corresponds to metamorphosis with major pigmentation changes, remodeling of the digestive tract and behavioral modifications. Our results show that TH levels and <italic>TR</italic> expressions control this remodeling process. Furthermore, recruiting larvae can freeze their TH signaling when relocated on the external slope, demonstrating an influence of the environment on metamorphosis. Chlorpyrifos (CPF), a known reef pollutant and endocrine disruptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Roche et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Botté et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Juberg et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Slotkin et al., 2013</xref>), affects <italic>A. triostegus</italic> metamorphosis by impairing TH signaling, preventing intestine lengthening, and inhibiting fish grazing activity. CPF therefore impairs <italic>A. triostegus</italic> control on algae spreading, which is a major threat for reef conservation. We extend our observation upon TH levels to four other coral reef fish species. Our work provides a unifying framework that integrates the developmental, ecological and evolutionary perspectives of vertebrate life history transitions. The involvement of the TH signaling pathway in this key post-embryonic step, thus prone to endocrine disruption, provides an obvious entry point to study how anthropogenic stressors may affect reef fish populations.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title><italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> larvae undergo a major and rapid remodeling at recruitment</title><p><italic>A. triostegus</italic> crest captured individuals (n = 297) experience an important weight loss between day 1 (0.71 ± 0.01 g) and day 8 (0.53 ± 0.01 g) following their entry in the reef (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A–B</xref>). Individuals also undergo extensive pigmentation changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C–L</xref>), as exemplified by the very rapid appearance of black stripes (less than four hours, MB pers. obs.) after entering the reef (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C–D, H-I</xref>). This is followed by the widening of these vertical black stripes and by the onset of the body’s white pigmentation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D–G</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1I–L</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.003</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Changes in <italic>Acanthrurus triostegus</italic> during larval recruitment.</title><p>Error bars represent standard errors. *p-value&lt;0.05; **p-value&lt;0.01; ***p-value&lt;0.001. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematization of the reef colonization by a larva (left) turning into a juvenile (right). The background color shading centered into the reef crest is re-used in following figures. (<bold>B</bold>) Weight variation during larval recruitment. n = 3 biological replicates for 5-to-10 km offshore fish (far), n = 5 for 2 km offshore fish (near) and n = 297 for crest to day 8 (d8) fish. Statistics: mean comparisons (Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney U-test). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata1">Figure 1—source data 1</xref> for detailed data and statistics. (<bold>C–G</bold>) Variation in pigmentation and morphology at different sampling points, (<bold>C</bold>) crest larva, (<bold>D</bold>) day 2 juvenile, (<bold>E</bold>) day 3 juvenile, (<bold>F</bold>) day 5 juvenile and (<bold>G</bold>) day 8 juvenile; scale bars indicate 0.5 cm. The white square represent the magnified region shown in the line below. These pictures are representative of n &gt; 50 fish (biological replicates) per developmental stage, sampled at n &gt; 20 different times during the year (technical replicates). (<bold>H–L</bold>) Close-up on the pigmented middle body band. Scale bars indicate 0.2 cm. These pictures are representative of n &gt; 50 fish (biological replicates) per developmental stage, sampled at n &gt; 20 different times during the year (technical replicates). (<bold>M–Q</bold>) X-Ray microtomography of larva, dentition A, B or C are highlighted respectively in red, blue or green. Scale bars indicate 0.5 mm. These pictures are representative of n = 2 fish (biological replicates) per developmental stage. (<bold>R–V</bold>) Histological sections (5 µm width) of intestines with haematoxylin/eosin staining. Scale bars indicate 200 µm. These pictures are representative of n = 6 sectioning technical replicates, performed twice (sampling technical replicates), on n = 2 fish (biological replicate). (<bold>W</bold>) Intestine length variation of <italic>A. triostegus</italic> during its larval recruitment. n = 9 to 14 biological replicates for each developmental stage (from n = 2 technical sampling replicates). Statistics: mean comparisons (Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney U-test). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig1sdata2">Figure 1—source data 2</xref> for detailed data and statistics. (<bold>X</bold>) Heatmap clustering of the 18S sequences identified in the intestine content of crest individual (n = 3, left panel), day 8 juveniles (n = 3, middle panel) and adults (n = 3, right panel). Each panel is made of three columns corresponding to one individual. Each line corresponds to one taxonomic group found in the intestines: <italic>Spermatophyta</italic> (dark green), <italic>Conoidasisa</italic> (cyan), <italic>Dinophyceae</italic> (light yellow), <italic>Protostomia</italic> (light mink), <italic>Phaeophyceae</italic> (brown), <italic>Florideophycae</italic> (dark pink), <italic>Chlorophyta</italic> (light green), <italic>Stramenopiles</italic> (orange) and <italic>Ascomycetes</italic> (grey).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.005</object-id><label>Figure 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title><italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> weight at different developmental stages.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig1-data1-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.006</object-id><label>Figure 1—source data 2.</label><caption><title><italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> intestine length at different developmental stages.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig1-data2-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Changes in <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> intestine and teeth during larval recruitment.</title><p>(<bold>A–O</bold>) Complete guts histology of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> after reef colonization. First column: anterior part of the intestine (first cm), middle column: medium part (variable), last column: posterior part of the intestine (1 cm), (<bold>A–C</bold>): crest individual, (<bold>D–F</bold>): 2 days juvenile, (<bold>G–I</bold>): 3 days juvenile, (<bold>J–L</bold>): 5 days juvenile, (<bold>M–O</bold>): 8 days juvenile. Scale bars represent 200 µm. These pictures are representative of n = 6 section technical replicates for each of the proximal, middle and distal intestine, and were performed twice (sampling technical replicates), on n = 2 fish (biological replicates). (<bold>P</bold>) Heat map of bacterial gut community. Each column is one individual. Each row is bacterial taxa. Only the taxa with differential representations between the samples are shown. Sampling stages: day 2, day 5, day 8 and adult are indicated below the heat map. The shape of each of this developmental stage is schematized over the heat map. Each column is highlighted by a circle, the difference in shade between the circles emphasizes the stage difference. The color of each square in the heat map is proportional to the abundance of the taxa (row) in the sample (column). (<bold>Q</bold>) µCT scan of a crest larva, lateral view. Dental family C are highlighted in red and dental family B in blue. (<bold>R</bold>) µCT scan of an adult, frontal view (mouth open). (<bold>Q–R</bold>) The scale bar indicates 0.5 mm. These pictures are representative of n = 2 fish (biological replicates).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig1-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group><p>Furthermore, using conventional X-Ray microtomography, we identified three different dental generations in crest larvae to day 8 juveniles (red, blue and green, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M–Q</xref>). Crest larvae present tiny and poorly mineralized pointed teeth at the distal ends of the jaws (red, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1R</xref>) that are likely remnants of an oceanic larval dentition (dentition A). Other medium-sized and more mineralized teeth are in function in medial areas of the jaws (blue, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M</xref>). These teeth display pointed cusps and belong to a more advanced dental generation (dentition B). Lastly, much larger teeth of the next generation (green, dentition C) are about to erupt from jaws in crest larvae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M</xref>) and replace A and B previous dentitions in day 2 to day 8 juveniles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1N–Q</xref>). These teeth are highly similar to the shovel-shaped adult teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1S</xref>) that serve for grazing algae on hard substrata. The rapid formation of dentition C is consistent with a diet shift from planktivorous to herbivorous at recruitment. This shift is precisely organized, since it begins in the sagittal area of all individuals, and secondarily extends to the distal parts of the jaw (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M–Q</xref>). The fact that crest captured larvae already have teeth of the C dentition about to erupt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M</xref>) indicates that fish are prepared for reef life conditions before reef entry.</p><p>The intestine also goes through a drastic remodeling at recruitment. In particular, the gastro-intestinal tract lengthens from about 2.52 ± 0.07 cm in crest captured larvae to 7.38 ± 0.14 cm in day 8 juveniles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1W</xref>). To characterize this change, we performed histological sections on the middle part of the intestine during the larval recruitment process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1R–V</xref>). Intestines of crest larvae and day 2 juveniles have a thick wall with many muscle fibers and regular villi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1R and S</xref>). At day 3, intestines undergo a spectacular remodeling with the disappearance of the epithelium, leaving only the muscular layer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1T</xref>), while epithelium reformation occurs later at day 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1U</xref>). In day 8 individuals, the intestine is fully remodeled: the epithelium is thicker and exhibits villi again (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1V</xref>). Such spectacular remodeling events are also observed in the proximal and distal portion of the intestines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A–O</xref>).</p><p>To assess whether and to what extent this intestine remodeling was correlated to a diet shift at larval recruitment, we sequenced <italic>A. triostegus</italic> digestive tract content (18S mass sequencing) to identify its eukaryotic composition. We investigated crest captured individuals, day 8 juveniles and adults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1W</xref>) using a blocking primer to minimize amplification of host sequences. Crest larval intestines are largely empty although we identified sequences of fungi and algae. In day 8 juveniles, the intestinal content is different with more brown and red algae, as well as few protostome sequences. This indicates a shift in the eukaryotic gut content between crest individuals and day 8 juveniles. Adults gut content is less diversified and is mainly composed of brown algae, red algae and alveolates, different from those found in day 8 juveniles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1W</xref>). Using 16S metagenomic sequencing, we found differences in the relative quantity of bacterial community between the juveniles at day 2, 5 and 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1P</xref>). The 16S profile of the adult is also different from the juvenile profile, with the notable presence of <italic>Lachnospiraceae</italic>, among which the giant bacteria <italic>Epulopiscium fishelsoni</italic> is a well-known symbiont of Acanthuridae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Clements and Bullivant, 1991</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Thyroid hormone signaling peaks at larval recruitment</title><p>Given the role of TH in vertebrate metamorphosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Laudet, 2011</xref>) and the spectacular transformations that <italic>A. triostegus</italic> undergoes at larval recruitment, we analyzed TH levels in larvae captured in the far ocean (from 5 to 10 km offshore, n = 3), near ocean (2 km offshore, n = 5), crest-captured larvae and juveniles (raised in situ in lagoon cages, n = 297) up to day 8 after recruitment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A–B</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.007</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Thyroid hormone signaling during <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> metamorphosis.</title><p>Error bars represent standard errors. *p-value&lt;0.05; **p-value&lt;0.01; ***p-value&lt;0.001. (<bold>A</bold>) T4 and (<bold>B</bold>) T3 dosage: Y-axis: T4 and T3 levels in pg.g<sup>−1</sup>; X-axis: sampling point. n = 3 for 5 to 10 km offshore fish (far), n = 5 for 2 km offshore fish (near), n = 297 for crest to day 8 (<bold>d8</bold>) fish. Statistics: mean comparisons (Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney U-test). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata1">Figure 2—source data 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata2">Figure 2—source data 2</xref> for detailed data and statistics. (<bold>C</bold>) Expression level of <italic>TRα-A, TRα-B, TRβ</italic> and <italic>Klf9</italic> by qPCR, normalized with <italic>Pold2</italic> and <italic>Rpl7</italic>. Y-axis; Relative normalized expression X-axis: gene and sampling point.. Far ocean larvae are split in two groups: Far a (black stripes) and Far b (white). For each panel, the color shading is the same one as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>. For each sampling point three biological replicates and three technical replicates were performed. Statistics: comparisons of each mean to the Crest condition mean (Student's t cumulative distribution function, which was automatically computed by <italic>qPCR software CFX Biorad Manager</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">CFX Manager SH, 2017</xref>). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata3">Figure 2—source data 3</xref> for detailed data and statistics.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.011</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title><italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> T4 levels in larvae and juveniles.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-data1-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.012</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 2.</label><caption><title><italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> T3 levels in larvae and juveniles.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-data2-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.013</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 3.</label><caption><title><italic>TR</italic> and <italic>Klf9</italic> expression levels in <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> at different developmental stages (qPCR).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-data3-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.014</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 4.</label><caption><title>Transactivation assay of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus TR</italic> for several thyroid hormone derivatives.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-data4-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.015</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 5.</label><caption><title>Transactivation assay of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus TR</italic> for the competition of T3 and NH3.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-data5-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata6"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.016</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 6.</label><caption><title>List of primers used in this study.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-data6-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata7"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.017</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 7.</label><caption><title>List of <italic>TR</italic> used for phylogenetic reconstruction.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-data7-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.008</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Characterization of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> thyroid hormone receptors.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representations of TRα-A, TRα-B and TRβ from upper to lower rows respectively. The amino acid numbering of the DBD (light gray) and LBD (dark grey) appear above each TR. The nine amino acid insertion of the TRβ long isoform is indicated below the gray dashed area. (<bold>B</bold>) Phylogenetic reconstruction of TR amino acid sequenced by maximum likelihood. Bootstrap over supporting each branches are indicated when &gt;700/1000. <italic>A. triostegus</italic> genes are highlighted in red. (<bold>C</bold>) Transactivation assay of TRs in HEK293T cells with a luciferase reporter. X-axis: Tested genes and treatment condition. T4: blue bars, T3: red bars, T2: green bars, Tetrac: purple bars and Triac: orange bars. The concentrations range from 10<sup>−9</sup> M to 10<sup>−7</sup> M which corresponds to the light and dark shade of each color. Tested genes are indicated on the bottom line. Y-axis: arbitrary luciferase unit. Three technical replicates were performed. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata4">Figure 2—source data 4</xref> for detailed data. (<bold>D</bold>) Transactivation assay of TRs in HEK293T cells with a luciferase reporter. X-axis: tested genes and treatment conditions. Light blue to dark blue bars: T3 treatments at 10<sup>−9</sup>, 10<sup>−8</sup>, and 10–7 M respectively. Light blue to dark blue dashed bars: T3 + NH3 treatments with T3 at 10<sup>−8</sup> M and NH3 at 10<sup>−8</sup>, 10<sup>−7</sup> and 10<sup>−6</sup> M respectively. Y-axis: arbitrary luciferase unit. Three technical replicates were performed. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata5">Figure 2—source data 5</xref> for detailed data.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.009</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Primers used in this study.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Degenerated primers used for the cloning of the <italic>A. triostegus</italic> genes in this study. (<bold>B</bold>) qPCR primers used in this study. (<bold>C</bold>) Primers used for 18S mass sequencing. The overlapping nucleotides between 18 SR and the blocking primer are indicated in bold. The mean annealing temperature of each primer is indicated in the last column. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata6">Figure 2—source data 6</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.010</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>List of thyroid hormone receptors sequences used for the phylogeny.</title><p>Species, genes, databases and accession numbers are indicated. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata7">Figure 2—source data 7</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig2-figsupp3-v1"/></fig></fig-group><p>T4 levels are low in far ocean larvae and rise in fish located closer to the reef (near ocean larvae), before dropping 6-fold between the near ocean larvae and the day 8 juveniles (p-value=0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). This indicates a peak of T4 in near ocean and in crest larvae. Far ocean larvae exhibit a high level of T3 but with an important variability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Although these larvae live in the same ecological niche (<italic>i.e.</italic> open ocean) and are roughly of the same size (4.7, 5.5, and 6.3 mm), they were captured in different locations and are probably not at the same developmental stage. Near ocean and crest captured larvae have similar levels of T3 that are 6-fold higher than the level observed in day 8 juveniles (p-value &lt; 0.001 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>).</p><p>We characterized the three TR of <italic>A. triostegus</italic>: TRα-A, TRα-B and TRβ. These receptors have between 86% (TRα-A) and 96% (TRβ) sequence identity with their zebrafish orthologs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A</xref>). The phylogenetic analysis indicates that each of the three TR clusters with its respective teleosts orthologs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Moreover, transactivation assays show that these receptors behave as genuine TR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1C</xref>). We thus assessed the expression levels of <italic>TRα-A</italic>, <italic>TRα-B</italic>, and <italic>TRβ</italic> during <italic>A. triostegus</italic> development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>), as well as <italic>Klf9</italic>, a conserved TR regulated gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Denver and Williamson, 2009</xref>). Far ocean larvae have two profiles: one with a very low <italic>TR</italic> and <italic>Klf9</italic> expressions (‘Far a’ ocean) and one with very high levels of expression (‘Far b’ ocean) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). This suggests that there are, at least, two distinct situations in far ocean larvae: larvae with low TH/<italic>TR</italic> levels and larvae in which TH/<italic>TR</italic> levels surge. Far b ocean, near ocean, and crest larvae have high expression levels of the all the <italic>TR</italic> as well as <italic>Klf9</italic>, indicating a strong activation of the TH signaling at these stages. We observed a drop of all <italic>TR</italic> expression between crest larvae and day 8 juveniles (p-values=0.001, 0.005 and 0.002 for <italic>TRα-A</italic>, <italic>TRα-B</italic> and <italic>TRβ</italic> respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Thyroid hormone signaling and the environment control larvae transformation</title><p>To link the TH pathway, the environment and the metamorphic changes occurring at larval recruitment, we disturbed the TH signaling and the location of crest-captured larvae during their metamorphosis (from capture to up to day 8 after reef colonization).</p><p>In order to study how the environment controls the metamorphosis processes, we first relocated crest-captured larvae back to the external slope immediately after their reef entry. Indeed, mimicking oceanic condition has been acknowledged to delay metamorphosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">McCormick, 1999</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, upper panel). Similar to this earlier study, we observed a striking delay in the white pigmentation appearance between the vertical black stripes in day 2 relocated fish compared to their lagoon raised counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, lower panel). The levels of T4 and T3 in fish relocated on the external slope at day 2, day 5 and day 8 are overall higher than the levels of their control counterparts in the lagoon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B–C</xref>). The levels of T4, in particular, remain similar in day 2 to day 8 juveniles to the levels in the crest condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). The expressions of <italic>TRs</italic> and <italic>Klf9</italic> in the relocated juveniles were also higher than in control juveniles at the same age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). This suggests that the environment effectively controls the metamorphosis by modulating the TH signaling.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.018</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Impact of the environment and thyroid hormone signaling on <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> metamorphic processes.</title><p>Error bars represent standard errors. *p-value&lt;0.05; **p-value&lt;0.01; ***p-value&lt;0.001. (<bold>A</bold>) Upper panel: schematization of the external slope experiment with control fish, in the lagoon (grey circle), and relocated fish, on the external slope (orange circle). Lower panel: comparison of the pigmentation between the relocated fish (left) and the control lagoon fish (right) at day 2. (<bold>B</bold>) T4 and (<bold>C</bold>) T3 dosage of crest captured larvae and day 2, 5 and 8 juveniles, in control (grey shade) or external slope (orange shade) conditions. n = 4 fish for each experimental condition. X-axis: sampling point, Y-axis: T4 or T3 level in pg.g<sup>−1</sup>. Statistics: mean comparisons between control and external slope (Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney U-test). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig3sdata1">Figure 3—source data 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig3sdata2">Figure 3—source data 2</xref> for detailed data and statistics. (<bold>D</bold>) Expression level of <italic>TRα-A, TRα-B, TRβ</italic> and <italic>Klf9</italic> by qPCR, normalized with <italic>pold2</italic> and rpl7 housekeeping genes, in control (grey shade) or external slope (orange shade) conditions. Y-axis: Relative normalized expression. X-axis: gene and stages. For each point three biological replicates and three technical replicates were performed. Statistics: comparisons of ‘external slope’ means to their ‘control’ counterparts (Student's t cumulative distribution function). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig3sdata3">Figure 3—source data 3</xref> for detailed data and statistics. (<bold>E</bold>) Intestine length in cm of fish at crest (<bold>C</bold>), day 2 (d2) or day 5 (d5) under different treatment conditions: solvent-control (grey shade), T3 +IOP treated at 10<sup>−6</sup> M (blue shade), NH3 treated at 10<sup>−6</sup> M (green shade), T3 +IOP + NH3 treated at 10<sup>−6</sup> M (blue and green dashed shade) or located to the external slope (orange shade). n &gt; 10 fish for each experimental condition. Statistics: ANOVA followed by Tukey posthoc tests, only significant differences with the respective solvent-control condition are indicated. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig3sdata4">Figure 3—source data 4</xref> for detailed data and statistics (<bold>F</bold>) Histological cross section (5 µm width) of intestine stained by haematoxylin/eosin. Scale bars indicate 200 µm. These pictures are representative of n = 2 microtome section and staining technical replicates, performed on n = 3 fish (biological replicate) per treatment and per developmental stage. Two technical replicates of this experiment were performed. (<bold>G</bold>) Mean number of bites (on turf algae) per fish in a batch of 18 fish at day 2 (<bold>d2</bold>) and day 5 (<bold>d5</bold>) under different treatment conditions: solvent control (DMSO, grey shade), T3 + IOP at 10<sup>−6</sup>µM (blue shade), NH3 at 10<sup>−6</sup>µM (green shade) or relocated to the external slope (orange shade). n = 3 to 6 independent bite counts (technical replicates) for each condition. Bite counting was not performed on crest captured individuals as <italic>A. triostegus</italic> larvae do not feed for at least 12 hr after colonizing the reef at night (MB pers. obs.). Statistics: same as in (<bold>E</bold>). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig3sdata5">Figure 3—source data 5</xref> for detailed data and statistics.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.021</object-id><label>Figure 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>T4 levels in external slope relocated <italic>Acanthus triostegus</italic>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig3-data1-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.022</object-id><label>Figure 3—source data 2.</label><caption><title>T3 levels in external slope relocated <italic>Acanthus triostegus</italic>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig3-data2-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.023</object-id><label>Figure 3—source data 3.</label><caption><title><italic>TR</italic> and <italic>Klf9</italic> expression levels in external slope relocated <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> (qPCR).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig3-data3-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.024</object-id><label>Figure 3—source data 4.</label><caption><title><italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> intestine length under pharmacological treatments or relocation.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig3-data4-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.025</object-id><label>Figure 3—source data 5.</label><caption><title><italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> grazing activity under pharmacological treatments or relocation.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig3-data5-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.019</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Thyroid hormone signaling and environment impact on the dentition and guts histology of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> at metamorphosis.</title><p>First column: X-Ray microtomography of larva, dentition A, B or C are highlighted respectively in red, blue or green. Scale bars indicate 0.5 mm. These pictures are representative of n = 3 fish (biological replicates) per developmental stage and per treatment condition. Second to fourth columns: complete guts histology (5 µm wide microtome sections) of <italic>A. triostegus</italic> at day 2 and day 5 following reef colonization. First column: anterior part of the intestine (first cm), middle column: medium part (variable), last column: posterior part of the intestine (last cm). Haematoxylin and eosin staining. Scale bars indicate 200 µm. These pictures are representative of n = 2 treatment technical replicates, and n = 2 microtome section and staining technical replicates, on n = 3 fish (biological replicates) per treatment and per day.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig3-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.020</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Pigmentation patterns and thyroid hormone signaling in <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> at day 2 (d2) and day (d5) during larval recruitment.</title><p>These pictures are representative of n &gt; 10 treatment technical replicates performed on n &gt; 100 fish (biological replicates) per treatment and per developmental stage.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig3-figsupp2-v1"/></fig></fig-group><p>To assess the implication of the TH signaling pathway on metamorphic processes, we then raised crest-captured larvae in situ in the lagoon and injected them daily, in their ventral cavity, with 20 µl of different drug solutions that activate or disrupt their TH molecular pathway. Four drug treatments were applied: (i) solvent control (DMSO diluted 10.000 times in Phosphate Buffer Saline 1X, as all drugs were made soluble in DMSO and diluted 10.000 times in PBS 1X); (ii) T3 +iopanoic acid (IOP) both at 10<sup>−6</sup> M, IOP being used as an inhibitor of the deiodinase enzymes that therefore prevents the degradation of injected T3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Galton, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Little et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Lorgen et al., 2015</xref>); (iii) NH3 at 10<sup>−6</sup> M, NH3 being used as an antagonist of TR that prevents the binding of TH on TR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Lim et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Renko et al., 2012</xref>) therefore disrupting <italic>A. triostegus</italic> TH pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1D</xref>); and (iv) T3 + IOP + NH3 all at 10<sup>−6</sup> M to ensure the non-toxicity of NH3.</p><p>We used intestine total length, internal structure of guts (intestinal microvilli), dentition and pigmentation as markers of the advancement of metamorphosis since they strongly change after reef recruitment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). T3 + IOP treatment increases the length of the intestine in day 2 and day 5 juveniles (p-values&lt;0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>, blue). On the contrary, NH3 treatment partially prevents the intestines lengthening occurring after recruitment (p-values&lt;0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>, green). Injections of T3 + IOP + NH3 result in an intestine length similar to the control individuals at day 2 and day 5 (p-values=0.486 and 0.444 respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). This shows that T3 and NH3 effectively compete, and confirms the non-toxicity of NH3. In parallel, intestines of fish relocated on the external slope are shorter than those of their lagoon counterparts at day 2 and day 5 (p-value&lt;0.001 and p-value=0.042 respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>, orange). This shows that their development has been slowed down, similarly to what we observed with the NH3 treatment. A similar pattern was observed concerning the microvilli remodeling within guts. In the anterior part of the guts, while T3 + IOP treatment accelerates the loss of the intestinal microvilli at day 2 and accelerates the development and the thickening of a new epithelium at day 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>, second column), NH3 treatment and external slope relocation prevent microvilli renewal at both day 2 and day 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>, third and fourth column). These observations can be extended to the anterior, medium and posterior sections of the guts (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). These changes are consistent with the notion that TH control remodeling of the guts at metamorphosis in <italic>A. triostegus</italic>. We did not observe any effect on teeth development neither with T3 + IOP or NH3 treatment, nor with external slope relocation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). Given that teeth remodeling is a lengthy process that starts very early on in oceanic larvae and therefore before reef colonization, it is not surprising that the treatments performed on crest captured larvae do not affect (or are too late to affect) teeth development. Also, contrarily to individuals relocated on the outer slope, we did not observe any effect of T3 + IOP nor NH3 treatments on skin pigmentation at day 2 and day 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>). This suggests that pigmentation during the larva to juvenile transition is strongly coupled to the environment but is not directly under TH control that may not sustain such rapid pigmentation changes. Taken together: (i) intestine lengthening and remodeling are mediated by TH signaling; and (ii) disturbing the TH pathway disrupts the normal development of fish after larval recruitment, showing that TH effectively controls some major aspects of <italic>A. triostegus</italic> metamorphosis.</p><p>Finally, we tested how TH signaling influences fish behavior. To achieve this, we used grazing activity (number of bites on algal turf), as <italic>A. triostegus</italic> larvae start to graze a couple of days after colonizing the reef, to investigate how TH signaling and metamorphosis completion influence the behavior of recruited fish. T3 + IOP treatment increases the grazing activity by around 50% in day 5 juveniles when compared to the control individuals (p-value=0.004, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3G</xref>, blue lanes). On the contrary, NH3 treatment significantly decreases the number of bites at day 2 by 33% (p-value&lt;0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3G</xref>, green lane). The grazing activity of fish relocated on the external slope (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>) is also diminished by more than 4-fold at day 2 (p-value&lt;0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3G</xref>, orange lanes). These data indicate that TH signaling promotes the biting activity of <italic>A. triostegus</italic> and subsequent grazing behavior adopted at larval recruitment. This shows that TH controls the transformations of the feeding process not only at the morphological and physiological levels but also at the behavioral level.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Thyroid hormone-mediated metamorphosis is conserved in coral reef fishes</title><p>To widen our understanding of coral reef fish metamorphosis, we investigated the TH signaling during larval recruitment in four other coral fish species (<italic>Rhinecanthus aculeatus</italic>, <italic>Chromis viridis</italic>, <italic>Chaetodon lunula</italic> and <italic>Ostorhinchus angustatus</italic>) from distant families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Near et al., 2012</xref>). In these species, both T4 and T3 levels drop between day 1 and day 8, up to 3-fold for T4 (in <italic>O. angustatus</italic>, p-value=0.029) and up to 4-fold for T3 (in <italic>R. aculeatus</italic>, p-value=0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). This drop of TH levels after reef entry strongly suggests that TH are also key determinants for the metamorphosis of these species. T4 levels in <italic>R. aculeatus</italic> and T3 levels in <italic>C. viridis</italic> also rise between near ocean and day 1 individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>), further confirming the model of a TH-mediated metamorphosis during coral reef fish larval recruitment. However, T4 levels are 3-fold higher in near ocean individuals than in day 1 individuals in <italic>C. viridis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). This suggests some potential species-specific variation in coral reef fish TH profiles at recruitment that would be extremely interesting to decipher in future studies on additional species and with regards to other aspects of coral reef fish ecology (<italic>e.g.</italic>, diets, size and pigmentation status at recruitment).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.026</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Thyroid hormone levels in distant coral reef fish at larval recruitment.</title><p>Error bars represent standard errors. *p-value&lt;0.05; **p-value&lt;0.01; ***p-value&lt;0.001. TH levels of: <italic>Rhinecanthus aculeatus</italic> (upper)<italic>, Chromis viridis</italic> (middle up), <italic>Chaetodon lunula</italic> (middle low) and <italic>Ostorhinchus angustatus</italic> (lower). n = 3 to 5 biological replicates for each condition. First column is T4, second column is T3. Y-axis: T4 or T3 level in pg.g<sup>−1</sup>. X-axis: sampling point (developmental stage). The phylogenic relationship between the species is plotted on the far left of the figure. Statistics: for each species, comparisons of each mean to the day 1 (d1) mean (Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney U-test). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata1">Figure 4—source data 1</xref> for detailed data and statistics.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.027</object-id><label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>T4 and T3 levels of various coral reef fishes at different development stages.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig4-data1-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig4-v1"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Reef pollutant disrupts the transformation of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic></title><p>Chlorpyrifos (CPF) is an agricultural insecticide that is widely used on tropical coastal crops, therefore one of the most common waterborne chemical pollutants encountered in coral reef surrounding waters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Cavanagh et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Leong et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Roche et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Botté et al., 2012</xref>). Given the endocrine determinants of coral reef fish metamorphosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>) and the CPF endocrine disruption characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Juberg et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Slotkin et al., 2013</xref>), we assessed the impact of CPF on <italic>A. triostegus</italic> metamorphosis. To achieve this, we used exposure doses previously reported in coral reef fish (1, 5 or 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> of seawater) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Botté et al., 2012</xref>). CPF treatment at 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> decreases the T3 levels by 50% in day 2 juveniles (p-value=0.021, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). No significant effect was observed on T4 levels regardless of CPF concentration and duration (p-value=0.205 for day 2 and p-value=0.496 for day 5, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A</xref>). We did not observe any effect of CPF treatments on fish pigmentation at day 2 and day 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>). However, CPF exposure at 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> prevents guts’ lengthening at day 2 (p-value=0.024, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref> left panel), and both exposure at 5 and 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> prevent intestines’ lengthening at day 5 (p-values=0.047 and 0.029 respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref> right panel). Strikingly, CPF exposure at 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> also decreases the grazing activity of day 2 juveniles with 2.63 ± 0.09 bites per fish per min contrasting with 3.62 ± 0.28 bites per fish per min in the solvent control condition (p-value=0.014, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). In day 5 juveniles, exposure at 5 and 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> decreases the grazing activity with respectively 2.68 ± 0.18 and 2.63 ± 0.05 bites per fish per min compared to 4.43 ± 0.33 bites per fish per min for the solvent control fish (p-values=0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). Such a behavior in fish treated with CPF results in up to a 14-fold reduction in the biomass of turf grazed after 5 days (p-value=0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.028</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Influence of chlorpyrifos exposure on <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> thyroid hormone signaling, intestine length, grazing activity, and algal removal efficiency.</title><p>Error bars represent standard errors. *p-value&lt;0.05; **p-value&lt;0.01; ***p-value&lt;0.001. (<bold>A</bold>) T3 level in pg.g<sup>−1</sup> of day 2 (d2) and day 5 (d5) fish exposed to different conditions: solvent control (C, acetone, white bars), or exposed to CPF at 1 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (1, light yellow bars), 5 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (5, yellow bars) or 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (30, dark yellow bars). Exposure started right after crest capture. n = 10 fish in each condition. Statistics: ANOVA followed by Tukey posthoc tests, only significant differences with the solvent-control condition are indicated. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata1">Figure 5—source data 1</xref> for detailed data and statistics. (<bold>B</bold>) Intestine length in cm of fish at day 2 (d2) or day 5 (d5) under different conditions: solvent control (C, acetone, white bars), or exposed to CPF at 1 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (1, light yellow bars), 5 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (5, yellow bars) or 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (30, dark yellow bars). Exposure started right after crest capture. n = 5 to 8 fish for each experimental condition. Statistics: same as in (<bold>A</bold>). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata2">Figure 5—source data 2</xref> for detailed data and statistics (<bold>C</bold>) Mean number of bites (on turf algae) per fish in a batch of 18 fish on reef turf at day 2 (d2) or day 5 (d5), under different conditions: solvent control (C, acetone, white bars), or exposed to CPF at 1 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (1, light yellow bars), 5 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (5, yellow bars) or 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (30, dark yellow bars). Exposure started right after crest capture. n = 3 independent bite counts for each condition. Statistics: same as in (<bold>A</bold>). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata3">Figure 5—source data 3</xref> for detailed data and statistics. (<bold>D</bold>) Mean turf biomass removed per fish in a batch of 10 fish, in 5 days following reef colonization, under different conditions: solvent control (C, acetone, white bars), or exposed to CPF at 1 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (1, light yellow bars), 5 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (5, yellow bars) or 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (30, dark yellow bars). Exposure started right after crest capture. n = 3 independent measurements of grazed turf for each condition. Statistics: comparisons of each mean to the solvent-control (<bold>C</bold>) mean (Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney U-test). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata4">Figure 5—source data 4</xref> for detailed data and statistics.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.030</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label><caption><title>T3 levels in <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> under different chlorpyrifos exposure conditions.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig5-data1-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.031</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Intestine length of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> under different chlorpyrifos exposure conditions.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig5-data2-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.032</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Grazing activity of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> under different chlorpyrifos exposure conditions.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig5-data3-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.033</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 4.</label><caption><title>Quantity of grazed algae by <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> under different chlorpyrifos exposure conditions.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig5-data4-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.034</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 5.</label><caption><title>T4 levels in <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> under different chlorpyrifos exposure conditions.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig5-data5-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig5-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.029</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Pigmentation patterns and chlorpyrifos exposure in <italic>A. triostegus</italic> at metamorphosis.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) T4 level in pg.g<sup>−1</sup> of day 2 (d2) and day 5 (d5) fish exposed to different conditions: solvent control (C, acetone, white bars), or exposed to CPF at 1 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (1, light yellow bars), 5 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (5, yellow bars) or 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> (30, dark yellow bars). Exposure started right after crest capture. n = 10 fish in each condition.. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata5">Figure 5—source data 5</xref> for detailed data and statistics. (<bold>B</bold>) Pigmentation patterns and in <italic>A. triostegus</italic> exposed to different conditions: solvent control, or CPF at 1 µg.l<sup>−1</sup>, 5 µg.l<sup>−1</sup>, or 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup> at day 2 (d2) and day (d5) during larval recruitment. These pictures are representative of n = 2 chlorpyrifos CPF exposure technical replicates performed on n = 10 fish (biological replicates) per condition and per day.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig5-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we investigated the morphological, physiological and behavioral changes occurring during <italic>A. triostegus</italic> larval recruitment. These results highlight profound anatomical and physiological transformations of the skin and the whole digestive tract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B–W</xref>). In particular, the differences in 16S gut content are likely the consequence of a diet shift (carnivorous to herbivorous) and an environmental shift occurring during larval recruitment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Frédérich et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Baldo et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Sullam et al., 2012</xref>). We hypothesize that intestine remodeling (i.e. the loss of the villi and internal structures) accelerates the shift of the gut microbiota by allowing the establishment of a new bacterial community fitting the diet change. The presence of <italic>Lachnospiraceae</italic> in the adult but not in the larvae is consistent with the hypothesis that this family of bacteria is acquired through the environment in surgeonfishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Miyake et al., 2016</xref>). Altogether, these observations reinforce the notion that the fish bacterial community depends on their diet and environment. These shifts of 16S and 18S gut contents, occurring between crest individuals and day 8 juveniles, strikingly coordinate with both the changes of the intestine and teeth morphologies observed during larval recruitment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M–V</xref>). All these changes from teeth to microbiota are consistent with <italic>A. triostegus</italic> change of diet after entering the reefs, conforming to previous observations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Randall, 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">McCormick, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Frédérich et al., 2012</xref>). This complete remodeling is associated with a severe weight loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>), suggesting that larval recruitment corresponds to a real metabolic challenge.</p><p>The molecular investigation of TH signaling in the recruiting larvae indicates a surge of TH levels and <italic>TR</italic> expressions in near ocean larvae and crest individuals, and a drop in juveniles, after reef entry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A–C</xref>). This indicates that migration towards the reefs marks the onset of metamorphosis and starts very early on (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). Consequently, the transformation process is already well advanced when larvae reach the reef, suggesting that this event is triggered in the open ocean by, yet unknown, environmental cues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). After reef entry, T3 treatment increases gut length while external slope relocation and NH3 treatment delay the metamorphosis, although they could not completely interrupt it (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A–B</xref>). These results are consistent with the model of metamorphosis in amphibians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brown and Cai, 2007</xref>) and other fish species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">McMenamin and Parichy, 2013</xref>). It is interesting to relate the morphological and physiological changes we have observed in <italic>A. triostegus</italic> with the TH-controlled post-embryonic process known in zebrafish (the major teleost fish developmental model, one of the few teleost fishes in which we have a functional knowledge of the metamorphosis process). Indeed, in both species, as well as in flatfish, another classical teleost model of metamorphosis, major pigmentation and craniofacial changes occur at metamorphosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">McMenamin and Parichy, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">McMenamin et al., 2014</xref>). It is not clear if the appearance of the dark melanophore stripes in zebrafish and <italic>A. triostegus</italic> is controlled by similar mechanisms. In <italic>A. triostegus</italic>, this event is extremely rapid (as fast as 2 hr after reef entry, MB pers. obs.), and strongly environmentally coupled, whereas in zebrafish juveniles the pigment pattern changes very gradually and is presumably not under selection for rapid change during metamorphosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">McMenamin et al., 2014</xref>). However, melanophores can differentiate rapidly (in less than 12 hr) when appropriately stimulated in juvenile zebrafish. For example, acute stimulation with TH may initiate rapid melanophore differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">McMenamin et al., 2014</xref>). Therefore, if the melanophore precursors are already in place and poised to differentiate in <italic>A. triostegus</italic>, it is possible that they could become melanized within a few hours upon direct stimulation with TH. Our NH3 treatments suggest that this may not be the case (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>), but this remains an open question that requires further investigation. Altogether, our findings indicate that the onset and coordination of metamorphosis are two distinct events, both coordinated by TH and under environmental control. They further demonstrate that <italic>A. triostegus</italic> larval recruitment is a TH-controlled metamorphosis, as in amphibians and flatfishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brown and Cai, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Laudet, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">McMenamin and Parichy, 2013</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.035</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Model of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> metamorphosis and disruption by chlorpyrifos.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of coral reef fish larval recruitment. TH level is plotted on the Y axis and development on the X axis. The onset of metamorphosis is in the open ocean and environmental influence upon development is plotted on the X-axis. (<bold>B</bold>) Consequences of undisturbed (upper panel) and CPF disturbed (lower panel) metamorphosis on grazing activity, and subsequent algal spreading and potential coral survival. Solid red bar indicates inhibition; dotted red line indicates lack of inhibition.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-27595-fig6-v1"/></fig><p>We demonstrated that the decrease of both T4 and T3 after reef entry can be generalized to phylogenetically distant coral fish species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). We propose that this decrease is valid for most if not all coral reef fishes, even if species-specific variations on this general theme can be observed, and that the larval recruitment of coral reef fish corresponds to a TH-controlled metamorphosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). Interestingly, variations in the magnitude of TH changes among the five coral reef fish species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>) are reminiscent of the situation in stickleback, where differences in TH signaling between two ecotypes support life history trait variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Kitano et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Kitano and Lema, 2013</xref>). We anticipate that this post-embryonic developmental step is shaped by evolution and varies according to species-specific life history traits such as pelagic larval duration, size at reef colonization and pigmentation status (i.e., metamorphic state of advancement) at recruitment. Given the dramatic diversity of life history strategies they propose, coral reef fish could be excellent models to decipher how these changes are elicited by changes in hormonal systems.</p><p>Among the endocrine disruptors already evidenced and encountered in coral reefs, CPF is known to be a thyroid disruptor with adverse effects on fish behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Sandahl et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kavitha and Rao, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Roche et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yang et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Botté et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Deb and Das, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Juberg et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Slotkin et al., 2013</xref>). We demonstrated that CPF exposure reduces <italic>A. triostegus</italic> physiological level of T3 at larval recruitment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). Consistently with our observations on NH3 treated fish, exposure to CPF impairs metamorphosis, as evidenced with the repression of guts’ lengthening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>), and the decrease in the juveniles’ grazing activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). This latter point led to a reduced algal removal efficiency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>). As <italic>A. triostegus</italic> is one of the major herbivorous fish in coral reefs, this can severely impair the ability of coral reefs to recover after an algal invasion (e.g., after a bleaching event) and therefore contributes to the worldwide degradation of reef health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Russ, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Almany et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Ledlie et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hughes et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hughes et al., 2014</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>).</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our results highlight how coral reef fish larval recruitment, the transition between the open ocean and the reef, is a TH-regulated metamorphosis at the crossroads of ecological, developmental, physiological and behavioral transformations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Holzer and Laudet, 2015</xref>). These findings also demonstrate how coral reef fish TH signaling and larval recruitment processes can be altered by reef pollution. Since metamorphosis and larval recruitment are essential for the maintenance of fish populations and subsequent coral reef resilience, this study provides a general framework to better understand, at the molecular level, how global changes, water pollution and human activities can threaten reef ecosystems.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Fish capture, husbandry and conservation</title><p> <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic>, <italic>Ostorinchus angustatus</italic>, <italic>Chaetodon lunula</italic>, <italic>Chromis viridis</italic> and <italic>Rhinecanthus aculeatus</italic> larvae were captured at Moorea Island, French Polynesia. Larvae were captured during the night while colonizing the reef crest, using a crest net and hand nets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Dufour and Galzin, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Besson et al., 2017</xref>). Larvae were then kept in cages located in situ in the lagoon and provided with continuous food from the water column supplemented with coral rubble and algal turf. For the clarity of this study, the age in day of the juvenile corresponds to the number of day spend in the reef in cages since capture, not the absolute age. Near ocean <italic>A. triostegus</italic> larvae were sampled at 1–2 km away from the reef crest using drifting light trap and hand nets from 0.5 m to 5 m depth. Far ocean <italic>A. triostegus</italic> larvae were also captured offshore by trawl haul more than 10 km away from the reef between 1 and 60 m deep. Larvae were euthanized in MS222 at 0.4 mg.ml<sup>−1</sup> in filtered seawater. For TH dosage, larvae were frozen dry and conserved at −20°C prior to extraction. For RNA extraction, larvae were lacerated and kept in RNAlater (<italic>Sigma</italic>) 1 hr on ice and stored at −20°C. For histology, larvae were rinsed in PBS 1X, dissected and the intestines were kept in Bouin’s fixative at room temperature. For µCT scan and metagenomics, Larvae were kept in 70% ethanol at room temperature.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Fish treatments</title><p><italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> captured at the crest were injected with 20 µl of drugs in the ventral cavity. Drugs tested were as follows: (i) solvent control (DMSO diluted 10.000 times in Phosphate Buffer Saline 1X, as all drugs were made soluble in DMSO and diluted 10.000 in PBS 1X); (ii) T3 + iopanoic acid (IOP) both at 10<sup>−6</sup> M,; (iii) NH3 at 10<sup>−6</sup> M; and (iv) T3 + IOP + NH3 all at 10<sup>−6</sup> M. IOP was used as an inhibitor of deiodinase enzymes, as evidenced in mammals and amphibians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Galton and Hiebert, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Galton and Hiebert, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Galton, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Simonides et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Medina et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Renko et al., 2012</xref>), and as routinely used in fish to prevent the immediate degradation of injected T3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Little et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Lorgen et al., 2015</xref>). NH3 is a known TR antagonist in vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Lim et al., 2002</xref>), a notion we confirmed in <italic>A. triostegus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1D</xref>). NH3 prevents the binding of TH on TR and impairs the binding of transcriptional coactivators to TR, which therefore remain in inactive conformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Figueira et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Lim et al., 2002</xref>). Fish were then kept in the lagoon in in situ cages and injected daily following the same protocol to maintain pharmacological treatment. Fish were sampled on the second and fifth day after the beginning of this protocol. DMSO non toxicity was tested by comparing the pigmentation, the teeth development, the intestine length and internal structures between solvent-control individuals (treated with DMSO diluted 10.000 times in PBS 1X), and control individuals (simply raised in situ in lagoon cages as mentioned in the previous paragraph) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Chlorpyrifos (CPF) exposure</title><p>After crest capture, <italic>A. triostegus</italic> larvae were transferred in aquaria (30 L x 20 W x 20 cm H) in groups of n = 10 fish. Each aquarium was filled with 9 liters of UV-sterilized and filtered - 10 µm filter, and was equipped with an air stone. Fish were then immediately exposed to: nothing (control), acetone at a final concentration of 1:1.000.000 (solvent control, as CPF was made soluble in acetone) or CPF at a final concentration of 1, 5, and 30 µg.l<sup>−1</sup>, as previously done in the literature in another coral reef fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Botté et al., 2012</xref>). All water was replaced every day, ensuring the maintenance of water quality as well as a continuous concentration of the pesticide or solvent. Fish were sampled the 2<sup>nd</sup> and 5<sup>th</sup> day after the beginning of this protocol. Acetone non toxicity was tested by comparing the TH levels, the pigmentation, and the intestine length between solvent-control and control individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A–B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Cloning of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> genes</title><p>Muscle from adult fish and whole larvae were used. Samples were cut using sterile scalpel blades and crushed in a Precelyss with Qiagen extraction buffer. RNA extractions were performed using the Macherey-Nagel RNA extraction kit following the manufacturer’s instructions. Total pooled RNAs were retro-transcripted with the Invitrogen Super Script III enzyme following the manufacturer’s instructions. For <italic>TR</italic> cloning, actinopterygian universal primers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>) were designed for <italic>TRα-A</italic>, <italic>TRα-B</italic> and <italic>TRβ</italic> to retrieve the full-length sequences of the genes. For <italic>polD2</italic> and <italic>rpl7</italic>, actinopterygian universal primers were designed to retrieve partial sequences including at least one exon-exon junction. PCR amplicon were cloned in the Invitrogen PCR II plasmid following the manufacturer instruction for sequencing. <italic>TRα-A</italic>, <italic>TRα-B</italic> and <italic>TRβ</italic> were subcloned in pSG5 between EcoRI sites for <italic>in cellulo</italic> expression.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>qPCR assay</title><p>Far ocean to day 8 juveniles were assayed. For each larvae 1 µg of RNA were used for retro-transcription using the <italic>Invitrogen Super Sript III</italic> following the manufacturer’s instructions, including a DNAse I treatment. qPCR primers were designed to anneal on different exons, R<italic>pl7</italic> and P<italic>old2</italic> were used as normalization genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>). qPCRs were performed in 96 well plate with the <italic>BioRad IQ Syber Green Super Mix</italic> in 10 µl of final reaction per well following the manufacturer’s ratios. qPCRs were assayed in a BioRad thermocyclers and analysed on <italic>BioRad CFX Manager software</italic>. Assays were performed on duplicates in at least two independent RNA extractions and retro-transcriptions. <italic>Klf9</italic>, which is known to respond to TH signaling, was used as a TH signaling reporter gene.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p>The amino acid sequences of <italic>A. triostegus</italic> cloned TRs as well as available TR sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3</xref>) were aligned using <italic>MUSCLE</italic> software. Trees were generated using the Maximum Likelihood method with the <italic>Seaview four</italic> software under the <italic>JTT model</italic> with estimated gamma shape and eight rate categories (RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_015059">SCR_015059</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gouy et al., 2010</xref>). Bootstrap analysis of 1000 replicates was carried out to support the tree.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Functional characterization of the receptors</title><p>Human embryonic kidney 293 cells (ATCC:CRL_11268, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_0045">CVCL_0045</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Iwema et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gutierrez-Mazariegos et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Sadier et al., 2015</xref>) were grown in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium supplemented with 10% of coal stripped foetal bovine serum and penicillin/streptomycin at 100 µg.ml<sup>−1</sup>. Cell were maintained at 37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and tests for mycoplasma contamination were negative. The transient transfection assays were carried out in 96-well plate with 30 000 cells per plate using <italic>Exgen500</italic> according to the manufacturer’s instructions. For each well, cells were transfected with 50 ng of total DNA: 12,5 ng of full-length receptor encoding plasmid, 12,5 ng of reporter plasmid with four DR4 repeat in the luciferase promoter, 12,5 ng of β-galactosidase encoding plasmid and 12,5 ng of <italic>pSG5</italic> empty plasmid. Drugs were incubated for 48 hr and cells were harvested using a passive lysis buffer and frozen at −20°C. On half of the lysate, luciferase activities were assayed with the luciferase reagent buffer from <italic>Promega</italic> on a <italic>Veritas Turner Biosystem luminometer</italic>. On the other half of the lysate, the β-galactosidase activity was measured using ONPG substrate and absorbance at 420 nm for normalization. Each assay was performed at least three times independently on well triplicates. Drugs from <italic>Sigma-Aldrich</italic> were diluted in DMSO à 10<sup>−2</sup> M then in sterile PBS1X prior treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Thyroid hormone quantification</title><p>TH were extracted from dry-frozen fish following an extraction protocol adapted from previous publications relating TH level variations in teleost fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Tagawa and Hirano, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Einarsdóttir et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kawakami et al., 2008</xref>). Far ocean larvae to day 8 juveniles were assayed. At least three individuals per sampling point were used. Each fish was first crushed with a <italic>Precelyss</italic> in 500 µl methanol, centrifuged at 4°C and supernatant reserved, three times. Pooled supernatant were dried at 70°C. Hormones were re-extracted with 400 µl methanol, 100 µl chloroform and 100 µl barbital buffer twice from the first dried extract. Pooled supernatant was dried out and extract was reconstituted in 2 ml of PBS1X for quantification. The quantification was performed following the <italic>Roche ELICA</italic> kit on a Cobas analyser by a medical laboratory according to the manufacturer’s standardized method.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Intestine histology</title><p>The intestines in Bouin’s fixative were embedded in paraffin. Sections of 5 µm were performed in the proximal, medial and distal part using a microtome (<italic>Leica</italic>). The histological sections were stained with Hematoxylin and Eosin. Photography were taken on a Leica microscope and the mosaic reconstructed using Image J software.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Gut metagenomics</title><p>For 16S mass sequencing, juveniles of 2, 5, 8 days after reef entry and adult <italic>A. triostegus</italic> gut were dissected in triplicates for a total of twelve samples. Total DNA was extracted with a <italic>Macherey-Nagel</italic> DNA extraction kit following the manufacturer’s recommendations. 16S library were constructed for each individual using the <italic>Ion 16S Metagenomic</italic> kit from <italic>Life technologies</italic> following the manufacturer’s recommendations. Sequencing of bacterial 16S was performed using a PGM Ion Torrent. Three controls for contaminations were performed. The environment control consisted of an open tube during the dissection. The extraction control monitored the DNA extraction process. The blank control monitored the library construction. The sequencing results were then analyzed using the <italic>Life technologies</italic> 16S pipeline. 18S mass sequencing was performed on crest larvae, 8 days juveniles and adults in triplicates. Intestine contents were extracted in the same condition as 16S. 18S library were constructed with the pre-amplified V7 region of the eukaryotic 18S (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>). A blocking primer was designed to prevent the amplification of host sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>). The blocking primer was designed to partially overlap the 18S reverse primer and was modified with a C3 spacer. Sequencing was performed using a <italic>PGM Ion Torrent</italic>. The sequences were assembled and blasted against the PR2 database, completed with 18S sequenced from multi-cellular organisms for taxonomic affiliation.</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>µCT scan analysis</title><p>Fish samples were conserved in 70% ethanol, dehydrated in successive baths of 95% ethanol, twice 100% ethanol and in vacuum arena for at least 4 hr. X-ray microtomographies were performed on a <italic>Phoenix Nanotom (General Electric)</italic> at 70 kV of tension, 100 mA of intensity with a tungsten filament. 3000 images per sample were taken at 500 ms of exposure per image and at a resolution ranging from 2.5 to 2.8 µm. 3D volumes were reconstructed and analysed with VGI studiomax software.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Grazing activity</title><p>For each condition (e.g. hormonal treatments, pesticide conditionings), 18 fish were placed in a 5 liter tank with coral rubbles covered with turf algae. After an acclimation period of 1 hr, we recorded the total number of bites made on turf algae during 10 min. This experiment was replicated with a new batch of fish 3 to 6 times depending on the condition.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Grazed turf biomass</title><p>For each pesticide exposition conditioning, we weighed (underwater) 3 pieces of coral rubble prior the introduction of a group of 20 crest captured fish (weight A), and after 5 days of grazing by this group of fish (weight B). For each piece of coral rubble, the weight of grazed algae was estimated through the difference weight B minus weight A.</p></sec><sec id="s4-14"><title>Statistical information</title><p>All statistical analyses were conducted using the <italic>R-Cran</italic> project free software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rproject.org/">http://www.rproject.org/</ext-link>, <italic>R-3.3.1</italic>). Mean comparisons were performed using Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney U-test when comparing two means, and using univariate analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey post-hoc test (should a significant difference be detected) for multiple comparisons. Prior ANOVA, normality of values (or residuals) and variance homogeneity were assessed using Shapiro and Bartlett tests. In qPCR analyses, comparisons of gene expression were performed through Student's t cumulative distribution functions, automatically computed by <italic>qPCR software CFX Biorad Manager</italic>, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">CFX Manager SH, 2017</xref>). All statistical information and data are available in each Figure source data (see Figure captions).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>We thank M Bronner, S McMenamin, D Hazlerigg and A Schreiber for their comments that greatly improved this manuscript. We would also like to thank H Jacob, C Gache, A Gilson, I Moniz, C Berthe, A Savura, D Van Osten and P Schep for their help to catch fish larvae. We thank S Planes, J Burden, T Lorin, M Manceau, P Salis and N Roux for critical reviewing and for their constructive discussion concerning coral fish ecology and development. We are grateful to V Domien for her fruitful advice on the design of the figures. We thank the association <italic>Te mana o te moana</italic> for the accommodation of our cages.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing, Wrote the paper, Designed the experiments, Performed gene cloning, qPCR, Transactivation assay, µCT scan, Hormone dosage, Assisted in metagenomics and analyzing the data, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Supervision, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing, Wrote the paper, Designed the experiments, Performed hormone dosage, Fish capture, Fish treatment, Grazing experiments, Histology and analyzing the data, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Data curation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Assisted with histology and data analysis, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Investigation, Visualization, Writing—review and editing, Assisted with fish capture, fish treatment and analysis of the data, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Data curation, Formal analysis, Assisted in gene cloning, Hormone dosage, Analysis of the data, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Data curation, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—review and editing, Performed the metagenomics, Design of the experiment and assisted in the analysis of the data, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>Data curation, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—review and editing, Performed the metagenomics analysis, Assisted in the experiment and the design, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>Data curation, Formal analysis, Visualization, Writing—review and editing, Assisted in the analysis of metagenomics data, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con9"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—review and editing, Assisted in the analysis of metagenimic data and design of the experiment, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con10"><p>Performed and analyzed X-ray microtomography, Read and commented on the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con11"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Data curation, Formal analysis, Supervision, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Project administration, Writing—review and editing, Wrote the paper, Designed the experiments, Performed fish capture, Analyzed the data, Assisted with preparing the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con12"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Data curation, Formal analysis, Supervision, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Project administration, Writing—review and editing, Wrote the paper, Designed the experiments</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Animal experimentation: This study was performed in strict accordance with the guidelines of the French Polynesia committee for publication and animal ethics. All the animals were handled in accordance with the guidelines CRIOBE-IRCP animal ethics committee, and every effort was made to minimize suffering. The experiments and protocols were approved by the CRIOBE-IRCP animal ethics committee (Decision letter 02-14-2015)</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.036</object-id><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-27595-transrepform-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almany</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Berumen</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorrold</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Planes</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Local replenishment of coral reef fish populations in a marine reserve</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>316</volume><fpage>742</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1140597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17478720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Riera</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tooming-Klunderud</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Albà</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzburger</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Gut microbiota dynamics during dietary shift in Eastern African cichlid fishes</article-title><source>Plos One</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0127462</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0127462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25978452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barth</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>From the ocean to a reef habitat: how do the larvae of coral reef fishes find their way home? A state of art on the latest advances</article-title><source>Life &amp; Environment</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Besson</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gache</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooker</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moussa</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Waqalevu</surname> <given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>LeRohellec</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaouen</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyrusse</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Berthe</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertucci</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brié</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Galzin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecchini</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Consistency in the supply of larval fishes among coral reefs in French Polynesia</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0178795</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0178795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28594864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bianco</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Deiodinases: implications of the local control of thyroid hormone action</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Investigation</source><volume>116</volume><fpage>2571</fpage><lpage>2579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI29812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17016550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Erezyilmaz</surname> <given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Flatt</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgiou</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadfield</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyland</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Maslakova</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pires</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reitzel</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Santagata</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Youson</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>What is metamorphosis?</article-title><source>Integrative and Comparative Biology</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icb/icl004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21672776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botté</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerry</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Codi King</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith-Keune</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Negri</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Effects of chlorpyrifos on cholinesterase activity and stress markers in the tropical reef fish <italic>Acanthochromis polyacanthus</italic></article-title><source>Marine Pollution Bulletin</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2011.08.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21962920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Amphibian metamorphosis</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>306</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2007.03.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17449026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>The role of thyroid hormone in zebrafish and axolotl development</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>94</volume><fpage>13011</fpage><lpage>13016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.24.13011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9371791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunskill</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coventry</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Organochlorine pesticide residues in soils and sediments of the Herbert and Burdekin river regions, North Queensland – implications for contamination of the great barrier reef</article-title><source>Marine Pollution Bulletin</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0025-326X(99)00058-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CFX Manager SH</collab></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><source>Data Analysis Formulas</source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biorad.com/webroot/web/pdf/lsr/literature/10014294.pdf">http://www.biorad.com/webroot/web/pdf/lsr/literature/10014294.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chopra</surname> <given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><chapter-title>Nature, source, and relative significance of circulating thyroid hormones</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Braverman</surname> <given-names>L. E</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Utiger</surname> <given-names>R. D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Werner and Ingbar’s the Thyroid</source><edition>7th Edn</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott-Raven</publisher-name><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>124</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clements</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullivant</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>An unusual symbiont from the gut of surgeonfishes may be the largest known prokaryote</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>173</volume><fpage>5359</fpage><lpage>5362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.173.17.5359-5362.1991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1885516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Jesus</surname> <given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpas</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Thyroid hormones promote early metamorphosis in grouper (<italic>Epinephelus coioides</italic>) larvae</article-title><source>General and Comparative Endocrinology</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/gcen.1998.7103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9748398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deb</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Chlorpyrifos toxicity in fish: A Review</article-title><source>Current World Environment Journal</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12944/CWE.8.1.17</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denver</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Identification of a thyroid hormone response element in the mouse <italic>Kruppel-like factor 9</italic> gene to explain its postnatal expression in the brain</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>150</volume><fpage>3935</fpage><lpage>3943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.2009-0050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19359381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixson</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Munday</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratchett</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Planes</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorrold</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Terrestrial chemical cues help coral reef fish larvae locate settlement habitat surrounding islands</article-title><source>Ecology and Evolution</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.53</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22393525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doherty</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><chapter-title>Variable replenishment and the dynamics of reef fish populations</chapter-title><source>Coral Reef Fishes: Dynamics and Diversity in a Complex Ecosystem</source><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>355</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dufour</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Galzin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>Colonization patterns of reef fish larvae to the lagoon at Moorea Island, French Polynesia</article-title><source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps102143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Einarsdóttir</surname> <given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Power</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smáradóttir</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Björnsson</surname> <given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Thyroid and pituitary gland development from hatching through metamorphosis of a teleost flatfish, the Atlantic halibut</article-title><source>Anatomy and Embryology</source><volume>211</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-005-0055-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16341547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figueira</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saidemberg</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Martínez</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanlan</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Baxter</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaf</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Palma</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Polikarpov</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Analysis of agonist and antagonist effects on thyroid hormone receptor conformation by hydrogen/deuterium exchange</article-title><source>Molecular Endocrinology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/me.2010-0202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21106879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frédérich</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Colleye</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepoint</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecchini</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Mismatch between shape changes and ecological shifts during the post-settlement growth of the surgeonfish, <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic></article-title><source>Frontiers in Zoology</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>8</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-9994-9-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22533865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galton</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiebert</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1987">1987</year><article-title>Hepatic iodothyronine 5-deiodinase activity in <italic>Rana catesbeiana</italic> tadpoles at different stages of the life cycle</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/endo-121-1-42</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3496211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galton</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiebert</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year><article-title>The ontogeny of iodothyronine 5'-monodeiodinase activity in <italic>Rana catesbeiana</italic> tadpoles</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>122</volume><fpage>640</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/endo-122-2-640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3257441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galton</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1989">1989</year><article-title>The role of 3,5,3'-triiodothyronine in the physiological action of thyroxine in the premetamorphic tadpole</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>2427</fpage><lpage>2433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/endo-124-5-2427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2785028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gouy</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guindon</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>SeaView version 4: A multiplatform graphical user interface for sequence alignment and phylogenetic tree building</article-title><source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msp259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19854763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutierrez-Mazariegos</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadendla</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierzchalski</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kane</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikawa</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiromori</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanishi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname> <given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourguet</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laudet</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A mollusk retinoic acid receptor (RAR) ortholog sheds light on the evolution of ligand binding</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>155</volume><fpage>4275</fpage><lpage>4286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.2014-1181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25116705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holzer</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Laudet</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Thyroid hormones: a triple-edged sword for life history transitions</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>R344</fpage><lpage>R347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2015.02.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25898108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellwood</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Connolly</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornell</surname> <given-names>HV</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlson</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Double jeopardy and global extinction risk in corals and reef fishes</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>2946</fpage><lpage>2951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.10.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25454782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellwood</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceccarelli</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoegh-Guldberg</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>McCook</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moltschaniwskyj</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratchett</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Steneck</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Willis</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Phase shifts, herbivory, and the resilience of coral reefs to climate change</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2006.12.049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17291763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwema</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Billas</surname> <given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonneton</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nierengarten</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaumot</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Laudet</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Moras</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Structural and functional characterization of a novel type of ligand-independent RXR-USP receptor</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>3770</fpage><lpage>3782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7601810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17673910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juberg</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehen</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Coady</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBaron</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname> <given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Chlorpyrifos: weight of evidence evaluation of potential interaction with the estrogen, androgen, or thyroid pathways</article-title><source>Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yrtph.2013.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23524272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kavitha</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname> <given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Toxic effects of chlorpyrifos on antioxidant enzymes and target enzyme acetylcholinesterase interaction in mosquito fish, <italic>Gambusia affinis</italic></article-title><source>Environmental Toxicology and Pharmacology</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.etap.2008.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21783910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawakami</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nozaki</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seoka</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumai</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Characterization of thyroid hormones and thyroid hormone receptors during the early development of Pacific bluefin tuna (<italic>Thunnus orientalis</italic>)</article-title><source>General and Comparative Endocrinology</source><volume>155</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygcen.2007.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17988667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawakami</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanda</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Characterization of thyroid hormone receptor alpha and beta in the metamorphosing Japanese conger eel, <italic>Conger myriaster</italic></article-title><source>General and Comparative Endocrinology</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0016-6480(03)00087-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12812781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitano</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lema</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Luckenbach</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawagishi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusakabe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Peichel</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Adaptive divergence in the thyroid hormone signaling pathway in the stickleback radiation</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>2124</fpage><lpage>2130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2010.10.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21093265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitano</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lema</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Divergence in thyroid hormone concentrations between juveniles of marine and stream ecotypes of the threespine stickleback (<italic>Gasterosteus aculeatus</italic>)</article-title><source>Evolutionary Ecology Research</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>153</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laudet</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>The origins and evolution of vertebrate metamorphosis</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>R726</fpage><lpage>R737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2011.07.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21959163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lecchini</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Planes</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Galzin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005b</year><article-title>Experimental assessment of sensory modalities of coral-reef fish larvae in the recognition of their settlement habitat</article-title><source>Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology</source><volume>58</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00265-004-0905-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lecchini</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaigs</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Galzin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005a</year><article-title>Larval sensory abilities and mechanisms of habitat selection of a coral reef fish during settlement</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><volume>143</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-004-1805-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15647903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lecchini</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Waqalevu</surname> <given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmentier</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Radford</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaigs</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Fish larvae prefer coral over algal water cues: implications of coral reef degradation</article-title><source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><volume>475</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps10094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ledlie</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname> <given-names>NAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bythell</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Polunin</surname> <given-names>NVC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardcastle</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Phase shifts and the role of herbivory in the resilience of coral reefs</article-title><source>Coral Reefs</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>641</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00338-007-0230-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leis</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormick</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><chapter-title>The biology, behavior, and ecology of the pelagic, larval stage of coral reef fishes</chapter-title><source>Coral Reef Fishes: Dynamics and Diversity in a Complex Ecosystem</source><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>199</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leong</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname> <given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustafa</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Contamination levels of selected organochlorine and organophosphate pesticides in the Selangor River, Malaysia between 2002 and 2003</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>1159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2006.06.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17027062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanlan</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlow</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>A thyroid hormone antagonist that inhibits thyroid hormone action in vivo</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>277</volume><fpage>35664</fpage><lpage>35670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M205608200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12095994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Little</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunisue</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannan</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Seebacher</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Thyroid hormone actions are temperature-specific and regulate thermal acclimation in zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>)</article-title><source>BMC Biology</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>26</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7007-11-26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23531055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorgen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casadei</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Król</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Birnie</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebbesson</surname> <given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsen</surname> <given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jørgensen</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dardente</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazlerigg</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Functional divergence of type 2 deiodinase paralogs in the Atlantic salmon</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>936</fpage><lpage>941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2015.01.074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25802152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchand</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffraisse</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Triqueneaux</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Safi</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Laudet</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Molecular cloning and developmental expression patterns of thyroid hormone receptors and T3 target genes in the turbot (<italic>Scophtalmus maximus</italic>) during post-embryonic development</article-title><source>General and Comparative Endocrinology</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygcen.2003.10.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14723886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCormick</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Makey</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufour</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Comparative study of metamorphosis in tropical reef fishes</article-title><source>Marine Biology</source><volume>141</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00227-002-0883-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCormick</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Delayed metamorphosis of a tropical reef fish (<italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic>):a field experiment</article-title><source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><volume>176</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps176025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMenamin</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McCann</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Eom</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Waller</surname> <given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamill</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhlman</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Parichy</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Thyroid hormone-dependent adult pigment cell lineage and pattern in zebrafish</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>345</volume><fpage>1358</fpage><lpage>1361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1256251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25170046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMenamin</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parichy</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><source>Metamorphosis in Teleosts</source><edition>1st edn</edition><publisher-name>Elsevier Inc</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medina</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gadea</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fachado</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Murillo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simovic</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pileggi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernández</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Edlund</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianco</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>The thyroid hormone-inactivating type III deiodinase is expressed in mouse and human beta-cells and its targeted inactivation impairs insulin secretion</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>152</volume><fpage>3717</fpage><lpage>3727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.2011-1210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21828183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyake</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngugi</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Stingl</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Phylogenetic diversity, distribution, and cophylogeny of giant bacteria (<italic>Epulopiscium</italic>) with their surgeonfish hosts in the Red Sea</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage> 1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27014209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Near</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eytan</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Dornburg</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wainwright</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Resolution of ray-finned fish phylogeny and timing of diversification</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>13698</fpage><lpage>13703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1206625109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22869754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Randall</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1961">1961</year><article-title>A contribution to the biology of the convict surgeonfish of the Hawaiian Islands, <italic>Acanthurus triostegus sandvicensis</italic></article-title><source>Pacific Science</source><volume>XV</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>272</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renko</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoefig</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiller</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schomburg</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Köhrle</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Identification of iopanoic acid as substrate of type 1 deiodinase by a novel nonradioactive iodide-release assay</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>153</volume><fpage>2506</fpage><lpage>2513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.2011-1863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22434082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roche</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvat</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramade</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Assessment of the pesticides pollution of coral reefs communities from French Polynesia</article-title><source>Revue d’écologie</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russ</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1984">1984</year><article-title>Distribution and abundance of herbivorous grazing fishes in the central Great Barrier Reef. I. Levels of variability across the entire continental shelf</article-title><source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps020023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadier</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevret</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Décimo</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sémon</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohmé</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruggiero</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlmann</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantalacci</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Laudet</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Tinkering signaling pathways by gain and loss of protein isoforms: the case of the EDA pathway regulator EDARADD</article-title><source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>129</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12862-015-0395-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26134525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandahl</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholz</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Comparative thresholds for acetylcholinesterase inhibition and behavioral impairment in coho salmon exposed to chlorpyrifos</article-title><source>Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1897/04-195R.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15683177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simonides</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulcahey</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Redout</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuidwijk</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wassen</surname> <given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Crescenzi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>da-Silva</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Harney</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Obregon</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianco</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Hypoxia-inducible factor induces local thyroid hormone inactivation during hypoxic-ischemic disease in rats</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Investigation</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>975</fpage><lpage>983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI32824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18259611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slotkin</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stapleton</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidler</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Does thyroid disruption contribute to the developmental neurotoxicity of chlorpyrifos?</article-title><source>Environmental Toxicology and Pharmacology</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.etap.2013.04.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23686008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solbakken</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Norberg</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittman</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Thyroxine as a mediator of metamorphosis of Atlantic halibut, <italic>Hippoglossus hippoglossus</italic></article-title><source>Environmental Biology of Fishes</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1007542526040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sullam</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Essinger</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozupone</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilham</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Environmental and ecological factors that shape the gut bacterial communities of fish: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>3363</fpage><lpage>3378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05552.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22486918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tagawa</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1989">1989</year><article-title>Changes in tissue and blood concentrations of thyroid hormones in developing chum salmon</article-title><source>General and Comparative Endocrinology</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0016-6480(89)90140-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2583473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tata</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Amphibian metamorphosis as a model for the developmental actions of thyroid hormone</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Endocrinology</source><volume>246</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mce.2005.11.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16413959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamano</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Differential gene expression of thyroid hormone receptor alpha and beta in fish development</article-title><source>General and Comparative Endocrinology</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/gcen.1997.7011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9446725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauridsen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Buels</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname> <given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>La Du</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruun</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanguay</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lein</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Chlorpyrifos-oxon disrupts zebrafish axonal growth and motor behavior</article-title><source>Toxicological Sciences</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/toxsci/kfr028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21346248</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.037</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bronner</surname><given-names>Marianne</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>California Institute of Technology</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Fish larval recruitment is a metamorphosis sensitive to reef pollutants&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by Marianne Bronner as the Senior Editor and Reviewing Editor. The following individuals involved in review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Sarah K McMenamin (Reviewer #1); David Hazlerigg (Reviewer #2); Alexander Schreiber (Reviewer #3).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>This paper considers the role of thyroid hormone in larval development in reef dwelling fish, with an emphasis on endocrine disruption and possible impacts on ecosystem health. Although the implication of TH in metamorphic change in reef dwelling fish is not surprising, the predicted impacts in terms of reef grazing are quite impressive. Thus, this is an important and timely study, one that successfully integrates endocrine, developmental, ecological, and toxicological influences on a key life history transition in a reef fish. Much of the text is cumbersome to read due to English not being the primary language of the authors. Specific required changes are listed below.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) On the drug / endocrine disruptor treatments, the authors are vague about mode of action. E.g. iopanoic acid (IPA) is described as &quot;an inhibitor of T4 degrading enzymes&quot;: actually IPA inhibits TH deiodinases, which act on both T4 and T3, and at least in mammals it is selective for outer ring deiodination by dio2. In fish the picture is probably less clear, due to uncertainties about pharmacological selectivity. Some more effort at clarity in this direction – not only for IPA but also for the other compounds employed – would be welcome.</p><p>2) By far the most interesting aspect of the study is the determination that larval recruitment in this species is indeed a TH-mediated process that induces diverse morphological and behavioral changes. The effects of chlorpyrifos on metamorphosis are interesting, but it is certainly a stretch to imply that chlorpyrifos is representative of all pollutants (there are many pollutants that likely don't affect TH, but instead affect other pathways, such as estrogen signaling). Therefore, the title should be revised as follows: &quot;Larval fish recruitment to reefs is a thyroid hormone-mediated metamorphosis sensitive to the pesticide chlorpyrifos&quot;.</p><p>3) The various morphological and histological analyses performed on natural <italic>A. Triostegus</italic> metamorphosis are excellent, and the changes in the gut are particularly fascinating! Considering this, it is surprisingly that the authors did not report the effects of T3/NH3 treatment or of CPF on any of these morphological features. Do these compounds have any effect on cross-sectional development of the gut, pigmentation, or dentition? If so, this should be reported and shown in a figure/table.</p><p>4) Please add more discussion of the gut 16S sequencing results. What does this imply about the ecology of larval vs. adult fish, and how does it integrate with the changes in craniofacial/tooth morphology and gut structure?</p><p>5) Are there any changes in pigment pattern, dentition or gut morphology in goitrogen-treated fish relative to controls? These should be shown, or if there are no changes, the lack of changes should be discussed.</p><p>6) Are there ocean samples for the other species examined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>? It would be valuable to show the increase in TH as fish approach the crest.</p><p>7) Are there any phenotypic aspects of metamorphosis that are blocked with CPF treatment?</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27595.038</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) On the drug / endocrine disruptor treatments, the authors are vague about mode of action. E.g. iopanoic acid (IPA) is described as &quot;an inhibitor of T4 degrading enzymes&quot;: actually IPA inhibits TH deiodinases, which act on both T4 and T3, and at least in mammals it is selective for outer ring deiodination by dio2. In fish the picture is probably less clear, due to uncertainties about pharmacological selectivity. Some more effort at clarity in this direction – not only for IPA but also for the other compounds employed – would be welcome.</p></disp-quote><p>The reviewers correctly pointed out our mistake in presenting the iopanoic acid (that we abbreviate IOP but that is abbreviated IPA by the reviewers) as “an inhibitor of T4 degrading enzyme”. We have corrected this mistake and changed this text into: “IOP being used as an inhibitor of the deiodinase enzymes”. To introduce the deiodinases to the reader we have also added the following sentence and reference in the Introduction: “The transformation of T4 into T3, and the degradation of T4 and T3 are controlled by a family of enzymes called deiodinases (Bianco and Kim 2006).” Concerning the selectivity of IOP (or IPA) for the outer ring deiodination performed by dio2, we are not aware of such a specificity. We have found some research discussing the effective inhibition of dio3 by IOP in mammals (Simonides et al. 2008; Medina et al. 2011). Moreover, in amphibians, both the inner ring and outer ring deiodination are inhibited by IOP, indicating that all the types of deiodinases are inhibited by IOP (Galton and Hiebert 1987; Galton and Hiebert 1988; Galton 1989). Nevertheless, we agree that deiodinases are less known in fish than in mammals and amphibians, because of fewer research. In our study, we used IOP to prevent the rapid degradation of T3 in the injected fish. Such treatments are routinely performed in fish to inhibit deiodinases (Little et al. 2013; Lorgen et al. 2015). Given the existing literature about IOP and its use, we believe that adding IOP to T3 can effectively prevents T3 degradation to ensure that the treatment exert a biological activity. We have added these clarifications in the Results section: “T3 + iopanoic acid (IOP) both at 10<sup>-6</sup> M, IOP being used as an inhibitor of the deiodinase enzymes that therefore prevents the degradation of injected T3 (Galton 1989; Little et al. 2013; Lorgen et al. 2015)”, and in the Materials and methods section: “IOP was used as an inhibitor of deiodinase enzymes, as evidenced in mammals and amphibians (Galton and Hiebert 1987; Galton and Hiebert 1988; Galton 1989; Simonides et al. 2008; Medina et al. 2011; Renko et al. 2012), and as routinely used in fish to prevent the immediate degradation of injected T3 (Little et al. 2013; Lorgen et al. 2015)”.</p><p>The other compound that we used is NH3, a TR antagonist that binds mammalian TR with a nanomolar affinity (Figueira et al. 2011). This compound works by preventing the binding of TH on TR (by occupying the pocket to which T3 normally binds) therefore impairing the recruitment of coactivators on TR, which thus remain in an inactive conformation (Figueira et al. 2011). To confirm the efficiency of NH3 as an antagonist on <italic>A. triostegus TRs</italic>, we have added, as a new panel D in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>, the results of a transactivation assayexperiment. This experiment shows that, in <italic>A. triostegus</italic>, the TR transcriptional activity induced by T3 is competitively inhibited in presence of NH3, in a dose dependant manner. Consequently, we have also added this clarification about NH3 in the Results section: “NH3 at 10<sup>-6</sup> M, NH3 being used as an antagonist of TR that prevents the binding of TH on TR (Lim et al. 2002; Renko et al. 2012) therefore disrupting <italic>A. triostegus</italic> TH pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1D</xref>)” and in the Materials and methods section: “NH3 is a known TR antagonist in vertebrates (Lim et al. 2002), a notion we confirmed in <italic>A. triostegus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1D</xref>). NH3 prevents the binding of TH on TR and impairs the binding of transcriptional coactivators to TR, which therefore remain in inactive conformation (Figueira et al. 2011; Lim et al. 2002).”.</p><p>We did not use goitrogens in this study, indeed goitrogens are inhibitor of TH synthesis and given that the TH level are already high in the crest captured larvae and decrease in the following days, we believe that goitrogen treatment would not be appropriate.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) By far the most interesting aspect of the study is the determination that larval recruitment in this species is indeed a TH-mediated process that induces diverse morphological and behavioral changes. The effects of chlorpyrifos on metamorphosis are interesting, but it is certainly a stretch to imply that chlorpyrifos is representative of all pollutants (there are many pollutants that likely don't affect TH, but instead affect other pathways, such as estrogen signaling). Therefore, the title should be revised as follows: &quot;Larval fish recruitment to reefs is a thyroid hormone-mediated metamorphosis sensitive to the pesticide chlorpyrifos&quot;.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with the reviewers. We have changed the manuscript title accordingly to the reviewers’ recommendations: &quot;Fish larval recruitment to reefs is a thyroid hormone-mediated metamorphosis sensitive to the pesticide chlorpyrifos&quot;.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) The various morphological and histological analyses performed on natural A. Triostegus metamorphosis are excellent, and the changes in the gut are particularly fascinating! Considering this, it is surprisingly that the authors did not report the effects of T3/NH3 treatment or of CPF on any of these morphological features. Do these compounds have any effect on cross-sectional development of the gut, pigmentation, or dentition? If so, this should be reported and shown in a figure/table.</p></disp-quote><p>Following reviewers’ recommendations we have conducted additional analyses in order to answer these concerns. These analyses have been performed on additional samples that we possessed since our initial sampling campaigns, and on new samples that we captured during a new sampling campaign dedicated to these revisions. As suggested we have looked for effect of these compounds on teeth and guts development, as well as pigmentation.</p><p>First, we did not observe any difference in teeth development between larvae treated with T3, NH3, or relocated on the external slope (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>, first column). Actually, it is not surprising that neither 2 to 5 days hormonal treatments nor environmental conditioning affect this developmental process, since teeth remodeling starts very early on in oceanic larvae, even before they enter in the reef (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore this remodeling is a lengthy process (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M-Q</xref>). We have discussed this point in our manuscript by adding: “We did not observe any effect on teeth development neither with T3+IOP or NH3 treatment, nor with external slope relocation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). Given that teeth remodeling is a lengthy process that starts very early on in oceanic larvae and therefore before reef colonization, it is not surprising that the treatments performed on crest captured larvae do not affect (or are too late to affect) teeth development”.Consequently to this observation, we did not proceed teeth morphology analyses in fish exposed to chlorpyrifos (CPF), as it seems unlikely that such exposure could lead to any teeth remodeling difference given that hormonal treatments did not.</p><p>Second, concerning pigmentation, black stripes appear rapidly in <italic>A. triostegus</italic> after larvae enter the reef (in 2 to 4 hours post-settlement, MB pers. obs.), and the white body pigmentation between the black vertical stripes appears at day 2 after reef entry (McCormick 1999). A clear pigmentation delay was observed in fish relocated on the external slope, as evidenced by McCormick (1999). We have presented this result more clearly: “In order to study how the environment controls the metamorphosis processes, we first relocated crest-captured larvae back to the external slope immediately after their reef entry. […] Similar to this earlier study, we observed a striking delay in the white pigmentation appearance between the vertical black stripes in day 2 relocated fish compared to their lagoon raised counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, lower panel).”</p><p>However, we did not observe any obvious difference in pigmentation between control larvae and larvae treated with T3+IOP, NH3 or exposed to CPF, both at day 2 and day 5. We have provided two additional figures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>) to present these observations that we have added in the Results section as follows: “Also, contrarily to individuals relocated on the outer slope, we did not observe any effect of T3+IOP nor NH3 treatments on skin pigmentation at day 2 and day 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>). This suggests that pigmentation during the larva to juvenile transition is strongly coupled to the environment but is not directly under TH control that may not sustain such rapid pigmentation changes” and: “We did not observe any effect of CPF treatments on fish pigmentation at day 2 and day 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>).” We suspect other hormonal systems to be at play here (cortisol in particular) and we are planning to test this hypothesis in a future study.</p><p>Finally, concerning the gut histology, we have performed and analyzed cross-sections of guts in fish treated with T3+IOP or NH3, as well as in fish relocated on the external slope. We observed interesting effects of these treatments on the microvilli remodeling during metamorphosis and we have added two additional figures to present these results (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). Indeed, we observed an early disappearance of microvilli in T3+IOP treated fish at day 2 post-settlement (in comparison to the control group, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>, second column, first row) and an advanced development of the second batch of microvilli (accompanied with an advanced thickening of the gut epithelium) in T3+IOP treated fish at day 5 post-settlement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>, second column, second row). At the opposite, NH3 treatment and external slope relocation both prevented guts remodeling at both day 2 and day 5, as evidenced in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref> (third and fourth column). These changes are perfectly consistent with the notion that guts remodeling at metamorphosis (both the lengthening and the microvilli renewal) are controlled by TH.</p><p>We have presented and explained these results in the Results section as follows: “A similar pattern was observed concerning the microvilli remodeling within guts. […] These changes are consistent with the notion that TH control remodeling of the guts at metamorphosis in <italic>A. triostegus.</italic>”</p><p>Please note that for reading convenience, the former <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>, is now the <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3G</xref> as the guts cross-sections have been inserted as the new <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>. Also former <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref> is now <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref> as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3C-E</xref> have been relabeled <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3B-D</xref> to present the experimental setup of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref> earlier in the text (which lead us to also present the results of the external slope relocation earlier in the text, and therefore to relabel all the panels of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p>Concerning CPF exposure, we do not possess biological samples that would permit us to analyze guts histology. Indeed, despite our substantial efforts and the additional sampling campaign, we did not succeed to capture/handle/transfer (from French Polynesia to France) these specific fish. However, we performed gut length analyses on extra frozen samples that we had conserved, and we observed, as expected, that the guts’ lengthening usually occurring at metamorphosis is delayed when fish are exposed to 5 and 30 µg.l<sup>-1</sup> CPF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). This lengthening delay is similar to the one observed with NH3 treated fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>) and is consistent with the notion that gut lengthening is controlled by TH (as evidenced in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>) as CPF exposure decreases T3 levels (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). These results on guts length and CPF exposure are now presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref> and are discussed as follows: “However, CPF exposure at 30 µg.l<sup>-1</sup> prevents guts’ lengthening at day 2 (p-value = 0.024, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref> left panel), and both exposure at 5 and 30 µg.l<sup>-1</sup> prevent intestines’ lengthening at day 5 (p-values = 0.047 and 0.029 respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref> right panel).” and: “Consistently with our observations on NH3 treated fish, exposure to CPF impairs metamorphosis, as evidenced with the repression of guts’ lengthening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>)”.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) Please add more discussion of the gut 16S sequencing results. What does this imply about the ecology of larval vs. adult fish, and how does it integrate with the changes in craniofacial/tooth morphology and gut structure?</p></disp-quote><p>We agree that the discussion following our 16S sequencing experiment results (in the Results section) was too short. We have complemented this discussion and moved it in the Discussion section: “These results highlight profound anatomical and physiological transformations of the skin and the whole digestive tract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B-W</xref>). […] All these changes from teeth to microbiota are consistent with <italic>A. triostegus</italic> change of diet after entering the reefs, conforming to previous observations (Randall 1961; McCormick 1999; Frédérich et al. 2012).” As explained above, we believe that changes in the gut bacterial community in <italic>A. triostegus</italic> are the consequence of the concomitant diet and environmental shifts occurring at larval recruitment.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) Are there any changes in pigment pattern, dentition or gut morphology in goitrogen-treated fish relative to controls? These should be shown, or if there are no changes, the lack of changes should be discussed.</p></disp-quote><p>There is apparently some sort of misunderstanding here as we did not treat the fish with goitrogens. We preferred to use NH3, a TR antagonist, to block the TH pathway instead of goitrogens (like methimazole and KClO<sub>3</sub>) that block the assimilation of iodine in the thyroid follicles or the TH synthesis in those same follicles (Schmidt et al. 2012). As evidenced in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A, 2B and 2C</xref>, levels of TH and expressions of <italic>TR</italic> are peaking at and before ref entry, so the use of goitrogens on crest captured larvae would not have been appropriate (i.e., too late). In contrast the use of NH3, a TR antagonist, was, to our knowledge, the best solution to disrupt the TH pathway in crest captured larvae. As discussed in full in our response to comment 3), we have effectively scrutinized the effect of NH3 on the pigmentation pattern, the dentition and the gut morphology. As mentioned above, we do observe a consistent effect of NH3 on gut histology and we invite the reviewers to see our reply to comment 3 for more details.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>6) Are there ocean samples for the other species examined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>? It would be valuable to show the increase in TH as fish approach the crest.</p></disp-quote><p>Following this comment we have performed TH level measurements on <italic>Rhinecanthus aculeatus</italic> and <italic>Chromis viridis</italic> oceanic larvae (near ocean samples) that we have added in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>. Unfortunately and despite our effort, we were not able to sample oceanic larvae of <italic>Chaetodon lunula</italic> and <italic>Ostorynchus angustatus</italic> in neither our previous nor novel near ocean and far ocean sampling campaigns. However, results on <italic>R. aculeatus</italic> and <italic>C. viridis</italic> confirm our model of TH peaking between oceanic and crest-captured individuals (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). We have edited the Results section for this figure as follows: “To widen our understanding of coral reef fish metamorphosis, we investigated the TH signaling during larval recruitment in four other coral fish species (<italic>Rhinecanthus aculeatus, Chromis viridis, Chaetodon lunula</italic> and <italic>Ostorhinchus angustatus</italic>) from distant families (Near et al. 2012). In these species, both T4 and T3 levels drop between day 1 and day 8, up to 3-fold for T4 (in O. angustatus, p-value = 0.029) and up to 4-fold for T3 (in <italic>R. aculeatus</italic>, p-value = 0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). […] This suggests some potential species-specific variation in coral reef fish TH profiles at recruitment that would be extremely interesting to decipher in future studies on additional species and with regards to other aspects of coral reef fish ecology (e.g., diets, size and pigmentation status at recruitment).”</p><p>We would like to thank the reviewers for this excellent suggestion that strengthens the generalization of our TH-mediated metamorphosis and larval recruitment model to other coral reef fishes and opens new insights for future research in this domain.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>7) Are there any phenotypic aspects of metamorphosis that are blocked with CPF treatment?</p></disp-quote><p>As suggested by the reviewers in their comment 3, we have analyzed the impact of CPF exposure on guts lengthening (which occurs at metamorphosis). We demonstrated that CPF diminished this lengthening, in very similar way as NH3 treatment (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). We have performed these requested analyses using supplementary frozen biological samples from our previous sampling campaign. Unfortunately, these frozen samples were not appropriate for gut histology analyzes. Also, we did not analyze the effect of CPF exposure on teeth remodeling since we did not observe any effect of T3 and NH3 treatments, as well as external slope relocation, on this teeth remodeling (as discussed in our reply to reviewers’ concern 3). Considering the lengthy process of teeth remodeling (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M-Q</xref>) and the fact that this process is already well advanced in crest individuals, it is not surprising that hormonal treatments and external slope relocation did not alter this remodeling, and it would be very unlikely that CPF exposure acts differently. Lastly, there was no effect of CPF exposure on pigmentation (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>). We invite the editor and the reviewers to see our reply to comment 3 for more details.</p><p>We believe that the additional analyses performed on guts lengthening (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>), accompanied by the initially performed analyses on the impact of CPF on <italic>A. triostegus</italic> feeding behavior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>) will be convincing enough for the reviewers to acknowledge that CPF is effectively impairing some aspects of metamorphosis (dropping TH levels, inhibiting guts lengthening and impairing the feeding behavior). In addition, we can also ensure that CPF is impairing other aspect of <italic>Acanthurus triostegus</italic> young settlers’ ecology, as we relate in a parallel study the impact of CPF on visual lateralization during settlement in <italic>A. triostegus</italic> (Besson et al. 2017, Exposure to agricultural pesticide impairs visual lateralization in a</p><p>larval coral reef fish, Scientific Reports, In Press). This study demonstrates that CPF can impair and even reverse visual lateralization in <italic>A. triostegus</italic> during this critical recruitment step.</p></body></sub-article></article>