<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">45061</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cancer Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Developmental Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The antimicrobial peptide defensin cooperates with tumour necrosis factor to drive tumour cell death in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-125004"><name><surname>Parvy</surname><given-names>Jean-Philippe</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6643-5686</contrib-id><email>j.parvy@beatson.gla.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-145360"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Yachuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-145361"><name><surname>Dostalova</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-127997"><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>Shu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-145362"><name><surname>Kurjan</surname><given-names>Alina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-145363"><name><surname>Bulet</surname><given-names>Philippe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-1348"><name><surname>Lemaître</surname><given-names>Bruno</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7970-1667</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-145364"><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>Marcos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-103669"><name><surname>Cordero</surname><given-names>Julia B</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1701-9480</contrib-id><email>julia.cordero@glasgow.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con9"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>CRUK Beatson Institute</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Glasgow</named-content></addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Global Health Institute, School of Life Sciences</institution><institution>Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Lausanne</named-content></addr-line><country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Invertebrate Genetics Laboratory</institution><institution>Genetic Strains Research Center, National Institute of Genetics</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Mishima</named-content></addr-line><country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="dept">Institute of Cancer Sciences</institution><institution>University of Glasgow</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Glasgow</named-content></addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution content-type="dept">Institute for Advanced Biosciences</institution><institution>CR University Grenoble Alpes, Inserm U1209, CNRS UMR5309, Immunologie Analytique des Pathologies Chroniques</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Grenoble</named-content></addr-line><country>France</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Oxford</institution><country>United Kingdom</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>Utpal</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>University of California, Los Angeles</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>30</day><month>07</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e45061</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2019-01-10"><day>10</day><month>01</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2019-06-26"><day>26</day><month>06</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2019, Parvy et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Parvy et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-45061-v1.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.001</object-id><p>Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) are small cationic molecules best known as mediators of the innate defence against microbial infection. While in vitro and ex vivo evidence suggest AMPs’ capacity to kill cancer cells, in vivo demonstration of an anti-tumour role of endogenous AMPs is lacking. Using a <italic>Drosophila</italic> model of tumourigenesis, we demonstrate a role for the AMP Defensin in the control of tumour progression. Our results reveal that Tumour Necrosis Factor mediates exposure of phosphatidylserine (PS), which makes tumour cells selectively sensitive to the action of Defensin remotely secreted from tracheal and fat tissues. Defensin binds tumour cells in PS-enriched areas, provoking cell death and tumour regression. Altogether, our results provide the first in vivo demonstration for a role of an endogenous AMP as an anti-cancer agent, as well as a mechanism that explains tumour cell sensitivity to the action of AMPs.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>Animals have a natural defence system – the immune system – that is needed to fight off disease-causing microbes, known as pathogens. One way the immune system attacks pathogens is by producing small microbe-killing molecules called antimicrobial peptides. These antimicrobial peptides carry a positive charge, which allows them to interact with and disrupt the negatively charged cell surfaces of many microbes. Healthy animal cells do not have these negatively charged components on their cell surface, which means they are invisible to antimicrobial peptides. Studies have reported that antimicrobial peptides can attack cancer cells grown in a dish. However, it was unclear whether they could fight cancer cells in a live animal.</p><p>Parvy et al. have now addressed this issue by studying tumours in the larvae of fruit flies. Flies with tumours made an antimicrobial peptide called Defensin, which normally helps to fight infections. When Parvy et al. deleted the gene coding for Defensin, less tumour cells were dying and the tumours became bigger. This result indicated that Defensin was protecting the fruit flies from tumours. Examining the tumours under the microscope showed that Defensin protein interacted with the membranes of tumour cells. Defensin was not, however, interacting with healthy cells.</p><p>Further analysis revealed that a negatively charged component of cell membranes called phosphatidylserine, which normally faces the inside of healthy cells, is exposed to the outer surface of tumour cells. This negatively charged molecule renders cancer cells visible to positively charged Defensin. Importantly, the exposure of the phosphatidylserine is mediated by the fly equivalent of a protein called Tumour Necrosis Factor, a key player in cancer biology. Defensin binding to tumour cells leads to their death.</p><p>These experiments in the fruit fly highlight key molecular mechanisms that allow antimicrobial peptides to fight cancer cells in a living organism. Because human tumour cells can also expose phosphatidylserine, these latest findings may open up the possibility of a new kind of anti-cancer therapy for patients.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>defensin</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial peptides</kwd><kwd>Drosophila</kwd><kwd>tumours</kwd><kwd>TNF</kwd><kwd>Phosphatidylserine</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd><italic>D. melanogaster</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000289</institution-id><institution>Cancer Research UK</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>A17196</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cordero</surname><given-names>Julia B</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100004440</institution-id><institution>Wellcome</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>104103/Z/14/Z</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cordero</surname><given-names>Julia B</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Natural activity of the antimicrobial peptide Defensin includes execution of tumour cell death by tumour necrosis factor in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Vast amount of evidence demonstrates the key role of systemic immunity in tumour progression and patient outcome. Efforts to manipulate the immune response to tumours are at the core of basic and translational cancer research. In mammals and flies, tumourigenesis triggers inflammation and activation of the immune system, leading to tumour cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Cordero et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Parameswaran and Patial, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Teng et al., 2008</xref>). Tumour Necrosis Factor (TNF) is an important player in these tumour/immune interactions and has pleiotropic effects on tumours, including induction of cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ham et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Parameswaran and Patial, 2010</xref>). This function is conserved in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, where the single TNF homolog Eiger (Egr), produced by tumour-associated macrophages (TAMs), has been shown to drive cell death of neoplastic tumours, generated in larval imaginal discs by the loss of apico-basal complex components such as Disc large 1, Scribble or Lethal giant larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Cordero et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Parvy et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, we have previously reported that tumours from <italic>disc large 1 Drosophila</italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> hereafter referred to as <italic>dlg</italic>), activate Toll pathway in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> fat body in an Egr-dependent manner, and this immune activation is necessary for TNF-dependent tumour cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>). However, the mechanisms by which activation of an immune response in the fat body executes tumour cell death remain unknown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.003</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title><italic>def</italic> is induced in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumour bearing animals.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Working model showing the cooperation between haemocyte-derived TNF and the immune response in the fat body in tumour cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) RT-qPCR analyses showing expression of several AMPs in the fat body of <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant tumour bearing larvae compared to wild-type (<italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic>) larvae (n = 4). (<bold>C</bold>) RT-qPCR analysis of <italic>def</italic> expression in <italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic> and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> whole larvae reared on antibiotics (n = 7). (<bold>D</bold>) RT-qPCR analysis showing <italic>def</italic> expression in larvae expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic> or a <italic>dlg-IR</italic> in the posterior part of the wing disc (<italic>en&gt;;UAS-dcr2</italic>) (n = 3). (<bold>E</bold>) Schematic representation of the <italic>def</italic> gene locus showing mutant alleles generated (UTR: Untranslated Regions, SP: Signal Peptide, PrD: Pro-Domain, Def: Mature Defensin). Statistical analysis: B-D, Student t-test, B, ***p=0.0003, C, **p=0.0074, D, *p=0.042.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><italic>def</italic> mediates animal survival to infection by Gram-positive bacteria.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Survival of <italic>def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> mutant flies (n = 53), upon Gram-positive, <italic>Listeria innocua</italic> infection, is compared to wild-type (<italic>wt</italic>) (n = 55) and <italic>spatzle (spz<sup>M7</sup>)</italic> (n = 30) (the Toll ligand) mutant flies. (<bold>B</bold>) Survival of <italic>def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> mutant flies (n = 37), upon Gram-negative, <italic>Erwinia carotovora carotovora</italic> infection, is compared to wild-type (<italic>wt</italic>) (n = 40) and <italic>relish (rel<sup>E20</sup>)</italic> (n = 10) (an Imd-pathway downstream effector) mutant flies. Statistical analysis: A, B, Log-rank test, A, ***p=0.00023, B, p=0.798.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig1-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>In <italic>Drosophila</italic> as in mammals, Toll pathway is well known to play a central role in the innate immune response to infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lemaitre et al., 1996</xref>). Downstream effectors of the Toll pathway include antimicrobial peptides (AMPs), which possess microbicidal activities against various pathogens. They display potent antimicrobial activity in vitro by disrupting negatively-charged microbial membranes. While intracellular activities have been reported, many AMPs kill pathogens by inserting into the lipid bilayer and disrupting the membrane integrity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brogden, 2005</xref>). Host cells are instead protected from AMP as they are positively charged and contain cholesterol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brender et al., 2012</xref>). In vitro studies have revealed AMPs capacity to kill cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Deslouches and Di, 2017</xref>). However, whether this cancer-killing activity is a natural function of AMPs is unknown, as there are no reports on an in vivo paradigm addressing such question. Since the Toll pathway is activated in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumour bearing larvae and is required for optimal TNF-induced tumour cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>), we hypothesised that AMPs may be involved in this process.</p><p>Here we show that <italic>Drosophila defensin</italic> is induced in the fat body and tracheal system of <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumour bearing larvae. We find Defensin consistently associated to dying tumour cells. Critically, systemic and tissue specific knockdown of Defensin demonstrates a non-redundant role of the AMP in controlling tumour growth through the induction of tumour cell death. Anti-tumoural Defensin production relies on TNF-dependent activation of both Toll and Imd pathway. Our results demonstrate that <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumours expose PS in response to haemocyte-derived TNF and that Defensin is present in PS enriched area on the tumour surface. Finally, we find that lack of TNF prevents PS exposure in tumours and makes them insensitive to the action of Defensin. Collectively, our results reveal an anti-tumoural role for Defensin in vivo and provide insights into the molecular mechanisms, which make tumours sensitive to the killing action of an endogenous AMP.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title><italic>dlg</italic> tumour bearing larvae express the AMP defensin</title><p>In order to assess expression of several AMPs we performed RT-qPCR analysis on fat bodies dissected from wild type controls (<italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic>) or <italic>dlg</italic> mutant larvae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Results showed consistent and statistically significant upregulation of <italic>defensin</italic> in fat bodies of <italic>dlg</italic> larvae compared to wild-type ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Other Toll-dependent AMPs display a trend to be increased (<italic>drosomycin</italic> and <italic>attacin A</italic>), even though data were highly variable amongst biological replicates, while other AMPs were not transcriptionally regulated (<italic>drosocyn</italic>, <italic>cecropin A1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Interestingly, human β-Defensin-1 displays anticancer activity in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bullard et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Sun et al., 2006</xref>), and deletion of human <italic>def</italic> appears prevalent in some cancer types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Ye et al., 2018</xref>). This prompted us to explore the role of <italic>Drosophila</italic> Defensin in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumours. Using <italic>dlg</italic> larvae reared on antibiotics, we confirmed that <italic>defensin</italic> upregulation was independent of the presence of microbes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). Moreover, larvae bearing <italic>dlg</italic> imaginal discs tumours induced by RNAi (<italic>en &gt;UAS-dcr2; UAS-dlg-IR</italic>) also displayed increased <italic>defensin</italic> expression, confirming <italic>def</italic> gene induction as a consequence of <italic>dlg</italic>-driven epithelial transformation rather than whole body dl loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). We conclude that Defensin, an AMP known for its activity against microbes, is induced, in a sterile environment, by the presence of tumours.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Defensin restrains <italic>dlg</italic> tumour growth and promotes tumour cell death</title><p>We next hypothesised that Defensin may be an important mediator of anti-tumour immunity in vivo. To test this hypothesis, we generated null mutant alleles for the <italic>defensin (def)</italic> gene using the CRISPR/Cas9 system (<italic>def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> and <italic>def<sup>sk4</sup></italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hanson et al., 2019</xref>). Survival analysis of <italic>def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> flies confirmed that this AMP contribute to resist systemic infection to certain Gram-positive bacteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Levashina et al., 1995</xref>). To evaluate the effect of Defensin on tumour development, we combined <italic>def</italic> and <italic>dlg</italic> loss of function alleles. Compared to <italic>dlg</italic> mutant animals, <italic>dlg;def</italic> double mutants displayed a significant increase in tumour size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). Tumour growth is limited by apoptotic tumour cell death as revealed by Dcp1 staining (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>). Interestingly, tumours from <italic>dlg;def</italic> double mutants display a very strong decrease in apoptosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B–E’</xref>), suggesting that increased tumour size in absence of Defensin is due to a decrease in tumour cell death. This was further supported by the similar proliferation rates measured in <italic>dlg</italic> and <italic>dlg,def</italic> mutant tumours as per quantification of anti-phophoHistone H3 staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A–E’</xref>). Importantly, the effect of Def on tumour size and cell death were still observed when <italic>dlg</italic> and <italic>dlg,def</italic> larvae were reared in sterile conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1F–J’</xref>) and further confirmed upon ubiquitous knock down of <italic>def</italic> using RNA interference (IR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F–J’</xref>). Furthermore, fat body overexpression of <italic>def</italic> significantly rescued tumour volume and tumour cell death of <italic>dlg;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> double mutant animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2K and L</xref>). Additionally, larval injection of a synthetic Defensin peptide increased tumour cell death of <italic>dlg</italic> or <italic>dlg;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> imaginal discs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2M</xref>), while it had no effect on tissues from wild-type larvae, indicating that Defensin can selectively promote cell death of tumour cells. Altogether, these results demonstrate that Defensin is required to control <italic>dlg</italic>-dependent tumourigenesis in vivo through induction of tumour cell death.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.005</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Def restricts tumour growth and promotes tumour cell death.</title><p>(<bold>A-E’</bold>) Quantification of tumour volume (TV) (<bold>A</bold>) and tumour cell death (TCD) (<bold>B</bold>) in wing imaginal discs from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> (n = 17), <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> (n = 19) and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk4</sup></italic> (n = 20) mutant larvae and representative immunofluorescence images of tissues quantified (<bold>C–E’</bold>). F, RT-qPCR analysis showing <italic>def</italic> expression upon ubiquitous knockdown (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>; tub&gt;</italic>) (n = 3). <bold>G-J’</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>G</bold>) and TCD (<bold>H</bold>) in wing imaginal discs from larvae ubiquitously expressing a <italic>control-IR</italic> (<italic>ctrl-IR</italic>: n = 10) or a <italic>def-IR</italic> (n = 15) and representative immunofluorescence images of tissues quantified (<bold>I–J’</bold>). <bold>K-L</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>K</bold>) and TCD (<bold>L</bold>) in wing imaginal discs from <italic>dlg</italic> mutant controls (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;lpp&gt;</italic>: n = 28), <italic>dlg;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> mutants controls (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk3</sup>;lpp&gt;</italic>: n = 31) or <italic>dlg;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> mutants expressing <italic>def</italic> in the fat body (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk3</sup>,UAS-def;lpp&gt;</italic>: n = 27). <bold>M</bold>, Effect of PBS (ctrl) or synthetic Def injection on TCD from wild-type larvae (<italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic>, ctrl: n = 10, Def: n = 9), <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> (ctrl: n = 10, Def: n = 10) and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> (ctrl: n = 11, Def: n = 18) mutant larvae. Tissues were stained with 4’,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, blue) for nuclei visualisation and with anti-cleaved Decapping protein 1 (Dcp1) antibody (red) to detect apoptotic cell death. Scale bars = 50 μm. Statistical analysis: A, B, K, L, One way ANOVA, *p&lt;0.05, ****p&lt;0.0001; F, Student t-test, ****p&lt;0.0001, G-H, Mann-Whitney test, G, **p=0.0054, H, ****p&lt;0.0001; M, Two way ANOVA (only relevant significant statistics are indicated), *p&lt;0.05, ****p&lt;0.0001.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig2-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.006</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Tumour suppression by Def is independent of infection and tumour cell proliferation.</title><p>(<bold>A-E’</bold>) Quantification of TV (<bold>A</bold>) and tumour proliferation (<bold>B</bold>) from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> (n = 19), <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> (n = 16) and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk4</sup></italic> (n = 17) mutant larvae and representative pictures of the corresponding tumours stained with DAPI (blue) or anti-phosphoHistone H3 (pH3) antibody to determine cell proliferation (red, <bold>C-E</bold> or white, <bold>C’–E’</bold>). <bold>F-J’</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>F</bold>) and TCD (<bold>G</bold>) from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> (n = 13), <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> (n = 13) and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk4</sup></italic> (n = 14) mutant larvae reared on antibiotics and representative pictures of the corresponding tumours stained with DAPI (blue) and anti-Dcp1 antibody (red) (<bold>H–J’</bold>). Scale bars = 50 μm. Statistical analysis: A, B, F, G, One way ANOVA, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig2-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Defensin remotely produced from immune tissues bind to tumour cells</title><p>Having shown that Defensin restrict tumour growth, we sought to determine the tissues that produced endogenous Defensin in the context of tumour bearing. Previous studies have shown that Defensin is not produced by imaginal discs or tumours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Bunker et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Külshammer et al., 2015</xref>). In the context of infection, Defensin can be produced by the fat body as well the tracheal and gut epithelium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Tzou et al., 2000</xref>). We monitored <italic>defensin</italic> expression by RT-qPCR in various immune tissues of tumour bearing animals. We observed that the fat body, homologue to the mammalian liver and adipose tissue, and the trachea, a network of tubes transporting oxygen to cells that resembles the mammalian vasculature, were the main sources of <italic>defensin</italic> in these animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). This was also supported by Defensin immunostaining, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B and C</xref>). Transcript assessment upon targeted IR knock down of <italic>defensin</italic> in the respective tissues further confirmed the domains of endogenous gene expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D and I</xref>). Importantly, knocking down <italic>defensin</italic> expression specifically in the fat body or the trachea of <italic>dlg</italic> animals, resulted in increased tumour size and decreased tumour cell death (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E–H’ and J–M’</xref>) confirming the non-redundant functional requirement of <italic>defensin</italic> in both tissues to efficiently promote tumour cell death.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.007</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Def from the trachea and the fat body mediates tumour cell death.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) RT-qPCR analysis of <italic>def</italic> expression in gut, fat body and trachea dissected from <italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic> or <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (n = 3). <bold>B-C</bold>, Fat body (<bold>B</bold>) and trachea (<bold>C</bold>) from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae stained with DAPI (blue) and anti-Def antibody (red). <bold>D</bold>, RT-qPCR analysis of <italic>def</italic> expression in <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;lpp&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic> or <italic>def-IR</italic> in the fat body (n = 4). <bold>E-H’</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>E</bold>) and TCD (<bold>F</bold>) in wing imaginal discs from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;lpp&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic> (n = 15) or <italic>def-IR</italic> (n = 17) in the fat body and representative immunofluorescence images of tissues quantified (<bold>G–H’</bold>). <bold>I</bold>, RT-qPCR analysis of <italic>def</italic> expression in dissected trachea from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;btl&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic> or <italic>def-IR</italic> in the trachea (n = 3). <bold>J-M’</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>J</bold>) and TCD (<bold>K</bold>) in wing imaginal discs from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;btl&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic> (n = 14) or <italic>def-IR</italic> (n = 16) in the trachea and representative immunofluorescence images of tissues quantified (<bold>L–M’</bold>). Tumours were stained with DAPI (blue) and anti-Dcp1 antibody (red). Scale bars = 50 μm. Statistical analysis: A, D, I, Student t-test, D, **p=0.0054, I, ****p&lt;0.0001; E, F, J, K, Mann-Whitney test, E, F, ****p&lt;0.0001, J, ***p=0.0009, K, ***p=0.0004.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig3-v1.tif"/></fig><p>To investigate the possibility that Defensin produced by the fat body and the trachea can specifically target tumour cells, we made use of an inducible haemagglutinin (HA) tagged form of Defensin (<italic>UAS-def-HA</italic>). We noticed leaky HA protein expression in the tracheal system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>) but not in the fat body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref>) of animals carrying the <italic>UAS-def-HA</italic> construct only. Therefore, we overexpressed <italic>UAS-def-HA</italic> in the fat body using a Gal4 specific driver (<italic>lpp &gt;def</italic> HA), which resulted in significant upregulation of Defensin in the fat body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1D</xref>) when compared to control conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref>), but also maintained the leaky expression of the transgene in the trachea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1C</xref>). Strikingly, overexpression of <italic>UAS-def-HA</italic> in the fat body resulted in Defensin-HA immunostaining in transformed imaginal discs from <italic>dlg</italic> mutant animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A–A’’ and B–B’’</xref>) but not in normal tissues from <italic>dlg</italic> heterozygous animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C and C’</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.008</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Def produced by immune tissues specifically targets tumour cells.</title><p>(<bold>A-A’’</bold>) DAPI (blue), anti-Dcp1 (green) and anti-HA antibody (red) staining of <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant tumour from larvae overexpressing a <italic>def-HA</italic> construct in the fat body and the trachea (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;lpp &gt;UAS-def-HA</italic>). <bold>B-B’’</bold>, Enlargement of inset from A’’ (white outline) showing Dcp1 (<bold>B</bold>), Def-HA (<bold>B’</bold>) and merged channels (<bold>B’’</bold>). <bold>C-C’</bold>, DAPI (blue), anti-Dcp1 (green) and anti-HA antibody (red) staining of <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> heterozygous wing disc from larvae overexpressing <italic>def-HA</italic> (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>/FM7;lpp &gt;UAS-def-HA</italic>). <bold>D-D’’</bold>, <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant tumour stained with DAPI (blue), anti-Def (red) and anti-Dcp1 (green) antibodies. <bold>E-E’’</bold>, Enlargement of inset from <bold>D’’</bold> (white outline) showing Dcp1 (<bold>E</bold>), Def (<bold>E’</bold>) and merged channels (<bold>E’’</bold>). F, Quantification of colocalization between Def and Dcp1 staining (n = 10). <bold>G-G’</bold>, wild type (<italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic>) wing imaginal disc stained with DAPI (blue), anti-Def (red) and anti-Dcp1 (green) antibodies. <bold>H-H’’</bold>, High-resolution imaging of a single dying tumour cell stained with DAPI (blue), anti-Def (red) and anti-Dcp1 (green) antibodies. A, C, D, G, Scale bars = 50 μm; B, E, Scale bars = 10 μm; H, Scale bar = 2.5 μm. Statistical analysis: F, Student t-test, **p=0.0093.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig4-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.009</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Characterisation of UAS-def-HA expression.</title><p>(<bold>A-B</bold>) DAPI (blue) and anti-HA antibody (red) staining showing basal expression of Def-HA in trachea (<bold>A</bold>) but not in fat body (<bold>B</bold>) of <italic>UAS-def-HA</italic> larvae. <bold>C-D</bold>, DAPI (blue) and anti-HA antibody (red) staining showing expression of Def-HA in the fat body and the trachea when overexpressed with a fat body specific driver (<italic>lpp &gt;UAS-def-HA</italic>). Scale bars = 50 μm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig4-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Consistently, using anti-Defensin antibody, we observed endogenous Defensin staining on <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumour (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D–D’’ and E–E’’</xref>) but not in wild-type discs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4G,G’</xref>). Interestingly, we observed Defensin preferentially bound to tumour areas enriched with apoptotic cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D–D’’ and E–E’’</xref>). This was confirmed by quantification of the amount of Def staining colocalising with Dcp1 staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F</xref>). High-resolution imaging showed Defensin enrichment at the membrane of these dying cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4H–H’’</xref>).</p><p>Altogether, these results show that Defensin produced by immune tissues selectively binds tumour cells to target them for apoptosis.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Toll and Imd pathway contribute to Defensin expression in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant larvae</title><p><italic>defensin</italic> expression upon systemic infection relies on both Toll and Imd pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lemaitre et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Leulier et al., 2000</xref>). While we previously showed that Toll pathway activation in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant larvae is required to achieve maximal tumour cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>), the involvement of the Imd pathway in tumour bearing animals was still elusive. To assess the contribution of the Imd pathway to both <italic>defensin</italic> expression and tumour burden, we analysed these two phenotypes in larvae deficient for the Imd-pathway. We observed a 55–60% decrease in <italic>defensin</italic> expression in <italic>dlg</italic> mutants carrying a loss of function allele affecting <italic>imd</italic> (<italic>dlg;imd<sup>1</sup>)</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>) or the gene encoding the downstream transcription factor Relish (<italic>dlg;rel<sup>E20</sup>)</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref>). Consistently, analysis of tumour phenotypes revealed increased tumour volume and decreased tumour cell death in <italic>dlg;imd<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic>dlg;rel<sup>E20</sup></italic> animals when compared with <italic>dlg</italic> counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B–E’ and G–J’</xref>). Altogether, these data demonstrate that the Imd pathway is required for <italic>defensin</italic> upregulation, impairment of tumour growth and induction of tumour cell death in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant larvae.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.010</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Imd pathway activation is required for <italic>def</italic> expression and Def-mediated tumour cell death.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) RT-qPCR analysis of <italic>def</italic> expression from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;imd<sup>1</sup></italic> mutant larvae (n = 4). <bold>B-E’</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>B</bold>) and TCD (<bold>C</bold>) in wing imaginal discs from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> (n = 15) and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;imd<sup>1</sup></italic> (n = 14) mutants larvae and representative immunofluorescence images of tissues quantified stained with DAPI (blue) and anti-Dcp1 antibody (red) (<bold>D–E’</bold>). <bold>F</bold>, RT-qPCR analysis showing <italic>def</italic> expression in <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>; rel<sup>E20</sup></italic> mutant animals (n = 5). <bold>G-J’</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>G</bold>) and TCD (<bold>H</bold>) from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> (n = 12) and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;rel<sup>E20</sup></italic> (n = 10) mutant larvae and representative pictures of the corresponding tumours (<bold>I–J’</bold>). Scale bars = 50 μm. Statistical analysis: A, F, Student t-test, A, ***p&lt;0.0003, F, ****p&lt;0.0001; B, C, G, H, Mann-Whitney test, B, C, H, ****p&lt;0.0001, G, **p=0.009.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig5-v1.tif"/></fig><p>Upon infection, AMP expression in the trachea exclusively relies on the Imd pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Tzou et al., 2000</xref>). We therefore looked at <italic>defensin</italic> expression and tumour phenotype in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant larvae where <italic>imd</italic> expression had been knocked down specifically within tracheal cells (<italic>dlg;btl &gt;imd-IR</italic>). In this setting, <italic>defensin</italic> expression was significantly reduced in the whole larvae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). Consistently, tumour volume was increased while tumour cell death was decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B–E’</xref>) showing the requirement of Imd pathway in the tracheal system to control tumour burden.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.011</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Imd and Toll pathway activation are required in the trachea and the fat body to promote Defensin-dependent tumour cell death.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) RT-qPCR analysis of <italic>def</italic> expression from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;btl&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic> or <italic>imd-IR</italic> in the trachea (n = 3). <bold>B-E’</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>B</bold>) and TCD (<bold>C</bold>) from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;btl&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic> (n = 18) or <italic>imd-IR</italic> (n = 15) in the trachea and representative immunofluorescence images of tissues quantified stained with DAPI (blue) and anti-Dcp1 antibody (red) (<bold>D–E’</bold>). <bold>F</bold>, RT-qPCR analysis of <italic>def</italic> expression from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;lpp&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic>, an <italic>imd-IR</italic> or a <italic>myd88-IR</italic> in the fat body. <bold>G-K’</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>G</bold>) and TCD (<bold>H</bold>) from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;lpp&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic>, an <italic>imd-IR</italic> or a myd88-IR in the fat body and representative immunofluorescence images of tissues quantified (<bold>I–K’</bold>). <bold>L-O</bold>, Quantification of TV (<bold>L, N</bold>) and TCD (<bold>M, O</bold>) from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;lpp&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic>, an <italic>imd-IR</italic> alone or in combination with a <italic>UAS-def</italic> in the fat body (<bold>L, M</bold>) and from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;lpp&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic>, a <italic>myd88-IR</italic> alone or in combination with a <italic>UAS-def</italic> in the fat body (<bold>N, O</bold>). Scale bars = 50 μm. Statistical analysis: A, Student t-test, A, ***p=0.0001; B, C, Mann-Whitney test, B, ***p=0.0003, C, ***p=0.0002; F, G, H, L-O, One way ANOVA, *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ****p&lt;0.0001.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig6-v1.tif"/></fig><p>In the fat body, both Imd and Toll pathways contribute to AMPs expression during infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Tzou et al., 2002</xref>). To evaluate the contribution of Toll and Imd pathways in fat body in tumour bearing larvae, we monitored <italic>defensin</italic> expression and tumour phenotype in <italic>dlg</italic> animals in which Toll or Imd pathways have been selectively knocked down in the fat body. Knocking down <italic>myd88,</italic> which encodes a common adaptor to Toll receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Imler and Zheng, 2004</xref>), or <italic>imd</italic> in the fat body resulted in a significant decrease in <italic>defensin</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6F</xref>) and, consistently, increased tumour volume and decreased tumour cell death (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6G–K’</xref>). Moreover, concomitant overexpression of <italic>defensin</italic> and <italic>Myd88-IR</italic> or <italic>Imd-IR</italic> in the fat body of <italic>dlg</italic> larvae was sufficient to significantly rescue the tumour volume and tumour cell death phenotypes resulting from fat body knockdown of <italic>Myd88</italic> or <italic>Imd</italic> in <italic>dlg</italic> animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6L–O</xref>).</p><p>We conclude that, in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant animals, Toll and Imd pathways have non-redundant roles in restricting tumour growth and promoting tumour cell death through the control of <italic>defensin</italic> expression. Importantly, forced <italic>defensin</italic> expression in an otherwise immune-compromised animal is sufficient to reduce tumour growth and to promote tumour cell death.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Defensin is enriched in tumour areas exposing phosphatidylserine</title><p>AMPs targeting of pathogens, involves the recognition of negatively charged molecules exposed on the cell surface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Yeaman and Yount, 2003</xref>). A key question raised by our study is how Defensin can selectively bind and kill tumour cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2M</xref>). Selective action of cationic AMP is attributed to their ability to interact with negatively charged membrane such as those found in bacteria. We hypothesised that the membrane of tumour cells from <italic>dlg</italic> mutant larvae might change their electrostatic properties, making them sensitive to the action of Defensin. Phosphatidylserine (PS) is a negatively charged phospholipid, normally restricted to the inner leaflet of the cell membrane. However, PS can be exposed on the outer leaflet for example in apoptotic cells, which tags these cells for phagocytosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Birge et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Shklyar et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Tung et al., 2013</xref>). Moreover, PS exposure has been shown to occur independently of apoptosis in many cancer cell types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Riedl et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, we investigated whether PS externalisation could be a factor allowing specific targeting of tumour cells by Defensin. Our data revealed that <italic>dlg</italic> but not wild-type tissues, displayed high levels of Annexin V staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A and F</xref>; compare to E), indicating increased exposure of PS by <italic>dlg</italic> tumours. We next looked at the ability of Defensin to specifically associate with tumour cells exposing PS and found that Defensin was enriched in Annexin V<sup>+ve</sup> areas on <italic>dlg</italic> tumours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A–A’’ and B–B’’</xref>). This was confirmed by quantification of the amount of Def staining colocalising with Annexin V staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref>). Thus, Defensin produced by immune responsive tissues binds specifically to tumour cells and this ability correlated with their exposure of PS.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.012</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>TNF is required for PS exposure and Defensin-driven tumour cell death.</title><p>(<bold>A-A’’</bold>) DAPI (blue), Annexin V (green) and anti-Def (red) staining of <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> mutant tumours. (<bold>B-B’’</bold>) Enlargement of inset from <bold>A’’</bold> (white outline) showing Annexin V (<bold>B</bold>), Def (<bold>B’</bold>) and merged channels (<bold>B’’</bold>). (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of colocalisation between Def and Annexin V staining (n = 18). (<bold>D</bold>) RT-qPCR analysis showing <italic>def</italic> expression in wild-type, <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> or <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;egr<sup>3</sup></italic> mutants. (<bold>E- G</bold>) Annexin V (green) and DAPI (blue) staining of wing imaginal discs from larvae of the indicated genotypes. (<bold>H, I</bold>) Annexin V (green) and DAPI (blue) staining of wing imaginal discs from <italic>dlg</italic> mutant larvae (<italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>,hml&gt;</italic>) expressing a <italic>ctrl-IR</italic> (n = 5) or an <italic>egr-IR</italic> (n = 9) in the haemocytes. (<bold>J</bold>) Quantification of Annexin V signal on tumours from the corresponding genotypes. (<bold>K</bold>) Quantification of TCD upon PBS (ctrl) or Def injection in wild-type (<italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic>, ctrl: n = 10, Def: n = 14), <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic> (ctrl/Def: n = 18) or <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;egr<sup>3</sup></italic> (ctrl: n = 20, Def: n = 13) mutant larvae. (<bold>L</bold>) A model for Def antitumoural activity. A, E-I, Scale bars = 50 μm; B, Scale bars = 20 μm. Statistical analysis: C, Student t-test, ****p&lt;0.0001; D, One way ANOVA, *p&lt;0.05; J, Mann-Whitney test, ***p=0.001; K, Two way ANOVA (only relevant significant statistics are indicated), *p&lt;0.05.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig7-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.013</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Def-HA does not associate to PS-negative <italic>egr</italic>-mutant tumours.</title><p>(<bold>A-B</bold>) DAPI (blue) and anti-HA antibody (red) staining showing expression of Def-HA in trachea (<bold>A</bold>) and fat body (<bold>B</bold>) of <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;egr<sup>3</sup>;lpp-gal4 &gt;UAS</italic> def-HA larvae. <bold>C-C’</bold>, DAPI (blue), anti-Dcp1 (green) and anti-HA antibody (red) staining showing absence of Def-HA on tumours of <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;egr<sup>3</sup>;lpp-gal4 &gt;UAS</italic> def-HA larvae. Scale bars = 50 μm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig7-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.014</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>TNF signalling activation does not require functional <italic>def</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A-C’</bold>) DAPI (white), anti-Dcp1 (red) and anti-Matrix metalloproteinase 1 (Mmp1, a reporter of JNK pathway activation, green) antibody staining of wing disc from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic>, <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk4</sup></italic> mutant larvae. <bold>D-F’</bold>, DAPI (white), Annexin V (green) and anti-Dcp1 (red) staining of tumours from <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup></italic>, <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> and <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>,imd<sup>1</sup></italic> mutant larvae. Scale bars = 50 μm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig7-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.015</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title><italic>scrib</italic> mutant tumours expose PS in a TNF-dependent manner and are sensitive to Def action.</title><p>(<bold>A-A’</bold>) DAPI (blue), anti-Dcp1 (red) and Annexin V (green) staining of <italic>scrib<sup>1</sup></italic> mutant tumours. (<bold>B-B’</bold>) DAPI (blue), anti-Dcp1 (red) and Annexin V (green) staining of egr<sup>3</sup>;<italic>scrib<sup>1</sup></italic> double mutant tumours. (<bold>C-C’’</bold>) <italic>scrib<sup>1</sup></italic> mutant tumour stained with DAPI (blue), anti-Dcp1 (green) and anti-Def (red) antibodies. <bold>D-D’’</bold>, Enlargement of inset from <bold>C’’</bold> (white outline) showing anti-Dcp1 (<bold>D</bold>), anti-Def (<bold>D’</bold>) and merged (<bold>D’’</bold>) channels. <bold>E, F</bold>, Quantification of tumour volume (<bold>E</bold>) and tumour cell death (<bold>F</bold>) in wing imaginal discs from <italic>scrib<sup>1</sup></italic> (n = 19) and <italic>def<sup>sk3</sup>;scrib<sup>1</sup></italic> (n = 18) mutant larvae. <bold>G-H’</bold>, representative immunofluorescence images of tissues quantified in E, F. A, B, C, G, H, Scale bars = 50 μm; D, Scale bar = 10 μm. Statistical analysis: E, F, Mann-Whitney test, E, **p=0.0015, F, ***p&lt;0.0001.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-fig7-figsupp3-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>The TNF homolog Eiger is required for PS exposure and defensin anti-tumoural activity</title><p>Previous studies have shown that circulating macrophage-like cells in <italic>Drosophila,</italic> called haemocytes, bind to <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumours and contribute to cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>). This process is mediated by the release of Egr from haemocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Cordero et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>), which then activates the JNK pathway in target cells to promote apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Igaki et al., 2009</xref>). Moreover, Toll pathway activation in tumour bearing animals also requires Egr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>). Accordingly, we found that <italic>defensin</italic> upregulation observed in <italic>dlg</italic> animals was lost in <italic>dlg;egr<sup>3</sup></italic> double mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7D</xref>). We next tested whether PS exposure in tumours was dependent on Eiger, and observed an almost complete loss of cell-surface PS in <italic>dlg;egr<sup>3</sup></italic> tumours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7E–G</xref>). Therefore, Egr is required for PS exposure in these tumours. We then analysed PS exposure in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumours, upon specific <italic>egr</italic> knockdown in haemocytes (<italic>dlg;hml &gt;egr-IR</italic>), and observed a strong decrease in cell surface-exposed PS compared to control tumours (<italic>dlg;hml &gt;ctrl-</italic>IR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7H–J</xref>). This indicates that PS exposure in tumour cells is likely triggered by the release of Egr from haemocytes. Finally, to further test the hypothesis that Def requires PS to bind to tumours, we assessed the ability of overexpressed Def-HA to bind to <italic>dlg,egr<sup>3</sup></italic> mutant tumours. Consistently with the observed basal and overexpressed Def-HA expression pattern in wild type tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>), Def-HA was expressed in the trachea and fat body of <italic>dlg,egr<sup>3</sup></italic> mutant animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1A,B</xref>). However, we did not find any detectable association of Def-HA to the surface of <italic>dlg,egr<sup>3</sup></italic> tumours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1C,C’</xref>).</p><p>Importantly, Egr-dependent signalling and PS exposure were intact in <italic>dlg;def</italic> and <italic>dlg;imd</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s2">Figure 7—figure supplement 2</xref>) indicating that both events precede the action of Defensin in <italic>dlg</italic> tumours. To further assess whether Egr was required for Defensin-induced tumour cell death, we injected synthetic Defensin peptide into control, <italic>dlg</italic> or <italic>dlg;egr<sup>3</sup></italic> mutant larvae. While, Defensin injection was able to robustly promote tumour cell death in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumours, it was unable to affect tumours derived from Egr-deficient animals, further demonstrating the requirement of Egr for tumour cell death induced by Defensin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7K</xref>).</p><p>Finally, we tested whether the antitumoral action of Def extended to other tumour models. We observed that tumours induced by the loss of <italic>scribble</italic> (<italic>scrib</italic>), another member of the same apico-basal complex as <italic>dlg,</italic> showed significant cell surface PS exposure, which was Egr dependent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s3">Figure 7—figure supplement 3A,A’</xref>; compare to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s3">Figure 7—figure supplement 3B,B’</xref>). Moreover, we detected Def enrichment in areas positive for Dcp1 staining on <italic>scrib</italic> tumours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s3">Figure 7—figure supplement 3C–C’’ and D–D’’</xref>). Consistently, removing <italic>def</italic> from <italic>scrib</italic> mutant animals led to increase in tumour volume and decrease in tumour cell death (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s3">Figure 7—figure supplement 3E–H’</xref>). Altogether, these results show that the sensitivity to Def is not restricted to <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumours but might rather be a general feature of neoplastic growth induced by loss of cell polarity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>While the role of antimicrobial peptides in innate immune defense has been well-recognised for decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bahar and Ren, 2013</xref>), recent reports revealed potential additional physiological functions of AMPs, including ageing and neurodegeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Cao et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kounatidis et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lezi et al., 2018</xref>), wound-healing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Chung et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tokumaru et al., 2005</xref>), resistance to oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mergaert et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Zhao et al., 2011</xref>), immune signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Tjabringa et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">van Wetering et al., 2002</xref>) and anti-cancer activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Deslouches and Di, 2017</xref>). However, due to the absence of AMP mutants, most of these studies have relied on the use of exogenous sources of AMPs or genetic modification of upstream regulators of AMP expression. Recently, the use of loss of function alleles of <italic>Drosophila</italic> Diptericin (DptB), allowed to establish a role for the AMP in long-term memory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Barajas-Azpeleta et al., 2018</xref>). Pioneer work reporting systematic deletion of multiple AMPs in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, opens the door for in-depth analysis of the endogenous functions of these molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hanson et al., 2019</xref>). Using such tools and a genetically defined in vivo tumour model, our study demonstrates a role for Defensin in the control of tumours and deciphers the molecular mechanism allowing specific tumour cell targeting by the AMP. Collectively, our results suggest that the two branches of <italic>Drosophila</italic> innate immunity contribute to tumour elimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7L</xref>). The cellular immune response to tumours involves the binding of haemocytes to tumour cells and activation of TNF pathway leading to PS exposure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7L</xref>). This is followed by a humoral response in distant tissues (fat body and trachea) that triggers tumour cell death through the action of Defensin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7L</xref>).</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>A role for a <italic>Drosophila</italic> AMP in tumour control</title><p>Using mutants as well as ubiquitous or targeted knockdowns, our study reveals that Defensin is non-redundantly required to drive tumour cell death and restrict tumour growth in neoplastic tumours generated by loss the apico-basal determinant Dlg and Scrib. This was reinforced by detection of Defensin on dying tumour cells as well as genetic rescue and injection experiments showing that Defensin can actively drive tumour cell death. Several in vitro studies in mammals have pointed to AMPs anti-tumoural potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Deslouches and Di, 2017</xref>). Amongst these suggested anticancer peptides, Human β-Defensin-1 (hBD1) appears downregulated in 82% of prostate cancer and 90% of renal clear cell carcinomas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Donald et al., 2003</xref>). Furthermore, expression of hBD1 induces cell death in prostate and renal cancer cells in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bullard et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Sun et al., 2006</xref>). Moreover, a recent report shows prevalent deletion of Human <italic>defensin</italic> gene cluster in some tumour types including prostate, lung and colorectal cancers, as well as a decrease overall survival in patients carrying these deletions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Ye et al., 2018</xref>). However, since the classification of a molecule as AMP is based on structural protein features, it is important to mention that Human Defensins are not homologous of, but rather have structural resemblances, to <italic>Drosophila</italic> AMPs due to convergent evolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Shafee et al., 2017</xref>). Further studies are required to determine if anticancer activity displayed by Defensins from different species is linked to their structural properties.</p><p>As upon infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Tzou et al., 2000</xref>), we show that the fat body and the trachea are the main sources of Defensin in tumour bearing larvae. Moreover, our results indicated that Defensin’s maximal expression and anti-tumour properties rely on Imd and Toll pathways activation. As expected from previous studies on anti-pathogenic immunity, Imd appears to play a critical role in the tracheal system, while both Imd and Toll drive Defensin expression in the fat body (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Hoffmann and Reichhart, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Tzou et al., 2002</xref>). Consistently, overexpressing Defensin partially rescued the effect of Imd or Toll knockdown on <italic>dlg</italic> tumours. However, Toll and Imd pathways are major regulators of multiple AMPs in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> fat body. Then, it is conceivable that AMPs other than Defensin may possess similar anti-tumoural activity. In fact, a recent study in <italic>Drosophila</italic> shows that ectopic expression of several antimicrobial peptides, including Defensin, can increase cell death in a haematopoietic tumour model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Araki et al., 2019</xref>). Authors of that study also reported activation of Toll and Imd pathways together with increased expression of several AMPs in those tumour bearing animals. Together with our study, this suggests potentially general anti-tumoural properties of <italic>Drosophila</italic> AMPs.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Defensin specifically targets tumour cells</title><p>Importantly, we show that Defensin targets tumour cells for apoptosis while sparing normal cells. As their human counterparts, we show that <italic>Drosophila</italic> tumours can expose PS independently of cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Riedl et al., 2011</xref>). Interestingly, an in vitro study showed selective anticancer activity of some synthetic peptides derived from beetle Defensin, against cancer cells exposing PS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Iwasaki et al., 2009</xref>). A similar targeting mechanism has also been proposed to explain temporin-1CEa or L-K6 anticancer activities towards melanoma cells and breast cancer cells respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Wang et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). PS is a mark of apoptotic cells, which is used as an ‘eat me’ signal by phagocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Shklyar et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Tung et al., 2013</xref>). In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, the phagocytic receptor Simu together with Draper contribute to the elimination of apoptotic cells through recognition of PS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Shklyar et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Tung et al., 2013</xref>). It would be interesting to test the role of these receptors in the control of tumour progression in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</p><p>Our results indicate that PS exposure precedes Defensin action and is not just an ‘eat-me’ signal but likely contributes to changing the membrane of tumour cells making them sensitive to the action of AMPs. It is tempting to speculate that the deleterious effect of AMPs observed upon ageing or neurodegeneration may involve a similar targeting mechanism of ‘foreign-looking’ or unfit cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cao et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kounatidis et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lezi et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>Noteworthy, other negatively charged molecules enriched on tumour surface such as heparan sulfates and O-glycosylated mucins may also contribute to the targeting by AMPs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hollingsworth and Swanson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Knelson et al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Defensin action requires TNF</title><p>TNF is a major player in the tumour microenvironment by exerting pleiotropic effects on both the tumour and its surroundings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ham et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Parameswaran and Patial, 2010</xref>). In our <italic>dlg</italic> mutant model, we observed that defensin induction requires TNF, supporting previous observations that induction of innate immune response in tumour bearing animal relied on Egr produced by the tumour (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>). Indeed, Toll activation in the fat body has been proposed to be a consequence of tumour-derived TNF, which drives haemocyte proliferation leading to an increase in Toll ligand Spatzle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>). Whether Imd pathway is also indirectly activated by the changes in immune cell activity in response to tumour or by alternative mechanisms remains an open question.</p><p>Our results show that haemocyte-derived TNF is required for PS exposure by the tumour, a key process for tumour targeting by Defensin. Consistently, haemocyte-derived TNF is shown to drive cell death in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant tumours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>). The precise molecular mechanisms driving PS exposure downstream of TNF remain unknown. However, haemocyte-derived TNF, activates JNK pathway, which triggers many changes in tumour cells including apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Igaki et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Moreno et al., 2002</xref>), ROS production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Fogarty et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Santabárbara-Ruiz et al., 2015</xref>), loss of cell polarity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Zhu et al., 2010</xref>), modification of extracellular matrix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Uhlirova and Bohmann, 2006</xref>), proliferation and cell migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Beaucher et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Igaki et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Pastor-Pareja et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Srivastava et al., 2007</xref>). Mild activation of JNK on its own is insufficient to drive PS exposure and tissue sensitivity to Defensin-induced cell death (data not shown). While a JNK-independent role of Egr in PS exposure and sensitivity to the AMP cannot be ruled out, TNF might also sensitise cells through activation of the JNK pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Cordero et al., 2010</xref>) and PS exposure, thus providing a secondary sensitisation mechanism of tumour cells to the action of Defensin. Further studies are needed to explore a potential link between JNK activation and PS exposure.</p><p>Another consequence of TNF-dependent JNK activation in tumours is the increased expression of matrix metalloproteases (Mmps) by tumour cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Uhlirova and Bohmann, 2006</xref>). Importantly, we show that Mmp-1 induction and then JNK pathway activation are still present in tumour from larvae devoided of Defensin. This demonstrates that TNF signalling acts upstream of Defensin. Mmps degrade the basal membrane facilitating metastasis of primary tumour cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Beaucher et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Pastor-Pareja et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Srivastava et al., 2007</xref>). Interestingly, a study reported that human Mmp-7 can cleave immature Defensins, promoting their activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wilson et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Wilson et al., 2009</xref>). Indeed, the pro-domain present in AMPs is thought to keep their in vivo activity silent, allowing local activation of AMP upon cleavage. While the mechanisms of <italic>Drosophila</italic> Defensin pro-domain cleavage remain unknown, it would be interesting to explore whether the changes in the tumour microenvironment could also affect Defensin activation.</p><p>In conclusion, our study provides the first direct in vivo demonstration of the role of an endogenous AMP as an anti-cancer agent in <italic>Drosophila</italic>. Our data point to a conserved mechanism of tumour control by AMPs, a potent arm of the innate immune system. Importantly, we identify cellular features within tumours, which may be predictive of their sensitivity to be targeted by AMPs. This study provides a new paradigm to decipher the molecular mechanisms influencing anti-tumoural functions of an AMP, which may extend to other non-canonical roles of AMPs, such as in ageing, long-term memory and wound healing. Moreover, together with the new genetic tools allowing targeting of all <italic>Drosophila</italic> AMPs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hanson et al., 2019</xref>), our study establishes new bases to explore in vivo a potential important natural mechanism of defence against tumours.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Reagent type <break/>(species) or resource</th><th>Designation</th><th>Source or reference</th><th>Identifiers</th><th>Additional <break/>information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td valign="top">w<sup>1118</sup></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Dewey et al., 2004</xref>)</td><td valign="top">BDSC: 3605; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/BDSC_3605">BDSC_3605</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td valign="top">w<sup>1118</sup> iso</td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ferreira et al., 2014</xref>)</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td valign="top">dlg<sup>40.2</sup>/FM7</td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Mendoza-Topaz et al., 2008</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Flybase_FBal0240608</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>FRT82B,scrib<sup>1</sup>/TM6</td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bilder et al., 2000</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Flybase_FBal0103577</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td valign="top">egr<sup>3</sup></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Igaki et al., 2002</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Flybase_FBal0147163</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>imd<sup>1</sup></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Leulier et al., 2000</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Flybase_ <break/>FBal0045906</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>rel<sup>E20</sup></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Leulier et al., 2000</xref>)</td><td valign="top">DGGR: 109927; <break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/DGGR_109927">DGGR_109927</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>def<sup>sk3</sup></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hanson et al., 2019</xref>)</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>def<sup>sk4</sup></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hanson et al., 2019</xref>)</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>btl-gal4,UAS-RFP/CyO</td><td>Irene Miguel-Aliaga</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>lpp-gal4/TM6B</td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Brankatschk and Eaton, 2010</xref>)</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>tub-gal4</td><td>Bloomington <italic>Drosophila</italic> Stock Center</td><td valign="top">BDSC: 5138; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/BDSC_5138">BDSC_5138</ext-link></td><td valign="top">y(1) w[*]; P{w[+mC]=tubP-GAL4}LL7/TM3, Sb(4) Ser(1)</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>hml<sup>Δ</sup>-gal4,UAS-gfp</td><td>Bruno Lemaitre</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>en-gal4</td><td>Bloomington <italic>Drosophila</italic> Stock Center</td><td>BDSC: 30564; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/BDSC_30564">BDSC_30564</ext-link></td><td valign="top"><italic>y1 w*; P{w + mW.hs=en2.4 GAL4}e16E</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>UAS-def IR</td><td>Vienna <italic>Drosophila</italic> Resource Centre</td><td valign="top">VDRC: 102437; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/Flybase_FBst0474306">Flybase_FBst0474306</ext-link></td><td valign="top">P{KK111656}VIE-260B</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>UAS-imd IR</td><td>Vienna <italic>Drosophila</italic> <break/>Resource Centre</td><td valign="top">VDRC: 101834; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/Flybase_FBst0473707">Flybase_FBst0473707</ext-link></td><td valign="top">P{KK109863}VIE-260B</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>UAS-myd88 IR</td><td>Vienna <italic>Drosophila</italic> Resource Centre</td><td valign="top">VDRC: 25402; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/Flybase_FBst0455868">Flybase_FBst0455868</ext-link></td><td valign="top">w<sup>1118</sup>; P{GD9716}v25402</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>UAS-dlg IR</td><td>Vienna <italic>Drosophila</italic> Resource Centre</td><td valign="top">VDRC: 41136; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/Flybase_FBst0463952">Flybase_FBst0463952</ext-link></td><td valign="top">w<sup>1118</sup>; P{GD4689}v41136/TM3</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila</italic> <break/><italic>melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>UAS-egr IR</td><td>Vienna <italic>Drosophila</italic> Resource Centre</td><td valign="top">VDRC: 108814; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/Flybase_FBst0480608">Flybase_FBst0480608</ext-link></td><td valign="top">P{KK103432}VIE-260B</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>UAS-w IR</td><td>Bloomington <italic>Drosophila</italic> Stock Center</td><td valign="top">BDSC: 25785; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/BDSC_25785">BDSC_25785</ext-link></td><td valign="top">y(1) v(1); P{y[+t7.7] v[+t1.8]=TRiP.JF01786}attP2</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>UAS-def</td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Tzou et al., 2000</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Flybase_FBal0145092</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>UAS-def-3xHA</td><td>FlyORF</td><td valign="top">FlyORF: F002467; <break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/Flybase_FBal0298643">Flybase_FBal0298643</ext-link></td><td valign="top">M{UAS-Def.ORF.3xHA.GW}ZH-86Fb</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>UAS-dcr2</td><td>Bloomington <italic>Drosophila</italic> Stock Center</td><td valign="top">BDSC: 24650; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/BDSC_24650">BDSC_24650</ext-link></td><td valign="top">w[1118]; P{w[+mC]=UAS-Dcr-2.D}2</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>)</td><td>spz<sup>M7</sup></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Neyen et al., 2014</xref>)</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-GFP (Chicken polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Abcam</td><td valign="top">Cat# ab13970; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_300798">AB_300798</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:4000)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-Def (Mouse polyclonal)</td><td valign="top">Dahua Chen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Ji et al., 2014</xref>)</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top">IF(1:100)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-HA (Mouse monoclonal)</td><td>Cell Signaling Technology</td><td valign="top">Cat# 2367, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_10691311">AB_10691311</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-dcp1 (Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td>Cell Signaling Technology</td><td valign="top">Cat# 9578, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2721060">AB_2721060</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:100)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-phospho-Histone H3 (Ser10) (Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td>Cell Signaling Technology</td><td valign="top">Cat# 9701, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_331535">AB_331535</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:100)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-phospho-Histone H3 (Ser28) (Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td>Cell Signaling Technology</td><td valign="top">Cat# 9713, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_823532">AB_823532</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:100)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-Mmp1 (Mouse clonality unknown)</td><td>Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank</td><td valign="top">Cat# 3B8D12, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_579781">AB_579781</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:10)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-Chicken IgY Alexa 488 <break/>(Goat polyclonal)</td><td>Molecular Probes</td><td valign="top">Cat# A-11039, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_142924">AB_142924</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:500)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-Mouse IgG Alexa 488 (Goat polyclonal)</td><td>Molecular Probes</td><td valign="top">Cat# A-11029, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_138404">AB_138404</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:500)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-Mouse IgG Alexa 594 <break/>(Goat polyclonal)</td><td>Molecular Probes</td><td valign="top">Cat# A-11032, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_141672">AB_141672</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:500)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-Rabbit IgG Alexa 488 (Goat polyclonal)</td><td>Molecular Probes</td><td valign="top">Cat# A-11008, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_143165">AB_143165</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:500)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-Rabbit IgG Alexa 594 <break/>(Goat polyclonal)</td><td>Thermo Fischer Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# A-11037, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2534095">AB_2534095</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IF(1:500)</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>rpl32-fwd</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">AGGCCCAAGATCGTGAAGAA</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">rpl32-rev</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">TGTGCACCAGGAACTTCTTGA</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>def-fwd</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">CTTCGTTCTCGTGGCTATCG</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>def-rev</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">ATCCTCATGCACCAGGACAT</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>def-PCR-fwd</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">TTATTGCAGAAACGGGCTCT</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>def-PCR-rev</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">ATGGTAAGTCGCTAACGCTAATG</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>def-seq</td><td>This paper</td><td>Sequencing primers</td><td valign="top">CGTGTCTTCCTGCACAGAAA</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>attA-fwd</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">ATGCTCGTTTGGATCTGACC</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>attA-rev</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">TCAAAGAGGCACCATGACCAG</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>cecA1-fwd</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">CTCAGACCTCACTGCAATAT</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>cecA1-rev</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">CCAACGCGTTCGATTTTCTT</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>dro-fwd</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">CGTTTTCCTGCTGCTTGCTT</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>dro-rev</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">GGCAGCTTGAGTCAGGTGAT</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>drs-fwd</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">CTCTTCGCTGTCCTGATGCT</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>drs-rev</td><td>This paper</td><td>PCR primers</td><td valign="top">ACAGGTCTCGTTGTCCCAGA</td></tr><tr><td>Peptide, recombinant protein</td><td valign="top"><italic>Drosophila</italic> endogenous Defensin</td><td valign="top">Bulet EIRL</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Peptide, recombinant protein</td><td valign="top"><italic>Drosophila</italic> Synthetic Defensin</td><td valign="top">Genepep</td><td valign="top">N/A</td><td valign="top">ATCDLLSKWNWNHTACAGHCIAKGFKGGYCNDKAVCVCRN</td></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">High Capacity cDNA Reverse <break/>Transcription Kit</td><td valign="top">Applied Biosystems</td><td valign="top">Cat# 4368813</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">PerfeCTa SYBR Green FastMix (Low ROX)</td><td valign="top">Quanta Bio</td><td valign="top">Cat# 95074–012</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">TRIzol Reagent</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# 15596018</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">Turbo DNA free Kit</td><td valign="top">Life Technologies LTD</td><td valign="top">Cat# AM1907</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td valign="top">High Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit</td><td valign="top">Applied Biosystems</td><td valign="top">Cat# 4368813</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">4′,6-Diamidine-2′-phenylindole dihydrochloride (DAPI)</td><td valign="top">Sigma</td><td valign="top">Cat# D9542</td><td valign="top">1 μg/mL</td></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Fiji</td><td>NIH</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fiji.sc/">https://fiji.sc/</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>GraphPad Prism 6</td><td>GraphPad</td><td>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_002798">SCR_002798</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>7500 Real-Time PCR Software</td><td>Applied Biosystems</td><td>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_014596">SCR_014596</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>BatchQuantify</td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Johansson et al., 2019</xref>)</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/emltwc/2018-Cell-Stem-Cell">https://github.com/emltwc/2018-Cell-Stem-Cell</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>GraphPad Prism 6</td><td>GraphPad</td><td>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_002798">SCR_002798</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td valign="top">Volocity 3D Image Analysis Software</td><td valign="top">Perkin Elmer</td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_002668">SCR_002668</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>ZEN two lite</td><td>Zeiss</td><td>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_013672">SCR_013672</ext-link></td><td/></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td valign="top">RNasine Plus RNase Inhibitor</td><td valign="top">Promega</td><td valign="top">Cat# N261</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td valign="top">Vectashield mounting media</td><td valign="top">Vector Laboratories, Inc.</td><td valign="top">Cat# H-1000–10</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td valign="top">Annexin V, Alexa Fluor 568 conjugate</td><td valign="top">Life Technologies LTD</td><td valign="top">Cat# A13202</td><td valign="top">1:20</td></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td valign="top">Annexin V, Alexa Fluor 488 conjugate</td><td valign="top">Life Technologies LTD</td><td valign="top">Cat# A13201</td><td valign="top">1:20</td></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td valign="top">Penicillin-Streptomycin (10,000 U/mL)</td><td valign="top">Thermo Fisher <break/>Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# 15140122</td><td valign="top">Pen: 100 IU/mL <break/>Strep: 100 mg/mL</td></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td valign="top">PfuUltra II Fusion HS DNA Polymerase</td><td valign="top">Agilent</td><td valign="top">Cat# 600670</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td valign="top">AnnexinV binding buffer</td><td valign="top">Fisher Scientific</td><td valign="top">Cat# BDB556454</td><td valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title><italic>Drosophila</italic> housekeeping and rearing</title><p>Flies were reared at 25°C under 12 hr/12 hr light/dark cycles on standard oatmeal and molasses medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Fernandez-Ayala et al., 2009</xref>). Details on fly strains used in this study are presented in the key resources table and detailed genotypes are included in corresponding figure legends.</p><p>For assessment of tumour volume and tumour cell death, flies were transferred to medium embryo collection cages and allowed to lay eggs for 8 hr at room temperature (RT) on agar/grape juice plates (2.1% agar, 25% grape juice, 1.25% sucrose, 0.2% methyl 4-hydroxybenzoate) supplemented with yeast paste. Plates were kept at 25°C until hatching. 200 larvae hatched within a 4 hr time window were collected and transferred to rearing bottles containing 45 mL of fly food to avoid any developmental delay and/or starvation effects due to overcrowding conditions. The tumour phenotype was analysed close to the normal developmental time, i.e. 7 days after hatching. Tumours were dissected and stained for further analysis (see below).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Generation of <italic>defensin</italic> mutants</title><p><italic>def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> and <italic>def<sup>sk4</sup></italic> mutants were generated using CRISPR/cas9 technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hanson et al., 2019</xref>). Mutants were isogenised through backcrosses with a <italic>w<sup>1118</sup> iso</italic> line as previously described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ferreira et al. (2014)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Survival assays</title><p>Survival of <italic>def<sup>SK3</sup></italic> animals was compared to wild type controls (isogenised background, <italic>iso</italic>). Male flies (5–7 days old) were pricked in the thorax with a needle dipped in a concentrated pellet of fresh overnight bacterial culture. Infected flies were kept at 29°C. <italic>Listeria innocua</italic> was cultured in Brain heart infusion medium at 37°C and used at optical density of 200 nm (OD<sub>600</sub>). <italic>Erwinia carotovora carotovora 15</italic> was cultured in Luria-Bertani broth at 29°C and used at OD<sub>600</sub> 200. Experiments were repeated three times independently and one representative experiment is shown.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><p>Tissues were dissected in Phosphate Buffer Saline (PBS) and fixed for 20 min in 4% formaldehyde. Fat body samples were fixed for 30 min using the same protocol. Tissues were washed three times in PBS containing 1% of Triton-X100 (PBT) and incubated overnight at 4°C with primary antibodies. Tissues were washed five times in PBT and incubated for 2 hr at RT with secondary antibodies and 4’,6-Diamidine-2′-phenylindole dihydrochloride (DAPI). After three washes in PBT, tissues were mounted in Vectashield using Secured-Seal spacers (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</p><p>Confocal images were captured using a Zeiss 710 or Zeiss 880 with Airyscan confocal microscope and processed with Fiji 2.0.0 or Adobe Photoshop C.S5.1.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Quantification of tumour volume and tumour cell death</title><p>For analysing tumour phenotype, images were acquired using optimal slice parameter and 12bits using a Zeiss 710 confocal microscope. Quantifications were made as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parisi et al., 2014</xref>). Briefly, we used Volocity 3D imaging analysis software to quantify the total volume of tumour identified by DAPI staining and cell death visualised with anti-Dcp1 staining. When haltere or leg discs tumours were still associated with the wing disc, they were not considered for quantification. Quantifications were done in at least three independent biological replicates for each genetic setting. Single representative experiments are presented except for <italic>dlg;def</italic> double mutant rescue experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2K–L</xref>) for which replicates are pooled due to the few larvae available. In all cases the difference between control and mutant tumour were strongly reproducible between replicates.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Quantification of colocalisation between Def and Dcp1 or Annexin V</title><p>To quantify Def/Dcp-1 and Def/Annexin V colocalisation, we determined the intensity of Def staining in areas of positive versus negative staining for the second marker using the ImageJ macro, BatchQuantify (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Johansson et al., 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Sterile rearing conditions</title><p>To rule out any effect of infection on the tumour phenotypes, <italic>Drosophila</italic> larvae were reared on standard food supplemented with penicillin and streptomycin when indicated in the figure.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>qRT-PCR analysis</title><p>Total RNA from 7 to 10 whole larvae or tissues collected from 10 to 20 larvae (10 larvae for fat body, 20 larvae for trachea) was extracted using TRIzol according to the manufacturer’s instructions. RNA was treated with Turbo DNA free Kit and RNA concentration and quality were monitored using a Nanodrop (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The same amount of total RNA (1 μg for whole larvae and fat body or 100 ng for trachea) was used to perform the three independent reverse-transcriptions using the High-Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit. cDNAs were pooled and qPCR was performed using PerfeCTa SYBR green following the manufacturer’s instructions. cDNA amplification was monitored with Applied Biosystems 7500 fast instruments. Serial 10-fold dilutions of an external standard were used to produce a standard curve, and RNA samples were included to control for the absence of DNA contamination. <italic>rpl32</italic> expression was used to normalise expression levels of target genes. Data was analysed using the Ct method (2<sup>-∆∆ct</sup>). All qPCR experiments were carried out on three to seven independent biological replicates (see figure legends for details) and, larvae were sampled from the same bottle used to analyse the tumour phenotype. GraphPad Prism7 software was used for graphical representation and statistical analysis. Primer targets and sequences are presented in key resources table.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>PCR amplification of genomic DNA</title><p>To verify the sequence of <italic>def<sup>sk3</sup></italic> and <italic>def<sup>sk4</sup></italic> mutants, genomic DNA was extracted from single flies by grinding whole animals with a 200 μL pipette tip containing 50 μL of squishing buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.2, 1 mM EDTA, 25 mM NaCl, 200 μg proteinase K) followed by incubation at 37°C for 30 min. Proteinase K was heat-inactivated at 95°C for 2 min. 1 μL of genomic DNA was used for PCR amplification using PfuUltra II Fusion DNA Polymerase and Eppendorf Mastercycler Ep Gradient Thermal Cycler.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Annexin V staining and quantification</title><p>Tumours were dissected in PBS and incubated in Annexin V binding buffer containing 5% of Alexa Fluor (488 nm or 568 nm) conjugated Annexin V for 10 min. Tissues were washed quickly in Annexin V binding buffer and fixed in 4% formaldehyde for 20 min. Immunostaining, mounting and imaging were then carried out as described above.</p><p>We used Fiji 2.0.0 software to quantify Annexin V staining at the tumour surface. Maximal Z-projection of whole tumours were generated and the Colour Threshold tool was then used to detect the red pixels that represented Annexin V staining at the surface of tumours. The hue slider was set to include only the red signal, and the brightness slider was adjusted to exclude any background signal. This area was then selected and measured in pixels.</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Synthetic defensin production and injections</title><p>The mature Defensin peptide was synthesised (over 90% purity) and the purity controlled by Genepep using Ultra Performance Liquid Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry. We subsequently compared the integrity of synthetic Defensin with authentic Defensin purified from <italic>Drosophila</italic> hemolymph using two complementary approaches, namely Matrix-Assisted Laser Desorption/Ionisation-Mass Spectrometry (MALDI-MS) for molecular mass determination and trypsin digestion followed by nanoLiquid Chromatography/Electrospray Ionisation tandem Mass Spectroscopy (nano<italic>LC/ESI MS/MS</italic>) for molecular integrity confirmation. Those analyses confirmed the similar mass between natural and synthetic Defensin (respectively provided by Bulet EIRL and Genepep) as well the presence of disulphide bonds within synthetic Def, demonstrating it is the mature peptide (Data not shown).</p><p>For injection experiments, larvae were collected, washed three times in cold sterile PBS and injected on a fly pad upon CO<sub>2</sub> anaesthesia using Nanoject II (Drummond) and glass capillaries 3.5 inch (Drummond). Larvae were injected with 69 nL of PBS containing 7.5 nmol of synthetic Defensin or 69 nL of PBS only as control. Larvae were then gently transferred into agar/grape juice plates and kept at 25°C. Tumours were dissected 4 hr after injection and stained for visualisation of nuclei and tumour cell death as describe above.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>All data are presented as mean ± SD and n values are indicated in the figure legends. Statistical analyses were carried out using GraphPad Prism7 software and only significant differences are indicated in dot-plots. Survival upon infection was analysed using Log-rank test. qPCR data were analysed using unpaired t-test with a two-tailed p value. Tumour volume and tumour cell death comparing two samples were analysed using Mann-Whitney test with a two-tailed p value and the one comparing three genotypes were analysed using One-way ANOVA followed by Turkey’s multiple comparisons test. Tumour volume from injected larvae was analysed using Two-way ANOVA followed by Turkey’s multiple comparisons test and only significant statistical differences between ctrl and Defensin injected larvae for each genotype tested are indicated.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Data and material availability</title><p>All raw data is available through <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5525/gla.researchdata.834">http://dx.doi.org/10.5525/gla.researchdata.834</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank the Vienna <italic>Drosophila</italic> Resource Centre, the Bloomington <italic>Drosophila</italic> Stock Centre and Mirka Uhlirova for fly stocks. We are thankful to Core Services and Advanced Technologies at the Cancer Research UK Beatson Institute (C596/A17196), with particular thanks to Beatson Advanced Imaging Resource. We are very grateful to Dr. Dahua Chen for sharing the anti-Defensin antibody, to Dr. Sébastien Voisin for his critical contribution in mass spectrometry analyses and to Dr. Mate Naszai for critical help in the quantification of staining co-localization. JPP and YY are supported by Cancer Research UK core funding through the CRUK Beatson Institute (A17196). JBC is a Sir Henry Dale Fellow jointly funded by the Wellcome Trust and the Royal Society (grant number 104103/Z/14/Z). <italic>In memory of Marcos Vidal (1974–2016).</italic></p> </ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf2"><p>Reviewing Editor, <italic>eLife</italic></p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing, Performed most of the experiments in this study</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Provided technical assistance</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Assayed survival upon infection in Def mutant flies (Figure 1-figure supplement 1)</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Investigation, Generated the Defensin mutant flies</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Provided technical assistance</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Resources, Formal analysis, Investigation, Writing—original draft, Analysed the quality of synthetic defensin</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>Resources, Formal analysis, Writing—original draft, Generated the defensin mutant flies, Provided useful comments and advice on the original manuscript draft</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>Conceptualization, Initiated project</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con9"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Validation, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Project administration, Writing—review and editing, Directed the study</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.016</object-id><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-45061-transrepform-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All raw data are available through <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5525/gla.researchdata.834">http://dx.doi.org/10.5525/gla.researchdata.834</ext-link>. Owing to the size of the dataset, it can be requested through the link.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurihara</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Awane</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohkawa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Anti-tumour effects of antimicrobial peptides, components of the innate immune system, against haematopoietic tumours in <italic>Drosophila mxc</italic> mutants</article-title><source>Disease Models &amp; Mechanisms</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>dmm037721 </elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dmm.037721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahar</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Antimicrobial peptides</article-title><source>Pharmaceuticals</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1543</fpage><lpage>1575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ph6121543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24287494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barajas-Azpeleta</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Welte</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidel</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McKinney</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dissel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Si</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Antimicrobial peptides modulate long-term memory</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1007440</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1007440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30312294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaucher</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hersperger</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Page-McCaw</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shearn</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Metastatic ability of <italic>Drosophila</italic> tumors depends on MMP activity</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>303</volume><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2006.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17239363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilder</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimon</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Cooperative regulation of cell polarity and growth by <italic>Drosophila</italic> tumor suppressors</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>289</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.289.5476.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10884224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birge</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeltz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanderley</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Calianese</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Barcinski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brekken</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchins</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Freimark</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Empig</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroit</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schett</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Phosphatidylserine is a global immunosuppressive signal in Efferocytosis, infectious disease, and cancer</article-title><source>Cell Death &amp; Differentiation</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>962</fpage><lpage>978</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cdd.2016.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26915293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brankatschk</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Lipoprotein particles cross the blood-brain barrier in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>10441</fpage><lpage>10447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5943-09.2010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20685986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brender</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>McHenry</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramamoorthy</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Does Cholesterol play a role in the bacterial selectivity of antimicrobial peptides?</article-title><source>Frontiers in Immunology</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>195</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2012.00195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22822405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brogden</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Antimicrobial peptides: pore formers or metabolic inhibitors in bacteria?</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15703760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bullard</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bose</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Belgrave</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaddy</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazen-Martin</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lage</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Keane</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganz</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Donald</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Functional analysis of the host defense peptide human beta Defensin-1: new insight into its potential role in cancer</article-title><source>Molecular Immunology</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2006.11.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17868871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bunker</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nellimoottil</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Boileau</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Classen</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilder</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>The transcriptional response to tumorigenic polarity loss in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e03189</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.03189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chtarbanova</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganetzky</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Dnr1 mutations cause neurodegeneration in <italic>Drosophila</italic> by activating the innate immune response in the brain</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>E1752</fpage><lpage>E1760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1306220110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23613578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiu</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Milla</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spletter</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Insight into insulin secretion from transcriptome and genetic analysis of insulin-producing cells of <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>197</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.113.160663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24558258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname> <given-names>EMC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Propst</surname> <given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hoek</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Komodo dragon-inspired synthetic peptide DRGN-1 promotes wound-healing of a mixed-biofilm infected wound</article-title><source>npj Biofilms and Microbiomes</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41522-017-0017-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28649410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cordero</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Macagno</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanatos</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Strathdee</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cagan</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidal</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Oncogenic Ras diverts a host TNF tumor suppressor activity into tumor promoter</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1011</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2010.05.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20627081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deslouches</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Di</surname> <given-names>YP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Antimicrobial peptides with selective antitumor mechanisms: prospect for anticancer applications</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>46635-46651</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.16743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28422728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dewey</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>McNabb</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Takanishi</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Truman</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Honegger</surname> <given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Identification of the gene encoding bursicon, an insect neuropeptide responsible for cuticle sclerotization and wing spreading</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>1208</fpage><lpage>1213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2004.06.051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15242619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donald</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Macoska</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganz</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname> <given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Petros</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Cancer-specific loss of beta-defensin 1 in renal and prostatic carcinomas</article-title><source>Laboratory Investigation</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.LAB.0000063929.61760.F6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12695553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez-Ayala</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vartiainen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemppainen</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Babusiak</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustalahti</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuomela</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeviani</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Dell</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rustin</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname> <given-names>HT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Expression of the <italic>Ciona intestinalis</italic> alternative oxidase (AOX) in <italic>Drosophila</italic> complements defects in mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation</article-title><source>Cell Metabolism</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2009.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19416715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname> <given-names>ÁG</given-names></name><name><surname>Naylor</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Esteves</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pais</surname> <given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>The Toll-dorsal pathway is required for resistance to viral oral infection in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>PLOS Pathogens</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e1004507</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25473839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fogarty</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Diwanji</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindblad</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tare</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amcheslavsky</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Makhijani</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brückner</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergmann</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Extracellular reactive oxygen species drive Apoptosis-Induced proliferation via <italic>Drosophila</italic> macrophages</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2015.12.064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26898463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ham</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Costa</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodt</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>The diverse roles of the TNF axis in cancer progression and metastasis</article-title><source>Trends in Cancer Research</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27928197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dostálová</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceroni</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Poidevin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaitre</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Synergy and remarkable specificity of antimicrobial peptides in vivo using a systematic knockout approach</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e44341</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30803481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichhart</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> innate immunity: an evolutionary perspective</article-title><source>Nature Immunology</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni0202-121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11812988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hollingsworth</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Mucins in cancer: protection and control of the cell surface</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Cancer</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc1251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Igaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanda</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto-Goto</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanuka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuranaga</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aigaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miura</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Eiger, a TNF superfamily ligand that triggers the <italic>Drosophila</italic> JNK pathway</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>3009</fpage><lpage>3018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/cdf306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12065414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Igaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagliarini</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Loss of cell polarity drives tumor growth and invasion through JNK activation in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1139</fpage><lpage>1146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2006.04.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16753569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Igaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastor-Pareja</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Aonuma</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miura</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Intrinsic tumor suppression and epithelial maintenance by endocytic activation of eiger/TNF signaling in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2009.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19289090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imler</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Biology of toll receptors: lessons from insects and mammals</article-title><source>Journal of Leukocyte Biology</source><volume>75</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1189/jlb.0403160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12960276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishibashi</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asaoka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamakawa</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Selective cancer cell cytotoxicity of enantiomeric 9-mer peptides derived from beetle defensins depends on negatively charged phosphatidylserine on the cell surface</article-title><source>Peptides</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.peptides.2008.12.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19154767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Cell-surface localization of pellino antagonizes Toll-mediated innate immune signalling by controlling MyD88 turnover in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>3458</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms4458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24632597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Naszai</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodder</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickering</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridgway</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Peschard</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brachmann</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordero</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sansom</surname> <given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>RAL GTPases drive intestinal stem cell function and regeneration through internalization of WNT signalosomes</article-title><source>Cell Stem Cell</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2019.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30853556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knelson</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nee</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Blobe</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Heparan sulfate signaling in cancer</article-title><source>Trends in Biochemical Sciences</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibs.2014.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24755488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kounatidis</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chtarbanova</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayne</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayanth</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganetzky</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ligoxygakis</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>NF-κB immunity in the brain determines fly lifespan in healthy aging and Age-Related neurodegeneration</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2017.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28445733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Külshammer</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundorf</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilinc</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frommolt</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagle</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhlirova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Interplay among <italic>Drosophila</italic> transcription factors Ets21c, fos and Ftz-F1 drives JNK-mediated tumor malignancy</article-title><source>Disease Models &amp; Mechanisms</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>1279</fpage><lpage>1293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dmm.020719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26398940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemaitre</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaut</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichhart</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>The dorsoventral regulatory gene cassette spätzle/Toll/cactus controls the potent antifungal response in <italic>Drosophila</italic> adults</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80172-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8808632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leulier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khush</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaitre</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase dredd is required to resist gram-negative bacterial infection</article-title><source>EMBO Reports</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/embo-reports/kvd073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11269502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levashina</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohresser</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulet</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichhart</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hetru</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Metchnikowin, a novel immune-inducible proline-rich peptide from <italic>Drosophila</italic> with antibacterial and antifungal properties</article-title><source>European Journal of Biochemistry</source><volume>233</volume><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1995.694_2.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7588819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lezi</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pujol</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chisholm</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Eroglu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsunami</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>An antimicrobial peptide and its neuronal receptor regulate dendrite degeneration in aging and infection</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>97</volume><elocation-id>e125</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2017.12.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendoza-Topaz</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Urra</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barría</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Albornoz</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugalde</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gundelfinger</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kukuljan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanxaridis</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsunoda</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceriani</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Budnik</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sierralta</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>DLGS97/SAP97 is developmentally upregulated and is required for complex adult behaviors and synapse morphology and function</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4395-07.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18171947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mergaert</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigenobu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowack</surname> <given-names>ECM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Metabolic integration of bacterial endosymbionts through antimicrobial peptides</article-title><source>Trends in Microbiology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2017.04.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Basler</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Evolution of TNF signaling mechanisms: jnk-dependent apoptosis triggered by eiger, the <italic>Drosophila</italic> homolog of the TNF superfamily</article-title><source>Current Biology : CB</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1263</fpage><lpage>1268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(02)00954-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12176339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neyen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bretscher</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Binggeli</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaitre</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Methods to study <italic>Drosophila</italic> immunity</article-title><source>Methods</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2014.02.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24631888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parameswaran</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Patial</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Tumor necrosis Factor-α signaling in macrophages</article-title><source>Critical Reviews in Eukaryotic Gene Expression</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1615/CritRevEukarGeneExpr.v20.i2.10</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parisi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanatos</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Strathdee</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidal</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Transformed epithelia trigger non-tissue-autonomous tumor suppressor response by adipocytes via activation of toll and eiger/TNF signaling</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.01.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24582964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parvy</surname> <given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgson</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordero</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> as a Model System to Study Nonautonomous Mechanisms Affecting Tumour Growth and Cell Death</article-title><source>BioMed Research International</source><volume>2018</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/7152962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastor-Pareja</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Grawe</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Martín-Blanco</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>García-Bellido</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Invasive cell behavior during <italic>Drosophila</italic> imaginal disc eversion is mediated by the JNK signaling cascade</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2004.07.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15363413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riedl</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinner</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Asslaber</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaider</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Walzer</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Novak</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohner</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zweytick</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>In search of a novel target — phosphatidylserine exposed by non-apoptotic tumor cells and metastases of malignancies with poor treatment efficacy</article-title><source>Biochimica Et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - Biomembranes</source><volume>1808</volume><fpage>2638</fpage><lpage>2645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2011.07.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santabárbara-Ruiz</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>López-Santillán</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martínez-Rodríguez</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Binagui-Casas</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pérez</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Milán</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Corominas</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Serras</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>ROS-Induced JNK and p38 signaling is required for unpaired cytokine activation during <italic>Drosophila</italic> regeneration</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1005595</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26496642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shafee</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lay</surname> <given-names>FT</given-names></name><name><surname>Phan</surname> <given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulett</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Convergent evolution of defensin sequence, structure and function</article-title><source>Cellular and Molecular Life Sciences</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-016-2344-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27557668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shklyar</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy-Adam</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishnaevski</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurant</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Caspase activity is required for engulfment of apoptotic cells</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Biology</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>3191</fpage><lpage>3201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.00233-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23754750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastor-Pareja</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Igaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagliarini</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Basement membrane remodeling is essential for <italic>Drosophila</italic> disc eversion and tumor invasion</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>2721</fpage><lpage>2726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0611666104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17301221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Golarz</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrish</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Almekinder</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Svoboda</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohl</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname> <given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Petros</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Human beta-defensin-1, a potential chromosome 8p tumor suppressor: control of transcription and induction of apoptosis in renal cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Cancer Research</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>8542</fpage><lpage>8549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-06-0294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16951166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teng</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Swann</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Koebel</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Immune-mediated dormancy: an equilibrium with cancer</article-title><source>Journal of Leukocyte Biology</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>988</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1189/jlb.1107774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18515327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tjabringa</surname> <given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Aarbiou</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ninaber</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Drijfhout</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sørensen</surname> <given-names>OE</given-names></name><name><surname>Borregaard</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabe</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiemstra</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>The antimicrobial peptide LL-37 activates innate immunity at the airway epithelial surface by transactivation of the epidermal growth factor receptor</article-title><source>The Journal of Immunology</source><volume>171</volume><fpage>6690</fpage><lpage>6696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.171.12.6690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14662872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tokumaru</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayama</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirakata</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsuzawa</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouhara</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanakawa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahata</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohyama</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashiyama</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugai</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Induction of keratinocyte migration via transactivation of the epidermal growth factor receptor by the antimicrobial peptide LL-37</article-title><source>The Journal of Immunology</source><volume>175</volume><fpage>4662</fpage><lpage>4668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.175.7.4662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tung</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaosa</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kita</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonaka</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanishi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Phosphatidylserine recognition and induction of apoptotic cell clearance by <italic>Drosophila</italic> engulfment receptor draper</article-title><source>The Journal of Biochemistry</source><volume>153</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jb/mvt014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23420848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzou</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohresser</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrandon</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Capovilla</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichhart</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaitre</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Imler</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Tissue-specific inducible expression of antimicrobial peptide genes in <italic>Drosophila</italic> surface epithelia</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1074-7613(00)00072-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzou</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>De Gregorio</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaitre</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>How <italic>Drosophila</italic> combats microbial infection: a model to study innate immunity and host-pathogen interactions</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Microbiology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5274(02)00294-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11834378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uhlirova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohmann</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>JNK- and Fos-regulated Mmp1 expression cooperates with Ras to induce invasive tumors in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>5294</fpage><lpage>5304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7601401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17082773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Wetering</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannesse-Lazeroms</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>van Sterkenburg</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiemstra</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Neutrophil defensins stimulate the release of cytokines by airway epithelial cells: modulation by dexamethasone</article-title><source>Inflammation Research</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/PL00000282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11852911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname> <given-names>XG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Melanoma cell surface-expressed phosphatidylserine as a therapeutic target for cationic anticancer peptide, temporin-1CEa</article-title><source>Journal of Drug Targeting</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/1061186X.2015.1113539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26596643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Cell surface binding, uptaking and anticancer activity of L-K6, a lysine/leucine-rich peptide, on human breast cancer MCF-7 cells</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>8293</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-08963-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28811617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouellette</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Satchell</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayabe</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>López-Boado</surname> <given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratman</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hultgren</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Matrisian</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Parks</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Regulation of intestinal alpha-defensin activation by the metalloproteinase matrilysin in innate host defense</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>286</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.286.5437.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10506557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirilä</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Valore</surname> <given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferri</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorsa</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganz</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Parks</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Differential processing of {alpha}- and {beta}-Defensin Precursors by Matrix Metalloproteinase-7 (MMP-7)</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>284</volume><fpage>8301</fpage><lpage>8311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M809744200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19181662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leong</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckel-Passow</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kocher</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Prevalent homozygous deletions of type I interferon and defensin genes in human cancers associate with immunotherapy resistance</article-title><source>Clinical Cancer Research</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>3299</fpage><lpage>3308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-17-3008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29618619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeaman</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yount</surname> <given-names>NY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Mechanisms of antimicrobial peptide action and resistance</article-title><source>Pharmacological Reviews</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/pr.55.1.2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12615953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Antimicrobial peptides increase tolerance to oxidant stress in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>286</volume><fpage>6211</fpage><lpage>6218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.181206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21148307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Activation of JNK signaling links lgl mutations to disruption of the cell polarity and epithelial organization in <italic>Drosophila</italic> imaginal discs</article-title><source>Cell Research</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2010.2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20066009</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.018</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Oxford</institution><country>United Kingdom</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Halder</surname><given-names>Georg</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution/></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;The antimicrobial peptide Defensin cooperates with Tumour Necrosis Factor to drive tumour cell death in <italic>Drosophila</italic>&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by two peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Utpal Banerjee as the Senior Editor. The following individual involved in review of your submission has agreed to reveal their identity: Georg Halder (Reviewer #3).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>This is an interesting manuscript about a topic of wide significance. The authors investigate the role of the antimicrobial peptide defensin in killing tumour cells in a <italic>Drosophila</italic> cancer model. They report that defensin is secreted by the fat body and trachea in response to Toll and Imd signalling and that defensin kills tumour cells by binding to cell surface phosphatidylserine, which become exposed in response to TNF signalling. This is novel and, if true, may provide the foundation of new approaches to understanding cell death and growth control in tumours.</p><p>For a rather radical proposal, the data need to be solid. In general, the results are convincing and carefully controlled but here are a few that are very important to the model but are not as convincing (or at least not as clearly presented) as most of the others. The reviewers' consensus is that the following issues need to be addressed before this paper could be accepted by <italic>eLife</italic>.</p><p>1) In Figure 4E they claim to show that humoral defensin is binding to 'transformed imaginal discs' in <italic>dlg</italic> mutant animals. This figure is hard to interpret. Tumour tissue seems to be marked by anti-Dcp1, a cell death marker, but it's not clear whether this marks the whole tumour. Moreover, the HA-defensin staining is very limited and does not obviously colocalise with Dcp1 or anything else. The idea that defensin binds to tumour tissue is central to the model 4E does not strongly support the idea. To be fair, the other data in Figure 4 are clearer and more convincing, but 4E is a problem. It would be better to show an image of the whole disc first so that we can appreciate the morphology and also how the staining looks over an entire tumour and not only in a small selected region. It would also be good to show the individual channels of 4G and to comment on the amount of non-overlap that is present.</p><p>2) Aspects of Figure 7, which is central to the conclusion that defensin binds to exposed PS on tumour cells, are also of concern. Panels A purport to show that defensin colocalises with annexin V, a marker of exposed PS, but the images do not show that convincingly. It is clear in A' and A' that there is plenty of non-overlap between the green annexin and red defensin. Much red defensin appears to label annexin-negative tissue. Without clearer data, preferably quantified, it is hard to support the conclusion.</p><p>3) The model that JNK activation is a prerequisite for defensin mediated tumour cell killing is of particular interest, as AMPs lack strong specificity towards killing cancer cells. However, since the experiments were done in <italic>egr</italic> mutants, which is a secreted protein that activates JNK signalling, it is not clear whether the requirement for JNK activation is in tumour cells and/or other cells. JNK could just as well act non-autonomously and this experiment would distinguish whether their model is correct or not. To further investigate this, the authors should test the effect of defensin overexpression on the efficacy of JNK induced cell death. This might best be done in clones with weak JNK activation, e.g. puckered hypomorphic clones. However, a scenario of double overexpression of defensin with a construct to activate JNK may be sufficient.</p><p>4) It is notable that the data in Figure 7C shows that the statistical confidence of the differences is rather low.</p><p>5) Both the written description and the diagrams in Figures 1 and 7 of the complex signalling between tumour cells, haemocytes, FB and trachea, involving TNF, Toll, Imd, and defensin, are complex and hard to follow. Of course this is partly because biology is complicated, but a better job could be done. It is important that readers do understand both the anatomical and the signalling aspects of the model.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.45061.019</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>[…] For a rather radical proposal, the data need to be solid. In general, the results are convincing and carefully controlled but here are a few that are very important to the model but are not as convincing (or at least not as clearly presented) as most of the others. The reviewers' consensus is that the following issues need to be addressed before this paper could be accepted by eLife.</p><p>1) In Figure 4E they claim to show that humoral defensin is binding to 'transformed imaginal discs' in dlg mutant animals. This figure is hard to interpret. Tumour tissue seems to be marked by anti-Dcp1, a cell death marker, but it's not clear whether this marks the whole tumour. Moreover, the HA-defensin staining is very limited and does not obviously colocalise with Dcp1 or anything else. The idea that defensin binds to tumour tissue is central to the model 4E does not strongly support the idea. To be fair, the other data in Figure 4 are clearer and more convincing, but 4E is a problem. It would be better to show an image of the whole disc first so that we can appreciate the morphology and also how the staining looks over an entire tumour and not only in a small selected region. It would also be good to show the individual channels of 4G and to comment on the amount of non-overlap that is present.</p></disp-quote><p>The goal of Figure 4E was to unambiguously show that none-tumour produced Def (fat body overexpressed Def-HA) binds to tumours but not wild type tissues (old Figure 4F, F’). As the reviewer pointed out, the assessment of endogenous Def in tumours does supports the selective binding of the AMP to the tumours (new Figure 4D-H’’). However, the reviewer is correct in that old Figure 4E was not clear enough to make the case for Def tumour binding and/or Dcp-1 co-localization. One of the issues is that, in addition to the tumour itself, tumour associated tissues, which are negative for Dcp-1 but produce Defensin (fat body and trachea) are almost always captured in these images. Def expression in such accessory tissues is obviously more robust in the context of Def-HA overexpression (Figure 4—figure supplement 1). We now provide new and significantly improved images of a whole tumour and zoomed-in areas of tumour tissue, including individual channels (new Figure 4A-B’’). For completeness, we also present quantifications, which confirm enrichment of endogenous Def in Dcp-1<sup>+ve</sup> areas on the tumours (new Figure 4F). For organisational purposes, pictures depicting basal UAS-Def-HA expression patterns and following fat body overexpression in wild type discs (old Figure 4A-D) are now in a new Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</p><p>Furthermore to unambiguously demonstrate the specificity of ectopically produced Def to bind to tumours exposing PS, we overexpressed Def-HA in the fat body of <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;egr<sup>3/3</sup></italic> animals (new Figure 7—figure supplement 1A, B). <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;egr<sup>3/3</sup></italic> tumours don’t expose PS and are refractive to Def killing action (Figures 7G and K). Consistently, they present no detectable staining for Def-HA (new Figure 7—figure supplement 1C, C’).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) Aspects of Figure 7, which is central to the conclusion that defensin binds to exposed PS on tumour cells, are also of concern. Panels A purport to show that defensin colocalises with annexin V, a marker of exposed PS, but the images do not show that convincingly. It is clear in A' and A' that there is plenty of non-overlap between the green annexin and red defensin. Much red defensin appears to label annexin-negative tissue. Without clearer data, preferably quantified, it is hard to support the conclusion.</p></disp-quote><p>As for the previous point we now present quantification of Def and AnnexinVco-localization (new Figure 7C). We also present individual channels for a more clear visualization of Annexin V and Def staining (new Figure 7A-A’’ and B-B’’). As noted by the reviewer, there are tumour areas stained with Def and not AnnexinV and vice versa. However, our data from images and quantifications clearly shows an enrichment of Def within AnnexinV<sup>+ve</sup> versus AnnexinV<sup>-ve</sup> tumour areas. Moreover, a new experiment showing that Def-HA can’t associate to <italic>dlg<sup>40.2</sup>;egr<sup>3/3</sup></italic> tumours also support this conclusion (see above and new Figure 7—figure supplement 1C, C’).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) The model that JNK activation is a prerequisite for defensin mediated tumour cell killing is of particular interest, as AMPs lack strong specificity towards killing cancer cells. However, since the experiments were done in egr mutants, which is a secreted protein that activates JNK signalling, it is not clear whether the requirement for JNK activation is in tumour cells and/or other cells. JNK could just as well act non-autonomously and this experiment would distinguish whether their model is correct or not. To further investigate this, the authors should test the effect of defensin overexpression on the efficacy of JNK induced cell death. This might best be done in clones with weak JNK activation, e.g. puckered hypomorphic clones. However, a scenario of double overexpression of defensin with a construct to activate JNK may be sufficient.</p></disp-quote><p>This is indeed a very interesting question. However, we would like to point that, our data definitely suggests that Egr and PS exposure, which is dependent on Egr, are a pre-requisite for Def killing of tumour cells. Even though Egr does activate JNK signaling, it may also be doing more than that in these tumours. In order to best address the reviewer’s question following his/her line of thought and with the tools that were available to us to perform experiments within the timeframe of this revision we did the following:</p><p>1- To achieve mild JNK activation as we successfully did in other contexts (Cordero et al., 2012), we overexpressed wild type JNK. Here, we used <italic>engrailed-gal4 (eng&gt;hep<sup>wt</sup></italic>) and analysed wing discs. This condition, led to mild apoptosis in the wing pouch but was not sufficient to drive detectable PS exposure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="respfig1">Author response image 1A-D</xref>). Therefore, and consistently with our model (PS exposure is required for Def killing), the administration of injected recombinant Def or genetic co-expression of UAS-Def did not modify JNK-dependent cell death (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="respfig1">Author response image 1C, D</xref>).</p><p>2- Given the mild basal phenotype obtained by overexpressing wild type JNK and following the second suggestion by the reviewer “a scenario of double overexpression of defensin with a construct to activate JNK may be sufficient<italic>”.</italic> We overexpressed activated <italic>hemipterous</italic> using <italic>rotund-gal4 (rn&gt;hep<sup>act</sup></italic>) as <italic>eng&gt;hep<sup>act</sup></italic> led to embryonic lethality. However, <italic>rn&gt;hep<sup>act</sup> </italic>discs presented a complete apoptosis of the wing pouch, and consistently extremely rare adult escapers were devoid of wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="respfig2">Author response image 2</xref> and data not shown). We reasoned that a quantifiable assessment of a potential enhancement of this phenotype was not going to be possible.</p><p>As per the results with <italic>hep<sup>wt</sup></italic>, we can conclude that a mild activation of JNK in an otherwise wild type tissue is not sufficient to allow apoptosis by Defensin. Nonetheless, we cannot exclude that an intermediate, sublethal, activation of the JNK pathway might lead to Def sensitivity. Alternatively, and given the absolute need of Egr for PS exposure for the Def anti-tumoural role, it is conceivable that the role of Egr in these tumours extends beyond activation of JNK. We have integrated these results in the revised Discussion of our manuscript.</p><fig id="respfig1"><label>Author response image 1.</label><caption><title>Anti-tumoural immunity in flies: the key players.</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Third instar larval imaginal wing disc overexpressing of <italic>hep<sup>wt</sup></italic> using <italic>engrailed-gal4, UAS-rfp (eng&gt;rfp; hep<sup>wt</sup></italic>) (<bold>A</bold>; red). Discs where stained with AnnexinV to visualize PS exposure (<bold>B</bold>; green). (<bold>C</bold>) Assessment of apoptotic cell death in wing discs from <italic>eng&gt;rfp; hep<sup>wt</sup></italic>animals injected with PBS (control) or recombinant Defensin. (<bold>D</bold>) Assessment of apoptotic cell death in wing discs from animal following overexpression of <italic>hep<sup>wt</sup> </italic>only, <italic>def</italic> only, or co-expression of both transgenes using combined <italic>eng-gal4</italic> and <italic>lpp-gal4</italic> drivers.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-resp-fig1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="respfig2"><label>Author response image 2.</label><caption><title>Anti-tumoural immunity in flies: the key players.</title><p>(A, B) Third instar larval imaginal wing disc overexpressing of <italic>hep<sup>act</sup></italic> using <italic>rutond-gal4 (rn&gt;hep<sup>act</sup></italic>).</p><p>Discs where stained with anti-Dcp1 to visualize apoptotic cell death (B; red).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-45061-resp-fig2-v1.tif"/></fig><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) It is notable that the data in Figure 7C shows that the statistical confidence of the differences is rather low.</p></disp-quote><p>This is a fair point. Reasons for this are likely due to the variability in <italic>def</italic> expression levels within the <italic>dlg</italic> animals. Moreover, we have done ANOVA to compare multiple samples in old Figure 7C (new Figure 7D), which is more stringent than T-test used in other cases in the manuscript where we compared only two sets of RT-QPCR data (e.g. Figure 1B). Therefore, even * is meaningful. Importantly, we do present several lines of evidence on the functional importance of Egr in the system.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) Both the written description and the diagrams in Figures 1 and 7 of the complex signalling between tumour cells, haemocytes, FB and trachea, involving TNF, Toll, Imd, and defensin, are complex and hard to follow. Of course this is partly because biology is complicated, but a better job could be done. It is important that readers do understand both the anatomical and the signalling aspects of the model.</p></disp-quote><p>We have now simplified the diagrams (new Figure 1A and Figure 7L) and text to focus on the key points addressed in this manuscript.</p></body></sub-article></article>