<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.2" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">71061</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.71061</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cell Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Members of the ELMOD protein family specify formation of distinct aperture domains on the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> pollen surface</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-242068"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Yuan</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3598-958X</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-230667"><name><surname>Amom</surname><given-names>Prativa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa1">†</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-242069"><name><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>Sarah H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-242070"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Byung Ha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa2">‡</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-242071"><name><surname>Helton</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2948-2368</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa3">§</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-47139"><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>Anna A</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2987-1718</contrib-id><email>dobritsa.1@osu.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Molecular Genetics and Center for Applied Plant Sciences, Ohio State University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Columbus</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>Sheila</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of California, Berkeley</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Kleine-Vehn</surname><given-names>Jürgen</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Freiburg</institution><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa1"><label>†</label><p>Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center, University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa2"><label>‡</label><p>Macrogen, Inc, Seoul, South Korea</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa3"><label>§</label><p>PPD Laboratories, Middleton, United States</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>30</day><month>09</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e71061</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2021-06-07"><day>07</day><month>06</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2021-09-01"><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a preprint at bioRxiv.</event-desc><date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2021-06-15"><day>15</day><month>06</month><year>2021</year></date><self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.448545"/></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021, Zhou et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhou et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-71061-v1.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="figures-pdf" xlink:href="elife-71061-figures-v1.pdf"/><abstract><p>Pollen apertures, the characteristic gaps in pollen wall exine, have emerged as a model for studying the formation of distinct plasma membrane domains. In each species, aperture number, position, and morphology are typically fixed; across species they vary widely. During pollen development, certain plasma membrane domains attract specific proteins and lipids and become protected from exine deposition, developing into apertures. However, how these aperture domains are selected is unknown. Here, we demonstrate that patterns of aperture domains in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> are controlled by the members of the ancient ELMOD protein family, which, although important in animals, has not been studied in plants. We show that two members of this family, MACARON (MCR) and ELMOD_A, act upstream of the previously discovered aperture proteins and that their expression levels influence the number of aperture domains that form on the surface of developing pollen grains. We also show that a third ELMOD family member, ELMOD_E, can interfere with MCR and ELMOD_A activities, changing aperture morphology and producing new aperture patterns. Our findings reveal key players controlling early steps in aperture domain formation, identify residues important for their function, and open new avenues for investigating how diversity of aperture patterns in nature is achieved.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><title>eLife digest</title><p>Zooming in on cells reveals patterns on their outer surfaces. These patterns are actually a collection of distinct areas of the cell surface, each containing specific combinations of molecules. The outer layers of pollen grains consist of a cell wall, and a softer cell membrane that sits underneath. As a pollen grain develops, it recruits certain fats and proteins to specific areas of the cell membrane, known as ‘aperture domains’. The composition of these domains blocks the cell wall from forming over them, leading to gaps in the wall called ‘pollen apertures’. Pollen apertures can open and close, aiding reproduction and protecting pollen grains from dehydration.</p><p>The number, location, and shape of pollen apertures vary between different plant species, but are consistent within the same species. In the plant species <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, pollen normally develops three long and narrow, equally spaced apertures, but it remains unclear how pollen grains control the number and location of aperture domains.</p><p>Zhou et al. found that mutations in two closely related <italic>A. thaliana</italic> proteins – ELMOD_A and MCR – alter the number and positions of pollen apertures. When <italic>A. thaliana</italic> plants were genetically modified so that they would produce different levels of ELMOD_A and MCR, Zhou et al. observed that when more of these proteins were present in a pollen grain, more apertures were generated on the pollen surface. This finding suggests that the levels of these proteins must be tightly regulated to control pollen aperture numbers. Further tests revealed that another related protein, called ELMOD_E, also has a role in domain formation. When artificially produced in developing pollen grains, it interfered with the activity of ELMOD_A and MCR, changing pollen aperture shape, number, and location.</p><p>Zhou et al. identified a group of proteins that help control the formation of domains in the cell membranes of <italic>A. thaliana</italic> pollen grains. Further research will be required to determine what exactly these proteins do to promote formation of aperture domains and whether similar proteins control domain development in other organisms.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>pollen</kwd><kwd>pollen aperture</kwd><kwd>membrane domain</kwd><kwd>pattern formation</kwd><kwd>ELMOD</kwd><kwd>MCR</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd><italic>A. thaliana</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000001</institution-id><institution>National Science Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MCB-1817835</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>Anna A</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100006928</institution-id><institution>Ohio State University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Mayers Undergraduate Summer Research Scholarship</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Amom</surname><given-names>Prativa</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Science Foundation-Research Experience for Undergraduates Supplement funding</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MCB-1517511</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Amom</surname><given-names>Prativa</given-names></name><name><surname>Helton</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>Anna A</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund4"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Ohio State University Center for Applied Plant Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>iCAPS internship</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Helton</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Pollen aperture patterning in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is controlled by members of the ELMOD protein family, whose expression levels in developing pollen lineage are tightly regulated.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>As part of cell morphogenesis, cells often form distinct plasma membrane domains that acquire specific combinations of proteins, lipids, and extracellular materials. Yet how these domains are selected and specified is often unclear. Pollen apertures offer a powerful model for studying this process. Apertures are the characteristic gaps on the pollen surface that receive little to no deposition of the pollen wall exine; during their formation, certain regions of the plasma membrane are selected and specified as aperture domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Zhou and Dobritsa, 2019</xref>). Pollen apertures create some of the most recognizable patterns on the pollen surface, usually conserved within a species but highly variable across species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Furness and Rudall, 2004</xref>). For instance, in wild-type <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> pollen, apertures are represented by three long and narrow furrows, equally spaced on the pollen surface and oriented longitudinally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A and A'</xref>). In other species, aperture positions, number, and morphologies can be different, suggesting that the mechanisms guiding aperture formation are diverse. While the diversity of aperture patterns has captivated scientists for decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Furness and Rudall, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Matamoro-Vidal et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Walker, 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Wodehouse, 1935</xref>), studies of the associated molecular mechanisms have only recently begun (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dobritsa and Coerper, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dobritsa et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lee et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Mutations in <italic>MCR</italic> reduce aperture number.</title><p>(<bold>A–E’</bold>) Confocal images of auramine O-stained pollen grains from wild-type (L<italic>er</italic>) and four <italic>mcr</italic> EMS mutants. Front (α) and back (α’) show the opposite views of the same pollen grain here and in other figures as indicated. (<bold>F, G</bold>) 3D reconstructions of tetrad-stage microspores showing lines of INP1-YFP (red arrows) in <italic>inp1</italic> and <italic>mcr</italic> mutants. DP: distal pole. (<bold>H, H’</bold>) <italic>mcr</italic> pollen with two apertures. Red boxes mark the regions where apertures are not fused. (<bold>I</bold>) Percentage of pollen grains with indicated number of apertures in pollen populations from <italic>mcr</italic>, 1n <italic>MiMe</italic>, and 1n <italic>mcr MiMe</italic> plants (n = 75–500). Error bars represent SD, calculated from 4 to 6 independent biological replicates. Apertures are indicated with arrowheads in (<bold>A–E’</bold>) and (<bold>H, H’</bold>). Scale bars, 10 μm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Diagrams summarizing the INP1-YFP localization in <italic>inp1</italic> and <italic>mcr</italic> tetrads, based on confocal imaging and 3D reconstruction of <italic>DMC1pr:INP1-YFP</italic>-expressing tetrads.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Positions of three equidistant lines formed by INP1-YFP in tetrad-stage <italic>inp1</italic> microspores always appear coordinated between the sister microspores, with each line in one microspore facing a line in one of its sisters. (<bold>B1-B14</bold>) Examples of placement of INP1-YFP ring-shaped lines in 14 <italic>mcr</italic> tetrads, which suggest that the lines in sister microspores are positioned independently. In all tetrads, the INP1-YFP lines in front-facing microspores (with the polar axis perpendicular to the plane of image) were oriented the same way to compare the positioning of the lines in three sister microspores between the tetrads. Solid lines and dotted lines represent the INP1-YFP lines that are, respectively, visible and invisible in that view.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig1-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>The reducing effect of <italic>mcr</italic> mutations on aperture number is manifested across different ploidy levels and arrangements of microspores.</title><p>(<bold>A–C’</bold>) Representative images of 1n <italic>MiMe</italic> pollen with three apertures (<bold>A, A’</bold>), four apertures (<bold>B, B’</bold>), and six apertures (<bold>C, C’</bold>). (<bold>D–E’</bold>) Representative images of 1n <italic>mcr MiMe</italic> pollen with <italic>mcr</italic>-like aperture (<bold>D, D’</bold>) and three apertures (<bold>E, E’</bold>). (<bold>F–G’</bold>) Representative images of 4n <italic>mcr tes</italic> pollen with four apertures (<bold>F, F’</bold>) and fused apertures (<bold>G, G’</bold>). Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig1-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Aperture domains first become visible at the tetrad stage of pollen development, when four sister microspores, the products of meiosis, are held together under the common callose wall and aperture factors, such as INAPERTURATE POLLEN1 (INP1) and D6 PROTEIN KINASE-LIKE3 (D6PKL3) in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and OsINP1 and DEFECTIVE IN APERTURE FORMATION1 (OsDAF1) in rice, accumulate at distinct domains of the microspore plasma membranes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dobritsa and Coerper, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dobritsa et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lee et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). These domains become protected from exine deposition and develop into apertures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dobritsa et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). Yet how aperture domains are selected and what mechanism guides their patterning remain completely unknown.</p><p>Recently, we isolated a new <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutant, <italic>macaron</italic> (<italic>mcr</italic>), in which pollen, instead of forming three apertures, develops a single ring-shaped aperture, suggesting that the affected gene is involved in specifying positions and number of aperture domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Plourde et al., 2019</xref>). Here, we perform a detailed analysis of this mutant and identify the <italic>MCR</italic> gene. We demonstrate that it belongs to the ancient family of ELMOD proteins, and that together with another member of this protein family in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, ELMOD_A, MCR acts at the beginning of the aperture formation pathway as a positive regulator of aperture domain specification. We provide evidence that aperture domains are highly sensitive to the levels of MCR and ELMOD_A, which can positively or negatively affect their number. We further demonstrate that a third member of this family, ELMOD_E, has an ability to influence the number, positions, and morphology of aperture domains, and we identify specific protein residues critical for this ability. Our study elucidates key molecular factors controlling aperture patterning and functionally characterizes members of the widespread, yet thus far uncharacterized family of the plant ELMOD proteins.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title><italic>mcr</italic> mutants develop a single ring-shaped pollen aperture composed of two equidistantly placed longitudinal apertures</title><p>In a screen of EMS-mutagenized <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants, we discovered four non-complementing mutants, which, instead of three equidistant pollen apertures, produced a single ring-shaped aperture dividing each pollen grain into two equal parts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B-E'</xref>). As the mutant phenotype resembled the French meringue dessert, we named these mutations <italic>macaron</italic> (alleles <italic>mcr-1</italic> through <italic>mcr-4</italic>).</p><p>Imaging of <italic>mcr</italic> microspore tetrads demonstrated that they develop normally and achieve a regular tetrahedral conformation. The ring-shaped aperture domains in <italic>mcr</italic> microspores, visualized with the help of the reporter INP1-YFP, are positioned so that they pass through the proximal and distal poles of each microspore (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1G</xref>; compare with the INP1-YFP localization in the absence of <italic>mcr</italic> mutation in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref>). Thus, like in wild-type pollen, apertures in <italic>mcr</italic> are placed longitudinally. However, while aperture positions in each wild-type microspore are coordinated with aperture positions in its three sisters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dobritsa et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>), in <italic>mcr</italic>, the ring-shaped apertures appear to be placed independently in sister microspores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>). Occasionally, instead of ring-shaped apertures, <italic>mcr</italic> pollen displays two unconnected apertures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1H and H'</xref>), suggesting that the ring-shaped aperture is a product of a two-aperture fusion. Thus, <italic>mcr</italic> mutations reduce the number of apertures, but do not affect their furrow morphology, longitudinal orientation, and equidistant placement. Like all the other previously characterized pollen aperture mutants in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, including <italic>inp1</italic> and <italic>inp2,</italic> which completely lack apertures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dobritsa and Coerper, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Dobritsa et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Lee et al., 2021</xref>), <italic>mcr</italic> mutants exhibited no obvious fertility defects.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>The <italic>mcr</italic> mutation reduces aperture number across different levels of ploidy and arrangements of microspores</title><p>We previously showed that aperture number strongly depends on microspore ploidy and is sensitive to cytokinetic defects that disrupt formation of normal tetrahedral tetrads, creating other arrangements of post-meiotic microspores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>). While normal haploid (1n) pollen develops three apertures, diploid (2n) pollen produces either four or a mixture of four and six apertures, depending on whether it was generated through tetrads or dyads. In contrast, 2n <italic>mcr</italic> pollen, produced through either tetrads or dyads, has three equidistant apertures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Plourde et al., 2019</xref>), suggesting that the increasing effect of higher ploidy on aperture number is counterbalanced by the defect in the <italic>MCR</italic> function.</p><p>We have now extended this analysis by assessing the effects of the <italic>mcr</italic> mutation on aperture formation under additional perturbations of ploidy or post-meiotic microspore arrangement. By creating 1n <italic>Mitosis instead of Meiosis</italic> (<italic>MiMe</italic>) plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">d’Erfurth et al., 2009</xref>) with the <italic>mcr</italic> mutation, we generated <italic>mcr</italic> pollen with normal ploidy (1n) via dyads, and not tetrads. As shown previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>), a majority of the 1n <italic>MiMe</italic> pollen grains (~60%) develop three normal apertures, with the rest forming mostly six apertures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1I</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A–C'</xref>). Yet, in the pollen of the 1n <italic>mcr MiMe</italic> plants, the number of apertures was reduced, with ~50–70% of pollen developing the <italic>mcr</italic> phenotype (either ring-shaped or two apertures) and the rest forming three apertures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1I</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2D–E'</xref>).</p><p>We further perturbed microspore formation and ploidy by crossing <italic>mcr-1</italic> with a mutant defective in the <italic>TETRASPORE (TES</italic>) gene. In <italic>tes</italic> mutants, microspore mother cells (MMCs) go through meiosis but fail to undergo cytokinesis, producing large pollen grains with four haploid nuclei and a high number (~10 or more) of irregularly placed and fused apertures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Spielman et al., 1997</xref>). Although in the double <italic>mcr tes</italic> mutant apertures are often positioned irregularly and fused together, their number was usually lower (~4–6) than in the single <italic>tes</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2F–G'</xref>). Altogether, these results indicate that <italic>mcr</italic> mutations have an overall reducing effect on aperture number, manifested across different levels of pollen ploidy and post-meiotic microspore arrangements.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title><italic>mcr</italic> acts genetically upstream of the aperture factors <italic>INP1</italic> and <italic>D6PKL3</italic></title><p>In wild-type tetrad-stage microspores, aperture factors INP1 and D6PKL3 localize to the three longitudinal aperture domains of the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dobritsa and Coerper, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dobritsa et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lee et al., 2018</xref>). Since <italic>mcr</italic> mutation affects INP1-YFP localization, causing it to migrate to a ring-shaped membrane domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1G</xref>), we tested whether <italic>mcr</italic> also affects the localization of D6PKL3, which likely acts upstream of INP1. We introgressed the previously characterized transgenic reporter <italic>D6PKL3pr:D6PKL3-YFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lee et al., 2018</xref>) into the <italic>mcr-1</italic> background. In <italic>mcr</italic> microspores, D6PKL3-YFP re-localized to a single ring-shaped domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>), indicating that MCR acts upstream of both INP1 and D6PKL3.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title><italic>MCR</italic> acts genetically upstream of the three known aperture factors, <italic>D6PKL3</italic>, <italic>INP1,</italic> and <italic>INP2</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) 3D reconstruction of tetrad-stage microspores showing lines of D6PKL3-YFP in <italic>mcr</italic> tetrads. (<bold>B–D</bold>) Pollen grains of <italic>mcr d6pkl3</italic>, <italic>mcr inp1</italic>, and <italic>mcr inp2</italic> double mutants. Apertures are indicated with arrowheads, and D6PKL3-YFP lines are indicated with red arrows. Scale bars, 10 μm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig2-v1.tif"/></fig><p>We also examined the genetic interactions between <italic>MCR</italic> and other aperture factors, including the recently discovered <italic>INP2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Lee et al., 2021</xref>), by combining their mutations. <italic>d6pkl3</italic> single mutants develop three apertures partially covered by exine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lee et al., 2018</xref>). Pollen of the <italic>mcr d6pkl3</italic> double mutants developed single ring-shaped apertures that were partially covered by exine, indicating that the two genes have an additive effect on aperture phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). In contrast, pollen grains of <italic>mcr inp1</italic> and <italic>mcr inp2</italic> completely lacked apertures, phenocopying single <italic>inp1</italic> and <italic>inp2</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dobritsa and Coerper, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Lee et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C and D</xref>). This indicates that <italic>INP1</italic> and <italic>INP2</italic> are epistatic to <italic>MCR</italic>, consistent with their roles as factors absolutely essential for aperture formation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>MCR is a member of the ancient ELMOD protein family</title><p>We mapped the <italic>mcr-1</italic> defect to a 77 kb interval on the second chromosome. One of the 25 genes in this interval, <italic>At2g44770</italic>, had a C-to-T mutation converting a highly conserved Pro165 (see below) into a Ser (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). Sequencing of <italic>At2g44770</italic> from the other three <italic>mcr</italic> alleles also revealed mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). <italic>mcr-2</italic> had a G-to-A mutation converting Gly129 into an Asp. <italic>mcr-3</italic> had a G-to-A mutation affecting the last nucleotide of the fifth intron, disrupting the splice acceptor site and causing a frame shift in the middle of the critical catalytic region (see below). In <italic>mcr-4</italic>, no mutations in the coding sequence (CDS) of <italic>At2g44770</italic> were found; however, there was a G-to-A mutation 310 nt downstream of the stop codon in its 3′ untranslated region (3′ UTR), suggesting that the 3′ UTR is important for regulation of this gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). In addition, plants with T-DNA insertions in this gene (<italic>mcr-5</italic>, <italic>mcr-6</italic>, and <italic>mcr-7</italic>) all produced pollen with the <italic>mcr</italic> phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>). Yet the T-DNA mutations, likely due to their residence in introns, were hypomorphic, as some pollen with three normal apertures was found in their populations (9% in <italic>mcr-5</italic> [n = 179], 13% in <italic>mcr-6</italic> [n = 216], and 22% in <italic>mcr-7</italic> [n = 78]). This was in contrast to the <italic>mcr-1</italic> through <italic>mcr-4</italic> mutations, in which the <italic>mcr</italic> aperture phenotype was fully penetrant.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>MCR, a member of the ELMOD protein family, is encoded by <italic>At2g44770</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Diagram of the <italic>MCR</italic> gene (<italic>At2g44770</italic>). Positions of seven mutations and several gene and protein regions are indicated. (<bold>B–D’</bold>) Pollen grains from <italic>mcr</italic> plants expressing <italic>MCRpr:gMCR</italic>, <italic>MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic>, and <italic>MCRpr:MCR CDS</italic> constructs. Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm. (<bold>E</bold>) Phylogenetic tree of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMOD proteins and expression patterns of the corresponding genes. Bootstrap values (%) for 1000 replicates are shown at tree nodes. RNA-seq data obtained from the TRAVA database are presented as a bubble heatmap (values indicate normalized read counts). Magenta box marks the bud stages associated with pollen aperture formation (stages follow the TRAVA nomenclature).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig3-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Protein sequence alignment of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMOD proteins.</title><p>Multiple sequence alignment was conducted by MAFFT and visualized by Espript3.0. Positions of ELMO domains and GAP regions in these proteins are indicated with a green box and an orange box, respectively. The mutated sites of <italic>mcr-1</italic>, <italic>mcr-2</italic>, and <italic>mcr-3</italic> are indicated. Blue triangle indicates the highly conserved Arg (R127 of MCR and ELMOD_A) in the GAP region.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig3-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>T-DNA insertion mutants of <italic>MCR</italic> produce pollen with a single ring-shaped aperture.</title><p>Pollen from wild type (<bold>A, A’</bold>; same pollen grain as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A and A'</xref>) and three T-DNA insertion alleles of <italic>MCR</italic> (<bold>B–D’</bold>). Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig3-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>We further verified the identity of <italic>MCR</italic> as <italic>At2g44770</italic> by creating complementation constructs and expressing them in the <italic>mcr-1</italic> mutant. The genomic construct <italic>MCRpr:gMCR</italic> (driven by the 3 kb DNA fragment upstream of the start codon [referred to as the <italic>MCR</italic> promoter] and containing introns and the 0.8 kb region downstream of the stop codon) restored three normal apertures in 10/10 T<sub>1</sub> transgenic plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B and B'</xref>). A similar genomic construct expressing protein fused at the C-terminus with yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) also successfully restored apertures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C and C'</xref>). In contrast, the <italic>MCRpr:MCR CDS</italic> construct, which contained only the CDS driven by the <italic>MCR</italic> promoter, did not rescue the <italic>mcr</italic> phenotype (0/6 T<sub>1</sub> plants had three apertures restored; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D and D'</xref>), indicating that additional regulatory regions are required for expression of this gene, consistent with the notion of the 3′ UTR importance. The <italic>MCR</italic> promoter and 3′ UTR were then included in all constructs for which we sought <italic>MCR</italic>-like expression and are herein referred to as the <italic>MCR</italic> regulatory regions.</p><p>The protein encoded by <italic>At2g44770</italic> contains the Engulfment and Cell Motility (ELMO) domain (InterPro006816) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). In animals, proteins with this domain belong to two families: (1) smaller ELMOD proteins, containing only the ELMO domain, and (2) larger ELMO proteins, containing, besides the ELMO domain, several other protein domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">East et al., 2012</xref>). The ELMOD family is believed to be the more ancient of the two, with ELMOD proteins already present in the last common ancestor of all eukaryotes and ELMO proteins appearing later in evolution in the opisthokont clade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">East et al., 2012</xref>). In mammals, ELMOD proteins act as non-canonical GTPase activating proteins (GAPs) for regulatory GTPases of the ADP-ribosylation factor (Arf) family, a subgroup within the Ras superfamily that includes Arf and Arf-like (Arl) proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bowzard et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Ivanova et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Turn et al., 2020</xref>). Unlike animals, plants only have members of the ELMOD family, and their roles remain essentially uncharacterized.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Another member of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMOD family, ELMOD_A, is also involved in aperture formation</title><p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the ELMOD family consists of six members, ELMOD_A through ELMOD_F (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>), in the nomenclature of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">East et al., 2012</xref>. MCR is ELMOD_B. One of the other five proteins, ELMOD_A, shares 86% sequence identity with MCR, and the rest have ~50–55% sequence identity with both MCR and ELMOD_A. Although the ELMOD proteins are broadly expressed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, young buds at or near the stages when apertures develop express mostly MCR and ELMOD_A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>).</p><p>Given the high similarity between MCR and ELMOD_A, we wondered if ELMOD_A also aids in aperture formation. We disrupted ELMOD_A with CRISPR/Cas9 by introducing a single-nucleotide insertion (A) after the codon 64 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Although this created a shift in the open reading frame and an early stop codon, it did not affect aperture formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B and B'</xref>). (Likewise, a second <italic>elmod_a</italic> CRISPR allele, in which deletion of the last nucleotide of the codon 64 resulted in a different frame shift and creation of another early stop codon, did not affect the formation of apertures.) We hypothesized that the lack of phenotype could be due to the ELMOD_A redundancy with MCR. To test this, we crossed the <italic>elmod_a</italic> mutant (carrying the CRISPR/Cas9 transgene) with the <italic>mcr-1</italic> mutant. Already in the F<sub>1</sub> generation, when all plants were expected to be double heterozygotes, we found several plants producing pollen with the <italic>mcr</italic>-like aperture phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C and C'</xref>). Sequencing of the <italic>MCR</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> genes from these plants showed that, as expected, they were heterozygous for <italic>MCR</italic>; however, they had homozygous or biallelic mutations in <italic>ELMOD_A</italic>, indicating that the CRISPR/Cas9 transgene continued targeting the wild-type copy of <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> in the F<sub>1</sub> progeny of the cross.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>ELMOD_A is involved in aperture formation.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Diagram of the <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> gene (<italic>At3g60260</italic>) and the CRISPR/Cas9-induced <italic>elmod_a</italic> mutation. Nucleotide and amino acid changes are indicated with red capital letters. 20 bp target sequence next to the underlined protospacer adjacent motif is shown in bold. Lowercase letters represent sequence of an intron. (<bold>B–G’</bold>) Pollen grains from <italic>elmod_a</italic> mutant and from the indicated homo- and heterozygous combinations of <italic>elmod_a</italic> and <italic>mcr</italic> mutations. (<bold>H–I’</bold>) Pollen grains from <italic>mcr elmod_a</italic> plants expressing <italic>EApr:gELMOD_A</italic> and <italic>EApr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic> constructs. (<bold>J–K’</bold>) Pollen grains from <italic>mcr</italic> plants expressing <italic>EApr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic> and <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic> constructs. Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig4-v1.tif"/></fig><p>The phenotype of these <italic>mcr/+ elmod_a</italic> mutants revealed that in the absence of <italic>ELMOD_A</italic>, <italic>MCR</italic> displays haploinsufficiency. Notably, when at least one wild-type copy of <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> is present, <italic>MCR</italic> is haplosufficient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D and D'</xref>). Therefore, these paralogs play redundant roles in the formation of aperture domains. Yet, since MCR can specify three normal apertures in the absence of ELMOD_A but not vice versa, its role appears to be more prominent compared to that of ELMOD_A.</p><p>We also tested how the lack of one wild-type copy of <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> and both wild-type copies of <italic>MCR</italic>, as well as the lack of wild-type copies of both genes, would affect aperture formation. In the <italic>mcr elmod_a/+</italic> plants, pollen had the <italic>mcr</italic> phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E and E'</xref>). However, when the function of both genes was completely disrupted, the resulting pollen produced either one greatly disrupted aperture with an abnormal, circular morphology and partially covered with exine, or formed no apertures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F-G'</xref>). Thus, the simultaneous loss of function of the two <italic>ELMOD</italic> family genes has a synergistic effect on aperture formation.</p><p>To confirm that these defects were caused by mutations in <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> and not off-site CRISPR targeting events, as well as to identify the <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> regulatory regions, we created two <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> genomic constructs driven by the 2 kb region upstream of its start codon – <italic>EApr:gELMOD_A</italic> (which also included a 0.3 kb <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> 3′ UTR) and <italic>EApr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic> (tagged with YFP and lacking the <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> 3′ UTR) – and transformed them into the <italic>mcr elmod_a</italic> double mutant, which no longer carried the CRISPR/Cas9 transgene. Both constructs successfully rescued formation of apertures (5/5 and 31/33 T<sub>1</sub> plants, respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4H–I'</xref>), indicating that the selected promoter region is sufficient for <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> functional expression. In addition, when <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> was expressed in the <italic>mcr</italic> single mutant from either its own promoter or from the <italic>MCR</italic> regulatory regions (<italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_A-YFP-MCR3′UTR</italic>), it also complemented the loss of <italic>MCR</italic> (12/12 and 14/14 T<sub>1</sub> plants; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4J–K'</xref>).</p><p>Thus, both ELMOD_A and MCR participate in aperture domain specification. Formation of three apertures in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> pollen requires either two intact copies of <italic>MCR</italic> or at least one copy of each of these two ELMOD family members.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>MCR and ELMOD_A are expressed in the developing pollen lineage but, unlike other aperture factors, do not accumulate at the aperture membrane domains</title><p>According to the publicly available RNA-seq data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Klepikova et al., 2016</xref>), <italic>MCR</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> are both expressed in young buds with pollen at or near the tetrad stage of development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). To confirm that in these buds <italic>MCR</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> are expressed in the developing pollen lineage, we created transcriptional reporter constructs <italic>MCRpr:H2B-RFP</italic> and <italic>EApr:H2B-RFP</italic>, expressing the nuclear marker H2B tagged with red fluorescent protein and transformed them into wild-type <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. In the resulting transgenic lines, <italic>MCR</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> promoters were active in the developing pollen lineage (MMCs, tetrads, and young free microspores) as well as in somatic anther layers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>MCR and ELMOD_A do not accumulate at the aperture membrane domains.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Confocal images of wild-type anthers, tetrads, and young microspores expressing <italic>MCRpr:H2B-RFP</italic> (upper panels) and <italic>EApr:H2B-RFP</italic> (lower panels). Scale bars, 20 μm for anthers and 5 μm for tetrads and young microspores. (<bold>B, C</bold>) Confocal images of cells in the developing pollen lineage from <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> (<bold>B</bold>) and <italic>mcr elmod_a EApr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) plants. Upper panels: YFP signal. Lower panels: merged signal from YFP (yellow), Calcofluor White (blue, callose wall), and CellMask Deep Red (magenta, membranous structures). Scale bars, 5 μm. Identical staining and color scheme are used for similar images of tetrads in other figures. CW: Calcofluor White; DR: CellMask Deep Red; MMC: microspore mother cell; Msp: microspore; Td: tetrad.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig5-v1.tif"/></fig><p>To find out if, like the previously discovered aperture factors INP1 and D6PKL3, MCR and ELMOD_A accumulate at the aperture domains of tetrad-stage microspores, we determined the subcellular localization of the YFP-tagged proteins expressed from the translational reporters <italic>MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> and <italic>EApr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic>, which rescued mutant phenotypes. Consistent with the results from the transcriptional reporters, the YFP signal was present in MMCs, tetrads, and young microspores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B and C</xref>). This signal was diffusely localized in the cytoplasm and prominently enriched in the nucleoplasm. No specific enrichment near the plasma membrane was observed. Therefore, MCR and ELMOD_A specify positions and number of aperture domains without visibly congregating there.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Invariant arginine in the putative GAP region is essential for MCR and ELMOD_A functions</title><p>Although ELMOD proteins do not have the typical GAP domain associated with the canonical Arf GAP proteins, they contain a conserved stretch of 26 amino acids, with 13 residues exhibiting a particularly high degree of conservation and forming the consensus sequence WX<sub>3</sub>G(F/W)QX<sub>3</sub>PXTD(F/L)<bold>R</bold>GXGX<sub>3</sub>LX<sub>2</sub>L. In mammalian ELMODs, this region is proposed to mediate their Arf/Arl GAP activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">East et al., 2012</xref>). The presence of the invariant Arg in this region is of particular importance since the activity of many GAP proteins of the Ras GTPase superfamily, including canonical Arf GAPs, relies on a catalytic Arg (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Scheffzek et al., 1998</xref>). Indeed, in mammalian ELMODs, the Arg in this putative GAP region was shown to be essential for their GAP activity, consistent with its role as the catalytic residue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">East et al., 2012</xref>). Even relatively small changes at this position, such as conversion to Lys, resulted in the complete loss of GAP activity.</p><p>Although plant ELMODs have only limited similarity to mammalian proteins (e.g., the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and human ELMODs have ~20% sequence identity), they contain the same conserved region and invariant Arg residue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). To test if this region is essential for function in MCR and ELMOD_A, we created constructs in which the invariant Arg (R127) was substituted with Lys (<italic>MCRpr:gMCR<sup>R127K</sup>-YFP</italic> and <italic>EApr:gELMOD_A<sup>R127K</sup>-YFP</italic>). These constructs were then expressed, respectively, in the <italic>mcr</italic> and <italic>mcr elmod_a</italic> mutants. Unlike the constructs with the wild-type MCR and ELMOD_A, the R127K constructs, although expressed normally, completely failed to restore the expected aperture patterns (0/8 T<sub>1</sub> plants for MCR<sup>R127K</sup>; 0/12 T1 plants for ELMOD_A<sup>R127K</sup>), indicating that, like in mammalian ELMODs, the Arg in the putative GAP region is critical for the activity of MCR and ELMOD_A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B and C</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>The R127 residue of MCR and ELMOD_A is essential for aperture formation.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Sequence alignment of the conserved GAP regions from six <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (At) and three human (Hs) ELMOD proteins, along with the consensus sequence. Invariant Arg residue (R127) and two other important residues (121 and 129) are indicated. N121 and C129, essential for AtELMOD_E function, are indicated by red squares. (<bold>B, C</bold>) Confocal images of pollen grains and tetrads from <italic>mcr</italic> and <italic>mcr elmod_a</italic> expressing, respectively, <italic>MCRpr:MCR<sup>R127K</sup>-YFP</italic> (<bold>B</bold>) and <italic>EApr:ELMOD_A<sup>R127K</sup>-YFP</italic> (<bold>C</bold>). Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm for pollen and 5 μm for tetrads.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig6-v1.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>The number of developing aperture domains is highly sensitive to the levels of MCR and ELMOD_A</title><p>While working with <italic>MCR-YFP</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_A-YFP</italic> transgenic lines, we made a surprising discovery. We noticed that while most of these lines had apertures restored to the expected number (i.e., three apertures for <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> and a ring-shaped aperture/two apertures for <italic>mcr elmod_a EApr:ELMOD_A-YFP</italic>), in some transgenic T<sub>1</sub> lines the number of apertures exceeded the expectations: with up to six apertures forming in <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> and up to four apertures in <italic>mcr elmod_a EApr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A and B'</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Aperture number is highly sensitive to the levels of MCR and ELMOD_A.</title><p>(<bold>A–B’</bold>) Pollen grains from the <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> and <italic>mcr elmod_a EApr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic> transgenic lines, respectively, with six and four apertures. (<bold>C, D</bold>) Quantification of aperture number and mean YFP signal in three homozygous lines of <italic>mcr MCRpr:</italic>g<italic>MCR-YFP</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) and <italic>mcr elmod_a EApr:</italic>g<italic>ELMOD_A-YFP</italic> (<bold>D</bold>). Stacked bars show the percentage of pollen grains (from ≥3 individual plants) with indicated number of apertures. Boxplots show mean YFP signal in the microspore nucleoplasm and cytoplasm. a. u.: arbitrary units. (<bold>E</bold>) Representative images of pollen grains and tetrads corresponding to data in (<bold>C</bold>). (<bold>F</bold>) Boxplots showing aperture number depends on the number of functional copies of <italic>MCR</italic>. Number of analyzed pollen grains (from ≥3 individual plants) is indicated. For all boxplots, boxes represent the first and third quartiles, central lines depict the median, small squares in the boxes indicate the mean values, and small shapes show individual samples. Whiskers extend to minimum and maximum values. ***p&lt;0.001 (two-tailed Student’s t-test). Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm for pollen and 5 μm for tetrads.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig7-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Representative aperture phenotypes and tetrads related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative images of pollen grains and tetrads used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7D</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative images of pollen grains and tetrads used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7F</xref>. Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm for pollen and 5 μm for tetrads.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig7-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>To test if different aperture numbers could be due to different levels of transgene expression, we examined YFP fluorescence in homozygous lines producing different aperture numbers. For both <italic>MCR</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> transgenes, the number of apertures positively correlated with the level of YFP signal in the microspore cytoplasm and nucleoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C–E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1A</xref>). In addition, in some lines, the number of apertures further increased in T<sub>2</sub> or T<sub>3</sub> generations compared to the numbers in T<sub>1</sub>, consistent with the transgene dosage increasing in later generations due to attaining homozygosity.</p><p>To further test the notion that aperture number depends on the <italic>MCR/ELMOD_A</italic> gene dosage/levels of expression, we modulated the dosage of <italic>MCR</italic>, starting with a defined transgene. We crossed a homozygous <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> plant from line 7-2, commonly producing &gt;6 apertures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref>), with (1) <italic>mcr</italic> and (2) wild type. In the resulting transgenic F<sub>1</sub> progeny of the first cross, <italic>MCR</italic> should be expressed from one source – a single copy of the transgene. In the F<sub>1</sub> progeny of the second cross, it should be expressed from two sources – one copy of the transgene plus one of the endogenous gene. In the pollen of these F<sub>1</sub> plants, the number of apertures correlated with the number of functional copies of <italic>MCR</italic>: pollen of <italic>gMCR-YFP/- mcr/mcr</italic> produced on average 4.68 ± 1.08 apertures compared to 5.85 ± 1.52 apertures in <italic>gMCR-YFP/- mcr/+</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B</xref>). We further assessed aperture phenotypes in the progeny of these plants that had a homozygous transgene and either zero or two copies of endogenous <italic>MCR</italic>. Both genotypes with the homozygous transgene produced many more apertures compared to plants with the hemizygous transgene, but they also differed significantly from each other, with the number of apertures correlating with the presence of endogenous <italic>MCR</italic> (8.08 ± 1.57 in <italic>MCR-YFP/MCR-YFP mcr/mcr</italic> vs. 9.34 ± 1.50 in <italic>MCR-YFP/MCR-YFP +/+</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B</xref>). These results indicate that the process of aperture domain specification is highly sensitive to the levels of MCR and ELMOD_A in developing microspores.</p></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>The ELMOD family in angiosperms has four distinct protein clades, with most species containing two A/B type proteins</title><p>To examine the evolutionary history of the plant ELMOD family, we retrieved 561 ELMOD sequences belonging to 178 species across the plant kingdom and used them for a detailed phylogenetic analysis. ELMOD proteins are widespread in plants, suggesting that they perform important functions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>ELMOD proteins exist across the plant kingdom.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree of ELMOD proteins across the plant kingdom. The four clades of angiosperm ELMODs are indicated. Orange circles: bootstrap values of 70–100%. (<bold>B</bold>) Inferred evolutionary history of the <italic>ELMOD</italic> gene family. Dots: inferred ancestral gene number in different plant groups; letters on top: ELMOD clades named after the corresponding <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> proteins; gray D indicates <italic>Arabidopsis ELMOD_D</italic> is likely a pseudogene; numbers on the right: estimated time of divergence in millions of years (MYA) calculated using the TimeTree database.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig8-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig8s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 8—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Angiosperm ELMOD proteins cluster into four clades.</title><p>Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree of ELMOD proteins from angiosperms. The four distinct clades have been collapsed and details of each clade are presented as the pruned circular tree on the right. Label color shows the taxonomic group of each protein as indicated on the right. Orange circles indicate bootstrap values higher than 70%. Red arrowheads indicate the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMOD proteins. The complete tree can be accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://itol.embl.de/shared/Zhou3117">http://itol.embl.de/shared/Zhou3117</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig8-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Green algae as well as non-vascular land plants (liverworts, mosses, and hornworts) typically have a single ELMOD protein, but an ancestor of lycophytes and ferns had a gene duplication (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A and B</xref>). Beginning with gymnosperms, the ELMOD family expanded and diversified, with distinct protein groups clustering with the A/B/C clade, the E clade, and the F clade (<italic>Arabidopsis</italic> proteins were used as landmarks in naming the clades). In early angiosperms, ELMOD proteins separated into four well-supported clades: A/B, C, E, and F (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A and B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1</xref>). The split within the aperture factor-containing A/B clade into the separate ELMOD_A and ELMOD_B (MCR) lineages happened late – in the common ancestor of the Brassicaceae family (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1</xref>). Yet, in many other angiosperm species, including magnoliids, monocots, basal eudicots, and multiple asterids and rosids, the A/B clade also contains at least two proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1</xref>). This shows that independent duplications in this lineage happened multiple times, suggesting the existence of strong evolutionary pressure to maintain more than one gene of the A/B type.</p></sec><sec id="s2-10"><title>Phylogenetic analysis of the ELMOD family reveals the importance of positions 165 and 129 and suggests ELMOD_D is likely a pseudogene</title><p>The extensive number of the retrieved ELMOD sequences allowed us to evaluate conservation of the residues disrupted in MCR by the <italic>mcr-1</italic> and <italic>mcr-2</italic> mutations. Pro165, converted into Ser in <italic>mcr-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>), was present in each of the 553 ELMOD sequences containing this region, suggesting a critical role in protein function. This Pro belongs to the highly conserved WEY<bold>P</bold>FAVAG motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>) found in all six <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMODs, as well as in the majority of ELMODs from other plants, including green algae.</p><p>The appearance of Asp at position 129 in <italic>mcr-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>) affects a site within the putative GAP region, neighboring the critical catalytic Arg127. This change is also highly unusual from the evolutionary perspective. Except for one likely pseudogene (see below), none of the other 560 ELMOD sequences from across the plant kingdom has an Asp at that site, consistent with the notion that an Asp at this position is not tolerated by natural selection and could be detrimental for all plant ELMOD proteins.</p><p>Our analysis of residues occupying position 129 in the GAP region across the angiosperm ELMOD proteins led to an interesting discovery. In the 365 analyzed angiosperm sequences, this site is occupied by only three amino acids: Cys, Gly, or Ala. (Earlier diverged plants have Ala or Gly at this site.) Strikingly, we found that all proteins with Cys129 cluster with the E clade, whereas nearly all proteins with Gly129 cluster with either the A/B or the F clades, and nearly all proteins with Ala129 cluster with the C clade. (Only six exceptions were found among the 365 sequences: in five cases, proteins containing Ala129 clustered with the A/B or the F clades, and in one case, a protein with Gly129 clustered with the C clade.) This suggested the intriguing possibility, tested later, that, in angiosperms, residues at position 129 are important for functional differentiation of the ELMOD proteins.</p><p>Besides <italic>mcr-2</italic>, the only protein with Asp at position 129 is the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMOD_D. However, it has several other features that suggest it is likely a pseudogene. At 213 amino acids, ELMOD_D is markedly shorter than the other five <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMODs (265–323 aa-long): it misses stretches of 52 aa upstream of the GAP region, 4 aa in the vicinity of the GAP region, and 22 aa at the very C-terminus of the protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). It also has major substitutions unique to this protein within or near its GAP region, which change the conserved Gly119 and Leu138 residues into Arg (the numbering within the GAP region is based on the MCR and ELMOD_A sequences; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). ELMOD_D clusters with the C clade and is most closely related to the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMOD_C, indicating that it is a product of a very recent duplication (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1</xref>). While some plants have more than one protein in the C clade, most others, including close relatives of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, have just a single C protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1</xref>), suggesting that a single C-type activity is sufficient for most species. These findings, combined with the extremely low levels of <italic>ELMOD_D</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>), support the hypothesis that this member of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMOD family is likely non-functional.</p></sec><sec id="s2-11"><title>ELMOD_E can influence aperture formation and produce a novel aperture pattern</title><p>To test if other ELMOD family members, besides MCR and ELMOD_A, might be involved in aperture formation, we examined the phenotypes of their single mutants and double mutants with <italic>mcr</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s1">Figure 9—figure supplement 1</xref>). All single mutants displayed normal aperture patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s1">Figure 9—figure supplement 1B–F'</xref>),while the double mutants exhibited <italic>mcr</italic> phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s1">Figure 9—figure supplement 1G–J'</xref>), indicating that, unlike <italic>ELMOD_A</italic>, the other four <italic>ELMOD</italic> genes do not interact synergistically with <italic>MCR</italic> in aperture formation.</p><p>We also assessed the ability of these genes to rescue the <italic>mcr</italic> aperture phenotype by expressing them, tagged with <italic>YFP</italic>, from the <italic>MCR</italic> regulatory regions. <italic>ELMOD_C</italic> showed some limited ability to restore three apertures in <italic>mcr</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s2">Figure 9—figure supplement 2A–D'</xref>), while <italic>ELMOD_D</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_F</italic> were unable to do it (6/6 and 22/22 T<sub>1</sub> plants; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s2">Figure 9—figure supplement 2E–F'</xref>). Based on the YFP signal, ELMOD_F-YFP was expressed at a level comparable with that of the MCR-YFP and ELMOD_A-YFP transgenes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s2">Figure 9—figure supplement 2G and G'</xref>). ELMOD_D-YFP, however, was undetectable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s2">Figure 9—figure supplement 2H and H'</xref>), consistent with the hypothesis that <italic>ELMOD_D</italic> is a pseudogene.</p><p>Most interestingly, the expression of <italic>ELMOD</italic>_<italic>E</italic> in <italic>mcr</italic> led to a neomorphic phenotype: instead of narrow longitudinal furrows, pollen of all seven T<sub>1</sub> plants developed multiple short, round apertures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9A and A'</xref>). To see if this effect was limited to the <italic>mcr</italic> background, we transformed the <italic>MCRpr:ELMOD_E-YFP</italic> construct into wild-type Col-0 plants. The T<sub>1</sub> plants showed a range of aperture phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9B–D'</xref>), yet multiple round apertures were commonly present, suggesting that <italic>ELMOD</italic>_<italic>E</italic> exerts a dominant negative effect when misexpressed in developing microspores.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig9" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMOD_E can affect aperture patterns.</title><p>(<bold>A–D’</bold>) Pollen grains from <italic>mcr</italic> (<bold>A, A’</bold>) and Col-0 (<bold>B–D’</bold>) plants expressing <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic>. (<bold>E, E’</bold>) Pollen grain from <italic>mcr</italic> plants expressing <italic>ELMOD_Epr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic>. (<bold>F–H’</bold>) Confocal images of tetrads expressing <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_Epr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic>. Adjacent panels show YFP signal (α) and merged signal (α’) from YFP, Calcofluor White (CW), and CellMask Deep Red (DR). (<bold>I–K’</bold>) Pollen grains from the F<sub>1</sub> plants produced by crossing <italic>mcr MCRpr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic> with three T<sub>3</sub> lines of <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> (with single homozygous insertions of the <italic>MCR-YFP</italic> transgene, expressed, respectively, at low, medium, and high levels). (<bold>L</bold>) Percentage of pollen grains with indicated number of apertures in the pollen populations from F<sub>1</sub> progeny of the <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> T<sub>3</sub>-7-2 line crossed with <italic>mcr</italic> or with <italic>mcr MCRpr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic>. Number of analyzed pollen grains (from at least two individual plants) is indicated. Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm for pollen and 5 μm for tetrads.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig9-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig9s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 9—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Disruptions of <italic>Arabidopsis ELMOD_C</italic>, <italic>ELMOD_D</italic>, <italic>ELMOD_E</italic>, and <italic>ELMOD_F</italic> do not affect aperture patterns.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Diagram of the <italic>ELMOD_C</italic> (<italic>At1g67400</italic>), <italic>ELMOD_D</italic> (<italic>At3g43400</italic>), <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> (<italic>At1g03620</italic>), and <italic>ELMOD_F</italic> (<italic>At3g03610</italic>) genes. T-DNA insertion sites are indicated for each gene. For <italic>ELMOD_E</italic>, CRISPR alleles (<italic>elmod-e<sup>CR</sup></italic>) were also generated in the wild-type and <italic>mcr</italic> backgrounds. Both alleles had frame shift mutations. The 20 bp target sequence next to the underlined protospacer adjacent motif is indicated in bold. Nucleotide and amino acid changes are indicated with red capital letters. (<bold>B–F’</bold>) Pollen grains of single T-DNA insertion mutants of <italic>ELMOD_C</italic>, <italic>ELMOD_D</italic>, <italic>ELMOD_E</italic>, <italic>ELMOD_F,</italic> and the CRISPR/Cas9 mutant of <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> (<italic>elmod_e<sup>CR</sup></italic>). (<bold>G–J’</bold>) Pollen grains of the double mutants <italic>mcr elmod_e<sup>CR</sup></italic> (<bold>G, G’</bold>)<italic>, mcr elmod_c</italic> (<bold>H, H’</bold>)<italic>, mcr elmod_d</italic> (<bold>I, I’</bold>)<italic>,</italic> and <italic>mcr elmod_f</italic> (<bold>J, J’</bold>). Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig9-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig9s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 9—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>ELMOD_C, but not ELMOD_D and ELMOD_F, can partially substitute for MCR in aperture formation.</title><p>(<bold>A–B’, E–F’</bold>) Pollen grains from <italic>mcr MCRpr:gELMOD_C-YFP</italic> (<bold>A–B’</bold>), <italic>mcr MCRpr:gELMOD_F-YFP</italic> (<bold>E, E’</bold>), and <italic>mcr MCRpr:gELMOD_D-YFP</italic> (<bold>F, F’</bold>). Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. (<bold>D, D’</bold> and <bold>G–H’</bold>) Confocal images of <italic>mcr</italic> tetrads expressing YFP fusions of ELMOD_C, ELMOD_F, and ELMOD_D. (<bold>D, D’</bold>) <italic>mcr</italic> tetrads expressing <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_C-YFP</italic> have detectable YFP fluorescence. (<bold>G, G’</bold>) <italic>mcr</italic> tetrads expressing <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_F-YFP</italic> show strong YFP fluorescence. (<bold>H, H’</bold>) There is no observable YFP fluorescence in the <italic>mcr</italic> tetrads expressing <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_D-YFP</italic>. Adjacent panels show YFP fluorescence (α) and merged fluorescent signal (α’) from YFP, Calcofluor White (CW), and CellMask Deep Red (DR). Scale bars, 10 μm for pollen and 5 μm for tetrads. (<bold>C, C’</bold>) Percentage of pollen grains with indicated number of apertures in pollen populations from the T<sub>1</sub> plants of <italic>mcr MCRpr:gELMOD_C-YFP</italic>. Number of analyzed pollen grains is indicated.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig9-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>We then tested whether <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> would have the same effect on aperture patterns when expressed from its own promoter. However, none of the 12 T<sub>1</sub> transgenic <italic>mcr</italic> plants expressing the <italic>ELMOD_Epr:ELMOD_E-YFP</italic> construct had any changes in the <italic>mcr</italic> aperture phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9E and E'</xref>). Analysis of the YFP signal showed that this gene is expressed in tetrad-stage microspores at much lower levels from its own promoter than from the <italic>MCR</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9F–H'</xref>). Thus, while ELMOD_E can influence aperture patterns, it is likely not normally involved in this process in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</p><p>To test if differences in the MCR levels could impact the ability of transgenic ELMOD_E to produce round apertures, we crossed a <italic>mcr MCRpr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic> line with the above described <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> lines 10-3, 13-5, and 7-2 that express MCR, respectively, at low, medium, and high levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref>). In the F<sub>1</sub> progeny of crosses with low and medium expressors, 10-3 and 13-5, pollen still produced round apertures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9I–J'</xref>). Yet, in the F<sub>1</sub> progeny of the cross with the high expressor 7-2, furrow aperture morphology was restored (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9K and K'</xref>), although these plants produced less pollen with a high number of furrows (&gt;4) compared to the original 7-2 plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9L</xref>). Together, these data support the idea that high level of MCR can counteract the neomorphic activity of ELMOD_E and suggest that MCR and ELMOD_E may compete for the same interactors.</p></sec><sec id="s2-12"><title>Residues 121 and 129 in the GAP region are important for the MCR- and ELMOD_E-specific functions in aperture formation</title><p>The different aperture phenotypes of <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> and <italic>mcr MCRpr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic> lines gave us an opportunity to test the hypothesis that residues at position 129 are important for functional differentiation of ELMODs from different clades. For E-clade proteins, we also noticed that Cys129 was always found together with Asn121. These residues are unique to this clade: 100% of the retrieved E-clade sequences (n = 69) have Asn121/Cys129 vs. 0% of sequences from the other clades (n = 297). Thus, this combination could be important for the E-clade functions. In the other three clades, position 121 is always occupied by Asp.</p><p>To investigate the importance of sites 121 and 129 for MCR and ELMOD_E functions, we created six constructs in which one or both residues at these positions were replaced with the residues typical of the other clade and expressed them in the <italic>mcr</italic> mutant. The MCR proteins carrying the E-specific residues at both positions (MCR<sup>D121N/G129C</sup>) or at the position 121 (MCR<sup>D121N</sup>) still retained most of the MCR function, with most T<sub>1</sub> plants producing three or more furrow apertures in most of their pollen grains (7/9 and 12/12 T<sub>1</sub> plants, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10A and B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s1">Figure 10—figure supplement 1A</xref>). However, when the E-specific residue was present only at position 129 (MCR<sup>G129C</sup>), MCR protein became less active, with only 5 out of 11 T<sub>1</sub> plants producing three furrow apertures in all or most of their pollen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10C</xref>). In the rest of these T<sub>1</sub> plants, the <italic>mcr</italic> phenotype was not rescued or was rescued poorly, with &lt;30% of pollen grains forming three apertures.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig10" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><title>Residues 121 and 129 in the GAP region are important for MCR- and ELMOD_E-specific functions in aperture formation.</title><p>Percentage of pollen grains with indicated number of apertures in the pollen populations from independent T<sub>1</sub> <italic>mcr</italic> plants expressing variants of <italic>MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> (<bold>A–C</bold>) or <italic>MCRpr:ELMOD_A-YFP</italic> (<bold>D–F</bold>) with residues 121 and/or 129 mutated. Number of analyzed pollen grains is indicated above the bars.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig10-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig10s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 10—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Representative aperture phenotypes observed in T<sub>1</sub> plants related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10</xref>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative aperture phenotypes (all furrows) observed in T<sub>1</sub> plants related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10A–C</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) More diverse aperture phenotypes observed in T<sub>1</sub> plants related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10D–F</xref>. Red box highlights the most common aperture morphologies of three normal or, sometimes, disconnected furrows observed in the T<sub>1</sub> plants related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10D</xref>. Three round apertures were only found in the T<sub>1</sub> plants related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10E and F</xref>. ≥4 apertures were mostly round. Apertures are indicated with arrowheads. Scale bars, 10 μm. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of aperture morphologies (furrows vs. round) in pollen with 3 apertures and ≥4 apertures in T<sub>1</sub> plants expressing <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic> with <italic>MCR</italic>-like mutations at positions 121 and 129 (related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10D–F</xref>). Total number of apertures analyzed for each aperture pattern across different T<sub>1</sub> plants expressing the same transgenic construct is indicated. Pollen with three apertures had predominantly furrows and pollen with ≥4 apertures had mostly round apertures.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-71061-fig10-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Experiments with the ELMOD_E proteins carrying the MCR residues at positions 121 and 129 confirmed the importance of Asn121 and Cys129 for the ELMOD_E neomorphic activity. In the case where both residues were replaced with the MCR residues (ELMOD_E<sup>N121D/C129G</sup>), ELMOD_E largely lost its ability to create round apertures and instead often restored three furrow-like apertures, thus acting like MCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s1">Figure 10—figure supplement 1B</xref>). In the cases when only one residue was changed (ELMOD_E<sup>N121D</sup> and ELMOD_E<sup>C129G</sup>), the mutant ELMOD_E proteins were still often able to produce multiple round apertures, although three normal furrows or a mixture of furrows and round apertures were also produced, suggesting that the single mutations reduced the ELMOD_E activity, but did not eliminate it entirely (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10E and F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s1">Figure 10—figure supplement 1B</xref>). While the number of apertures produced in these experiments varied and some pollen grains had both furrows and round apertures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s1">Figure 10—figure supplement 1B</xref>), in general, there was a strong correlation between the number of apertures per pollen and their shape. Analysis of 207 pollen grains from across the ELMOD_E<sup>N121D/C129G</sup> transgenic lines showed that when pollen had three apertures, they were mostly represented by furrows (95%, n = 468 apertures), whereas in pollen with four or more apertures, apertures were mostly round (84%, n = 239 apertures; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s1">Figure 10—figure supplement 1C</xref>). Similar trends were also observed in ELMOD_E<sup>N121D</sup> and ELMOD_E<sup>C129G</sup> transgenic lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10s1">Figure 10—figure supplement 1C</xref>).</p><p>Taken together, these results show that residues at positions 121 and 129 in the GAP region provide important contributions to the specific functions of MCR and ELMOD_E. Yet they are less critical for MCR, in accord with the fact that Asp121 and Gly129 are not unique to the A/B clade. In the case of ELMOD_E, the E-clade-specific combination of Asn121/Cys129 appears to be essential for its distinct activity. When both residues undergo MCR-like changes, ELMOD_E loses its neomorphic activity, instead becoming capable of carrying out the MCR role in aperture formation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>How developing pollen grains create beautiful and diverse geometrical aperture patterns has been a long-standing problem in plant biology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Fischer, 1889</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Ressayre et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Wodehouse, 1935</xref>). In this study, we uncovered the first set of molecular factors, belonging to the ELMOD protein family, that have a clear ability to regulate the number, positions, and morphology of aperture domains. MCR and its close paralog ELMOD_A act as (somewhat) redundant positive regulators of furrow aperture formation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</p><p>Our genetic analysis places MCR and ELMOD_A at the beginning of the aperture formation pathway, upstream of the previously discovered aperture factors D6PKL3, INP1, and, likely, INP2, the recently identified partner of INP1. Previous studies showed that INP1 and INP2 act as the executors of the aperture formation program, absolutely essential for aperture development but not able on their own to influence the number and positions of aperture domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dobritsa et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Lee et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Li et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>). D6PKL3 was proposed to act upstream of INP1, defining the features of aperture domains, yet it also largely lacks the ability to initiate completely new domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lee et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Zhou and Dobritsa, 2019</xref>). In <italic>mcr</italic> microspores, D6PKL3 and INP1 re-localize to the ring-shaped aperture domains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1G</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2A</xref>), indicating that they become attracted to the newly specified aperture domains and the ELMOD proteins act as patterning factors, contributing to symmetry breaking and selection of sites for aperture domains.</p><p>Our data demonstrate that the aperture domains forming in each microspore are highly sensitive to the ELMOD_A/MCR protein dosage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C–G'</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>). Increased dosage leads to a higher number of apertures, while decreased dosage results in fewer, and the reducing effect of the loss in <italic>MCR</italic> activity on aperture number is maintained across different levels of ploidy and post-meiotic arrangements of microspores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1I</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>), which were previously shown to be important factors in aperture patterning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>). Thus, modulation of ELMOD protein levels might offer a mechanism for creating different aperture patterns in different species. Interestingly, within the genus <italic>Pedicularis,</italic> some species display the <italic>mcr</italic>-like ring-shaped apertures, while others produce three apertures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Wang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). Our findings suggest that such variations in aperture patterns could conceivably be due to variations in ELMOD proteins or their effectors or regulators. Importantly, while great diversity of pollen aperture numbers is found across plant species, within a species, this trait tends to be very robust. For example, in wild-type <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the number of apertures rarely deviates from three (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>). Our results, therefore, imply that, normally, levels of MCR and ELMOD_A are very tightly controlled, and there must exist mechanisms to ensure this control.</p><p>The discovery that <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> can also influence aperture patterns in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and create multiple round apertures instead of three furrows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9A–B'</xref>) suggests that the regulation of <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> might also contribute to the diversity of aperture patterns in nature. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> does not seem to be usually involved in aperture formation. Yet, when misexpressed from the <italic>MCR</italic> regulatory regions, it interferes with MCR and ELMOD_A activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9I–L</xref>), resulting in the formation of new aperture domains.</p><p>ELMODs are ancient proteins, predicted to have been present in the last common ancestor of all eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">East et al., 2012</xref>). In animals, these proteins act as non-canonical GAPs, regulating activities of both Arf and Arl GTPases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bowzard et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Ivanova et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Turn et al., 2020</xref>). Arf GTPases are commonly associated with the recruitment of vesicle coat proteins to different membrane compartments to initiate vesicle budding and trafficking, while the roles of the related Arl proteins are less understood and likely more diverse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Sztul et al., 2019</xref>). Although the function of ELMOD proteins in plants is unknown, their presence in green algae and other basal plants lineages suggests that they have been playing important roles in plant cells since their inception. Our phylogenetic analysis indicates that this family in plants is monophyletic, and the genes have duplicated and diversified over the course of plant evolution.</p><p>The angiosperm ELMOD family has four distinct clades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A and B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1</xref>). In many species, the A/B clade, containing MCR and ELMOD_A, has two or more proteins due to independent duplications that occurred multiple times in evolution. This suggests that species might be under a selective pressure to keep more than one A/B type protein, implying that the processes in which these proteins are involved (e.g., aperture formation) benefit from genetic redundancy and, thus, are highly important.</p><p>Further studies will be required to establish the biochemical role of plant ELMOD proteins. Like their animal counterparts, plant ELMODs may be involved in regulation of Arf/Arl activities. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> has 19 ARFs and ARLs, which, with few exceptions, mostly remain uncharacterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Delgadillo et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Gebbie et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">McElver et al., 2000</xref> ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Singh et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Vernoud et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Xu and Scheres, 2005</xref>). The roles attributed to members of this family – for example, in secretion, endocytosis, activation of phosphatidyl inositol kinases, and actin polymerization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Singh and Jürgens, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Sztul et al., 2019</xref>) – are all potentially fitting with the formation of distinct aperture domains. The protein region proposed to be the GAP region in mammalian ELMODs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">East et al., 2012</xref>) is conserved in plant proteins, and the invariant Arg residue believed to be catalytic in mammalian ELMODs is also necessary for function in MCR and ELMOD_A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B and C</xref>). Interestingly, some positions within the conserved GAP region show strict residue specificity in different clades, suggesting that they could be important for functional diversity of these proteins. Consistent with this, we found the combination of Asn121/Cys129 to be key for the ELMOD_E neomorphic aperture-forming activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10</xref>).</p><p>Alternatively, plant ELMODs could have evolved functions different from their animal counterparts and regulate targets other than ARFs/ARLs. Interestingly, the only study done so far on an ELMOD protein in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hoefle and Hückelhoven, 2014</xref>) pulled out the barley homolog of ELMOD_C in a yeast two-hybrid screen as an interactor of a ROP GAP, a GAP for a different class of small GTPases, Rho-of-plants (ROPs). Rho GTPases (including ROPs) are well-known regulators of cell polarity and domain formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Feiguelman et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Yang and Lavagi, 2012</xref>), so their involvement in aperture formation cannot be excluded.</p><p>In summary, we presented critical players in the process of patterning the pollen surface. These players belong to the ELMOD protein family, which, while undoubtedly important, has not yet been characterized in plants. Future studies should focus on identifying the interactors of the ELMOD proteins and on understanding the mechanisms through which they specify positions and shape of aperture domains without noticeably accumulating at these regions.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">Reagent type (species) or resource</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Designation</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Source or reference</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Identifiers</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gene (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>ELMOD_A</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.arabidopsis.org/">https://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>AT3G60260</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gene (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>MCR/ELMOD_B</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.arabidopsis.org/">https://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>AT2G44770</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gene (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>ELMOD_C</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.arabidopsis.org/">https://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>AT1G67400</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gene (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>ELMOD_D</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.arabidopsis.org/">https://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>AT3G43400</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gene (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>ELMOD_E</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.arabidopsis.org/">https://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>AT1G03620</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gene (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>ELMOD_F</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.arabidopsis.org/">https://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>AT3G03610</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Strain, strain background(<italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">GV3101</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Widely distributed</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Competent cells</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Genetic reagent(<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>mcr-1</italic></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">This study, EMS mutagenesis</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref> for <break/>all other genetic reagents</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Auramine O</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A96825</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Vectashield antifade solution</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Vector Labs</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">H-1000-10</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Calcofluor White</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PhytoTechnology Laboratories</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C1933</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">CellMask Deep Red</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C10046</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">NIS Elements v.4.20</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Nikon Microscopy</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">MAFFT version 7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Katoh and Standley, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Katoh et al., 2002</xref></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mafft.cbrc.jp/alignment/software/">https://mafft.cbrc.jp/alignment/software/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">TrimAl</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Capella-Gutiérrez et al., 2009</xref></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://vicfero.github.io/trimal/">https://vicfero.github.io/trimal/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IQ-TREE</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Nguyen et al., 2015</xref></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iqtree.org/">http://www.iqtree.org/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Origin version 2018</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">OriginLab</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.originlab.com/">https://www.originlab.com/</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">N/A</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title><p><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> genotypes used in this study were either in Columbia (Col) or Landsberg <italic>erecta</italic> (L<italic>er</italic>) background. Pollen from wild-type Col- and L<italic>er</italic> has indistinguishable aperture phenotypes. The following genotypes were also used: <italic>mcr-1</italic>, <italic>mcr-2</italic>, <italic>mcr-3</italic>, <italic>mcr-4</italic>, <italic>mcr-5</italic> (CS853233), <italic>mcr-6</italic> (SALK_205528C), <italic>mcr-7</italic> (SALK_203827C), <italic>elmod_c</italic> (SALK_076565), <italic>elmod_d</italic> (SALK_031512), <italic>elmod_e</italic> (SALK_082496), <italic>elmod_f</italic> (SALK_010379), <italic>inp1-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dobritsa and Coerper, 2012</xref>), <italic>inp2-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Lee et al., 2021</xref>), <italic>d6pkl3-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lee et al., 2018</xref>), <italic>inp1-1 DMC1pr:INP1-YFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dobritsa et al., 2018</xref>), <italic>d6pkl3-2 D6PKL3pr:D6PKL3-YFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lee et al., 2018</xref>), <italic>tes</italic> (SALK _113909), <italic>MiMe</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">d’Erfurth et al., 2009</xref>), and <italic>cenh3-1 GFP-tailswap</italic> (CS66982). <italic>mcr-1</italic> through <italic>mcr-4</italic> mutants were discovered in a forward genetic screen performed on an EMS-mutagenized L<italic>er</italic> population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Plourde et al., 2019</xref>). <italic>mcr-5</italic> through <italic>mcr-7</italic> mutants and <italic>elmod_c</italic> through <italic>elmod_f</italic> mutants were ordered from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (ABRC). Plants were grown at 20–22°C with the 16 hr light/8 hr dark cycle in growth chambers or in a greenhouse at the Biotechnology support facility at OSU.</p><p>To generate the 2n <italic>mcr tes</italic> plants, <italic>mcr-1</italic> mutant was crossed with heterozygous <italic>tes</italic>, double heterozygotes were recovered in F<sub>1</sub> by genotyping (primers listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>), and double homozygotes were identified in F<sub>2</sub> population. The generation of haploid <italic>mcr MiMe</italic> plants was similar to the procedure previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>). In brief, <italic>mcr-1</italic> mutant was first crossed with plants that were triple heterozygotes for <italic>atrec8-3</italic>, <italic>osd1-3</italic>, and <italic>atspo11-1-3</italic> (<italic>MiMe</italic> heterozygotes), then the quadruple heterozygotes were identified among the F<sub>1</sub> progeny by genotyping and crossed as males with <italic>cenh3-1 GFP-tailswap</italic> homozygous plants that were used as haploidy inducers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Ravi and Chan, 2010</xref>). 1n F<sub>1</sub> progeny of this cross were identified by their distinctive morphology as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Ravi and Chan, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>), and the triple 1n <italic>MiMe</italic> and quadruple 1n <italic>mcr MiMe</italic> mutants were identified by genotyping (primers listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Unlike other 1n genotypes generated by this cross, which were sterile, the 1n plants with <italic>MiMe</italic> mutations were fertile and produced 1n pollen via mitosis-like division and dyad formation.</p><p>Mapping of the <italic>MCR</italic> locus <italic>mcr-1</italic> mutant with L<italic>er</italic> background was crossed with Col-0, and individual F<sub>2</sub> plants were screened under a dissecting microscope for the presence of the distinctive angular mutant phenotype in their dry pollen. In total, 369 plants with mutant phenotype were selected, and their genomic DNA was isolated. To map the <italic>MCR</italic> locus, we first conducted bulked segregant analysis, followed by the map-based positional cloning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lukowitz et al., 2000</xref>). The insertion-deletion (InDel) molecular markers were developed based on the combined information from the 1001 Genomes Project database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1001 Genomes Consortium, 2016</xref>) and the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Mapping Platform (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Hou et al., 2010</xref>). The <italic>MCR</italic> locus was mapped to a 77 kb region between markers 2–18.39 Mb (18,395,427 bp) and 2–18.47 Mb (18,472,092 bp) on chromosome 2. Molecular markers used for mapping are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>. Out of the 25 genes located in this interval, we sequenced 11 genes, prioritized based on their predicted expression patterns and gene ontology, and found that one of them, <italic>At2g44770</italic>, contained a missense mutation. Sequencing of the other three non-complementing EMS alleles identified in the forward genetic screen (<italic>mcr-2</italic> to <italic>mcr-4</italic>) also revealed presence of mutations in <italic>At2g44770</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Inactivation of <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> with CRISPR/Cas9</title><p>Two guide RNAs against target sequences at the beginning of the <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> and <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> CDS were selected with the help of the CRISPR-PLANT platform (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.genome.arizona.edu/crispr/">https://www.genome.arizona.edu/crispr/</ext-link> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Xie et al., 2014</xref>) and individually cloned into the <italic>Bsa</italic>I site of the pHEE401E vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Wang et al., 2015</xref>) as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Xing et al., 2014</xref>), using, respectively, two sets of complementary primers: <italic>elmod_a</italic> sgRNA-F/R and <italic>elmod_e</italic> sgRNA-F/R (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). The resulting constructs were separately transformed into the <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101, and then used to transform <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Col-0 plants or <italic>mcr-1</italic> mutants (the latter only with the anti-<italic>ELMOD_E</italic> construct) using the floral-dip method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Clough and Bent, 1998</xref>). The T<sub>1</sub> transformants were selected on ½ strength MS plates supplemented with 1% (w/v) sucrose, 0.8% (w/v) agar, and 50 µg/mL hygromycin, their DNA was extracted, and the regions surrounding the target sequences were sequenced. For <italic>ELMOD_A</italic>, 5 of 25 T<sub>1</sub> plants had homozygous, biallelic, or heterozygous mutations. Sequencing the progeny of these plants demonstrated that all homozygous/biallelic mutants developed frame shifts in the <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> CDS after the codon 64 (by acquiring either a 1-nt insertion three nucleotides before PAM or a 1-nt deletion two nucleotides before PAM). An <italic>elmod_a</italic> mutant with a single A insertion, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, and still carrying CRISPR/Cas9 transgene, was crossed with the <italic>mcr-1</italic> mutant to obtain the <italic>mcr elmod_a</italic> double mutant. For <italic>ELMOD_E</italic>, 1 out of 12 and 1 out of 20 T<sub>1</sub> plants had biallelic mutations, respectively, in Col-0 and <italic>mcr-1</italic> backgrounds. In T<sub>2</sub> generation, homozygous mutants with a frame shift in the CDS were identified: in <italic>elmod_e<sup>CR</sup></italic>, a 13-nt region located four nucleotides before PAM was deleted and replaced with a different 9-nt sequence; in <italic>mcr elmod_e<sup>CR</sup></italic>, a single A was inserted four nucleotides before PAM. These mutants were used to observe the aperture phenotypes.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Generation of transgenic constructs and plant transformation</title><p>A 3076 bp fragment upstream of the start codon of <italic>MCR</italic> was used as the <italic>MCR</italic> promoter for all <italic>MCRpr</italic> constructs. To generate the <italic>MCRpr:gMCR</italic> construct, the promoter and the 2868 bp genomic fragment from the <italic>MCR</italic> start codon to 798 bp downstream of the stop codon were separately amplified from Col-0 genomic DNA and cloned into <italic>Sac</italic>I/<italic>Nco</italic>I sites in the pGR111 binary vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Dobritsa et al., 2010</xref>) through In-Fusion cloning (Takara). An <italic>Age</italic>I site was introduced in front of the <italic>MCR</italic> start codon for ease of subsequent cloning. For <italic>MCRpr:MCR CDS</italic>, the genomic fragment was replaced with the <italic>MCR</italic> coding sequence, which was amplified from the <italic>MCR</italic> cDNA construct CD257409 obtained from ABRC. For <italic>MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> construct, the genomic fragment of <italic>MCR</italic> was amplified without the stop codon and cloned upstream of <italic>YFP</italic> into the pGR111 binary vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Dobritsa et al., 2010</xref>). Additionally, a 497 bp 3′ UTR region from <italic>MCR</italic> was then cloned downstream of <italic>YFP</italic>. Since we achieved phenotypic rescue and observed strong YFP signal with this construct, we used this combination of regulatory elements in all subsequent constructs for which we wanted to achieve the <italic>MCR</italic>-like expression. The constructs <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_A/C/D/E/F-YFP</italic> were created in a similar way.</p><p>For all <italic>EApr</italic> constructs, a 2163 bp fragment upstream of the start codon of <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> was amplified from Col-0 genomic DNA and used as the <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> promoter. For <italic>EApr:gELMOD_A</italic>, a 2833 bp fragment, which included a 296 bp region downstream of the stop codon, was subcloned into pGR111 downstream of <italic>EApr</italic>. A <italic>Bam</italic>HI site was introduced in front of the start codon for ease of subsequent cloning. For <italic>EApr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic>, a 2534 bp genomic fragment (from the <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> start codon to immediately upstream of the stop codon) was cloned between the <italic>EApr</italic> and <italic>YFP</italic>. For <italic>ELMOD_Epr:ELMOD_E-YFP</italic>, a 1469 bp fragment upstream of the start codon of <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> was amplified from Col-0 genomic DNA and used as the <italic>ELMOD_E</italic> promoter to replace the <italic>MCR</italic> promoter in <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic>.</p><p>To generate the reporter constructs <italic>MCRpr:H2B-RFP</italic> and <italic>EApr:H2B-RFP</italic>, the <italic>H2B-RFP</italic> fusion gene was cloned into the <italic>Bam</italic>HI/<italic>Spe</italic>I sites downstream of the respective promoters in pGR111. To create constructs with single and double nucleotide substitutions, PCR-based site-directed mutagenesis was performed with IVA mutagenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">García-Nafría et al., 2016</xref>) using <italic>gMCR</italic>-pGEM-T Easy, <italic>gELMOD_A</italic>-pGEM-T Easy, and <italic>gELMOD_E</italic>-pGEM-T Easy as templates. The mutated sequences then replaced the respective wild-type sequences in <italic>MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic>-pGR111, <italic>EApr:ELMOD_A-YFP</italic>-pGR111, and <italic>MCRpr:gELMOD_E-YFP</italic>-pGR111. All primers used for creating constructs are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>. All constructs were verified by sequencing and transformed by electroporation into the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> strain GV3101 together with the helper plasmid pSoup. <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> cultures confirmed to contain the constructs of interest were then transformed into <italic>mcr</italic> or <italic>mcr elmod_a</italic> by floral dip (<italic>mcr elmod_a</italic> was verified to lack the anti-ELMOD_A CRISPR/Cas9 transgene).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Confocal microscopy and image analysis</title><p>Preparation and imaging of mature pollen grains, MMC, tetrads, and free microspores were performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reeder et al., 2016</xref>). Imaging was done on a Nikon A1+ confocal microscope with a 100× oil-immersion objective (NA = 1.4), using 1× confocal zoom for anthers, 3× zoom for pollen grains, 5× zoom for MMC and tetrads, and 5× or 8× zoom for free microspores. For imaging mature pollen grains, pollen was placed into an ~10 μL drop of auramine O working solution (0.001%; diluted in water from the 0.1% [w/v] stock prepared in 50 mM Tris-HCl), allowed to hydrate for ~5 min, covered with a #1.5 cover slip, and sealed with nail polish. Exine was excited with a 488 nm laser and fluorescence was collected at 500–550 nm. To count aperture number, images from the front and back view of pollen grain were taken. If some apertures were present on sides of a pollen grain not directly visible by focusing on the front and on the back, then z-stacks were taken (step size = 500 nm) and 3D images were reconstructed using NIS Elements software v.4.20 (Nikon) and used for counting aperture number.</p><p>For imaging cells of the developing pollen lineage, anthers were dissected out of stage 9 flower buds and placed into a small drop of Vectashield antifade solution supplemented with 0.02% Calcofluor White and 5 μg/mL membrane stain CellMask Deep Red. Cells in the pollen lineage were released by applying gentle pressure to the coverslip placed over the anthers. To obtain fluorescence signals, the following excitation/emission settings were used: RFP, 561 nm/580–630 nm; YFP, 514 nm/522–555 nm; Calcofluor White, 405 nm/424–475 nm; CellMask Deep Red, 640 nm/663–738 nm. Z-stacks of tetrads were obtained with a step size of 500 nm and 3D reconstructed using NIS Elements v.4.20 (Nikon).</p><p>To compare the YFP fluorescence intensity in three different lines of <italic>mcr MCRpr:gMCR-YFP</italic> or <italic>mcr elmod_a EApr:gELMOD_A-YFP</italic>, tetrads were prepared simultaneously and imaged on the same day under identical acquisition settings on Nikon A1+ confocal microscope. The mean YFP signal intensities in nucleoplasm and cytoplasm of tetrads (n ≥ 15) were separately measured with the help of the region of interest (ROI) statistics function in NIS Elements v.4.20 (Nikon). For each tetrad, a single optical section showing both nucleoplasm and cytoplasm was selected and analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Sequence retrieval and phylogenetic analysis of the plant ELMOD family</title><p>ELMOD family members in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> have the following accession numbers: <italic>ELMOD_A</italic>, <italic>At3g60260; MCR</italic>, <italic>At2g44770; ELMOD_C</italic>, <italic>At1g67400; ELMOD_D</italic>, <italic>At3g43400; ELMOD_E</italic>, <italic>At1g03620; ELMOD_F, At3g03610</italic>. The phylogenetic tree of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMOD proteins in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref> was built using the neighbor-joining (NJ) algorithm of MEGA X (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Kumar et al., 2018</xref>), with bootstrap support calculated for 1000 replicates.</p><p>Sequences of ELMOD proteins from species across the plant kingdom were retrieved from the Phytozome v.12 database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz/portal.html">https://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz/portal.html</ext-link>) and the 1000 Plants (1KP) database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://db.cngb.org/onekp/">https://db.cngb.org/onekp/</ext-link>, last accessed in May 2020; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Wickett et al., 2014</xref>). MCR protein sequence was used as a query for an online BLASTP search of these databases with default parameters. The protein sequences with the E-value ≤1e-10, sequence identity ≥30%, and Bit-Score ≥ 60 were identified as ELMODs and further confirmed by a local BLASTP search using each of the other <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ELMODs as a query. In the cases when two or more proteins were potentially translated from the same gene, the one providing the best match with the query was selected. In total, 561 ELMOD protein sequences from 178 representative species belonging to eudicots (36 species/195 sequences), monocots (14/94), magnoliids (20/64), basal angiosperms (5/13), gymnosperms (17/62), ferns (17/44), lycophytes (20/29), bryophytes (37/47; including 18 sequences from 15 liverworts, 6 sequences from 5 hornworts, and 23 sequences from 17 mosses), and green algae (12/13) were retrieved and used for phylogenetic analysis.</p><p>Multiple sequence alignment was performed using MAFFT v7.017 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Katoh and Standley, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Katoh et al., 2002</xref>) with the L-INS-i algorithm and default parameters. Sites with greater than 20% gaps were trimmed by TrimAl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Capella-Gutiérrez et al., 2009</xref>) and manually inspected for overhangs. ModelFinder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kalyaanamoorthy et al., 2017</xref>; accessed through IQ-TREE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Nguyen et al., 2015</xref>]) was run to find the best-fit amino acid substitution model. The alignment in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref> was visualized with Espript3.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Gouet et al., 1999</xref>). Phylogenetic trees were constructed using IQ-TREE with the maximum likelihood (ML) method, SH-aLRT test, and ultrafast bootstrap with 1000 replicates. For the tree on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A</xref>, containing sequences from across the plant kingdom, 267 sequences were used, including all sequences retrieved from green algae, bryophytes, lycophytes, ferns, gymnosperms, and basal angiosperms, as well as 24 sequences from magnoliids, 19 sequences from three monocots, and 16 sequences from three eudicots. For the tree on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1</xref>, containing only angiosperm sequences, we used all 366 sequences retrieved for this group. Phylogenetic trees were visualized in iTOL v.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Letunic and Bork, 2021</xref>) and can be accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://itol.embl.de/shared/Zhou3117">http://itol.embl.de/shared/Zhou3117</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Expression pattern analysis of the <italic>Arabidopsis ELMOD</italic> genes</title><p>RNA-seq data for different tissues/developmental stages of six <italic>Arabidopsis ELMOD</italic> genes were obtained from the TRAVA database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://travadb.org/">http://travadb.org/</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Klepikova et al., 2016</xref>). The ‘Raw Norm’ option was chosen for read counts, and default settings were used for all other options. The retrieved RNA-seq data were presented as a bubble heatmap using TBtools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Chen et al., 2020</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Quantification and statistical analysis</title><p>Quantification of aperture numbers and YFP signal was done with NIS Elements v.4.20 software (Nikon). For each line, the aperture number of 160 pollen grains from at least three different plants was counted and the mean YFP fluorescence of at least 15 tetrads from the same plants was measured. Graphs were generated using Microsoft Excel or Origin version 2018 software. Binary comparisons were performed using a two-tailed Student’s t-test in Microsoft Excel; results with the p values below 0.05 were judged significantly different. The p values are represented as (***p&lt;0.001), (**p&lt;0.01), *p&lt;0.05. All error bars represent standard deviation (SD). For all boxplots, the box defines the first and third quartile, the central line depicts the median, and the small square in the box represents the mean value. Whiskers extend to minimum and maximum values. Outliers are indicated as ∗. Different shapes show individual samples. Details of statistical analysis, number of quantified entities (n), and measures of dispersion can be found in the corresponding figure legends.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf2"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Visualization, Writing – original draft, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Formal analysis, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Investigation, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Formal analysis, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Supervision, Visualization, Writing – original draft, Writing – review and editing</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Primers, molecular markers, and mutants/transgenic lines used in this study.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-71061-supp1-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-71061-transrepform1-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files. Source data files have been provided for Figure 1I; Figure 3E; Figures 7C, D and F; Figure 8 and Figure 8-figure supplement 1; Figure 9E and Figure 9-figure supplement 2E; Figure 10 and Figure10-figure supplement 1C.</p></sec><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Funding for this project was provided by the US National Science Foundation (MCB-1817835, awarded to AAD). We also acknowledge the support of the OSU Mayers Undergraduate Summer Research Scholarship to PA, the NSF-REU supplement funding to PA and AH, and the iCAPS internship from the OSU Center for Applied Sciences to AH.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>1001 Genomes Consortium</collab></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>1,135 genomes reveal the global pattern of polymorphism in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>166</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.05.063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27293186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowzard</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>ELMOD2 is an arl2 gtpase-activating protein that also acts on ARFS</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>282</volume><fpage>17568</fpage><lpage>17580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M701347200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capella-Gutiérrez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Silla-Martínez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldón</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Trimal: A tool for automated alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analyses</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>1972</fpage><lpage>1973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Tbtools: An integrative toolkit developed for interactive analyses of big biological data</article-title><source>Molecular Plant</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1194</fpage><lpage>1202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2020.06.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32585190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Floral dip: A simplified method for agrobacterium-mediated transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00343.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delgadillo</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zouhar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanmartín</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>LTF</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussey</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez-Serrano</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>MTV proteins unveil er- and microtubule-associated compartments in the plant vacuolar trafficking pathway</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>117</volume><fpage>9884</fpage><lpage>9895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1919820117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32321832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>S-I</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbanczyk-Wochniak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Huhman</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Preuss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumner</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>LAP5 and LAP6 encode anther-specific proteins with similarity to chalcone synthase essential for pollen exine development in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>153</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.157446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20442277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Geanconteri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kooyers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Coerper</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbanczyk-Wochniak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bench</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumner</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Preuss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>A large-scale genetic screen in arabidopsis to identify genes involved in pollen exine production</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>157</volume><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.179523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21849515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coerper</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>The novel plant protein inaperturate pollen1 marks distinct cellular domains and controls formation of apertures in the arabidopsis pollen exine</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>4452</fpage><lpage>4464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.101220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23136373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Pollen aperture factor INP1 acts late in aperture formation by excluding specific membrane domains from exine deposition</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>176</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.00720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28899962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>d’Erfurth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolivet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Froger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Catrice</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Novatchkova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Turning meiosis into mitosis</article-title><source>PLOS Biology</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e1000124</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19513101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>East</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowzard</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dacks</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>ELMO domains, evolutionary and functional characterization of a novel gtpase-activating protein (GAP) domain for ARF protein family gtpases</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>287</volume><fpage>39538</fpage><lpage>39553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.417477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23014990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feiguelman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yalovsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>ROP gtpases structure-function and signaling pathways</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>176</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.01415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29150557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1889">1889</year><source>Beiträge Zur Vergleichenden Morphologie Der Pollen-Körner</source><publisher-name>J. U. Kern’s Verlag</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furness</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudall</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Pollen aperture evolution--a crucial factor for eudicot success?</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2004.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15003239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>García-Nafría</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Greger</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>IVA cloning: A single-tube universal cloning system exploiting bacterial in vivo assembly</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep27459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27264908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gebbie</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Burn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hocart</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Genes encoding adp-ribosylation factors in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> L. Heyn.; Genome analysis and antisense suppression</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eri099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15723828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gouet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Courcelle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Métoz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>ESPRIPT: Analysis of multiple sequence alignments in postscript</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/15.4.305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10320398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoefle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hückelhoven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A barley engulfment and motility domain containing protein modulates RHO gtpase activating protein hvmagap1 function in the barley powdery mildew interaction</article-title><source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-013-0145-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24142383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>L-J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>A platform of high-density indel/caps markers for map-based cloning in arabidopsis</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>880</fpage><lpage>888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04277.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20561258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>East</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Characterization of recombinant ELMOD (cell engulfment and motility domain) proteins as gtpase-activating proteins (gaps) for ARF family gtpases</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>289</volume><fpage>11111</fpage><lpage>11121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.548529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24616099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalyaanamoorthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TKF</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jermiin</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Modelfinder: Fast model selection for accurate phylogenetic estimates</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28481363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Misawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>MAFFT: A novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast fourier transform</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>3059</fpage><lpage>3066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkf436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12136088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>MAFFT Multiple Sequence Alignment Software Version 7: Improvements in Performance and Usability</article-title><source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>772</fpage><lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klepikova</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasianov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerasimov</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Logacheva</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Penin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>A high resolution map of the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> developmental transcriptome based on RNA-seq profiling</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>1058</fpage><lpage>1070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27549386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knyaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>MEGA X: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms</article-title><source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>1547</fpage><lpage>1549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msy096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29722887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zourelidou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmeister</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwechheimer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Arabidopsis Protein Kinase D6PKL3 Is Involved in the Formation of Distinct Plasma Membrane Aperture Domains on the Pollen Surface</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>2038</fpage><lpage>2056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.18.00442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30150313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moberg</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Amom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Amstutz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandna</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Helton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrianova</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhulin</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>A species-specific functional module controls formation of pollen apertures</article-title><source>Nature Plants</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>966</fpage><lpage>978</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41477-021-00951-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34183783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letunic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><source>Interactive Tree of Life (ITOL) v5: An Online Tool for Phylogenetic Tree Display and Annotation</source><publisher-name>Nucleic Acids Research</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Menni Schuler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Suárez Santiago</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Inp1 involvement in pollen aperture formation is evolutionarily conserved and may require species-specific partners</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>69</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erx407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29190388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukowitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillmor</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Positional cloning in arabidopsis. Why it feels good to have a genome initiative working for you</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>123</volume><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.123.3.795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10889228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matamoro-Vidal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Furness</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouyon</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Evolutionary stasis in pollen morphogenesis due to natural selection</article-title><source>The New Phytologist</source><volume>209</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26248868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McElver</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rumbaugh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>The titan5 gene of arabidopsis encodes a protein related to the ADP ribosylation factor family of GTP binding proteins</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1379</fpage><lpage>1392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.12.8.1379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10948257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>IQ-TREE: A fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies</article-title><source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25371430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plourde</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Amom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawes</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Changes in morphogen kinetics and pollen grain size are potential mechanisms of aberrant pollen aperture patterning in previously observed and novel mutants of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>PLOS Computational Biology</source><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e1006800</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30817762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>SWL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Haploid plants produced by centromere-mediated genome elimination</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>464</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20336146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>A ploidy-sensitive mechanism regulates aperture formation on the arabidopsis pollen surface and guides localization of the aperture factor inp1</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e1006060</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27177036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ressayre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Godelle</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Raquin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouyon</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Aperture pattern ontogeny in angiosperms</article-title><source>The Journal of Experimental Zoology</source><volume>294</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jez.10150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12210113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheffzek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadian</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittinghofer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Gtpase-activating proteins: Helping hands to complement an active site</article-title><source>Trends in Biochemical Sciences</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0968-0004(98)01224-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9697416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jürgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Specificity of plant membrane trafficking – arfs, regulators and coat proteins</article-title><source>Seminars in Cell &amp; Developmental Biology</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2017.10.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kientz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stierhof</surname><given-names>Y-D</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fäßler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knöll</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Franz-Wachtel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Macek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Skriver</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimpl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jürgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>A single class of ARF gtpase activated by several pathway-specific arf-gefs regulates essential membrane traffic in arabidopsis</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1007795</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1007795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30439956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spielman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Preuss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Tetraspore is required for male meiotic cytokinesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Development</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>2645</fpage><lpage>2657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.124.13.2645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9217006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sztul</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherfils</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dacks</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambright</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>F-JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Randazzo</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Santy</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schürmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelmi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yohe</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>ARF gtpases and their Gefs and gaps: Concepts and challenges</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>1249</fpage><lpage>1271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E18-12-0820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31084567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turn</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>East</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Prekeris</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>The ARF gap elmod2 acts with different gtpases to regulate centrosomal microtubule nucleation and cytokinesis</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>2070</fpage><lpage>2091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E20-01-0012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32614697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernoud</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Analysis of the small gtpase gene superfamily of arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>131</volume><fpage>1191</fpage><lpage>1208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.013052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12644670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1974">1974</year><article-title>Aperture evolution in the pollen of primitive angiosperms</article-title><source>American Journal of Botany</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>1112</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.1537-2197.1974.tb12329.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackmore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Pollen morphology in relation to floral types and pollination syndromes in Pedicularis (Orobanchaceae</article-title><source>Plant Systematics and Evolution = Entwicklungsgeschichte Und Systematik Der Pflanzen</source><volume>277</volume><elocation-id>153</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Egg cell-specific promoter-controlled CRISPR/CAS9 efficiently generates homozygous mutants for multiple target genes in arabidopsis in a single generation</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>144</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0715-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26193878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshinari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara-Nishimura</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitani-Ueno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Polar localization of the NIP5;1 boric acid channel is maintained by endocytosis and facilitates boron transport in Arabidopsis roots</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>824</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.16.00825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28341806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickett</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirarab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Warnow</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Matasci</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayyampalayam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Burleigh</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gitzendanner</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruhfel</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wafula</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Der</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Melkonian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothfels</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pokorny</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>DeGironimo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Surek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Villarreal</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Roure</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>dePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Deyholos</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Baucom</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutchan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>GKS</given-names></name><name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Phylotranscriptomic analysis of the origin and early diversification of land plants</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>E4859</fpage><lpage>E468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1323926111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25355905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wodehouse</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1935">1935</year><source>Pollen Grains: Their Structure, Identification and Significance in Science and Medicine</source><publisher-loc>New York and London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Genome-wide prediction of highly specific guide RNA spacers for crispr-cas9-mediated genome editing in model plants and major crops</article-title><source>Molecular Plant</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssu009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24482433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A CRISPR/CAS9 toolkit for multiplex genome editing in plants</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biology</source><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>327</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-014-0327-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25432517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Dissection of arabidopsis ADP-RIBOSYLATION FACTOR 1 function in epidermal cell polarity</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.104.028449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavagi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Spatial control of plasma membrane domains: ROP gtpase-based symmetry breaking</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2012.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23177207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Rice pollen aperture formation is regulated by the interplay between osinp1 and osdaf1</article-title><source>Nature Plants</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41477-020-0630-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32284546</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobritsa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Formation of aperture sites on the pollen surface as a model for development of distinct cellular domains</article-title><source>Plant Science</source><volume>288</volume><elocation-id>110222</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2019.110222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31521218</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.71061.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>Sheila</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of California, Berkeley</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>Sheila</given-names></name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>University of California, Berkeley</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>Sharon A</given-names></name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>Purdue University</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text id="box1"><p>Our editorial process produces two outputs: i) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2021.06.15.448545">public reviews</ext-link> designed to be posted alongside <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.06.15.448545v1">the preprint</ext-link> for the benefit of readers; ii) feedback on the manuscript for the authors, including requests for revisions, shown below. We also include an acceptance summary that explains what the editors found interesting or important about the work.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Acceptance summary:</bold></p><p>The authors identify a role in Arabidopsis pollen aperture formation for members of the ELMOD family of proteins. They use genetics, transgenic constructs, and site-directed mutagenesis to pinpoint important residues for protein function in this process. The authors thoroughly addressed the reviewer comments.</p><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Members of the ELMOD protein family specify formation of distinct aperture domains on the Arabidopsis pollen surface&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by 3 peer reviewers, including Sheila McCormick as the Reviewing Editor and Reviewer #1, and the evaluation has been overseen by Jürgen Kleine-Vehn as the Senior Editor. The following individual involved in review of your submission has agreed to reveal their identity: Sharon A Kessler (Reviewer #2).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed their reviews with one another, and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) Address the issue of hypomorphic T-DNA alleles in the Discussion.</p><p>2) If possible, provide a more thorough quantification of round vs furrow in the complementation experiments.</p><p>3) Consider including information about the fertility of the mutants, to enrich the biological context.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>Lines 164-167. Odd that the T-DNA mutations were hypomorphic – this needs to be addressed in the discussion.</p><p>Line 194 – the more ancient of what? ELMOD and larger ELMO? What is the D supposed to designate, the word domain? Please clarify.</p><p>Line 396, a bit confusing, consider re-ordering this section. At first it is not clear why is it notable that no other plants have an Asp at the Gly129 site. Having an Asp is a mutant, right? Later you say that plants have either Cys, Gly or Ala.</p><p>Line 492-3, I would tone down this statement.</p><p>The discussion is too speculative about things that are not addressed in this paper.</p><p>And why the sentences about Pedicularis? I would delete, i.e. lines 562-563 are complete speculation.</p><p>Lines 590-592 don't add much; same comment for lines 607-609, same for lines 610-615.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>The manuscript is clearly written and a pleasure to read. I just have few suggestions for improving the paper.</p><p>1. The ploidy and microspore arrangement data in Figures 1 and 1-S2 are interesting, but they are not linked to any of the other data in the paper and not mentioned at all in the discussion. This data could be removed to streamline the paper.</p><p>2. The ELMOD_A CRISPR description in the Results section is difficult to follow. The description implied that the lines used for the mcr complementation studies had undefined CRISPR-induced mutations. These lines were more clearly described in the methods-some of this description should be moved to the results and the exact effect of the CRISPR allele in Figure 4 needs to be more clearly defined. The single A insertion is near an exon/intron junction-does it affect splicing? Is it actually a knock-out allele, or does it retain some function? This is important for the claim that single elmod_a mutants don't have a phenotype-if this is just a knockdown allele then a true knockout could have a more severe phenotype, even though both would be complemented with a wild-type transgene.</p><p>3. It is not clear why &quot;furrowed and round&quot; apertures were lumped together in one category in Figure 10 D-F. Dividing them into 2 categories would allow the authors to compare the complementation of aperture shape with the ELMOD_E variants (are they mostly round or mostly furrowed, or is it even?)</p><p>4. Lines 395-398: I don't think it is relevant to look specifically for a GLY129ASP change in the other ELMODs. This specific mutation came from an EMS mutagenesis-why would it be expected to occur naturally?</p><p>5. Lines 417-431: The conclusion that ELMOD_D is a pseudogene may be premature since it is expressed. The authors should add the alternative explanation that this gene may have acquired a new function.</p><p>6. As I looked at the beautiful pollen aperture phenotypes throughout the manuscript, I wondered if the aperture area was conserved in the different mutant/ ectopic expression backgrounds. Having 1 aperture that extends around the circumference of the pollen grain is obviously not the same as having 1 small, round aperture, but is it similar in area to 3 furrows? The ELMOD_E lines with round apertures also tended to have more apertures-is the total aperture area regulated by some other mechanism? This is just a comment, not a suggestion that needs to be addressed with more experiments for this publication.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #3 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>1. Fig. 1F,G, suggest using a different colored arrowheads, e.g. red on a greenish yellow background and signal, not yellow as they currently are.</p><p>2. Up till point 2 in the previous section, and L152, what I missed is the pollen tube emergence and fertility phenotype of these and previously characterized mutants. Later on, L239 referred to a double mcr elmod_a double mutant; again a note on fertility would be good. It would enrich the biological context to have related these in the Introduction for the inp, d6pk3, mcr-1 mutants, and mention it for the newly created mutants (even when without impact).</p><p>3. L163-end, can you provide insight on why the T-DNA insertions are hypomorphic, whereas mcr1 is totally penetrant (0% normal), what about mcr2-4?</p><p>4. Fig. 4; it would be nice to have indicated the percentage of defective pollen, especially in the homozygous heterozygous combinations.</p><p>5. I find that the detail descriptions of elmod e,d,f in Fig. 9, while the genetic and morphological results were hard-earned, they are distracting. The authors can very easily summarize them in one or two sentences and let the results be in Supplement, and move on to focus on the ELMOD E studies. Also L475-477 is cumbersome; is it the same as in the original line 7-2/mcr?</p><p>6. Fig. 6, N121 C129 are not shown in blue as indicated in the legend.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.71061.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) Address the issue of hypomorphic T-DNA alleles in the Discussion.</p></disp-quote><p>All three T-DNA alleles have their insertion sites inside introns, suggesting these alleles might be knockdown mutants that still retain some MCR activity. We have now added this statement to the Results. We do not think that this point requires to be further addressed in the Discussion, since T-DNA insertions in introns that do not cause a complete gene inactivation are not too unusual (please see our response to Reviewer 1 for references and additional discussion on this point).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) If possible, provide a more thorough quantification of round vs furrow in the complementation experiments.</p></disp-quote><p>We have now quantified these results based on the images of representative pollen grains and show the data in Figure 10—figure supplement 1C.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) Consider including information about the fertility of the mutants, to enrich the biological context.</p></disp-quote><p>All the mutants have normal fertility, like all the other Arabidopsis aperture mutants we have been working with, including mutants that produce no apertures. We have now included this information in the Results (lines 88-91).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>Lines 164-167. Odd that the T-DNA mutations were hypomorphic – this needs to be addressed in the discussion.</p></disp-quote><p>We do not think that the observation that T-DNA insertion alleles are hypomorphic is too surprising. All three T-DNA insertion mutants have their insertions sites within introns. Furthermore, in <italic>mcr-7</italic>, which produces the largest proportion of pollen with wild-type apertures (~20%), the T-DNA insertion lies before the beginning of the coding sequence. It is thus probable that these mutations create knockdown, rather than knockout, alleles, which does happen with intron-based T-DNA insertions. See, for example, the following references:</p><p>Wang, Y. H. (2008) How effective is T-DNA insertional mutagenesis in Arabidopsis. J Bioch Tech 1, 11-20</p><p>Sato, H., Shibata, F., Murata, M. (2005) Characterization of a Mis12 homologue in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. Chromosome Res 13, 827–834. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10577-005-1016-3">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10577-005-1016-3</ext-link></p><p>Chuang, H., Zhang, W., Gray, W. M. (2004) Arabidopsis <italic>ETA2</italic>, an apparent ortholog of the human cullin-interacting protein CAND1, is required for auxin responses mediated by the SCF<sup>TIR1</sup> ubiquitin ligase. Plant Cell 16, 1883–1897. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1105/tpc.021923">https://doi.org/10.1105/tpc.021923</ext-link></p><p>Verelst, W., Saedler, H., Münster, T. (2007) MIKC* MADS-protein complexes bind motifs enriched in the proximal region of late pollen-specific Arabidopsis promoters, Plant Physiol 143, 447–460, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.106.089805">https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.106.089805</ext-link></p><p>Jones, M.A., Raymond, M.J. and Smirnoff, N. (2006), Analysis of the root-hair morphogenesis transcriptome reveals the molecular identity of six genes with roles in root-hair development in Arabidopsis. Plant J 45, 83-100. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02609.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02609.x</ext-link></p><p>Imai, A., Matsuyama, T., Hanzawa, Y., Akiyama, T., Tamaoki, M., Saji, H., Shirano, Y., Kato, T., Hayashi, H., Shibata, D., Tabata, S., Komeda, Y., Takahashi, T. (2004) Spermidine synthase genes are essential for survival of Arabidopsis, Plant Physiol 135, 1565–1573, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.104.041699">https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.104.041699</ext-link></p><p>Collados Rodríguez, M., Wawrzyńska, A., Sirko, A. (2014) Intronic T-DNA insertion in Arabidopsis <italic>NBR1</italic> conditionally affects wild-type transcript level, Plant Signal Behav, 9:12, e975659,DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.4161/15592324.2014.975659">10.4161/15592324.2014.975659</ext-link></p><p>Sandhu, K. S., Koirala, P. S., Neff, M. M. (2013) The <italic>ben1-1</italic> brassinosteroid-catabolism mutation is unstable due to epigenetic modifications of the intronic T-DNA insertion, G3, 3, 1587–1595, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1534/g3.113.006353">https://doi.org/10.1534/g3.113.006353</ext-link></p><p>The main purpose for our use of these alleles was to find out if they would also have the <italic>mcr</italic> aperture phenotype, which they all did. This served as one more piece of evidence that we had identified the correct gene. We have now added a statement about the intronic location of T-DNA insertions to the Results (line 165), but we do not think this point requires a further discussion.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Line 194 – the more ancient of what? ELMOD and larger ELMO? What is the D supposed to designate, the word domain? Please clarify.</p></disp-quote><p>This nomenclature is already established based on the animal protein studies, and for this reason we would like to adhere to it, but it is certainly confusing. The D in ELMOD represents ‘domain’, and the family and its members are typically referred to simply as ‘ELMOD’ to differentiate them from members of the ELMO family (which also have the ELMO domain). Compared to the ELMO family, the ELMOD family is believed to be the more ancient. We have now clarified this point (lines 195-197).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Line 396, a bit confusing, consider re-ordering this section. At first it is not clear why is it notable that no other plants have an Asp at the Gly129 site. Having an Asp is a mutant, right? Later you say that plants have either Cys, Gly or Ala.</p></disp-quote><p>In total, we retrieved 561 ELMOD sequences from across the plant kingdom. Among them, only one sequence, which happened to be AtELMOD_D from Arabidopsis, a possible pseudogene, was found to have an Asp at the position 129. The other 560 ELMOD sequences have either Cys, Gly or Ala at the position 129. This analysis suggested that Asp at this position is not tolerated by natural selection and might be detrimental for all plant ELMOD proteins. In the MCR protein of the <italic>mcr-2</italic> mutant, Gly129 is replaced with Asp, which appears to make this protein non-functional. Later in the manuscript we explain that in angiosperms we found a very strong correlation between an amino acid occupying position 129 and a clade with which each protein sequence clustered, suggesting that this position could be important for protein function as well as for functional diversification among the ELMOD clades.</p><p>We have now modified this paragraph (lines 395-400), transferring the emphasis from Gly129 to the appearance of Asp, which represents a highly unusual amino acid for this position. The discussion of the amino acids that are normally found at this position is left until the next paragraph.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Line 492-3, I would tone down this statement.</p></disp-quote><p>We have replaced this statement with the following: “Together, these data support the idea that high level of MCR can counteract the neomorphic activity of ELMOD_E and suggest that MCR and ELMOD_E may compete for the same interactors”.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>The discussion is too speculative about things that are not addressed in this paper.</p></disp-quote><p>We have modified portions of the Discussion, but we also use it as a place for putting our findings into a larger context and presenting some ideas for future studies.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>And why the sentences about Pedicularis? I would delete, i.e. lines 562-563 are complete speculation.</p></disp-quote><p>We have modified these sentences to make it clearer that we are speculating here, but we still would like to keep them. How the diversity of aperture patterns is generated is one of the most fascinating questions in this field. Mentioning the aperture patterns in Pedicularis, some of which resemble the <italic>mcr</italic> phenotype in Arabidopsis, allows us to connect the mutant phenotype we discovered in a laboratory model organism to a phenomenon that occurs in nature and highlights variations of aperture patterns within a single genus. By suggesting that variations in aperture patterns in Pedicularis could be caused by variations in ELMOD proteins or their regulators or interactors, we formulate a potentially testable hypothesis.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Lines 590-592 don't add much; same comment for lines 607-609, same for lines 610-615.</p></disp-quote><p>We believe that the sentences in lines 590-592 (lines 588-590 in the revision) make an important point. The fact that in most analyzed angiosperm species the A/B clade had more than one member suggest that there could be a selective pressure to maintain redundancy of that protein activity, hinting at the importance of the process(es) in which these proteins are involved.</p><p>We removed lines 607-609, but we kept the lines 610-615 (lines 605-611 in the revision) since we think it is important to mention the possibility that plant ELMODs might be doing something different from what they are doing in animals.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>The manuscript is clearly written and a pleasure to read. I just have few suggestions for improving the paper.</p><p>1. The ploidy and microspore arrangement data in Figures 1 and 1-S2 are interesting, but they are not linked to any of the other data in the paper and not mentioned at all in the discussion. This data could be removed to streamline the paper.</p></disp-quote><p>We would prefer to keep this part because it provides important observations related to the mechanism of aperture pattern formation. It shows that the reducing effect of the <italic>mcr</italic> mutation on aperture number is quite general, since it is manifested across different levels of ploidy and post-meiotic microspore arrangement, which we previously showed to be important factors in aperture patterning. How higher ploidy causes an increase in aperture number is still unclear, but an increased expression of aperture factors due to higher gene dosage is one possibility. This would be consistent with the data we present later in the manuscript showing that apertures are sensitive to the levels of MCR and ELMOD_A expression. To make this part less ‘stand-alone’, we now refer to this result in the Discussion (lines 556-559).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2. The ELMOD_A CRISPR description in the Results section is difficult to follow. The description implied that the lines used for the mcr complementation studies had undefined CRISPR-induced mutations. These lines were more clearly described in the methods-some of this description should be moved to the results and the exact effect of the CRISPR allele in Figure 4 needs to be more clearly defined. The single A insertion is near an exon/intron junction-does it affect splicing? Is it actually a knock-out allele, or does it retain some function? This is important for the claim that single elmod_a mutants don't have a phenotype-if this is just a knockdown allele then a true knockout could have a more severe phenotype, even though both would be complemented with a wild-type transgene.</p></disp-quote><p>The CRISPR mutant of ELMOD_A is expected to be a knockout. The mutation is an insertion of a single A nucleotide early in the coding sequence (between codons 64 and 65), just before the beginning of the sequence encoding the ELMO domain and three nucleotides before the beginning of the second intron (the inserted nucleotide is at the position -4 relative to the intron). This insertion creates a frame shift that would lead to a greatly truncated protein independently of whether it affects the splicing of that intron. With this insertion, the translation machinery will encounter premature stop codons in all possible scenarios: (a) if splicing occurs normally; (b) if the second intron is not spliced; (c) if the next GT site is used as a donor site for splicing. (Still, the splicing of this intron is unlikely to be affected in this case as only the last two positions (-1 and -2) at the end an exon are typically important for pairing with snRNAs, while other exonic splicing signals lie much further interior within exons (Wilkinson et al. (2020) Ann. Rev. Biochem. 89:359-388; Fu et al. (2004) Cell 119: 736-738)).</p><p>We should also mention that in addition to this allele, which was used for crossing with the <italic>mcr</italic> mutation and all the subsequent work, we generated a second CRISPR allele of ELMOD_A which has a single nucleotide deletion (DT) in the last nucleotide of the codon 64. This mutation causes a different frame shift and is also expected to result in very early termination of translation in any splicing scenario, yet the mutant also produced pollen with normal apertures.</p><p>We have modified the part in the Results describing the <italic>elmod_a</italic> CRISPR alleles to clarify the nature of these mutations (lines 212-217). We have also changed the illustration of the <italic>elmod_a</italic> CRISPR allele on Figure 4A to indicate more clearly that a frame shift occurred. (We have similarly changed the illustrations for <italic>elmod_e</italic> CRISPR alleles on Figure 9—figure supplement 1A.)</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3. It is not clear why &quot;furrowed and round&quot; apertures were lumped together in one category in Figure 10 D-F. Dividing them into 2 categories would allow the authors to compare the complementation of aperture shape with the ELMOD_E variants (are they mostly round or mostly furrowed, or is it even?)</p></disp-quote><p>We have now quantified these results based on images of representative pollen grains from across the multiple T<sub>1</sub> lines expressing the same construct and show the data in Figure 10—figure supplement 1C. In cases when three apertures form, they tend to be furrow-like, whereas when ≥4 apertures form, they tend to be round.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4. Lines 395-398: I don't think it is relevant to look specifically for a GLY129ASP change in the other ELMODs. This specific mutation came from an EMS mutagenesis-why would it be expected to occur naturally?</p></disp-quote><p>To better understand how significant a mutation is for protein function, it would certainly make sense to check whether an amino acid affected by that mutation normally shows strong conservation, whether the change is substantial from a biochemical perspective, and whether a similar substitution might exist in related proteins in nature. To do this, it helps to look at the amino acids occupying the same position in orthologs and paralogs of the studied protein.</p><p>In the case of the Gly129Asp mutation in <italic>mcr-2</italic>, we found that the appearance of Asp represents a very unusual change from the evolutionary perspective: only one sequence out of the 561 analyzed contained an Asp at that position, and as explained below, we suspect that sequence actually corresponds to a pseudogene. The position 129 is quite conserved, with only three amino acids normally found at that position across the plant ELMOD family and nearly all A/B proteins having a Gly there. Finally, from the biochemical perspective, an appearance of the negatively charged Asp instead of Gly (or Ala and Cys that are also found at this position) represents a substantial change.</p><p>We have modified this paragraph (lines 395-400) to emphasize how unusual the appearance of Asp at this position is (with the implication that such change could be sufficient to inactivate the protein). The discussion of the amino acids normally occupying this position is now left until the next paragraph.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5. Lines 417-431: The conclusion that ELMOD_D is a pseudogene may be premature since it is expressed. The authors should add the alternative explanation that this gene may have acquired a new function.</p></disp-quote><p>Although it is typically difficult to prove that a sequence behaves as a pseudogene in the absence of early stop codons or other mutations that would clearly disrupt its function (frame shifts, large insertions or deletions), we think that the combined evidence for ELMOD_D being a likely pseudogene is quite strong:</p><p>1) The mRNA expression levels of <italic>ELMOD_D</italic> are extremely low (no more than 2 normalized read counts in any tissue listed in the RNA-seq database TRAVA <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://travadb.org/browse/DeSeq/At3g43400/RawNorm/AvNorm/Color=RCount/">http://travadb.org/browse/DeSeq/At3g43400/RawNorm/AvNorm/Color=RCount/</ext-link>) (Figure 3E). (Since the wording describing the nearly complete lack of ELMOD_D expression might have been a bit confusing in the previous version of the manuscript, we have slightly modified this part (line 431)).</p><p>2) The YFP-tagged ELMOD_D protein, driven by the <italic>MCR</italic> regulatory elements, could not be detected (Figure 9—figure supplement 2H-H’).</p><p>3) The predicted protein is much shorter than the other members of the ELMOD family, with multiple regions missing, including some conserved portions of the ELMO domain (Figure 3—figure supplement 1).</p><p>4) As explained above, ELMOD_D is the only ELMOD protein out of the 561 examined which contains an Asp at position 129. A mutation that creates Asp at the same position in the MCR protein leads to protein inactivation. In addition, arginines found in ELMOD_D at the two positions near the GAP region (corresponding to Gly119 and Leu138 in MCR) also represent highly unusual and biochemically significant changes that are not found in any other ELMOD protein.</p><p>5) Other plants, including close relatives of Arabidopsis, lack orthologs of ELMOD_D.</p><p>Although each of these reasons, on their own, would not be sufficient to suggest that ELMOD_D is a pseudogene, we think that together they provide a good argument in favor of this possibility, which we still describe as a hypothesis, not a fact.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>6. As I looked at the beautiful pollen aperture phenotypes throughout the manuscript, I wondered if the aperture area was conserved in the different mutant/ ectopic expression backgrounds. Having 1 aperture that extends around the circumference of the pollen grain is obviously not the same as having 1 small, round aperture, but is it similar in area to 3 furrows? The ELMOD_E lines with round apertures also tended to have more apertures-is the total aperture area regulated by some other mechanism? This is just a comment, not a suggestion that needs to be addressed with more experiments for this publication.</p></disp-quote><p>It’s an interesting idea! In general, the more furrow-shaped apertures develop on the pollen surface, the shorter they tend to be, so this hypothesis would make sense. Such study, however, is likely to be tricky, since in order to see apertures on the entire pollen surface, the normally spherical pollen grains have to be flattened. As a result, the apparent shape and size of apertures might be somewhat distorted, which may affect measurements and conclusions.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #3 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>1. Fig. 1F,G, suggest using a different colored arrowheads, e.g. red on a greenish yellow background and signal, not yellow as they currently are.</p></disp-quote><p>We have changed the color of arrows to red in Fig. 1F, 1G (and in the similar Fig. 2A).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2. Up till point 2 in the previous section, and L152, what I missed is the pollen tube emergence and fertility phenotype of these and previously characterized mutants. Later on, L239 referred to a double mcr elmod_a double mutant; again a note on fertility would be good. It would enrich the biological context to have related these in the Introduction for the inp, d6pk3, mcr-1 mutants, and mention it for the newly created mutants (even when without impact).</p></disp-quote><p>All the described mutants have no noticeable fertility defects and produce normal seed sets. The normal fertility in <italic>mcr</italic> and other mutants studied here is consistent with the normal fertility of the previously characterized pollen aperture mutants in Arabidopsis, including the ones that completely lack apertures (<italic>inp1</italic>, <italic>inp2</italic>) (Dobritsa et al. (2011) Plant Phys. 157:947-970; Dobritsa and Coerper (2012) Plant Cell 24:4452-4464; Lee et al. (2021) Nat. Plants 7:966-978). Additionally, it has been previously shown that pollen tubes in Arabidopsis and many other species of Brassicaceae have an ability to emerge through exine and not through the aperture sites (Edlund et al. (2016) Am. J. Bot. 103:1006-1019). For these reasons, observing normal fertility in the <italic>mcr</italic> mutants was not surprising. Thus, we have not specifically looked at the pollen tube emergence in the <italic>mcr</italic> mutants, but their ability to set a large number of seeds indicates that their pollen tubes do not have problems with emerging.</p><p>We have now added a statement mentioning that, like other aperture mutants in Arabidopsis, <italic>mcr</italic> mutants exhibit no noticeable fertility problems (lines 88-91). For the reasons mentioned above, we do not think that we need to indicate this for all the other <italic>mcr</italic> combinations created in this study.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3. L163-end, can you provide insight on why the T-DNA insertions are hypomorphic, whereas mcr1 is totally penetrant (0% normal), what about mcr2-4?</p></disp-quote><p>As described in our response to the question from the Reviewer 1, we think that because the insertion sites of all the T-DNA mutants are in introns, these mutants represent knockdown alleles that retain partial activity. Pollen in <italic>mcr-</italic>2 through <italic>mcr</italic> -4 only has <italic>mcr</italic> aperture phenotype.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4. Fig. 4; it would be nice to have indicated the percentage of defective pollen, especially in the homozygous heterozygous combinations.</p></disp-quote><p>All the mutants in Fig. 4 (those not carrying <italic>MCR</italic> or <italic>ELMOD_A</italic> transgenes) produced viable pollen grains with the indicated aperture phenotypes. In each case, the phenotypes were fully penetrant. The mutants expressing transgenes showed some variations in aperture number, with some transgenic lines producing more than the expected number of apertures, but we describe this later in the manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5. I find that the detail descriptions of elmod e,d,f in Fig. 9, while the genetic and morphological results were hard-earned, they are distracting. The authors can very easily summarize them in one or two sentences and let the results be in Supplement, and move on to focus on the ELMOD E studies. Also L475-477 is cumbersome; is it the same as in the original line 7-2/mcr?</p></disp-quote><p>We have somewhat shortened the two paragraphs dealing with the <italic>C</italic>, <italic>D</italic>, and <italic>F</italic> genes, and rearranged the panels in Figure 9 – Supplemental Fig. 2 to follow the narrative. We have simplified the sentence in L475-477 and combined it with a previous sentence. The new sentence (lines 467-470) reads: “Yet, in the F<sub>1</sub> progeny of the cross with the high expressor 7-2, furrow aperture morphology was restored (Figure 9K–9K’), although these plants produced less pollen with a high number of furrows (&gt;4) compared to the original 7-2 plants (Figure 9L).”</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>6. Fig. 6, N121 C129 are not shown in blue as indicated in the legend.</p></disp-quote><p>These two amino acids of AtELMOD_E were in fact indicated in blue in the previous version, but to make them more noticeable, we have now indicated them by red squares.</p></body></sub-article></article>