<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">44702</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CNS myelination and remyelination depend on fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-128327"><name><surname>Dimas</surname><given-names>Penelope</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">†</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-100620"><name><surname>Montani</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8243-6734</contrib-id><email>laura.montani@biol.ethz.ch</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">†</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-89997"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>Jorge A</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0159-4133</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-128328"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-128329"><name><surname>Trötzmüller</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-137385"><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>Joanne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-128330"><name><surname>Semenkowich</surname><given-names>Clay F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-128331"><name><surname>Köfeler</surname><given-names>Harald C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-100622"><name><surname>Suter</surname><given-names>Ueli</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9211-5184</contrib-id><email>ueli.suter@biol.ethz.ch</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con9"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Institute of Molecular Health Sciences, Swiss Federal Institute of Technology, ETH Zürich</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Zürich</named-content></addr-line><country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Center for Medical Research</institution><institution>Medical University of Graz</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Graz</named-content></addr-line><country>Austria</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Division of Endocrinology, Metabolism and Lipid Research</institution><institution>Washington University Medical School</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">St. Louis</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Bronner</surname><given-names>Marianne E</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>California Institute of Technology</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bergles</surname><given-names>Dwight E</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="equal-contrib1"><label>†</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>07</day><month>05</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e44702</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-12-24"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2019-04-27"><day>27</day><month>04</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2019, Dimas et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Dimas et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-44702-v1.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.001</object-id><p>Oligodendrocytes (OLs) support neurons and signal transmission in the central nervous system (CNS) by enwrapping axons with myelin, a lipid-rich membrane structure. We addressed the significance of fatty acid (FA) synthesis in OLs by depleting FA synthase (FASN) from OL progenitor cells (OPCs) in transgenic mice. While we detected no effects in proliferation and differentiation along the postnatal OL lineage, we found that FASN is essential for accurate myelination, including myelin growth. Increasing dietary lipid intake could partially compensate for the FASN deficiency. Furthermore, FASN contributes to correct myelin lipid composition and stability of myelinated axons. Moreover, we depleted FASN specifically in adult OPCs to examine its relevance for remyelination. Applying lysolecithin-induced focal demyelinating spinal cord lesions, we found that FA synthesis is essential to sustain adult OPC-derived OLs and efficient remyelination. We conclude that FA synthesis in OLs plays key roles in CNS myelination and remyelination.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>myelination</kwd><kwd>oligodendrocytes</kwd><kwd>remyelination</kwd><kwd>fatty acid synthesis</kwd><kwd>high fat diet</kwd><kwd>myelin lipids</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Mouse</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001711</institution-id><institution>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds zur Förderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Suter</surname><given-names>Ueli</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001711</institution-id><institution>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds zur Förderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>PMPDP3 139610</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Montani</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Endogenous synthesis of fatty acids by oligodendrocytes is essential for development and repair in the central nervous system.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Under the control of a complex bidirectional signaling program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Herbert and Monk, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Klingseisen and Lyons, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nave and Werner, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Osso and Chan, 2017</xref>), oligodendrocytes (OLs) encase central nervous system (CNS) axons with myelin, a highly organized and compacted multi-membrane structure. Myelination allows rapid transmission of action potentials and preserves axonal integrity by multiple mechanisms, including metabolic support by OLs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Fünfschilling et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lee et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Simons et al., 2014</xref>). Thus, loss of myelin in diseases of diverse etiology, such as in multiple sclerosis, ultimately results in axonal degeneration and clinical deterioration of affected patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Franklin and Ffrench-Constant, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nave and Werner, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Saab and Nave, 2017</xref>). During postnatal development, OL progenitor cells (OPCs) undergo a tightly orchestrated differentiation program leading to mature OLs that contact axons and wrap them with myelin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nave and Werner, 2014</xref>). A significant population of OPCs remains resident in the adult CNS, designated adult OPCs (aOPCs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Dimou and Gallo, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Franklin and Ffrench-Constant, 2017</xref>). Upon a demyelinating injury, aOPCs are activated, migrate to the lesion site, proliferate, undergo differentiation, and mature into OLs that remyelinate axons. Hence, aOPCs-derived OLs substitute for pre-existing ones which are lost upon demyelination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Crawford et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Franklin and Ffrench-Constant, 2017</xref>). However, this program often fails in myelin-defective lesions leaving axons particularly vulnerable. While a number of exogenous and endogenous factors are known to restrict the regenerative potential of aOPCs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Franklin and Ffrench-Constant, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Miron, 2017</xref>), the roles of modulators of their metabolic state remain largely unknown.</p><p>Myelin is characterized by an exceptionally high lipid content (~80% of dry weight) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Chrast et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nave and Werner, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Schmitt et al., 2015</xref>). Fatty acids (FAs) are fundamental building blocks for both glycolipids and phospholipids, which comprise the largest proportion of myelin membrane lipids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Harayama and Riezman, 2018</xref>). FAs can be acquired from the pool present in the circulation due to dietary intake (essential and non-essential FAs), through horizontal flux from adjacent cells (essential and non-essential FAs), or are cell-endogenously synthesized (non-essential FAs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Camargo et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Currie et al., 2013</xref>). However, the relative contribution of uptake versus synthesis to the final pool of FAs in OLs at different stages of differentiation remains to be determined.</p><p>The mTORC1-SCAP signaling axis regulates a plethora of lipogenic pathways via cleavage of Sterol Regulatory Element-Binding Proteins (SREBPs). These transcription factors are major modulators of FA and cholesterol metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Laplante and Sabatini, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Porstmann et al., 2008</xref>), including in OLs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Camargo et al., 2017</xref>). Accordingly, depletion of mTOR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Wahl et al., 2014</xref>), the functionally required mTORC1 subunit Raptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bercury et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Lebrun-Julien et al., 2014</xref>) or SCAP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Camargo et al., 2017</xref>) in OLs causes reduced radial growth of myelin, mimicking the phenotype triggered by depletion of the SREBP-downstream target squalene synthase, an enzyme required for cholesterol synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Saher et al., 2005</xref>). Genetic depletion of Raptor and SCAP in OLs results also in reduced expression of FA synthase (FASN) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Camargo et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Lebrun-Julien et al., 2014</xref>) – the enzyme responsible for the synthesis of the 16-carbon palmitic acid that is used as substrate for subsequent synthesis of longer FAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Currie et al., 2013</xref>). However, the functional role of endogenous FA synthesis in OL differentiation and CNS myelination, and how diminished FASN expression impacts upon the observed mTORC1/SCAP-knockout phenotypes, is not clear.</p><p>We previously found that de novo FA synthesis is essential for correct onset of myelination by Schwann cells, the myelinating cells of the peripheral nervous system (PNS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Montani et al., 2018</xref>). In the present study, we have tested whether OLs rely also on endogenous FA synthesis for developmental myelination. Furthermore, we investigated whether remyelination after injury depends on FA synthesis by OLs. In development, we addressed this question by genetically depleting FASN in the OL lineage of transgenic mice. To analyze the role of endogenous FA synthesis in remyelination of adults, we deleted FASN specifically from aOPCs and their progeny, in conjunction with a focal demyelinating spinal cord lesion using the well-established lysolecithin gliotoxin-injection model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Blakemore and Franklin, 2008</xref>). Our data reveal that endogenous FA synthesis in OLs is required for correct CNS myelination in development and essential for efficient remyelination in adulthood.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Depletion of FASN in oligodendrocytes</title><p>OLs have the capacity to cover numerous axons with multiple membrane layers to form myelin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nave and Werner, 2014</xref>). Thus, we hypothesized that OLs may depend on endogenous FASN-driven FA synthesis for myelin production. Indeed, OLs transcribe FASN at high levels (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.stanford.edu/group/barres_lab/cgi-bin/igv_cgi_2.py?lname=Fasn">http://web.stanford.edu/group/barres_lab/cgi-bin/igv_cgi_2.py?lname=Fasn</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>). To test our hypothesis, we used mouse genetics to ablate FASN specifically in the OL lineage. Conditionally mutant <italic>Fasn</italic><sup>lox/lox</sup> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Chakravarthy et al., 2005</xref>) were crossed with mice expressing Cre recombinase under the control of <italic>Olig2</italic> gene regulatory elements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Schüller et al., 2008</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a</xref>). The resulting <italic>Fasn</italic> mutants were viable, fertile and born according to Mendelian distribution. Loss of FASN expression was confirmed by immunohistochemistry in differentiated (CC1+) OLs of postnatal day (P) 14 mutants in spinal cord white matter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1b,c</xref>), in agreement with highly efficient recombination in OL lineage cells as monitored by inclusion of the Cre-dependent reporter <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Srinivas et al., 2001</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1a,b</xref>). Comparable loss of FASN was also found in the gray matter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2a,b</xref>). Note that large motoneurons in the ventral horn showed strong FASN expression, which was retained in mutant mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2a,b</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.002</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Generation of mutant mice lacking FASN in the oligodendrocyte lineage.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Experimental strategy of conditional <italic>Fasn</italic> allele inactivation upon <italic>Olig2</italic>-driven Cre expression in vivo. (<bold>b</bold>) Schematic of thoracic spinal cord. Square insert ‘c’: White matter (WM) where subsequent immunostaining images were acquired. GM = gray matter (<bold>c</bold>) Representative immunostaining of cross-sectioned spinal cord from P14 CT and cMU mice, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice examined for each, CT and cMU. Prominent cytoplasmic FASN expression in differentiated OLs (CC1+; examples indicated by arrowheads) in CT, but not in cMU. Nuclear marker: DAPI. Scale bars: 20 μm. CT<italic> =</italic> control, cMU = conditional mutant, GM = gray matter, WM = white matter.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.003</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Recombination efficiency in spinal cord white matter.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative immunostaining of cross-sectioned thoracic spinal cord white matter from P14 CT and cMU mice, <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and cMU. Cre-dependent expression of the reporter R<italic>osa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> allele is detectable in oligodendrocyte lineage cells (Olig2+, examples indicated by arrowheads), including OPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+, examples indicated by arrows). Nuclear marker: DAPI. Scale bar: 25 μm, applying to the entire panel. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graphs to (<bold>a</bold>) with quantification of percentage of recombined OPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+ YFP+) over total OPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+), and quantification of percentage of recombined oligodendrocyte lineage cells (Olig2+ YFP+) over total oligodendrocyte lineage cells (Olig2+). Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and cMU; both dorsal and ventral white matter of 3 spinal cord hemi-sections were quantified per animal, with at least 43 PDGFRα+ YFP+ and at least 255 Olig2+ YFP+ cells quantified per hemi-section (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; for recombination frequency of OPCs: cMU vs. CT, p=0.0967, <italic>t</italic> = 1.881; for recombination frequency of oligodendrocyte lineage cells: cMU vs. CT, p=0.9943, <italic>t</italic> = 0.0074. Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT<italic> =</italic> control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig1-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>FASN expression in gray matter oligodendrocytes of CT but not in cMU mice.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Schematic of the thoracic spinal cord. Square insert ‘b’: Gray <italic>matter</italic> (GM) area where subsequent immunostaining images were acquired. WM = white matter. (<bold>b</bold>) Representative immunostaining of cross-sectioned thoracic spinal cord from P14 CT and cMU mice, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice examined for each, CT and cMU. Prominent cytoplasmic FASN expression in differentiated OLs (CC1+; examples indicated by arrowheads) in CT, but not in cMU. FASN is present in CC1- motoneurons (identified by their characteristic large size) in the ventral horn of the spinal cord GM in CT mice and also retained in cMUs (examples indicated by arrows). Nuclear marker: DAPI. Scale bars: 20 μm. CT = control, cMU = conditional mutant, GM = gray Matter, WM = white matter.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig1-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>FASN is dispensable for proliferation and differentiation along the oligodendrocyte lineage</title><p>Before OLs reach the myelinating stage, their progenitors (OPCs) need to proliferate, differentiate and mature. In some proliferating cells such as in cancer and neuronal progenitors, FASN activity is required to support increased metabolic demands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Currie et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Knobloch et al., 2013</xref>). Thus, we analyzed OL proliferation by EdU incorporation but found no detectable differences between mutants and controls at both P4 and P10 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2a,b</xref>). Next, we addressed whether lack of FASN may affect differentiation along the OL lineage during development. Initial immunohistochemical analyses revealed marginal (if any) FASN expression in white matter OPCs (PDGFRα+ cells) of the P14 spinal cord (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1a</xref>), compared to high levels in differentiated OLs (CC1+ cells) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1a</xref>). Further comparative analyses of mutant and control mice yielded no significant differences in the percentages of OPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1b,c</xref>), total OL lineage cells (Olig2+) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2c,d and e</xref>) and differentiated OLs (CC1+ Olig2+) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2c,d and e</xref>) in spinal cord white matter at P4, P10 and P14. Taken together, these data indicate that FASN is not required for correct proliferation and differentiation of the OL lineage to CC1+ cells during postnatal development.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.005</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis is not required to achieve correct numbers of oligodendrocyte lineage cells during development.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative immunostaining of ventral white matter in cross-sectioned spinal cords of P4 and P10 mice identifying proliferating (EdU+) OLs (Olig2+; examples indicated by arrowheads), <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU. Nuclear marker: DAPI. Scale bar: 50 μm, applying to entire panel. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graphs to (<bold>a</bold>) with quantification of percentage of proliferating OLs (EdU+ Olig2+) over total number of OLs (Olig2+) in spinal cord white matter of CT and cMU mice at P4 and P10. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU; random fields of both dorsal and ventral white matter of 4 sections quantified per animal, with at least 83 Olig2+ cells quantified per section (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P4: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.6876, <italic>t =</italic> 0.4326; P10: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.5448, <italic>t =</italic> 0.6608). (<bold>c</bold>) Representative immunostaining of ventral white matter in cross-sectioned spinal cords from P4, P10, and P14 mice identifying differentiated OLs (CC1+; examples indicated by arrowheads), OLs (Olig2+) and total number of cells (DAPI+), <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU at P4 and P10, <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and cMU at P14. Nuclear marker: DAPI. Scale bar: 50 μm, applying to entire panel. (<bold>d, e</bold>) Corresponding graphs to (<bold>c</bold>) with quantification of percentage of total OLs (Olig2+) (<bold>d</bold>) and differentiated OLs (CC1+ Olig2+) (<bold>e</bold>) over total number of cells (DAPI+), in the spinal cord white matter of CT and cMU mice at P4, P10 and P14. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU at P4 and P10, and <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and cMU at P14. Random fields of both dorsal and ventral white matter of at least 3 sections quantified per animal, with at least 83 Olig2+ cells quantified per section (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; % Olig2+/DAPI+ at P4: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.8280, <italic>t =</italic> 0.2319; at P10: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.6694, <italic>t =</italic> 0.46; at P14: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.3340, <italic>t =</italic> 1.028; % CC1+ Olig2+ / DAPI+ at P4: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.3405, <italic>t =</italic> 1.081; at P10: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.8490, <italic>t =</italic> 0.2031; at P14: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.2061, <italic>t =</italic> 1.376). Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT<italic> =</italic> control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig2-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.006</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>FASN expression in oligodendrocyte progenitors is marginal and dispensable for their early maintenance.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative immunostaining of ventral white matter in cross-sections of lumbar spinal cords from P14 CT mice depicting marginal (if any) FASN expression in OPCs (PDGFRα+; examples indicated by arrows and outlining) compared to comparatively high expression in differentiated OLs (CC1+; example indicated by arrowhead). <italic>n</italic> = 3 examined CT mice. Scale bar: 20 μm, applying to entire panel. (<bold>b</bold>) Representative immunostainings of ventral white matter in cross-sectioned lumbar spinal cords from P4, P10 and P14 CT and cMU mice, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU, at P4 and P10, and <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for each, CT and cMU, at P14. Images identify OPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+, arrows). Nuclear marker: DAPI. Scale bar: 20 μm, applying to entire panel. (<bold>c</bold>) Corresponding graphs to (<bold>b</bold>) with quantification of percentage of OPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+) over total number of cells (DAPI+) in the spinal cord white matter of CT and cMU mice at P4, P10 and P14. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU, at P4 and P10, and <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for each, CT and cMU, at P14. Random fields of both dorsal and ventral white matter in at least 3 sections quantified per animal, with at least 121 PDGFRα+ Olig2+ cells quantified per section (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P4: cMU vs. CT, p=0.0903, <italic>t</italic> = 2.223; at P10: cMU vs. CT, p=0.8527, <italic>t</italic> = 0.198; at P14: cMU vs. CT, p=0.1030, <italic>t</italic> = 1.922). Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT = control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig2-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis is critical for accurate CNS myelination, including radial myelin growth</title><p>Based on the observed high levels of FASN expression in differentiated (CC1+) OLs, we addressed next whether these cells rely on endogenous FA synthesis to myelinate. Thus, we performed EM ultrastructural morphological analysis of the ventral spinal cord white matter from control and mutant mice at P14 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). We found that mutant mice exhibited more axons not encased by myelin compared to controls (69.57 ± 3.75% in mutants vs. 53.56 ± 2.37% in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3a,b</xref>). Moreover, g-ratio analysis (i.e. ratio of axon to fiber (axon + myelin) diameter) revealed that mutant myelinated axons had overall thinner myelin compared to controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3c</xref>). These data were confirmed by analysis of the correlation of g-ratio and fiber diameter with axon diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3d,e</xref>). To understand whether lack of FASN resulted in persistently reduced myelination of axons, we compared the ultrastructural morphology of white matter of the ventral spinal cord of mutant versus control mice at P180. Although myelination progressed in both cases, a higher percentage of not-yet myelinated axons persisted in the spinal cord white matter of mutant mice (15.21 ± 2.92% in mutants vs. 6.59 ± 1.01% in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3g</xref>). In addition, marked hypomyelination of mutant axons also persisted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3f</xref>, arrows), confirmed by g-ratio analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3h,i and j</xref>). We conclude that endogenous FA synthesis in OLs is critical for accurate myelination in the spinal cord, including efficient myelin growth. Our findings may reflect that lack of endogenous FA synthesis limits total myelin production of each mutant OL and/or the number of myelin sheaths that can be generated. Other contributing factors to the mutant OL phenotype might include altered timing in the onset of individual myelin sheath formation.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.007</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes is essential to achieve accurate myelination in the spinal cord.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative EM images of P14 control (CT, <bold>a’ and a’’</bold>) and conditional mutant (cMU, <bold>b’ and b’’</bold>) white matter from the ventral funiculi of lumbar spinal cords. cMUs show more naked axons, not-yet enwrapped by myelin, when compared to CTs. cMUs also display thinner myelin (examples indicated by arrows). Scale bars: 2 μm. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of percentage of not myelinated axons at P14. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU, with at least 590 axons quantified per animal in random fields selected in the same anatomical area (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P14: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0225, <italic>t =</italic> 3.614), *p&lt;0.05. (<bold>c</bold>) Overall hypomyelination at P14 in cMU as shown by g-ratio analysis. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P14: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0025, <italic>t =</italic> 6.731), **p&lt;0.01. (<bold>d, e</bold>) Linear correlation of g-ratio versus axon diameter (<bold>d</bold>) and of fiber diameter versus axon diameter (<bold>e</bold>), in the ventral white matter spinal cord of cMU compared to CT at P14. 100 myelinated axons per mouse analyzed in random fields selected in the same anatomical area, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU. (<bold>f</bold>) Representative EM images of P180 CT and cMU white matter from ventral funiculi of lumbar spinal cords. cMUs show more naked axons (false colored in orange) compared to CTs. cMU axons are encased by thinner myelin (examples indicated by arrows) compared to CTs. Scale bars: 5 μm. (<bold>g</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of percentage of not myelinated axons at P180. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU, with at least 220 axons quantified per animal, in random fields selected in the same anatomical area (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P180: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0493, <italic>t =</italic> 2.791), *p&lt;0.05. (<bold>h</bold>) Overall hypomyelination at P180 in cMU compared to CT, as shown by g-ratio analysis. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P180: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0027, <italic>t =</italic> 6.651), **p&lt;0.01. (<bold>i, j</bold>) Linear correlation of g-ratio versus axon diameter (<bold>i</bold>) and of fiber diameter versus axon diameter (<bold>j</bold>), in the ventral white matter spinal cord of cMU compared to CT at P180. At least 65 myelinated axons per mouse analyzed in random fields selected in the same anatomical area, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU. Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT<italic> =</italic> control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig3-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.008</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Recombination efficiency in the optic nerve.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative immunostaining of cross-sectioned optic nerves from P14 CT and cMU mice, <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and cMU. Cre-dependent expression of the reporter <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> allele is detectable in oligodendrocyte lineage cells (Olig2+, examples indicated by arrowheads), including OPCs (PDGFRα+ and Olig2+, examples indicated by arrows). Nuclear marker: DAPI. Scale bar: 25 μm, applying to entire panel. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graphs to (<bold>a</bold>) with quantification of percentage of recombined OPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+ YFP+) over total OPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+), and quantification of percentage of recombined oligodendrocyte lineage cells (Olig2+ YFP+) over total oligodendrocyte lineage cells (Olig2+). Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and cMU; whole surface of 3 optic nerve sections were quantified per animal, with at least 19 PDGFRα+ YFP+ and at least 80 Olig2+ YFP+ cells quantified per section (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; for recombination frequency of OPCs: cMU vs. CT, p=0.1394, <italic>t</italic> = 1.641; for recombination frequency of oligodendrocyte lineage cells: cMU vs. CT, p=0.3650, <italic>t</italic> = 0.9603. Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT<italic> =</italic> control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig3-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.009</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes is essential to achieve accurate myelination of the optic nerve.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative EM images of optic nerves from P14 control (CT) and conditional mutant (cMU) mice. Note the increased number of axons not-yet enwrapped by myelin in cMUs when compared to CTs. cMUs also display aberrant myelinated-axon profiles (example indicated by arrowhead). Scale bars: 2 μm. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of the percentage of not myelinated axons at P14. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU, with at least 4500 axons quantified per animal in random fields selected in the same anatomical area (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P14: cMU vs. CT, p=0.0006, <italic>t</italic> = 9.999), ***p&lt;0.001. (<bold>c</bold>) g-ratio analysis. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P14: cMU vs. CT, p=0.4162, <italic>t</italic> = 0.906). (<bold>d, e</bold>) Linear correlation of g-ratio versus axon diameter (<bold>d</bold>) and of fiber diameter versus axon diameter (<bold>e</bold>) in optic nerves of cMU compared to CT at P14. 100 myelinated axons per mouse analyzed in random fields selected in the same anatomical area, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU. (<bold>f</bold>) Representative EM images of optic nerves from P180 CT and cMU mice. cMUs show more axons not-yet enwrapped by myelin (examples false colored in orange) when compared to CTs. cMU axons are also covered by thinner myelin (examples indicated by arrows) compared to CTs. Scale bars: 2 μm. (<bold>g</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of percentage of not myelinated axons at P180. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU, with at least 1500 axons quantified per animal, in random fields selected in the same anatomical area (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P180: cMU vs. CT, p=0.0345, <italic>t</italic> = 3.15), *p&lt;0.05. (<bold>h</bold>) Overall hypomyelination in cMU compared to CT at P180, as shown by g-ratio analysis. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P180: cMU vs. CT, p=0.0062, <italic>t</italic> = 5.269), **p&lt;0.01. (<bold>i, j</bold>) Linear correlation of g-ratio versus axon diameter (<bold>i</bold>) and of fiber diameter versus axon diameter (<bold>j</bold>), in optic nerves of cMU compared to CT at P180. 100 myelinated axons per mouse analyzed, in random fields selected in the same anatomical area, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU. Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT = control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig3-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.010</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes is essential to achieve accurate myelination of the corpus callosum.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative EM images of corpus callosum from P180 CT and cMU mice. cMUs show slightly more axons not-yet enwrapped by myelin compared to CTs. cMU axons are also covered by thinner myelin compared to CTs. Scale bars: 1 μm (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of the percentage of not myelinated axons at P180. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for each, CT and cMU, with at least 2243 axons quantified per animal in random fields selected in the same anatomical area (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; cMU vs. CT, p=0.0152, <italic>t</italic> = 3.362), *p&lt;0.05. Bars represent mean ±SEM. (<bold>c</bold>) g-ratio analysis. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for each, CT and cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; cMU vs. CT, p&lt;0.0001, <italic>t</italic> = 8.841), ***p&lt;0.001. Bars represent mean ±SEM. (<bold>d, e</bold>) Linear correlation of g-ratio versus axon diameter (<bold>d</bold>) and of fiber diameter versus axon diameter (<bold>e</bold>) in corpus callosum of cMU compared to CT at P180. At least 100 myelinated axons per mouse analyzed in random fields selected in the same anatomical area, <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for each, CT and cMU. CT<italic> =</italic> control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig3-figsupp3-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>To examine whether anatomically differently located OLs are similarly dependent on endogenous FA synthesis, we extended our study to the optic nerve. As observed in the spinal cord, high recombination efficiency in OL lineage cells was also found in this structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1a,b</xref>). In line with our findings in the spinal cord, P14 optic nerves of mutant mice displayed a higher percentage of axons not-yet encased by myelin compared to controls (84.08 ± 0.33% in mutants vs. 75.68 ± 0.77% in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2a,b</xref>). Although the onset of myelination progressed in both mutants and controls, also P180 mutant optic nerves retained more axons not encased by myelin (21.16 ± 5.1% in mutants vs. 4.29 ± 1.6% in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2f</xref>, false colored, and g). Overall, no significant hypomyelination was detectable in optic nerves of mutant mice in early development (P14) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2c,d and e</xref>). Analysis of P180 optic nerves revealed, however, that mutant OLs failed to support ongoing myelin growth accurately, resulting in pronounced hypomyelination in adulthood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2f</xref>). This observation was confirmed by overall g-ratio quantification (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2h</xref>) and correlation analyses of g-ratio and fiber diameter versus axon diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2i,j</xref>). We conclude that FASN activity in OLs is required for accurate myelination also in the optic nerve, albeit with subtle differences to the spinal cord.</p><p>Since the corpus callosum is often explored in myelin research, we examined also this brain region in the adult. Similar to our findings in the spinal cord and in the optic nerve, an increased fraction of axons that were not enwrapped by myelin was detected in the corpus callosum of P180 mutant mice (72.27 ± 0.98% in mutants vs. 63.53 ± 2.41% in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3a,b</xref>). In addition, myelinated axons displayed relatively thinner myelin in mutants, as indicated by the higher g-ratio values compared to controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3a,c</xref>) and confirmed by scatter plots of g-ratio and fiber diameter versus axonal diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3d,e</xref>).</p><p>Taken together, our studies of different CNS regions revealed that endogenous FA synthesis by OLs is required for correct myelination in various areas. More detailed comparisons require further investigations, including complementary approaches to alleviate technical limitations. Such examinations may well uncover more subtle variations between these regions, possibly relating to the physiological context of each environment, including local differences in astrocyte coupling, or potential intrinsic differences between oligodendrocyte lineage cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Dimou and Simons, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Marques et al., 2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis contributes to the stability of myelinated axons and correct CNS myelin lipid composition</title><p>A further characteristic feature in spinal cord tissue of P14 mutant mice were some aberrant vacuolated myelin-axon profiles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4a</xref>), confirmed by quantification (3.81 ± 0.15% in mutants vs. 0.25 ± 0.08% in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4b</xref>). These structures resembled those observed in the PNS when Schwann cells lack FASN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Montani et al., 2018</xref>). Irregular myelin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4a</xref>, arrowheads) was often surrounding axons which appeared compressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4a</xref>, asterisks). Similarly, examination of optic nerves revealed a comparable increase in anomalous myelin-axon profiles in mutant mice (5.41 ± 1.0% in mutants vs. 0.75 ± 0.19% in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1a,b</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.011</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes is required to maintain structural stability of myelinated axons.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Exemplary EM images of aberrant myelin-axon profiles showing vacuolation (examples indicated by arrowheads) in the ventral white matter of spinal cords of P14 cMUs. Where identifiable, axons associated with aberrant structures are indicated by asterisks. Scale bars: I = 5 µm, II = 2 µm, III = 2 µm, IV = 2 µm, V = 5 µm, VI = 2 µm, VII = 2 µm. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of the percentage of aberrant myelin-axon profiles. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P14: cMU vs. CT p&lt;0.0001, <italic>t =</italic> 21.16), ***p&lt;0.001. At least 8300 axons per mouse analyzed in random fields selected in the same anatomical area. (<bold>c</bold>) Total FA composition of myelin purified from spinal cords of P60 CT and cMU mice, divided in non-essential FAs (NEss), conditional-essential FAs (Cond Ess) and essential FAs (Ess). Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for CT and <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; NEss: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.2609, <italic>t =</italic> 1.267; Cond Ess: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.6625, <italic>t =</italic> 0.4635; Ess: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.4435, <italic>t =</italic> 0.8317). (<bold>d</bold>) Quantification of the most abundant FAs found in myelin purified from spinal cords of CT and cMU mice. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for CT and <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; Oleic: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.2525, <italic>t =</italic> 1.293; Palmitic: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.7377, <italic>t =</italic> 0.3542; Stearic: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.4966, <italic>t =</italic> 0.7328). (<bold>e, f, g</bold>) Content of ceramides (<bold>e</bold>), cerebrosides (<bold>f</bold>) and sphingomyelin (<bold>g</bold>) in myelin isolated from spinal cords of cMU compared to CT mice. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for each, CT and cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; ceramides: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.2822, <italic>t =</italic> 1.181; cerebrosides: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.2722, <italic>t =</italic> 1.209; sphingomyelin: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.2310, <italic>t =</italic> 1.333). (<bold>h, i, j, k</bold>) Total content of phosphatidylinositols (PI), phosphatidylserines (PS), phosphatidylcholines (PC) and phosphatidylethanolamines (PE) in myelin isolated from spinal cords of CT and cMU mice. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for each, CT and cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; PI: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.1765, <italic>t =</italic> 1.532; PS: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0031, <italic>t =</italic> 4.784; PC: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.2698, <italic>t =</italic> 1.216; PE: cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.7236, <italic>t =</italic> 0.3706), **p&lt;0.01. Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT<italic> =</italic> control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig4-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.012</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes supports structural stability of myelinated axons in the optic nerve.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) EM images of aberrant myelinated axon profiles (examples indicated by arrowheads) in the optic nerve of P14 cMU mice. Scale bars: I = 2 µm, II = 1 µm, III = 2 µm, IV = 1 µm, V = 1 µm, VI = 1 µm. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of percentage of aberrant myelin-axon profiles. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; at P14: cMU vs. CT, p=0.0101, <italic>t</italic> = 4.595), *p&lt;0.05. At least 3600 axons per mouse analyzed, in random fields selected in the same anatomical area. Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT = control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig4-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.013</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Lipid profiles of spinal cord myelin of adult control and FASN mutant mice.</title><p>Lipids extracted from myelin isolated from spinal cords of control (CT) and mutant (cMU) mice were identified and quantified by liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry. Individual species of 10 highest total FAs (<bold>a</bold>), all identified ceramides (<bold>b</bold>), cerebrosides (<bold>c</bold>), and sphingomyelin (<bold>d</bold>), 10 highest phosphatidylcholines (PC) (<bold>e</bold>), phosphatidylinositols (PI) (<bold>f</bold>), phosphatidylserines (PS) (<bold>g</bold>), and phosphatidylethanolamines (PE) (<bold>h</bold>) are shown. Lipid amounts were normalized to total protein content of samples. Significance was calculated compared to controls. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for CT and <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for cMU for analysis of total FAs, and <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for each, CT and cMU for all other lipid analysis (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; Total Fatty Acids: 18:1n9, p=0.2525, <italic>t</italic> = 1.293; 16:0, p=0.7377, <italic>t</italic> = 0.3542; 18:0, p=0.4966, <italic>t</italic> = 0.7328; 18:1n11, p=0.9865, <italic>t</italic> = 0.01774; 20:4n6, p=0.7340, <italic>t</italic> = 0.3593; 22:6n3, p=0.6994, <italic>t</italic> = 0.4091; 22:4n6, p=0.6471, <italic>t</italic> = 0.4866; 20:0, p=0.9834, <italic>t</italic> = 0.02188; 22:1n7, p=0.4538, <italic>t</italic> = 0.8119; 14:0, p=0.5017, <italic>t</italic> = 0.7237; Ceramides: 18:0, p=0.4388, <italic>t</italic> = 0.8291; 24:1, p=0.3224, <italic>t</italic> = 1.078; 22:1, p=0.2792, <italic>t</italic> = 1.189; 24:0, p=0.2705, <italic>t</italic> = 1.214; 24:2, p=0.4223, <italic>t</italic> = 0.8609; 20:0, p=0.1532, <italic>t</italic> = 1.635; 22:0, p=0.4065, <italic>t</italic> = 0.8925; 18:1, p=0.2146, <italic>t</italic> = 1.387; 20:1, p=0.1721, <italic>t</italic> = 1.55; Cerebrosides: 24:1, p=0.8276, <italic>t</italic> = 0.2274; 24:0, p=0.1838, <italic>t</italic> = 1.502; 18:0, p=0.2138, <italic>t</italic> = 1.39; 22:0, p=0.2293, <italic>t</italic> = 1.338; 22:1, p=0.1417, <italic>t</italic> = 1.691; 24:2, p=0.9312, <italic>t</italic> = 0.0899; 20:0, p=0.1270, <italic>t</italic> = 1.771; 26:1, p=0.3540, <italic>t</italic> = 1.004; Sphingomyelin: 24:1, p=0.2507, <italic>t</italic> = 1.271; 18:0, p=0.4947, <italic>t</italic> = 0.7268; 24:0, p=0.3124, <italic>t</italic> = 1.103; 22:0, p=0.2253, <italic>t</italic> = 1.352; 20:0, p=0.2421, <italic>t</italic> = 1.298; 22:1, p=0.2618, <italic>t</italic> = 1.239; 24:2, p=0.4736, <italic>t</italic> = 0.7643; 16:0, p=0.9749, <italic>t</italic> = 0.03276; 18:1, p=0.8476, <italic>t</italic> = 0.2007; PC: 34:1, p=0.1620, <italic>t</italic> = 1.594; 36:1, p=0.0993, <italic>t</italic> = 1.948; 32:0, p=0.4570, <italic>t</italic> = 0.7948; 34:0, p=0.8025, <italic>t</italic> = 0.2614; 38:1, p=0.5828, <italic>t</italic> = 0.5803; 36:2, p=0.1624, <italic>t</italic> = 1.593; 38:2, p=0.4233, <italic>t</italic> = 0.8591; 38:6, p=0.3106, <italic>t</italic> = 1.107; 38:4, p=0.7018, <italic>t</italic> = 0.4018; 32:1, p=0.7399, <italic>t</italic> = 0.3478; PI: 38:4, p=0.1932, <italic>t</italic> = 1.465; 38:5, p=0.2254, <italic>t</italic> = 1.351; 40:6, p=0.6283, <italic>t</italic> = 0.5099; 36:4, p=0.0097, <italic>t</italic> = 3.73; 38:6, p=0.1153, <italic>t</italic> = 1.84; 36:1, p=0.0445, <italic>t</italic> = 2.534; 34:1, p=0.0715, <italic>t</italic> = 2.186; 40:4, p=0.8491, <italic>t</italic> = 0.1986; 40:5, p=0.9242, <italic>t</italic> = 0.09923; 36:2, p=0.0351, <italic>t</italic> = 2.711; PS: 36:1, p=0.0113, <italic>t</italic> = 3.602; 40:6, p=0.1262, <italic>t</italic> = 1.775; 38:1: p=0.0075, <italic>t</italic> = 3.949; 36:2, p=0.0193, <italic>t</italic> = 3.173; 38:4, p=0.0631, <italic>t</italic> = 2.277; 40:4, p=0.6789, <italic>t</italic> = 0.4349; 38:2, p=0.0065, <italic>t</italic> = 4.075; 40:2, p=0.0544, <italic>t</italic> = 2.385; 38:3, p=0.7193, <italic>t</italic> = 0.3768; 34:1, p=0.0276, <italic>t</italic> = 2.893; PE: 40:6, p=0.8894, <italic>t</italic> = 0.1451; 38:4, p=0.5126, <italic>t</italic> = 0.6958; 38:1, p=0.2972, <italic>t</italic> = 1.141; 36:1, p=0.5587, <italic>t</italic> = 0.619; 36:2, p=0.1676, <italic>t</italic> = 1.57; 38:5, p=0.9192, <italic>t</italic> = 0.1058; 34:1, p=0.1794, <italic>t</italic> = 1.52; 38:2, p=0.4110, <italic>t</italic> = 0.8834; 40:4, p=0.3597, <italic>t</italic> = 0.9915; 38:6, p=0.4677, <italic>t</italic> = 0.7751), *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01. Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT = control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig4-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Since FAs are key structural components of cellular membranes, we investigated the lipid composition of myelin in mutant mice that lack FA synthesis in OLs compared to controls. To this end, we quantified FAs and FA-derived lipid classes in myelin purified from spinal cords of P60 mice. No significant alterations were detectable in essential (diet-derived), conditional-essential (derived from essential) and non-essential FAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2a</xref>) of mutants. Furthermore, we found no difference in the content of palmitate, the direct product of FASN enzymatic activity in mutant vs. control myelin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4d</xref>). Myelin from spinal cords of mutant mice contained also similar amounts of ceramides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4e</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2b</xref>), cerebrosides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2c</xref>), and sphingomyelin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4g</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2d</xref>) compared to controls. Besides some minor alterations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>), strikingly elevated total levels of phosphatidylserines were found in mutants compared to controls (393.5 ± 25.53 in mutants vs. 269.6 ± 4.38 in controls, pmol/mg of proteins) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4i</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2g</xref>). We conclude that lack of endogenous FA synthesis in OLs has a modest influence on the resulting lipid composition of myelin.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Transcriptome analysis of optic nerves of <italic>Fasn</italic> mutant mice reveals oligodendrocyte defects in late stages of maturation, including myelination</title><p>Our results obtained so far indicated that FASN is critical for timely onset of OLs myelination and subsequent radial growth of CNS myelin, but does not play a major role in OL lineage progression based on expression of Olig2, PDGFRα, and CC1 as analytic markers. It is well known, however, that aside from being building blocks for different lipid species, FAs play other key roles such as a source of energy by oxidation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lodhi and Semenkovich, 2014</xref>), through palmitoylation of proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Resh, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Salaun et al., 2010</xref>), and by modulating transcriptional networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Ahmadian et al., 2013</xref>). In this context, we have previously identified activation of PPARγ as a mediator of FASN in triggering onset of PNS myelination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Montani et al., 2018</xref>). In view of these findings, molecular alterations due to lack of FASN in the OL lineage appeared likely. Given that we had not observed significant alterations in OL differentiation up to the CC1+ stage, such potential changes are predicted to reflect functions of OL-derived FASN in the transition of CC1+ OLs to the final stages of maturation up to myelination completion. We addressed this issue by comparing the optic nerve transcriptome of P14 mutant and control mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata1">Figure 5—source data 1</xref>). In line with our morphological findings, Metacore enrichment analysis revealed repression of GeneOntology Processes associated with development of the nervous system, OL differentiation, and myelination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5a,b</xref>). A more detailed Metacore Pathway analysis highlighted downregulation of known regulatory axes of OL maturation and myelination, including cytoskeleton proteins, cell-cell and ECM-cell interactions, as well as epigenetic and transcriptional regulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5a,b</xref>). To explore these dysregulations further, we compared them to OLs single cell transcriptomic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Marques et al., 2016</xref>). This comparison revealed that mutant optic nerves displayed increased expression of a subset of transcripts enriched in mature OLs (MOL 1–6 in ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Marques et al., 2016</xref>) such as Klk6, Sepp1, and Glul. In parallel, reduced expression of several transcripts enriched in myelin-forming OLs (MFOL1/2 in ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Marques et al., 2016</xref>) including Ctps, Sirt2, Gpr17, Olig1, Mag and Mobp was identified. Following up on these findings by a candidate approach, we detected also reduced expression of transcripts encoding well known myelin-associated proteins such as PLP1, MBP and CNP, and of major regulators of OLs including Sox10, Sox8, and Myrf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bujalka et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hornig et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Li and Richardson, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Turnescu et al., 2018</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>). Combined with our previous findings, the dysregulated molecular fingerprint revealed by these data is consistent with a functional role for FASN in late OL maturation and myelination. However, the impaired myelination in mutant mice may also contribute to the transcriptome differences compared to controls.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.014</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Transcriptome analysis of optic nerves of <italic>Fasn</italic> mutant mice reveal oligodendrocyte defects in late stages of maturation, including myelination.</title><p>(<bold>a, b</bold>) GeneOntology analysis depicting biological processes affected by down-regulated (<bold>a</bold>) and up-regulated (<bold>b</bold>) transcripts in P14 optic nerves of mutant (cMU) mice. Metacore Pathway analysis showing pathways affected by downregulated (<bold>a</bold>) and upregulated (<bold>b</bold>) transcripts in P14 optic nerves of cMU mice. Data points represent the count of regulated transcript for each category and pathway. (<bold>c</bold>) Heat map of RNA-seq data of CT and cMU optic nerves at P14, depicting Fasn and selected down- and up-regulated modulators of OL differentiation, maturation and myelination (FDR &lt; 0.05). Markers identified by comparison with OLs single cell sequencing data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Marques et al., 2016</xref>) are marked with an asterisk. <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for cMU, <italic>n</italic> = 4 mice for CT. CT<italic> =</italic> control, cMU = conditional mutant, MFOLs = myelin-forming oligodendrocytes, MOLs = mature oligodendrocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Marques et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.016</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Expressed transcripts in optic nerves from control and cMU mice at P14.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig5-data1-v1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig5-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.015</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>FASN deficiency is correlated with molecular signs of defective oligodendrocyte maturation.</title><p>Graph of qRT-PCR analysis of Sox10, Myrf and MBP in optic nerves of P14 CT and cMU mice. Data are normalized to β-actin and to the mean of CTs (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; Sox10: p=0.0385, <italic>t</italic> = 2.641, <italic>n</italic> = 4 for CT and <italic>n</italic> = 4 for cMU; Myrf: p=0.0326, <italic>t</italic> = 2.765, <italic>n</italic> = 4 for CT and <italic>n</italic> = 4 for cMU; MBP: p=0.0078, <italic>t</italic> = 3.405, <italic>n</italic> = 6 for CT and <italic>n</italic> = 5 for cMU), *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01. Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT = control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig5-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Increased dietary intake of lipids can partially rescue lack of fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes</title><p>Increasing dietary intake of lipids was unable to rescue lack of endogenous FA synthesis by Schwann cells in PNS myelination, instead being surprisingly detrimental (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Montani et al., 2018</xref>). To investigate whether such a treatment could rescue myelination if OLs are deficient in FA synthesis, we fed mutant and control mice either a 60% high fat diet (HFD; % of caloric intake from fat, enriched in palmitic acid; complete FA content in Materials and methods), previously shown to be capable of rescuing diminished lipogenesis in astrocytes in vivo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Camargo et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Camargo et al., 2017</xref>), or a standard diet (STD; complete FA content in Materials and methods). Pregnant females and subsequently born pups were fed with the different diets from E14 up to P40, the time of analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6a</xref>). We found that the HFD regimen lead to improved myelin radial growth in the spinal cord of mutant mice compared to mutant mice fed with STD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6b,c and d</xref>). There were no significant effects of HFD on radial myelin growth in control mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6b,c and d</xref>). Myelinated fibers in the spinal cord of mutant mice treated with HFD were still hypomyelinated compared to those of control mice under HFD or STD, but less so than those of mutant mice under STD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6b,c and d</xref>). We conclude that lack of endogenous FA synthesis in OLs during development can be partially compensated by increasing dietary lipid intake.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.017</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Increasing dietary lipid intake can partially compensate defects in radial myelin growth caused by lack of endogenous fatty acid synthesis in oligodendrocytes.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Scheme of the experimental design. (<bold>b</bold>) Exemplary EM micrographs of the ventral funiculus of the lumbar spinal cord from mutant (cMU) and control (CT) mice that were fed a standard (STD) or a high-fat (HFD) diet. Scale bars: 5 µm. (<bold>c</bold>) Linear correlation of g-ratio versus axon diameter. At least 84 myelinated axons analyzed per mouse, in random fields selected in the same anatomical area, from <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU, STD and HFD. (<bold>d</bold>) Overall hypomyelination in cMU compared to CT fed STD at P40, and partial recovery of radial myelination in cMU fed with HFD, as shown by g-ratio analysis. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and cMU, STD and HFD (one-way Anova; Treatment: p&lt;0.0001, <italic>F</italic><sub>3,8</sub> = 113.2; with Sidak’s multiple comparisons test; cMU STD vs. CT STD: p&lt;0.0001, <italic>t =</italic> 15.96; cMU HFD vs. CT HFD: p<italic>=</italic>0.0002, <italic>t =</italic> 8.597; CT HFD vs CT STD: p<italic>=</italic>0.7703, <italic>t =</italic> 1.339; MU HFD vs. MU STD: p<italic>=</italic>0.0019, <italic>t =</italic> 6.025), ***p&lt;0.001, **p&lt;0.01. Bars represent mean ±SEM. STD = standard diet, HFD = high fat diet, CT<italic> =</italic> control, cMU = conditional mutant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig6-v1.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Depletion of fatty acid synthase in adult oligodendrocyte progenitors to study CNS remyelination</title><p>Following demyelination, new myelin is formed by aOPCs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Crawford et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Franklin and Ffrench-Constant, 2017</xref>). To address the significance of FA synthesis in this process, we conditionally ablated the <italic>Fasn</italic> gene specifically in aOPCs of transgenic mice using tamoxifen-activatable Cre recombinase under the control of <italic>Pdgfr</italic>α gene regulatory elements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Rivers et al., 2008</xref>). Recombination also activated YFP expression via the Cre-dependent reporter <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Srinivas et al., 2001</xref>) that was included in both, induced mutants (i-cMU) and induced control (CT) mice. This experimental design allowed us to follow the fate of recombined cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7a</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1a,b</xref>). We then addressed how loss of FASN in aOPCs affects remyelination of a demyelinated focal lesion in the spinal cord, induced by injection of the gliotoxin lysolecithin (experimental setting schematized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7b</xref>). Such lesions undergo a stereotyped timed program of remyelination that is characterized by high proliferation of recruited aOPCs, followed by their differentiation into CC1+ OLs, OL maturation, and onset of remyelination within the first 10–14 days post lesion (dpl), which is largely completed by 21 dpl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Fancy et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Zawadzka et al., 2010</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7b</xref>). Immunohistochemistry revealed high FASN expression in differentiated CC1+ aOPC-derived OLs in control mice at the lesion site 7 dpl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7c,d</xref>). As expected, this expression was lost in mutant mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7c,d</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.018</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Generation of tamoxifen-inducible <italic>PdgfrαCreERT2:FASN-floxed</italic> conditionally mutant mice.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Tamoxifen-mediated nuclear translocation of <italic>Pdgfrα</italic>-driven CreERT2 induces conditional <italic>Fasn</italic> allele inactivation (i-cMU) and expression of yellow fluorescent protein (YFP). (<bold>b</bold>) Timeline of de-/re-myelination experiments: Focal demyelination of the ventral spinal cord white matter was induced by injection of lysolecithin 4 weeks post-tamoxifen administration. The tissue was analysed 7, 10, 14, 21 and 56 days post-lysolecithin injection (dpl). (<bold>c</bold>) Schematic of lysolecithin-induced demyelinated focal lesion in the ventral funiculus of the thoracic spinal cord (level T12). Square insert indicates the area where immunostaining images were acquired. (<bold>d</bold>) Representative immunostainings of lesioned areas in cross-sectioned thoracic spinal cords from CT and i-cMU mice 7 dpl, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice analyzed for each, CT and i-cMU. Note the prominent FASN expression in the cytoplasm of recombined aOPC-derived differentiated OLs (CC1+ YFP+ FASN+, examples indicated by arrowheads) in CT, but not in i-cMU (CC1+ YFP+ FASN-, examples indicated by dotted lines) lesions. Nuclear marker: DAPI. Scale bar: 20 μm, applies to entire panel. CT<italic> =</italic> control, i-cMU = inducible conditional mutant, dpl = days post-lysolecithin injection.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig7-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.019</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Recombination efficiency in spinal cords of <italic>PdgfrαCreERT2:Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> control animals induced with tamoxifen.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Exemplary immunostaining of cross-sectioned thoracic spinal cord white matter from 5 weeks post tamoxifen, <italic>n</italic> = 3 CT mice. Cre-dependent expression of the reporter <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> allele is detectable in aOPCs (PDGFRα+ YFP+, example indicated by arrow), whereas other aOPCs remain unrecombined (PDGFRα+ YFP-, examples indicated by arrowheads). Nuclear marker: DAPI. Scale bar: 20 μm, applying to entire panel. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graph to (<bold>a</bold>) with quantification of percentage of recombined aOPCs (PDGFRα+ YFP+) over total aOPCs (PDGFRα+). Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 CT mice; 3 spinal cord sections were quantified per animal, with at least 36 PDGFRα+ YFP+ cells quantified per animal. Bar represents mean ± SEM.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig7-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Fatty acid synthesis is required to sustain aOPC-derived oligodendrocytes during remyelination</title><p>To explore the role of FA synthesis in OLs during remyelination, we next analyzed FASN expression in aOPCs and the effects of its depletion on their differentiation following demyelination. Comparable to our developmental studies, we found only marginal expression (if any) of FASN in aOPCs located in acute lesions at 7 dpl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1a</xref>). Statistical analysis of immunohistochemical data revealed no significant difference between induced mutant and control mice in numbers of recombined aOPCs (YFP+ PDGFRα+ Olig2+) when data were analyzed over time at 7, 10, 14 and 21 dpl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1b,c</xref>). However, if mutants and controls were statistically compared at the individual time points, a modest but significant reduction in recombined aOPCs was apparent at 14 dpI and 21 dpl (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; i-cMU vs. CT, at 14 dpl: p=0.0164, <italic>t</italic> = 3.027; at 21 dpl: p=0.041, <italic>t</italic> = 2.434). We conclude that FASN is mostly dispensable for building up and maintaining the pool of aOPCs at the lesion site, given that in our lesion model this pool is largely established at 10 dpI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1b,c</xref>). In line with this interpretation, and similar to the developmental situation, we also found that FASN is not essential for early proliferation of OL lineage cells (Olig2+) as tested by Ki67 immunohistochemistry at 7 dpl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s2">Figure 8—figure supplement 2a,b</xref>).</p><p>Next, we examined whether FASN is required during differentiation and maturation of aOPCs into myelinating OLs following demyelination. We found no difference in the number of recombined total (Olig2+ YFP+) and differentiated (CC1+ Olig2+ YFP+) aOPC-derived OLs in mutant and control mice during early differentiation (7 dpI and 10 dpl) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8a,b and c</xref>). However, the number of both recombined total (Olig2+ YFP+) and differentiated (CC1+ Olig2+ YFP+) OLs was substantially lower in mutants compared to controls when remyelination was ongoing (14 dpl), with no major recovery at 21 dpl (Olig2+ YFP+ cells per area (mm<sup>2</sup>) at 14 dpl: 98.4 ± 13.71 in mutants vs. 294.60 ± 28.05 in controls; at 21 dpl: 108.10 ± 11.93 in mutants vs. 237.70 ± 22.55 in controls; CC1+ Olig2+ YFP+ cells per area (mm<sup>2</sup>) at 14 dpl: 45.18 ± 6.71 in mutants vs. 193.20 ± 11.73 in controls; at 21 dpl: 74.60 ± 5.00 in mutants vs. 183.00 ± 18.47 in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8a,b and c</xref>). This impairment was present already at the onset of remyelination (12 dpl; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s3">Figure 8—figure supplement 3a,b and c</xref>), suggesting that OL death might be involved. Cleaved caspase 3 (cC3) immunostaining at 11 dpl did not detect a significant increase in the percentage of apoptotic differentiated recombined OLs (cC3+ CC1+ YFP+) in lesions of mutants compared to controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s3">Figure 8—figure supplement 3d,e</xref>). However, we found such cells at very low frequency, contributing to a rather high variability between animals and limiting the power of our analysis and its interpretation. Thus, we assume that our inability to find an expected significant increase in cC3-associated OL cell death in mutants is likely due to either very fast removal of dying cells or cell death not marked by cC3-positivity, possibilities that we were unable to explore further due to technical limitations.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig8" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.020</object-id><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis is required for maintaining the adult oligodendrocyte progenitor-derived oligodendrocyte population during remyelination.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative immunostaining of lesions of control (CT) and inducible conditional mutant (i-cMU) mice on cross sections of ventral white matter of the spinal cord at 7, 10, 14 and 21 days post-lysolecithin injection (dpl), <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. Images depict recombined aOPC-derived differentiated OLs (CC1+ Olig2+ YFP+, examples indicated by arrowheads). Scale bar: 20 μm, applies to entire panel. (<bold>b, c</bold>) Corresponding graphs with quantification of (<bold>b</bold>) recombined OLs (Olig2+ YFP+) and (<bold>c</bold>) recombined aOPC-derived differentiated OLs (CC1+ Olig2+ YFP+) in lesion areas of ventral spinal cord white matter of CT and i-cMU mice at 7, 10, 14 and 21 dpl. Data were normalized per area. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. Lesion areas of at least 4 sections quantified per animal (2-way Anova; (<bold>b</bold>) Genotype: p&lt;0.0001<italic>, F</italic><sub>1,32</sub>= 30.28; (<bold>c</bold>) Genotype: p&lt;0.0001<italic>, F</italic><sub>1,32</sub>= 84.52; with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test; (<bold>b</bold>) 7 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.9829; 10 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.6132; 14 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p&lt;0.0001; 21 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0071; (<bold>c</bold>) 7 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.9971; 10 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0900; 14: i-cMU vs. CT, p&lt;0.0001; 21 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p&lt;0.0001), ***p&lt;0.001, **p&lt;0.01. Bars represent mean ± SEM. CT<italic> =</italic> control, i-cMU = inducible conditional mutant, dpl = days post-lysolecithin injection.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig8-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig8s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.021</object-id><label>Figure 8—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>FASN expression in adult oligodendrocyte progenitors is marginal and largely dispensable for their response following demyelination.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative immunostaining of the lesion area in cross sections of the spinal cord of induced control (CT) mice at 7 days post-lysolecithin injection (dpl). Images depict marginal expression of FASN in recombined aOPCs (PDGFRα+ YFP+, examples indicated by arrows, FASN- cells outlined) compared to differentiated aOPC-derived OLs (PDGFRα- YFP+, examples indicated by arrowheads). <italic>n</italic> = 5 analyzed CT mice. Scale bar: 20 μm. (<bold>b</bold>) Representative immunostainings of the lesion area in cross sections of the spinal cord at 7, 10, 14 and 21 dpl from CT and induced conditional mutant (i-cMU) mice, <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. Images depict recombined aOPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+ YFP+, examples indicated by arrowheads). Scale bar: 20 μm, applies to entire panel. (<bold>c</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of recombined aOPCs (PDGFRα+ Olig2+ YFP+) in the lesion area of CT and i-cMU mice at 7, 10, 14 and 21 dpl. Data were normalized per area. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. Lesion areas from at least 4 sections quantified per animal (2-way Anova; Genotype: p=0.1589, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,32</sub>= 2.081; with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test; 7 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p=0.9907; 10 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p&gt;0.9999; 14 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p=0.1175; 21 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p=0.9420). Bars represent mean ± SEM. CT = control, i-cMU = inducible conditional mutant, dpl = days post lysolecithin injection.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig8-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig8s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.022</object-id><label>Figure 8—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>FASN expression is dispensable for the proliferation of oligodendrocytes lineage cells in remyelination.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative immunostaining in the lesion area of cross-sectioned thoracic spinal cords of control (CT) and inducible conditional mutant (i-cMU) mice at 7 dpl. <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. Images depict proliferating recombined OL lineage cells (Ki67+ Olig2+ YFP+, examples indicated by arrowheads). Scale bar: 20 μm, applies to entire panel. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of the percentage of proliferative recombined OL lineage cells (Ki67+ Olig2+ YFP+) over total recombined OL lineage cells (Olig2+ YFP+) in the lesion area in cross sections of thoracic spinal cords at 7 dpl, from CT and i-cMU mice. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. Lesion areas from at least 4 sections quantified per animal (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; i-cMU vs. CT: p=0.2636, <italic>t</italic> = 1.202). Bars represent mean ±SEM. CT = control, i-cMU = inducible conditional mutant, dpl = days post-lysolecithin injection.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig8-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig8s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.023</object-id><label>Figure 8—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>FASN is critical to sustain adult oligodendrocyte progenitor-derived oligodendrocytes during remyelination.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative immunostaining of the lesion area in cross sections of the thoracic spinal cord at 12 days post-lysolecithin injection (dpl) from control (CT) and inducible conditional mutant (i-cMU) mice, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. Images depict recombined aOPCs-derived differentiated OLs (CC1+ Olig2+ YFP+, examples indicated by arrowheads). Scale bar: 20 μm. (<bold>b, c</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of (<bold>b</bold>) recombined aOPCs-derived differentiated OLs (CC1+ Olig2+ YFP+) and (<bold>c</bold>) recombined OL lineage cells (Olig2+ YFP+) in the lesion of CT and i-cMU mice 12 dpl. Data were normalized to the area. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. Lesion areas of at least 4 sections quantified per animal (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; (<bold>b</bold>): i-cMU vs. CT, p=0.0060, <italic>t</italic> = 5.319, (<bold>c</bold>): i-cMU vs. CT, p=0.0059, <italic>t</italic> = 5.341), **p&lt;0.01. (<bold>d</bold>) Exemplary immunostaining of the lesion area in cross sections of the thoracic spinal cord of i-cMU mice at 11 dpl. Images depict an exemplary apoptotic recombined differentiated OL, expressing cleaved caspase 3 (cC3+ CC1+ YFP+, example indicated by arrowhead). Scale bar: 20 μm. (<bold>e</bold>) Corresponding graph with quantification of the percentage of apoptotic recombined differentiated OLs (cC3+ CC1+ YFP+) over total recombined differentiated OLs (CC1+ YFP+) in the lesion area of CT and i-cMU mice, 11 dpl. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 5 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. At least 14 sections quantified per animal (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; i-cMU vs. CT: p=0.1470, <italic>t</italic> = 1.606). Bars represent mean ± SEM. CT = control, i-cMU = inducible conditional mutant, cC3 = cleaved caspase 3, dpl = days post-lysolecithin injection.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig8-figsupp3-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Overall our data indicate a crucial role for FA synthesis in sustaining aOPC-derived OLs during remyelination. However, we cannot rule out that also the mild reduction in the number of aOPCs in mutants at 14 dpI and 21 dpl makes some contribution to the observed phenotype. In this context, we favor the interpretation that the observed decrease in CC1+ recombined OLs in mutant animals during remyelination may promote a mild reaction of aOPCs, potentially with the goal of some compensation. If the recombined cells cannot be sustained and die while differentiating from aOPCs towards myelinating oligodendrocytes, this may cause a slight reduction of the remaining numbers of recombined aOPCs. Alternatively, aOPCs may have intrinsic differences in their dependency on FASN compared to developmental OPCs with regard to survival. We consider this less likely given the low expression of FASN by developmental OPCs and aOPCs.</p></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>Fatty acid synthesis is essential for efficient CNS remyelination</title><p>Based on our findings, we next investigated whether the observed drop in differentiated OLs causes a failure of accurate remyelination in mutants. Thus, we analyzed the ultrastructural morphology of remyelinating spinal cord lesions by comparative EM as remyelinated axons can be distinguished by their relatively thin myelin compared to developmentally achieved myelination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Franklin and Ffrench-Constant, 2017</xref>). Consistent with the reduced number of differentiated CC1+ OLs present during the active remyelination phase at 14 dpl, we found that mutant mice displayed more axons not encased by myelin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9a</xref>, false colored) compared to control mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9a</xref>). Quantification confirmed these observations (35.63 ± 3.42% demyelinated axons in mutants vs. 22.68 ± 1.58% in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9b</xref>). Also at 21 dpl, only 8.24 ± 0.70% of axons remained demyelinated in control mice, compared to 18.00 ± 1.91% in mutants. At this time point, focal lesions approach their full remyelination potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Crawford et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Franklin and Ffrench-Constant, 2017</xref>). In agreement, further analysis of a later time point (56 dpl) revealed only a slight additional decrease in the percentage of demyelinated fibers in control mice to 5.58 ± 1.02% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9b</xref>). Similarly, this value decreased also in mutants to 12.04 ± 1.11% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9b</xref>). However, in direct comparison of controls and mutants at 56 dpI, mutants still retained a larger percentage of demyelinated axons (12.04 ± 1.11% in mutants vs. 5.58 ± 1.02% in controls) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9b</xref>). Remyelinated profiles of both control and mutant mice showed characteristically thin myelin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9a</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Franklin and Ffrench-Constant, 2017</xref>), with no significant difference detectable in the thickness of myelin by average g-ratio analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9c</xref>) and by linear correlation of g-ratio versus axon diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9d</xref>) at the sampled time points (14, 21 and 56 dpl). We conclude that FASN and consequently FA synthesis in OLs is essential for efficient remyelination in adult mice.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.024</object-id><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><title>De novo fatty acid synthesis is essential to achieve efficient remyelination in the spinal cord.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative EM images of lesions in the spinal cord of control (CT) and inducible conditional mutant (i-cMU) mice during remyelination at 14, 21 and 56 days post-lysolecithin injection (dpl). i-cMUs show persistently increased numbers of demyelinated axons (examples false colored in orange) compared to CTs up to 56 dpl. Scale bars: 3 μm. (<bold>b</bold>) Corresponding graphs with quantification of percentage of demyelinated axons within the remyelinated lesion area at 14, 21 and 56 dpl. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. The entire lesion area was quantified, at least 550 axons counted per animal (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; 14 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0263, <italic>t =</italic> 3.439; 21 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0086, <italic>t =</italic> 4.803; 56 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.0127, <italic>t =</italic> 4.290), *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01. (<bold>c</bold>) g-ratio analysis of remyelinated fibers at 14, 21 and 56 dpl in i-cMU compared to CTs. Data points represent <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and i-cMU (unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test; 14 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.1146, <italic>t =</italic> 2.011; 21 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.3146, <italic>t =</italic> 1.149; 56 dpl: i-cMU vs. CT, p<italic>=</italic>0.1481, <italic>t =</italic> 1.789). (<bold>d</bold>) Linear correlation of g-ratio versus axon diameter in remyelinating lesions of i-cMU compared to CT mice, at 14, 21 and 56 dpl. At least 50 myelinated axons per mouse analyzed, <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice for each, CT and i-cMU. Bars represent mean ± SEM. CT<italic> =</italic> control, i-cMU = inducible conditional mutant, dpl = days post-lysolecithin injection.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-44702-fig9-v1.tif"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Oligodendrocytes require rapid access to large quantities of lipids over a short period of time to achieve accurate production of the considerable membrane mass required to myelinate multiple axons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Chrast et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nave and Werner, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Schmitt et al., 2015</xref>). To which extent this demand is supported by endogenous synthesis in OLs and/or lipid uptake is not fully understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Chrast et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Schmitt et al., 2015</xref>). In support of a critical role for OL-endogenous lipid biosynthesis, the mTORC1/SREBP signaling axis was suggested to be critical for efficient CNS myelination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Camargo et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Lebrun-Julien et al., 2014</xref>). Furthermore, OLs depend on cholesterol synthesis for efficient radial growth of myelin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Saher et al., 2005</xref>). Postnatally, newly added cholesterol – the major sterol present in myelin – can only be synthesized within the CNS, while the other main myelin lipids share FAs as building blocks that might be either locally synthesized or taken up from the bloodstream (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Currie et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Harayama and Riezman, 2018</xref>). Here, we have addressed the need for FA synthesis in OLs by depleting FASN in transgenic mice. This multifunctional enzyme is responsible for the synthesis of palmitate, the substrate for the production of more complex FAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Currie et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Harayama and Riezman, 2018</xref>). We show that lack of FASN in OLs results in deficits in CNS myelination, including a decreased capacity for myelin to grow. Thus, OLs strictly depend on de novo endogenous FA synthesis to achieve normal myelination.</p><p>Another source for non-essential FAs, and the only source available for essential ones, is the uptake from the FA pool present in the circulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Harayama and Riezman, 2018</xref>). We have previously demonstrated that increasing dietary lipids by administering a HFD cannot ameliorate the dysmyelination resulting from lack of FASN in myelinating Schwann cells of the PNS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Montani et al., 2018</xref>). Thus, we were somewhat surprised to find that the same HFD experimental regimen was able to achieve partial amelioration of the CNS hypomyelination caused by lack of FASN in OLs. Similarly, it has been shown that the HFD used in our study could partially substitute for the lack of SCAP in another CNS cell population, the astrocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Camargo et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Camargo et al., 2017</xref>). The causative mechanisms for these differences between the PNS vs. CNS remain to be determined. Future studies will need to take into account that the two tissues appear to have evolved distinct compensatory mechanisms to deal with this situation. Specifically, adipocytes that are present in the layers surrounding peripheral nerves (i.e. epineurial adipocytes) can carry out lipolysis, potentially to provide supporting lipids when endogenous synthesis in Schwann cells fails (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Montani et al., 2018</xref>) or might become limiting. In contrast, the CNS contains astrocytes which can provide horizontal lipid flux to OLs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Camargo et al., 2017</xref>). However, the specifics of qualitative (i.e. which lipid species are involved) and quantitative contributions, both spatially and temporally, are challenging open research questions. In addition, the relevance of such mechanisms to the maintenance of homeostatic physiology and in disease situations remain important topics to be investigated.</p><p>Given the relevance of efficient remyelination as a drug target in diseases such as multiple sclerosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cole et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Franklin and Ffrench-Constant, 2017</xref>) and the currently clinically explored potential of biotin – an important regulator of FA synthesis – in multiple sclerosis treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sedel et al., 2016</xref>), we were motivated to evaluate the significance of FA synthesis by OLs also in remyelination. To realize this goal, we used the focal lysolecithin-induced demyelinating-remyelinating lesion model in the spinal cord of transgenic mice after depleting FASN specifically in aOPCs. We show that de novo synthesis of FAs is crucial to sustain remyelinating aOPC-derived OLs and is ultimately required for successful remyelination. Specifically, we found that after being able to differentiate correctly, the number of aOPCs-derived OLs was substantially reduced in mutants compared to controls at onset of remyelination, persisting at later time points. Thus, endogenous FA synthesis appears to be pivotal to maintain survival of newly differentiated and mature aOPCs-derived OLs when myelination starts. At the myelin level, depletion of FASN in aOPCs and their progenies was associated with reduced numbers of remyelinated axons in mutants compared to controls from 14 dpl (first time point analyzed) up to 56 dpl (latest time point analyzed). This rather strong phenotype was not expected, since we anticipated that partial disruption of the blood-brain (-spinal cord) barrier in the lesioned CNS may lead to facilitated access of OLs to supplementary FA sources, that is from the pool of FAs in the blood, either directly or from increased horizontal flux from astrocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Camargo et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Saher et al., 2012</xref>). Possibly, saturation of molecules mediating FA-uptake and/or unknown regulatory mechanisms might restrict the FA uptake capacity of OLs not allowing full compensation for the lack of endogenous synthesis. Such mechanisms may also be differentially regulated in lesioned versus intact tissue. Future studies in this context should be aimed at achieving a detailed understanding of the molecular mechanisms that regulate synthesis and trafficking of FAs in the normal and diseased CNS, with a particular emphasis on OLs, astrocytes and blood vessels, including endothelial cells and pericytes. Such knowledge is expected to broaden our understanding of the fundamental mechanisms that regulate developmental myelination, pathological states in diseases, and remyelination after injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Chrast et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Schmitt et al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Reagent type <break/>(species) or resource</th><th>Designation</th><th>Source or reference</th><th>Identifiers</th><th>Additional <break/>information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>M. musculus</italic>)</td><td><italic>Fasnlox/lox</italic></td><td>PMID:16054078</td><td>MGI:3765070</td><td>Dr. Clay F. <break/>Semenkovich, Washington University, St. Louis USA</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>M. musculus</italic>)</td><td><italic>PdgfraCreERT2</italic></td><td>PMID:18849983</td><td>MGI:3832569</td><td>Dr. William D. Richardson, <break/>University College London, London UK</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>M. musculus</italic>)</td><td><italic>Olig2Cre</italic></td><td>Jackson Laboratory</td><td>Stock#:011103; MGI:3810299</td><td>PMID:18691547</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent (<italic>M. musculus</italic>)</td><td><italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic></td><td>Jackson Laboratory</td><td>Stock#:006148; MGI:3621481</td><td>PMID:11299042</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>Genotyping <break/>primer: Fasn forward</td><td>PMID:29434029</td><td/><td>5'-GGATAGCTGTGTAGTGTAACCAT-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>Genotyping primer: Fasn reverse</td><td>PMID:29434029</td><td/><td>5’-GGTCACCCAGCAGGAAAGGGC- 3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>Genotyping primer: Cre forward</td><td>PMID: 29434029</td><td/><td>5’-TTCCCGCAGAACCTGAAGATGTTCG-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>Genotyping primer: Cre reverse</td><td>PMID: 29434029</td><td/><td>5’-GGGTGTTATAAGCAATCCCCAGAAATG-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>Genotyping primer: Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP forward</td><td>PMID: 28522536</td><td/><td>5’-AAAGTCGCTCTGAGTTGTTAT-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>Genotyping primer: Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP reverse transgenic</td><td>PMID: 28522536</td><td/><td>5’-GCGAAGAGTTTGTCCTCAACC-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>Genotyping primer: Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP reverse wildtype</td><td>PMID: 28522536</td><td/><td>5’-GGAGCGGGAGAAATGGATATG-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence- <break/>based reagent</td><td>qRT-PCR primer: SOX10 Forward</td><td>This paper</td><td/><td>5’-CCGACCAGTACCCTCACCT-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>qRT-PCR primer: SOX10 Reverse</td><td>This paper</td><td/><td>5’- TCAATGAAGGGGCGCTTGT-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>qRT-PCR primer: MYRF Forward</td><td>This paper</td><td/><td>5’-ATGGAGGTGGTGGACGAGAC-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based reagent</td><td>qRT-PCR primer:MYRF Reverse</td><td>This paper</td><td/><td>5’-GGCGTCCTCTTTGCCAATGT-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence- <break/>based reagent</td><td>qRT-PCR primer: MBP Forward</td><td>This paper</td><td/><td>5’-ACACGAGAACTACCCATTATGGC-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence- <break/>based reagent</td><td>qRT-PCR primer: <break/>MBP Reverse</td><td>This paper</td><td/><td>5’-CCAGCTAAATCTGCTGAGGGGA-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence- <break/>based reagent</td><td>qRT-PCR primer: <break/>Actin Forward</td><td>PMID: 28880149</td><td/><td>5’-GTCCACACCCGCCACC-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence- <break/>based reagent</td><td>qRT-PCR primer: Actin Reverse</td><td>PMID: 28880149</td><td/><td>5’-GGCCTCGTCACCCACATAG-3’</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Rabbit polyclonal anti-cleaved Caspase 3</td><td>Cell signaling <break/>Technology, Danvers, MA, USA</td><td>Cat# 9661; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2341188">AB_2341188</ext-link></td><td>1:500 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Mouse monoclonal anti-CC1</td><td>Merck Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA</td><td>Cat; # OP80; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2057371">AB_2057371</ext-link></td><td>Development: 1:200 dilution; <break/>Remyelination 1:300 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>rabbit polyclonal anti-FASN</td><td>Abcam, UK</td><td>Cat# Ab22759; <break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_732316">AB_732316</ext-link></td><td>1:200 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Chicken polyclonal anti-GFP</td><td>Abcam, UK</td><td>Cat# Ab13970; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_300798">AB_300798</ext-link></td><td>1:1000 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>mouse monoclonal anti-ki67</td><td>Dako Agilent, <break/>Santa Clara, CA, USA</td><td>Cat# m7249; clone MIB-5; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2250503">AB_2250503</ext-link></td><td>1:200 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>rat monoclonal anti-MBP</td><td>Serotec/BioRad <break/>Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA</td><td>Cat# MCA409S; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_325004">AB_325004</ext-link></td><td>Development: 1:200 dilution; Remyelination 1:300 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Goat polyclonal anti-Olig2</td><td>R and D Systems, <break/>Minneapolis, MN, USA</td><td>Cat# AF2418; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2157554">AB_2157554</ext-link></td><td>1:25 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>mouse monoclonal anti-Olig2</td><td>Merck Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA</td><td>Cat# MABN50; clone 211F1.1; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_10807410">AB_10807410</ext-link></td><td>1:1000 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>rabbit polyclonal anti-Olig2</td><td>Merck Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA</td><td>Cat# AB9610; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_570666">AB_570666</ext-link></td><td>Development: 1:500 dilution; Remyelination 1:400 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Rabbit monoclonal anti-PDGFRα</td><td>Cell signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA</td><td>Cat# 3174; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2162345">AB_2162345</ext-link></td><td>1:500 dilution</td></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>Click-iT EdU <break/>Assay</td><td>Thermo Fisher <break/>Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA</td><td>Cat# C10337</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>Mouse blocking reagent</td><td>Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA</td><td>Cat# MKB-2213</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>Streptavidin/Biotin blocking Kit</td><td>Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA</td><td>Cat# SP-2002</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>Qiagen MiniKit (RNeasy Mini Kit)</td><td>Qiagen, Hilden, Germany</td><td>Cat# 74104</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>TruSeq Stranded mRNA Sample Prep Kit</td><td>Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA</td><td>Cat# 20020594</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial <break/>assay or kit</td><td>Maxima RT-Kit</td><td>Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA</td><td>Cat# K1641</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Lysolecithin</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich, Sant Louis, MO, USA</td><td>Cat# L4129</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Tamoxifen</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich, Sant Louis, MO, USA</td><td>Cat# T5648</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Lipid standards</td><td>Avanti Polar Lipids, Alabaster, AL, USA</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Lipid Data Analyzer software</td><td>PMID: 29058722</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Photoshop CS5 or CS6</td><td>Adobe</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, <break/>algorithm</td><td>FIJI</td><td>ImageJ (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://imagej.nih.gov/ij/">http://imagej.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>)</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>STAR Aligner(v2.5.1b)</td><td>PMID: 23104886</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>RSEM (v1.2.22)</td><td>PMID: 21816040</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>EdgeR</td><td>PMID: 19910308</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Metacore (vs6.33)</td><td>Thomson Reuters</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td>Standard diet (STD)</td><td>KLIBA NAFAG, Provimi KLIBA, Switzerland</td><td>Cat# 3437</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td>High fat diet (HFD)</td><td>KLIBA NAFAG, Provimi KLIBA, Switzerland</td><td>Cat# 2127</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Contacts for reagents and resource sharing</title><p>Requests for further information and reagents may be directed to the corresponding author Ueli Suter (usuter@biol.ethz.ch). <italic>Fasn</italic><sup>lox/lox</sup> mice are available from the Semenkovich laboratory after executing an MTA with Washington University. The <italic>Pdgfr</italic>α<italic>CreERT2</italic> mice are available from the Richardson laboratory after executing an MTA with the University College London. From Jackson Laboratory are available: <italic>Olig2Cre</italic> mice (JAX Stock #011103) and <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> mice (JAX Stock #006148).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>FASN conditional knockout mice</title><p>For developmental studies, mice (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>) homozygous for the fatty acid synthase (<italic>Fasn</italic>) floxed allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Chakravarthy et al., 2005</xref>) (Strain of origin: 129X1/SvJ, subsequently crossed with 129X1/SvJ * C57BL/6 * DBA) were crossed with mice expressing Cre recombinase under the control of the <italic>Olig2</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Schüller et al., 2008</xref>) (Strain of origin: C57BL/6) to obtain <italic>Cre</italic><sup>+</sup>:<italic>Fasn<sup>lox/lox</sup></italic> mutant mice, and <italic>Fasn<sup>lox/lox</sup></italic> or <italic>Fasn<sup>lox/wt</sup></italic> control mice. For experiments assessing recombination frequencies, a <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Srinivas et al., 2001</xref>) (Strain of origin: C57BL/6) was included.</p><p>For remyelination studies, mice homozygous for the <italic>Fasn</italic> floxed allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Chakravarthy et al., 2005</xref>) (Strain of origin: 129X1/SvJ, subsequently crossed with 129X1/SvJ * C57BL/6 * DBA) were crossed with reporter mice homozygous for the <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> allele and with mice expressing CreERT2 recombinase, activatable upon tamoxifen injection, under the control of the <italic>Pdgfr</italic>α promoter (<italic>Pdgfr</italic>α<italic>CreERT2)</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Rivers et al., 2008</xref>) (Strain of origin: C57BL/6). Control mice were <italic>Pdgfr</italic>α<italic>CreERT2<sup>+</sup>:Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP:FASN<sup>wt/wt</sup></italic> for immunohistochemical analysis and <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP:FASN<sup>lox/lox</sup></italic> for electron microscopy analysis. Mutant mice were <italic>Pdgfr</italic>α<italic>CreERT2<sup>+</sup>:Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP:FASN<sup>lox/lox</sup></italic> for all analyses. All mice were injected with tamoxifen. <italic>Fasn</italic> floxed mice were backcrossed for at least three generations to C57BL/6 background, and <italic>Olig2Cre</italic>, <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> and <italic>Pdgfr</italic>α<italic>CreERT2</italic> mice were kept on a C57BL/6 background.</p><p>Both male and female mice were used throughout all experiments. Mice were group-caged, kept in a 12 hr light/dark cycle, with water and food provided ad libitum. Littermates and age-matched mice were assigned to experimental groups according to age and genotype. No method of randomization was applied. Animals were fed a standard (STD) (Cat# 3437, KLIBA NAFAG, Provimi KLIBA, Switzerland) or a high-fat diet (HFD) (Cat# 2127, KLIBA NAFAG, Provimi KLIBA, Switzerland), as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Montani et al., 2018</xref>). Briefly, pregnant females were fed the high fat diet from gestational day 14 until weaning of the pups 3 weeks after birth. Pups were subsequently separated from the mother and kept on a high fat diet until being sacrificed at 40 days of age. Diets content of fatty acids (in percentage) in HFD vs. STD was: C12 0.03 vs. 0.002, C14 0.440 vs. 0.008, C15 0.000 vs. 0.002, C16 8.220 vs. 0.719, C17 0.000 vs. 0.004, C18 4.500 vs. 0.157, C20 0.020 vs. 0.010, C22 0.000 vs. 0.004, C24 0.000 vs. 0.012, C14:1 0.170 vs. 0.001, C16:1c7 1.000 vs. 0.052, C18:1c9 14.120 vs. 1.024, C20:1c9 0.000 vs. 0.013, C22:1c9 0.000 vs. 0.002, C18:2c9c12 4.810 vs. 2.107, C18:3c9c12c15 0.590 vs. 0.212, C20:4(n-6) 0.560 vs. 0.009, C22:5(n-3) 0.000 vs. 0.001. Cholesterol was present in the same percentage (0.030) in both HFD and STD.</p><p>Genotypes were determined by PCR on genomic DNA (<italic>Fasn</italic> primers: 5’-Forward GGATAGCTGTGTAGTGTAACCAT-3’, Reverse 5’-GGTCACCCAGCAGGAAAGGGC-3’; <italic>Cre</italic> primers: Forward 5’-TTCCCGCAGAACCTGAAGATGTTCG-3’, Reverse 5’-GGGTGTTATAAGCAATCCCCAGAAATG-3’, <italic>Rosa26-loxPstoploxP-YFP</italic> primers: Forward 5’-AAAGTCGCTCTGAGTTGTTAT-3’, Reverse transgenic 5’-GCGAAGAGT TTGTCCTCAACC-3’, Reverse wild type 5’-GGAGCGGGAGAAATGGATATG-3’). All animal experiments were performed with the approval and in strict accordance with the guidelines of the Zurich Cantonal Veterinary Office (ref ZH161/2014, ZH090/2017, ZH03/2012, ZH264/2014, ZH207/2017).</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Tamoxifen administration</title><p>CreERT2-mediated recombination in 8 to 10 week-old mice was induced by a single daily intraperitoneal injection of 2 mg tamoxifen (Cat# T5648, Sigma-Aldrich, Sant Louis, MO, USA; 20 mg/ml stock solution in sunflower oil containing 10% ethanol) over 5 consecutive days.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Focal spinal cord demyelinating lesions</title><p>Four weeks after tamoxifen induction, demyelinated lesions were induced in the ventral funiculus of the thoracic spinal cord at intervertebral level T12/T13 as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Fancy et al., 2011</xref>). Mice received a preoperative subcutaneous injection of 0.1 mg/kg (of body weight) of buprenorphine (Temgesic solution injectable 0.3 mg/ml, Indivior, Switzerland) in Ringer solution (Braun, Switzerland), and were anesthetized by isoflurane inhalation. A dorsal laminectomy was performed at the T12/T13 level, and the dura pierced with an acupuncture needle. 1 µl of 1% lysolecithin (Cat# L4129, Sigma-aldrich, Sant Louis, MO, USA) in 1x PBS, pH 7.4, was injected hemilaterally in the ventral funiculus at a rate of 0.5 µl per minute, with a glass needle coupled to a Hamilton syringe, via a three-way micromanipulator (Narishige, Japan). The overlaying musculature was sutured, and wound clips were applied to close the skin above. Animals were allowed to recover on a heating pad at 37°C. Animals received twice daily a subcutaneous injection of 0.1 mg/kg (of body weight) of buprenorphine (Temgesic solution injectable 0.3 mg/ml, Indivior, Switzerland) for two days following the injury. For additional analgesic treatment, animals were supplied with <italic>ad libitum</italic> 0.01 mg/ml buprenorphine (Temgesic solution injectable 0.3 mg/ml, Indivior, Switzerland) in drinking water for three days following injury.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>TEM and SEM microscopy</title><p>Mice were anaesthetized by terminal intraperitoneal injection of pentobarbital, 10% in saline solution (0.9% NaCl) (Eskonarkon, Streuli Pharma, Switzerland). Mice were intracardially perfused with 0.1M phosphate buffer (PB) pH 7.4, followed by a 2.5% glutaraldehyde/4% paraformaldehyde solution in 0.1M PB. After dehydration through an acetone series, tissues were post-fixed in 2% osmium tetroxide overnight, and embedded in Spurr’s resin (Electron Microscopy Sciences, Hatfield, PA, USA). Ultrathin sections were cut on a Leica UC-7 (Leica microsystems, Germany) or a Reichert-Jung Ultra cut E ultramicrotome (Leica microsystems, Germany, 65 nm-thick for transmission electron microscopy (TEM) or 99 nm-thick for scanning electron microscopy (TEM)). Sections transferred onto copper grids with a carbon film (Electron Microscopy Sciences, Hatfield, PA, USA) for TEM or ITO coverslips (Optic Balzers, Germany) for SEM, were counterstained with 2% uranyl acetate and 1% lead citrate. Images were acquired with a Morgagni 268 (FEI) for TEM, for analysis of developmental myelination. For reconstruction of entire lesion areas for the remyelination analysis, SEM was used. Images were acquired using the in-lens detector of a Merlin FEG SEM (Zeiss, Germany) operating at 2 KeV, attached to the ATLAS module (Zeiss, Germany). The entire lesion area was imaged as multiple individual images, with overlap between adjacent ones. Alignment and merging of these images was performed using FIJI (ImageJ) and Photoshop CS5 or CS6 (Adobe). Brightness and contrast of EM images were adjusted for optimal detection of the structures.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Antibodies</title><p>The following antibodies were used: Rabbit anti-cleaved Caspase 3 (IHC 1:500, Cat# 9661, Cell signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2341188">AB_2341188</ext-link>), mouse anti-CC1 (IHC 1:200 in the analysis of development, 1:300 in the analysis of remyelination, Cat# OP80, Merck Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2057371">AB_2057371</ext-link>), rabbit anti-FASN (IHC 1:200, Cat# Ab22759, Abcam, UK; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_732316">AB_732316</ext-link>), chicken anti-GFP (IHC 1:1000, Cat# Ab13970, Abcam, UK; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_300798">AB_300798</ext-link>), mouse anti-ki67 (IHC 1:200, Cat# m7249, clone MIB-5, Dako Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2250503">AB_2250503</ext-link>), rat anti-MBP (IHC 1:200 in the analysis of development, IHC 1:300 in the analysis of remyelination, Cat# MCA409S, Serotec/BioRad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_325004">AB_325004</ext-link>), goat anti-Olig2 (IHC 1:25, Cat# AF2418, R and D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2157554">AB_2157554</ext-link>; biotinylated), mouse anti-Olig2 (IHC 1:1000, clone 211F1.1, Cat# MABN50, Merck Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_10807410">AB_10807410</ext-link>), rabbit anti-Olig2 (IHC 1:500 in the analysis of development, IHC 1:400 in the analysis of remyelination, Cat# AB9610, Merck Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_570666">AB_570666</ext-link>), rabbit anti-PDGFRα (IHC 1:500, Cat# 3174, Cell signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2162345">AB_2162345</ext-link>), donkey anti-chicken Alexa488 (IHC 1:1000, Cat# 703-545-155, Jackson ImmunoResearch, West Grove, PA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2340375">AB_2340375</ext-link>), goat anti-mouse Alexa488 (IHC 1:300, Cat# A11029, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_138404">AB_138404</ext-link>), donkey anti-mouse Alexa546 (IHC 1:1000, Cat# A10036, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2534012">AB_2534012</ext-link>), goat anti-mouse Alexa546 (IHC 1:1000, Cat# A11030, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_144695">AB_144695</ext-link>), goat anti-mouse Alexa647 (IHC 1:1000, Cat# A21237, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_1500743">AB_1500743</ext-link>), donkey anti-rabbit Alexa488 (IHC 1:1000, Cat# A21206, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2535792">AB_2535792</ext-link>), donkey anti-rabbit Alexa647 (IHC 1:1000, Cat# A31573, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2536183">AB_2536183</ext-link>), goat anti-rabbit Alexa546 (IHC 1:1000, Cat# A11035, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_143051">AB_143051</ext-link>), goat anti-rabbit Alexa594 (IHC 1:300, Cat# A11012, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_141359">AB_141359</ext-link>), goat anti-rabbit Alexa647 (IHC 1:1000, Cat# A21244, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_141663">AB_141663</ext-link>), goat anti-rat Alexa647 (IHC 1:300, Cat# A21247, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_141778">AB_141778</ext-link>), Streptavidin-Alexa647 (IHC 1:1000, Cat# S21374, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2336066">AB_2336066</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Immunostaining</title><p>Cell proliferation was analyzed using the Click-iT EdU Assay (Invitrogen), according to manufacturer’s protocol. Mice received a single intraperitoneal injection of EdU (50 mg/Kg of weight) and the tissue of interest was harvested 2 hr after the injection.</p><p>Mice were anaesthetized by terminal intraperitoneal injection of pentobarbital, 10% in saline solution (0.9% NaCl) (Eskonarkon, Streuli Pharma, Switzerland). Mice were intracardially perfused with 1x PBS pH 7.4, followed by 4% paraformaldehyde, 5% sucrose in 1x PBS. Dissected tissues were post-fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde, 5% sucrose in 1x PBS overnight at 4°C and cryoprotected in 30% sucrose in PBS for 24 hr at 4°C. Tissues embedded in O.C.T. Tissue Tek (Sakura, The Netherlands) were cut on a cryostat in 10 µm sections with distance between serial sections of 100 µm, and transferred to SuperFrost Plus (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) coated slides. Slides were stored at −80°C until further use.</p><p>For immunostaining, slides were defrosted at room temperature (RT) for at least 30 min and rinsed 3x with 1% Triton X-100 in 1x PBS. Blocking and permeabilization was done with 1% Triton X-100, 10% goat or donkey serum, in 1x PBS for 30 min. Sections were incubated with primary antibodies, diluted in blocking solution, overnight at 4°C. The following day, sections were washed 3 × 10 min with 0.1% Triton X-100 in 1x PBS and incubated with secondary antibodies, diluted in blocking solution, for 2 hr at RT. Sections were washed twice with 0.1% Triton X-100 in 1x PBS, and incubated with 4′,6′-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) for 10 min. After a last 10 min wash with 1x PBS, sections were coverslipped with ImmuMount (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). For CC1, cleaved caspase 3, and Ki67 stainings, an antigen retrieval step was added to the above protocol. Briefly, after thawing slides were incubated in a pre-heated antigen retrieval solution in a water bath for 20 min (for analysis of development: Sodium citrate buffer (10 mM Tri-sodium citrate dehydrate, 0.05% Tween-20, pH 6.0) incubated at 95°C, for analysis of remyelination Tris-EDTA buffer (10 mM Trizma Base (Sigma-aldrich, St Louis, MI, USA), 1 mM EDTA, 0.05% Tween-20, pH 9.0) incubated at 86°C). For stainings with mouse anti-CC1 antibody performed for the analysis of remyelination, sections were next incubated with mouse blocking reagent (Cat# MKB-2213, Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA) for 1 hr at RT followed by primary antibody incubation and further processed according to manufacturer’s recommendations in 1% Triton X-100 in 1x PBS to prevent cross-reaction of anti-mouse secondary antibodies with endogenous antibodies.</p><p>For stainings with biotinylated anti-Olig2 antibody, sections were treated with a Streptavidin/Biotin blocking Kit (Cat# SP-2002, Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Lipid analysis</title><p>For lipidomic analysis, myelin from spinal cords dissected from P60 control and mutant mice was isolated by sucrose density gradient centrifugation, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Larocca and Norton, 2007</xref>). Briefly, spinal cords were transferred in suspension buffer (0.3 M sucrose containing as adjuvants 20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT, 100 µM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF), 10 µg/ml leupeptin, and 10 µg/ml antipain) and tissue disrupted in a glass and stainless steel homogenizer. The homogenate was layered onto a 0.83 M sucrose solution with the same adjuvants, and centrifuged at 75000 g for 30 min at RT. The obtained white band of crude myelin membranes was collected and subjected to three cycles of osmotic shock in 20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4 with adjuvants, 1x at 75000 g and 2x at 12000 g at 4°C. Myelin pellets were resuspended in suspension buffer and subjected to a repetition of density centrifugation and osmotic shock. Finally, obtained myelin pellets were resuspended in 0.83 M sucrose solution with adjuvants. This was overlaid with suspension buffer and centrifuged at 75000 g for 30 min at 4°C. The myelin fraction was subjected to a last repetition of osmotic shock and the pellet resuspended in Tris-HCl buffer and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. Purified myelin was stored at −80°C until further processing.</p><p>Lipid standards were obtained from Avanti Polar Lipids (Alabaster, AL, USA). Analysis of lipid species was performed according to published methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Fauland et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Triebl et al., 2017</xref>). Samples were extracted with methyl tert-butyl ether (MTBE) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Matyash et al., 2008</xref>). Lipid extracts were evaporated and resuspended in 1 ml chloroform/methanol (1/1; v/v). Each lipid extract was then split for analysis of total fatty acids (350 µl), positive ESI LC-MS/MS (18 µl) and negative ESI LC-MS/MS (18 µl). Lipid extracts for LC-MS/MS analysis were evaporated, spiked with a mix of quantitative LIPID MAPS internal standards and 2 µl of spiked samples were injected onto a Thermo 1.9 µm Hypersil GOLD C8, 100 × 1 mm HPLC column mounted in an Dionex Ultimate 3000 UHPLC instrument (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Data acquisition was performed by Orbitrap Velos Pro (Thermo Fisher Scientific) full scans at a resolution of 100 k and &lt;5 ppm mass accuracy with external calibration. Nominal mass resolution product ion spectra were acquired in preview mode at the LTQ. A chromatography with Electron Impact Mass Spectrometry (GC-EI/MS) of Total fatty acids (free + esterified) were determined by gas chromatography - electron impact mass spectrometry (GC-EI/MS). Lipid extracts were dried and suspended in 1 ml methanolic NaOH. After 10 min incubation at 80°C, samples were cooled for 5 min on ice. Then, 1 ml BF<sub>3</sub> was added and incubated for 10 min at 80°C. Fatty acid methyl esters were extracted with 1 ml saturated NaCl and 2 ml hexane. The hexane phase was dried and methyl esters dissolved in 1.5 ml hexane. A Trace-DSQ GC-MS (Thermo Fisher Scientific) equipped with a 30 m column (model TR-FAME, Thermo Fisher Scientific) was used for analysis. Helium was used as carrier gas at a flow of 1.3 ml/min, in split mode, at 250°C injector temperature. Initial oven temperature of 150°C was held for 0.5 min and then temperature was increased to 180°C at a rate of 10 °C/min. This was followed by a further increase to 190°C at a rate of 0.5 °C/min and then increased to 250°C at a rate of 40 °C/min and kept for 3 min. The mass spectrometer was run in EI mode and fatty acids were detected in full scan of m/z 80–400. Source temperature was set to 250°C and the transfer line temperature to 200°C. Internal standards used in LC-MS were (product number, lipid shorthand nomenclature, amount/sample): LM-1100, PE 12:0/13:0, 160 pmol; LM-1102, PE 17:0/20:4, 160 pmol; LM-1103, PE 21:0/22:6, 160 pmol; LM-1104, PE 17:0/14:1, 160 pmol; LM-1302, PS 17:0/20:4, 240 pmol; LM-1300, PS 12:0/13:0, 240 pmol; LM-1304, PS 17:0/14:1, 240 pmol; LM-1000, PC 12:0/13:0, 200 pmol; LM-1002, PC 17:0/20:4, 200 pmol; LM-1003, PC 21:0/22:6, 200 pmol; LM-1004, PC 17:0/14:1, 200 pmol; LM-1601, LPC 17:1, 80 pmol; LM-6002, sphingolipid mix, 120 pmol; LM-1500, PI 12:0/13:0, 320 pmol; LM-1502, PI 17:0/20:4, 320 pmol; LM-1504, PI 17:0/14:1, 320 pmol.</p><p>LC = liquid chromatography, ESI = electrospray ionization, MS = mass spectrometry, FT-ICR = Fourier transform ion cyclotron resonance, GC = gas chromatography, EI = electron impact, DSQ = dual stage quadrupole, m/z = mass/ charge number, LM-n = Lipid Maps-ID number, PE = phosphatidylethanolamine, PS = phosphatidylserine, PC = phosphatidylcholine, PI = phosphatidylinositol.</p><p>Data were processed by Lipid Data Analyzer software as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hartler et al., 2017</xref>), relying on exact mass, retention time and MS/MS spectra. Annotation of lipid species followed the shorthand nomenclature of the International Lipid Classification and Nomenclature Committee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Liebisch et al., 2013</xref>). During lipid extraction procedure, the fraction containing proteins was lyophilized. Proteins were dissolved in lysis buffer (1% Rapigest (Waters/Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA), Tris pH 7.4, 0.1 mM EDTA) and quantified on a Nanodrop Lite (Nanodrop Technologies, Thermo Fisher Scientific) spectrophotometer. Lipid amounts were normalized to the sample total protein content.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Sequencing</title><p>Total RNA was isolated with a Qiagen MiniKit according to manufacturer’s protocols, quantity and quality were determined with Nanodrop Lite (NanoDrop Technologies, Thermo Fisher Scientific), Qubit 2.0 Fluorometer (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and Bioanalyzer 2100 (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA). The TruSeq Stranded mRNA Sample Prep Kit (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) was used in the succeeding steps. Briefly, poly-A containing RNA molecules were purified from the total RNA samples (100 ng) using oligo-dT attached magnetic beads. Isolated RNA was reverse-transcribed into double-stranded cDNA, with actinomycin added during first-strand synthesis. The cDNA samples were fragmented, end repaired and polyadenylated before ligation of TruSeq adapters. Fragments containing TruSeq adapters on both ends were selectively enriched with PCR. The quality and quantity of the enriched libraries were validated using Qubit 2.0 Fluorometer and Bioanalyzer 2100. The product is a smear with an average fragment size of approximately 360 bp. The libraries were normalized to 10 nM in Tris-Cl 10 mM, pH 8.5 with 0.1% Tween-20. Sequencing was performed on an Illumina HiSeq 4000 in single end 125 bp mode. The raw reads were first cleaned by removing adapter sequences, trimming low quality ends, and filtering reads with low quality (phred quality &lt;20). Read-alignment was done with STAR (v2.5.1b). Ensembl genome build GRCm38 was used as reference and gene annotations downloaded on 2015-06-25 from Ensembl. Applied STAR alignment options were: OutFilterType BySJout, outFilter MatchNmin30, outFilter Mismatch Nmax10, outFilter MismatchNoverLmax0.05, alignSJDB overhangMin1, aligns overhangMin8, alignIntron Max1000000, alignMatesGap Max1000000, outFilterMultimapN max50. Quantification of gene level expression was carried out using RSEM (v1.2.22) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Li and Dewey, 2011</xref>). Differential expression was computed using the generalized linear model implemented in the Bioconductor package EdgeR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Robinson et al., 2010</xref>). To correct for multiple testing, the Benjamini-Hochberg algorithm was applied and adjusted p-values computed. Only significantly differentially expressed transcripts (FDR ≤ 0.05, no fold change threshold) were loaded onto Metacore (vs6.33) for enrichment analysis of GeneOntology processes and Metacore pathways.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>qRT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA was isolated with a Qiagen MiniKit according to the manufacturer’s protocols; quantity and quality were determined with Nanodrop Lite (NanoDrop Technologies). RNA samples were reverse-transcribed to cDNA with oligo(dT) random primers in the presence of RNaseOUT (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) with the Maxima RT kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). Targeted sequences were amplified with exon/exon boundary-spanning probes and detected by measurement of SYBRgreen on a LightCycler 480 (Roche, Switzerland). Cp values were determined with the LightCycler 480 software (Roche, Switzerland). Primers used were: SOX10 Forward 5’-CCGACCAGTACCCTCACCT-3’, Reverse 5’-TCAATGAAGGGGCGCTTGT-3’, MYRF Forward 5’-ATGGAGGTGGTGGACGAGAC-3’, Reverse 5’-GGCGTCCTCTTTGCCAATGT-3’, MBP Forward 5’-ACACGAGAACTACCCATTATGGC-3’, Reverse 5’-CCAGCTAAATCTGCTGAGGGGA-3’, Actin Forward 5’-GTCCACACCCGCCACC-3’, Reverse 5’-GGCCTCGTCACCCACATAG-3’.</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All experiments were quantified blindly to the genotype and treatment group. Statistics were analyzed using GraphPad Prism vs6.01. Data were assumed to be normally distributed, but not formally tested. Variance was assumed to be equal between groups of data. No statistical methods were used to predetermine sample size, but our sample sizes are similar than those generally employed in the field. Statistical significance was determined using an unpaired two-tailed two sample Student’s t-test for two group comparisons. Multiple groups analysis was performed with analysis of variance (ANOVA) and post-hoc test as detailed in text and figures. Data show mean ±SEM. Significance was set at p&lt;0.05 *, p&lt;0.01 **, p&lt;0.001 ***.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Data availability</title><p>RNA-sequencing data are available on NCBI’s GEO database, accession number GSE112725.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank all members of the Suter lab for data discussion, the Functional Genomic Center of Zürich and the ScopeM imaging facility of ETH Zürich for excellent technical support. We also thank Drs. William Richardson and David Rowitch for transgenic mice and advice. This work was supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNF) to US. LM was supported by a SNF Marie-Heim-Voegtlin fellowship (PMPDP3 139610).</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>Resources, Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con9"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Data curation, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Project administration, Writing—review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Animal experimentation: All animal experiments were performed with the approval and in strict accordance with the guidelines of the Zurich Cantonal Veterinary Office (Permit Numbers ZH161/2014, ZH090/2017, ZH03/2012, ZH264/2014, ZH207/2017).</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.025</object-id><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-44702-transrepform-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Sequencing data have been deposited in GEO under accession code GSE112725. All data generated or analysed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files. Source data files have been provided for Figure 5.</p><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><element-citation id="dataset1" publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><data-title>Role of fatty acid synthase in oligodendrocyte myelination</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id assigning-authority="NCBI" pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE112725">GSE112725</pub-id></element-citation></p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmadian</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hah</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liddle</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Downes</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Pparγ signaling and metabolism: the good, the bad and the future</article-title><source>Nature Medicine</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.3159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23652116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bercury</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachs</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahrendsen</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Macklin</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Conditional ablation of raptor or rictor has differential impact on oligodendrocyte differentiation and CNS myelination</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>4466</fpage><lpage>4480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4314-13.2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24671993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blakemore</surname> <given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Remyelination in experimental models of toxin-induced demyelination</article-title><source>Current Topics in Microbiology and Immunology</source><volume>318</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-540-73677-6_8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18219819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bujalka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Koenning</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Perreau</surname> <given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pope</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitew</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>QR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wegner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Svaren</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Willingham</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barres</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>MYRF is a membrane-associated transcription factor that autoproteolytically cleaves to directly activate myelin genes</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1001625</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23966833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camargo</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Brouwers</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Loos</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutmann</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Smit</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Verheijen</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>High-fat diet ameliorates neurological deficits caused by defective astrocyte lipid metabolism</article-title><source>The FASEB Journal</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>4302</fpage><lpage>4315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.12-205807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22751013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camargo</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Goudriaan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van Deijk</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Otte</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brouwers</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lodder</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutmann</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nave</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dijkhuizen</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansvelder</surname> <given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chrast</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smit</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Verheijen</surname> <given-names>MHG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Oligodendroglial myelination requires astrocyte-derived lipids</article-title><source>PLOS Biology</source><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e1002605</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1002605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28549068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakravarthy</surname> <given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tordjman</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Turk</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Semenkovich</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>&quot;New&quot; hepatic fat activates PPARalpha to maintain glucose, lipid, and cholesterol homeostasis</article-title><source>Cell Metabolism</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2005.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16054078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chrast</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Saher</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nave</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Verheijen</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Lipid metabolism in myelinating glial cells: lessons from human inherited disorders and mouse models</article-title><source>Journal of Lipid Research</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.R009761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21062955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname> <given-names>KLH</given-names></name><name><surname>Early</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Drug discovery for remyelination and treatment of MS</article-title><source>Glia</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>1565</fpage><lpage>1589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.23166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28618073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Foerster</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kougioumtzidou</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grist</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Pre-Existing mature oligodendrocytes do not contribute to remyelination following Toxin-Induced spinal cord demyelination</article-title><source>The American Journal of Pathology</source><volume>186</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajpath.2015.11.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26773350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Currie</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zechner</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Walther</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Farese</surname> <given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Cellular fatty acid metabolism and cancer</article-title><source>Cell Metabolism</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2013.05.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23791484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dimou</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>NG2-glia and their functions in the central nervous system</article-title><source>Glia</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>1429</fpage><lpage>1451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.22859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26010717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dimou</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Diversity of oligodendrocytes and their progenitors</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2017.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29078110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fancy</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrington</surname> <given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuen</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Silbereis</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranzini</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruce</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Otero</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusse</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowitch</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Axin2 as regulatory and therapeutic target in newborn brain injury and remyelination</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>1009</fpage><lpage>1016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21706018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fauland</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Köfeler</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Trötzmüller</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopf</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartler</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberl</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitraju</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lankmayr</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Spener</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>A comprehensive method for lipid profiling by liquid chromatography-ion cyclotron resonance mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Journal of Lipid Research</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>2314</fpage><lpage>2322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.D016550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21960706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname> <given-names>RJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ffrench-Constant</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Regenerating CNS myelin - from mechanisms to experimental medicines</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>769</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn.2017.136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29142295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fünfschilling</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Supplie</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahad</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Boretius</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saab</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgar</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinkmann</surname> <given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassmann</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzvetanova</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Möbius</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Suter</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamprecht</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sereda</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Moraes</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Frahm</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goebbels</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nave</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Glycolytic oligodendrocytes maintain myelin and long-term axonal integrity</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>485</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22622581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harayama</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Riezman</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Understanding the diversity of membrane lipid composition</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm.2017.138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29410529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartler</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Triebl</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegl</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trötzmüller</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rechberger</surname> <given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeleznik</surname> <given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zierler</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Torta</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cazenave-Gassiot</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenk</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauland</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheelock</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Armando</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Quehenberger</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakelam</surname> <given-names>MJO</given-names></name><name><surname>Haemmerle</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Spener</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Köfeler</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thallinger</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Deciphering lipid structures based on platform-independent decision rules</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>1174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29058722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herbert</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Monk</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Advances in myelinating glial cell development</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2016.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27930937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hornig</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fröb</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogl</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermans-Borgmeyer</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamm</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Wegner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The transcription factors Sox10 and myrf define an essential regulatory network module in differentiating oligodendrocytes</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e1003907</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klingseisen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Axonal regulation of central nervous system myelination: structure and function</article-title><source>The Neuroscientist</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073858417703030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28397586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knobloch</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zurkirchen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>von Schoultz</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamboni</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Araúzo-Bravo</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Karalay</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Suter</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roccio</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lutolf</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Semenkovich</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessberger</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Metabolic control of adult neural stem cell activity by Fasn-dependent lipogenesis</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>493</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23201681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laplante</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>mTOR signaling in growth control and disease</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>149</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.03.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22500797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larocca</surname> <given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Norton</surname> <given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Isolation of myelin</article-title><source>Current Protocols in Cell Biology</source><volume>25</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/0471143030.cb0325s33</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebrun-Julien</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachmann</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Norrmén</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trötzmüller</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Köfeler</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rüegg</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname> <given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Suter</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Balanced mTORC1 activity in oligodendrocytes is required for accurate CNS myelination</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>8432</fpage><lpage>8448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1105-14.2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24948799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lengacher</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Farah</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname> <given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsingalia</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellerin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Magistretti</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothstein</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Oligodendroglia metabolically support axons and contribute to neurodegeneration</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>487</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22801498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewey</surname> <given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>323</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Evolution of the CNS myelin gene regulatory program</article-title><source>Brain Research</source><volume>1641</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2015.10.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26474911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liebisch</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vizcaíno</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Köfeler</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Trötzmüller</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Spener</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakelam</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Shorthand notation for lipid structures derived from mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Journal of Lipid Research</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.M033506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23549332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lodhi</surname> <given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Semenkovich</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Peroxisomes: a nexus for lipid metabolism and cellular signaling</article-title><source>Cell Metabolism</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2014.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24508507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marques</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeisel</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Codeluppi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>van Bruggen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendanha Falcão</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Häring</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochgerner</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanov</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gyllborg</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Muñoz Manchado</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>La Manno</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lönnerberg</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Floriddia</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezayee</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernfors</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenas</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hjerling-Leffler</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harkany</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Linnarsson</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Castelo-Branco</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Oligodendrocyte heterogeneity in the mouse juvenile and adult central nervous system</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>352</volume><fpage>1326</fpage><lpage>1329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaf6463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27284195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matyash</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebisch</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurzchalia</surname> <given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Shevchenko</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwudke</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Lipid extraction by methyl-tert-butyl ether for high-throughput lipidomics</article-title><source>Journal of Lipid Research</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.D700041-JLR200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18281723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miron</surname> <given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Microglia-driven regulation of oligodendrocyte lineage cells, Myelination, and remyelination</article-title><source>Journal of Leukocyte Biology</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>1103</fpage><lpage>1108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1189/jlb.3RI1116-494R</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28250011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montani</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Norrmén</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohl</surname> <given-names>HBF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinelli</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Trötzmüller</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Figlia</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimas</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>von Niederhäusern</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwager</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessberger</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Semenkovich</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Köfeler</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Suter</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>De novo fatty acid synthesis by schwann cells is essential for peripheral nervous system myelination</article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>217</volume><fpage>1353</fpage><lpage>1368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201706010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29434029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nave</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname> <given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Myelination of the nervous system: mechanisms and functions</article-title><source>Annual Review of Cell and Developmental Biology</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-cellbio-100913-013101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25288117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osso</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Architecting the myelin landscape</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2017.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28709021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porstmann</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cully</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leevers</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname> <given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>SREBP activity is regulated by mTORC1 and contributes to Akt-dependent cell growth</article-title><source>Cell Metabolism</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2008.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18762023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Resh</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Fatty acylation of proteins: the long and the short of it</article-title><source>Progress in Lipid Research</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plipres.2016.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27233110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rivers</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizzi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamen</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Psachoulia</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wade</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessaris</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>PDGFRA/NG2 glia generate myelinating oligodendrocytes and piriform projection neurons in adult mice</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1392</fpage><lpage>1401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18849983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>edgeR: a bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saab</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nave</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Myelin dynamics: protecting and shaping neuronal functions</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2017.09.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29065345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saher</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brügger</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappe-Siefke</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Möbius</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tozawa</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehr</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieland</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishibashi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nave</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>High cholesterol level is essential for myelin membrane growth</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn1426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15793579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saher</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudolphi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Corthals</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruhwedel</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Löwel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dibaj</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrette</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Möbius</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nave</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Therapy of Pelizaeus-Merzbacher disease in mice by feeding a cholesterol-enriched diet</article-title><source>Nature Medicine</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1130</fpage><lpage>1135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.2833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22706386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salaun</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaves</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chamberlain</surname> <given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The intracellular dynamic of protein palmitoylation</article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>191</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>1238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201008160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21187327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantuti Castelvetri</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Metabolism and functions of lipids in myelin</article-title><source>Biochimica Et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - Molecular and Cell Biology of Lipids</source><volume>1851</volume><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2014.12.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schüller</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Heine</surname> <given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kho</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillon</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname> <given-names>YG</given-names></name><name><surname>Huillard</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ligon</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez-Buylla</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowitch</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ligon</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Acquisition of granule neuron precursor identity is a critical determinant of progenitor cell competence to form Shh-induced medulloblastoma</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2008.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18691547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sedel</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mock</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tourbah</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Targeting demyelination and virtual hypoxia with high-dose biotin as a treatment for progressive multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2015.08.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26327679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simons</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Misgeld</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerschensteiner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A unified cell biological perspective on axon-myelin injury</article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>206</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201404154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25092654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivas</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>William</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanabe</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessell</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantini</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Cre reporter strains produced by targeted insertion of EYFP and ECFP into the ROSA26 locus</article-title><source>BMC Developmental Biology</source><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>4</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-213X-1-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11299042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Triebl</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trötzmüller</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartler</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stojakovic</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Köfeler</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Lipidomics by ultrahigh performance liquid chromatography-high resolution mass spectrometry and its application to complex biological samples</article-title><source>Journal of Chromatography B</source><volume>1053</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jchromb.2017.03.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turnescu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Arter</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiprich</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamm</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Waisman</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wegner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Sox8 and Sox10 jointly maintain myelin gene expression in oligodendrocytes</article-title><source>Glia</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.23242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29023979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>McLane</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bercury</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Macklin</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Mammalian target of rapamycin promotes oligodendrocyte differentiation, initiation and extent of CNS myelination</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>4453</fpage><lpage>4465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4311-13.2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24671992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zawadzka</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivers</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fancy</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamen</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncharevich</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohl</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizzi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowitch</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessaris</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Suter</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>CNS-resident glial progenitor/stem cells produce schwann cells as well as oligodendrocytes during repair of CNS demyelination</article-title><source>Cell Stem Cell</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2010.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20569695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloan</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholze</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Keeffe</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Phatnani</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Guarnieri</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Caneda</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruderisch</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liddelow</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Daneman</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Barres</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>JQ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>An RNA-sequencing transcriptome and splicing database of glia, neurons, and vascular cells of the cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>11929</fpage><lpage>11947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1860-14.2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25186741</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.029</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bergles</surname><given-names>Dwight E</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>Teresa</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>Rutgers</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;CNS myelination and remyelination depend on fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by Marianne Bronner as the Senior Editor, a Reviewing Editor, and two reviewers. The following individuals involved in review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Teresa Wood (Reviewer #2).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>This study explored the role of fatty acid synthesis in the development of oligodendrocytes and myelin during early postnatal life in mice, and remyelination in the adult CNS. The authors conditionally deleted fatty acid synthase (FASN) from oligodendrocyte progenitors (OPCs) in the developing CNS and found that while this did not impair the proliferation and differentiation of OPCs, it slowed the process of myelination, altered the lipid composition of myelin and disrupted myelin integrity. This delay in myelination was partially reversed by feeding FASN cKO mice a high fat diet. Deletion of FASN from OPCs in the adult CNS similarly impaired the regeneration of myelin sheaths. Together, these findings indicate that de novo fatty acid synthesis is critical for both developmental myelination and remyelination.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) The authors should quantify the percentage recombination and knockout of FASN in both their developmental model and tamoxifen inducible model. They have the tools to do so and may even have the data to hand in tissue collected. This is particularly important in addressing the apparent diversity in phenotype between optic nerve and spinal cord, and in the difference in phenotypic severity of developmental myelination and remyelination in the spinal cord.</p><p>Could such differences be explained simply by recombination efficiency?</p><p>If recombination efficiency is similar in spinal cord and optic nerve, the authors should still discuss whether the difference they see there in developmental myelination really reflects intrinsic differences in oligodendrocytes, as suggested, or possibly local differences in astrocyte coupling etc.</p><p>2) Figure 3: EM analysis shows an increase in unmyelinated axons in mutant mice. The authors conclude that FASN is critical for timely onset of myelination. However, the decrease in myelinated axons may not be due to timing of onset, especially since recovery does not occur at P180. Since oligodendrocytes wrap multiple axons per cell, the phenotype could also be attributed to less myelin being produced by each mutant oligodendrocyte and/or fewer myelin sheaths. Another possibility is that the aberrant myelin observed in the mutants reduces their ability to wrap the same number of axon segments. Wording should be altered to reflect other possible conclusions from the EM data.</p><p>3) Figure 3—figure supplement 1: The authors address possible differential dependence on FASN by studying myelin in the spinal cord and optic nerve and conclude that FASN is critical in diverse OL populations. Do the authors have any information from their existing samples on the corpus callosum to strengthen this conclusion?</p><p>4) Figure 8: It is unclear whether the decrease in CC1+ cells at 14 and 21 dpl is due to a deficit in the OPC population, a differentiation deficit, or cell death. TUNEL staining may capture more dying cells than cC3 staining and should be paired with a marker for OPCs and a marker for mature OLs to determine which population is affected. Some information on this could be accomplished on existing tissues. The authors should try to increase their &quot;n&quot; for the experiment assessing the contribution of cell death to the phenotypes observed in oligodendrocyte number in mutants during remyelination. It is great that the authors show actual data points, but this reveals huge diversity in Figure 8—figure supplement 3D and E, and I strongly suspect that this experiment would not have had sufficient power to detect a statistically significant increase in cell death, which is indeed suggested by the large fold increase. I appreciate that achieving high statistical power in mammalian in vivo experiments is challenging, but I think this issue needs to be acknowledged. At the very least the authors should discuss this point, lest they run the risk of conveying a potentially misleading false negative.</p><p>5) Figure 8: The observed reduction in recombined OPCs in FASN mutants during remyelination (subsection “Increased dietary intake of lipids can partially rescue lack of fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes”) needs to be further discussed. It is interesting that developmental OPCs are unaffected, but adult OPCs show a deficit during remyelination.</p><p>6) Is it possible for the authors to try a high fat diet supplementation following remyelination? This could help assess whether lipid synthesis is a bottleneck to remyelination. Apologies if this has been tested in the past by others, but, if not, this could be a timely opportunity to do so. The authors discuss their surprise in observing a strong phenotype observed for remyelination in the FASN inducible mutants. However, it is possible that the dietary support, or shuttling through astrocytes is actually compromised by the environment of a demyelinating lesion, and it would be interesting to see if high fat diet could help circumvent any such disruption.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44702.030</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) The authors should quantify the percentage recombination and knockout of FASN in both their developmental model and tamoxifen inducible model. They have the tools to do so and may even have the data to hand in tissue collected. This is particularly important in addressing the apparent diversity in phenotype between optic nerve and spinal cord, and in the difference in phenotypic severity of developmental myelination and remyelination in the spinal cord.</p><p>Could such differences be explained simply by recombination efficiency?</p><p>If recombination efficiency is similar in spinal cord and optic nerve, the authors should still discuss whether the difference they see there in developmental myelination really reflects intrinsic differences in oligodendrocytes, as suggested, or possibly local differences in astrocyte coupling etc.</p></disp-quote><p>We have now quantified the recombination percentages using a Cre-dependent reporter allele (since FASN protein was barely detectable in oligodendrocyte progenitor cells). The corresponding data have been added to the revised manuscript (Figure 1—figure supplement 1, Figure 3—figure supplement 1, and Figure 7—figure supplement 1). Accordingly, we have also adjusted the text. However, we have refrained from making potentially over-interpreting statements based on our findings. This choice relates to the highly relevant points raised by the reviewers about potential oligodendrocyte-intrinsic versus local tissue differences in the various regions. Indeed, our evaluation of various myelinated regions was intended to examine whether FASN expression is in principle required for anatomically differently located oligodendrocytes. Thus, the main conclusion of our analysis is that accurate developmental myelination in the spinal cord, the optic nerve, and in the corpus callosum (see answer to point 3 below) depends on FASN expressed by oligodendrocytes. To which extent our findings in the different regions might relate to different environments and physiological contexts, or might be due to potential intrinsic differences between oligodendrocyte lineage cells, remains to be investigated. We have altered the wording in the revised manuscript to reflect these points more clearly. We thank the reviewers for indicating this potential misunderstanding out to us.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) Figure 3: EM analysis shows an increase in unmyelinated axons in mutant mice. The authors conclude that FASN is critical for timely onset of myelination. However, the decrease in myelinated axons may not be due to timing of onset, especially since recovery does not occur at P180. Since oligodendrocytes wrap multiple axons per cell, the phenotype could also be attributed to less myelin being produced by each mutant oligodendrocyte and/or fewer myelin sheaths. Another possibility is that the aberrant myelin observed in the mutants reduces their ability to wrap the same number of axon segments. Wording should be altered to reflect other possible conclusions from the EM data.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree that our wording in this context was not optimal. Thus, we have ameliorated the text to provide a more precise description of the various possibilities, following the valuable suggestions of the reviewers. We thank the reviewers for this input.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) Figure 3—figure supplement 1: The authors address possible differential dependence on FASN by studying myelin in the spinal cord and optic nerve and conclude that FASN is critical in diverse OL populations. Do the authors have any information from their existing samples on the corpus callosum to strengthen this conclusion?</p></disp-quote><p>We have now analyzed the corpus callosum. The corresponding results, revealing that correct myelination in this region is also dependent on FASN expression by oligodendrocytes, have been added to the manuscript (Figure 3—figure supplement 3, and text).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) Figure 8: It is unclear whether the decrease in CC1+ cells at 14 and 21 dpl is due to a deficit in the OPC population, a differentiation deficit, or cell death. TUNEL staining may capture more dying cells than cC3 staining and should be paired with a marker for OPCs and a marker for mature OLs to determine which population is affected. Some information on this could be accomplished on existing tissues. The authors should try to increase their &quot;n&quot; for the experiment assessing the contribution of cell death to the phenotypes observed in oligodendrocyte number in mutants during remyelination. It is great that the authors show actual data points, but this reveals huge diversity in Figure 8—figure supplement 3D and E, and I strongly suspect that this experiment would not have had sufficient power to detect a statistically significant increase in cell death, which is indeed suggested by the large fold increase. I appreciate that achieving high statistical power in mammalian in vivo experiments is challenging, but I think this issue needs to be acknowledged. At the very least the authors should discuss this point, lest they run the risk of conveying a potentially misleading false negative.</p></disp-quote><p>We have dedicated substantial efforts to characterize cell death in the oligodendrocyte lineage. Beyond the data included in the manuscript, which consists of the percentage of CC1+ YFP+ cC3+ oligodendrocytes at 11 dpl, we have also assessed:</p><p>a) The population of CC1- YFP+ cC3+ not-differentiated oligodendrocytes and found only one positive cell in one of the animals analyzed (quantified on the same images which generated the data included in the manuscript, at 11 dpl).</p><p>b) Additional time points (10 dpI, 12 dpl; analysis of sections covering the entire lesions in 3 control and 3 i-cMU mice) revealed no YFP+ Cc3+ cells.</p><p>We also tested three different TUNEL protocols and assay kits from two independent manufacturer's, but unfortunately, none of these methods enabled, in our hands, robust co-staining of TUNEL with antibodies recognizing either YFP or CC1. As the careful comparative analysis of cell death in controls versus mutants mandates the colocalization of apoptosis markers with oligodendrocyte lineage cells and a recombination marker, we are unable to draw firm conclusions from these experiments.</p><p>Despite our best efforts, and also due to technical limitations of the experiments and available tools, we consider it unlikely that extending the analysis to increase “n” would provide a satisfying answer in this context. However, as suggested by the reviewer, we acknowledge now this limitation of our analysis explicitly in the revised manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) Figure 8: The observed reduction in recombined OPCs in FASN mutants during remyelination (subsection “Increased dietary intake of lipids can partially rescue lack of fatty acid synthesis by oligodendrocytes”) needs to be further discussed. It is interesting that developmental OPCs are unaffected, but adult OPCs show a deficit during remyelination.</p></disp-quote><p>We discuss this issue now in the revised manuscript in condensed form. One interpretation of our findings is that the observed decrease in CC1+ recombined OLs in mutant animals during remyelination promotes a mild reaction from the aOPCs, potentially with the goal of some compensation. If the recombined cells cannot be sustained and die while differentiating from aOPCs towards myelinating oligodendrocytes, this may cause a slight reduction of the remaining numbers of recombined aOPCs. Alternatively, aOPCs may have intrinsic differences in their dependency on FASN compared to developmental OPCs with regard to survival. We consider this less likely given the low expression of FASN by developmental OPCs and aOPCs.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>6) Is it possible for the authors to try a high fat diet supplementation following remyelination? This could help assess whether lipid synthesis is a bottleneck to remyelination. Apologies if this has been tested in the past by others, but, if not, this could be a timely opportunity to do so. The authors discuss their surprise in observing a strong phenotype observed for remyelination in the FASN inducible mutants. However, it is possible that the dietary support, or shuttling through astrocytes is actually compromised by the environment of a demyelinating lesion, and it would be interesting to see if high fat diet could help circumvent any such disruption.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with the reviewers that such studies are highly interesting, including investigations of the conceptual issue of lipid flux from the diet to oligodendrocytes in the context of remyelinating lesions, taking into account shuttling through astrocytes. However, such a study is quite challenging to perform accurately. Mainly due to the complexity of the lesion setting (including potential damage to the blood-CNS barrier), the accurate selection of the experimental conditions and the interpretation of the study will be demanding, not the least since high fat diet supplementation is likely to influence inflammation and potentially other variables. Thus, we feel that such an analysis requires a rather extensive dedicated research project on its own to yield comprehensive and robust results.</p></body></sub-article></article>