<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">63810</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.63810</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology and Infectious Disease</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Infection with a newly designed dual fluorescent reporter HIV-1 effectively identifies latently infected CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-211036"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Jinfeng</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8356-030X</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-211037"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Hongbo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-143110"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jiacong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-223935"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Shujing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-223936"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Xinyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-211038"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yanyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-223937"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Zhuanglin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-211039"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Zhongsi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-210361"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9973-8130</contrib-id><email>dengkai6@mail.sysu.edu.cn</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund4"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund5"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund6"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con9"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Institute of Human Virology, Key Laboratory of Tropical Disease Control of Ministry of Education, Zhongshan School of Medicine, Sun Yat-sen University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Guangzhou</named-content></addr-line><country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Immunology, Zhongshan School of Medicine, Sun Yat-sen University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Guangzhou</named-content></addr-line><country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Infectious Diseases, Fifth Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Zhuhai</named-content></addr-line><country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>Miles P</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>University of New South Wales</institution><country>Australia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Symons</surname><given-names>Jori</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University Medical Center</institution><country>Netherlands</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>09</day><month>04</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e63810</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2020-10-07"><day>07</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2021-04-04"><day>04</day><month>04</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021, Cai et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cai et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-63810-v2.pdf"/><abstract><p>The major barrier to curing HIV-1 infection is a small pool of latently infected cells that harbor replication-competent viruses, which are widely considered the origin of viral rebound when antiretroviral therapy (ART) is interrupted. The difficulty in distinguishing latently infected cells from the vast majority of uninfected cells has represented a significant bottleneck precluding comprehensive understandings of HIV-1 latency. Here we reported and validated a newly designed dual fluorescent reporter virus, DFV-B, infection with which primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells can directly label latently infected cells and generate a latency model that was highly physiological relevant. Applying DFV-B infection in Jurkat T cells, we generated a stable cell line model of HIV-1 latency with diverse viral integration sites. High-throughput compound screening with this model identified ACY-1215 as a potent latency reversing agent, which could be verified in other cell models and in primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from ART-suppressed individuals ex vivo. In summary, we have generated a meaningful and feasible model to directly study latently infected cells, which could open up new avenues to explore the critical events of HIV-1 latency and become a valuable tool for the research of AIDS functional cure.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>HIV-1</kwd><kwd>latent infection</kwd><kwd>cell model</kwd><kwd>latency reversing agent</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Human</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>81672024</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100012166</institution-id><institution>National Basic Research Program of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2018ZX10302103</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100012166</institution-id><institution>National Basic Research Program of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2017ZX10202102</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund4"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>32070159</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund5"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003453</institution-id><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2017A030306005</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund6"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Guangdong Innovative and Entrepreneurial Research Team Program</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2016ZT06S638</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>A novel reporter model system serves as a valuable tool for studying latent HIV-1 infection and identifies potent latency reversing agent.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Despite antiretroviral therapy (ART) efficiently blocks productive HIV-1 replication, viruses persist in a small pool of latently infected CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, which are widely considered the major barrier to curing HIV-1 infection. These latently infected cells harbor transcriptional silent but replication-competent proviral genome, which was demonstrated to be the origin of rapid viral rebound after ART is interrupted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Finzi et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Chun et al., 2008</xref>). Latently infected CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are essentially indistinguishable from uninfected cells and are therefore not recognized by immune responses, including broadly neutralizing antibodies or cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs). Current technologies also do not allow direct identification or purification of live latently infected cells from the infected individuals on ART. It is therefore vitally important to create novel and physiological relevant cell models of HIV-1 latency, which can be further exploited to study the mechanisms underlying HIV-1 latency and to develop novel strategies for AIDS functional cure.</p><p>The difficulty in distinguishing latently infected cells from the vast majority of uninfected cells has represented a major bottleneck precluding comprehensive understandings of HIV-1 latency. To tackle this question, researchers have tried to establish reporter virus systems to differentiate productively and latently infected cells. The reporter viruses usually incorporate two fluorescent proteins, with one dependent on LTR activity while the other under the control of a constitutive promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Calvanese et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dahabieh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Battivelli et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Kim et al., 2019</xref>). However, some apparent defects existed with the previously reported systems, especially when infecting primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells: (a) unclear cell subpopulations, for example, the boundaries of productively infected cells were obscured (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Calvanese et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Battivelli et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Kim et al., 2019</xref>); (b) potential interference of cytokines on HIV-1 latency, as all infected cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dahabieh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Battivelli et al., 2018</xref>) were maintained in IL-2 containing medium for latency establishment; and (c) low frequency of reactivation of the identified latently infected cells, for instance, only 5% of HIV<sub>GKO</sub> cells were reactivated by bryostatin-1 and panobinostat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Battivelli et al., 2018</xref>), which bona fide limit its application to explore the mechanism of HIV latency maintenance and reactivation in vitro.</p><p>To improve on the cell model of HIV-1 latency, here we set up a newly designed dual fluorescent reporter virus, DFV-B, infection of which can distinguish latently infected from productively infected and uninfected cells. With DFV-B infection, we can sort out latently infected primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, in which more than 50% can be reactivated by subsequent PMA and ionomycin stimulation. We also showed that DFV-B infection in Jurkat cells can generate a bunch of stable latently infected cells (named J-mC cells), which were obtained by natural infection, therefore circumventing the clonal-derived biases of some previous cell lines like J-Lat. We went on to show that the J-mC system is a robust model of HIV-1 latency, as a high-throughput compound screening with this model successfully identifies a novel latency reversal agent (LRA) ACY-1215, whose activity could be verified in other cell models and in primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from ART-suppressed individuals. As an oral HDAC6-selective inhibitor, ACY-1215 has a higher safety and tolerability profile than the currently available pan-HDAC inhibitors such as SAHA or panobinastat, making it a promising LRA in future applications for HIV-1 functional cure.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>DFV-B infection directly identifies latently infected primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells</title><p>To specifically identify latently infected cells, we constructed a new reporter virus by engineering GFP and mCherry into the HIV-1 genome, in which GFP expression was controlled by LTR, while mCherry expression was independently controlled by the constitutive promoter EF-1α. This viral construct was named DFV-B (dual fluorescent virus-B) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). To test the infectivity of DFV-B, activated primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from HIV-1 naïve individuals were infected with DFV-B incorporating a CXCR4-tropic env (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Productively infected (double-positive, DP) and latently infected (single mCherry-positive, mC) CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were clearly distinguishable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>), and the percentage of the DP cells was roughly 16 times more than the single mC-positive cells on day 3 post-infection (p.i.) in STCM (Super T cell medium) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). To mimic the process of infected activated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells transitioning back to a more resting state, and monitor how the dynamics of productive and latent infection change during this process, DFV-B-infected cells were transferred to cytokine-free medium (CFM) on day 3 p.i. As culture time increased, the proportion of DP cells decreased significantly, while the proportion of mC cells gradually increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). mC cells accounted for up to 30% of the total infected cells on day 10 p.i. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>), suggesting some of the productively infected cells survived, reverted to a more resting state, and turned off viral gene (GFP) expression, which may add to the increased proportion of latently infected cells.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Infection with a newly designed dual fluorescent reporter HIV-1 identifies latently infected primary CD4<sup>+ </sup>T cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Diagram of the derivation of DFV-B from the original NL4-3 strain of HIV-1. Top panel depicts the genomic structure of HIV-1 NL4-3; bottom panel shows the genomic structure of DFV-B and the major modifications comparing to NL4-3. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative experiment of DFV-B infection in activated primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. Top panel depicts the scheme of experimental procedure. Isolated primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from HIV naïve individuals were stimulated with αCD3/αCD28 antibodies in the presence of IL-2 and TCGF for 3 days, and the activated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were then infected with DFV-B incorporating a CXCR4-tropic Env at the MOI of 0.1 to 1 for 3 days in STCM and were subsequently transferred to CFM. Bottom panel shows the infection profiles of stimulated primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells by DFV-B at indicated time points. (<bold>C</bold>) Data from panel B are displayed graphically. Line charts show the percentages of latent infection (mC) and productive infection (DP). Histogram represents the cell viability. Data indicate mean ± SD from three different donors. TCGF: T cell growth factor; CFM: cytokine-free medium; STCM: super T cell medium, CFM with IL-2 and TCGF.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><p>To validate the single mC-positive cells that were indeed latently infected, a series of experiments were performed as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>. We sorted the DP, the single mC-positive, and the double-negative (DN) cells by flow cytometry at 7 days post DFV-B infection and validated the purity of each population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A</xref>). The sorted mC cells were then cultured in CFM and activated by PMA and ionomycin for 3 days. During this process, the viability of mC cell population was more than 40% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Compared to the DMSO control, over 50% of total cells were converted from mC to DP cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), suggesting that more than half of the latently infected cells were reactivated. At the same time, DP and DN cells were not affected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). In addition, these sorted populations were analyzed for HIV-1 RNA and protein expression. As expected, the DP cells transcribed significantly higher amounts of HIV-1 mRNA, nearly 10 times as the mC cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). HIV-1 Gag and Vif protein production were detected by western blot in DP cells, but not in mC cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). To further verify that the absence of GFP production was due to viral latency but not possible genomic deletion, we quantified the cell-associated DNA and RNA of fluorescent protein from different populations respectively. Comparing to the uninfected DN cells, both GFP-DNA and mCherry-DNA were comparable between mC and DP cells, indicating no difference in viral integration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>). Meanwhile, levels of GFP mRNA in DP cells were much higher than that in mC cells, but mCherry mRNA levels remained the same (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>), consistent with the phenotypes observed by FACS. A small fraction of single GFP<sup>+</sup> cells existed after DFV-B infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>), and we traced and found that the proportion of single GFP<sup>+</sup> cells decreased from 0.7% to 0.2% (similar to uninfected cells) as the culture time increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1C</xref>), which is significantly lower than the previous reported dual reporter viral systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Calvanese et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Kim et al., 2019</xref>). The integrated DNA levels of GFP and mCherry in this single GFP<sup>+</sup> cells were not different (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1D</xref>), suggesting both reporters were still stably integrated. We speculated that this unlikely phenotype of single GFP<sup>+</sup> cells could be due to the differential dynamics of fluorescent protein degradation. Taken together, these results demonstrated that infection of DFV-B reporter virus in primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells could directly identify live latently infected cells.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Validation of the DFV-B infected mC population as latently infected primary CD4<sup>+ </sup>T cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic of experimental design. (<bold>B</bold>) Reactivation of the sorted different cell populations. Cells were cultured in CFM with 50 ng/ml PMA and 1 μM ionomycin and measured by flow cytometry 3 days later. Data shown from three different donors (mean ± SD). p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ***p&lt;0.001; ****p&lt;0.0001; ns, not significant. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of cell-associated HIV-1 mRNA of different sorted populations. HIV-1 mRNAs were measured by real-time qPCR. RNA copies were normalized to the uninfected group. Each symbol represents the mean of three replicates (n = 8). (<bold>D</bold>) Western blot analysis of HIV-1 protein production in different sorted cell populations. (<bold>E</bold>) Quantification of the cell-associated DNA and RNA of GFP and mCherry in the sorted populations. The DNA and mRNA of GFP and mCherry were quantified relative to cellular GAPDH, respectively. Data shown from three biological replicates (mean ± SD). p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ns, not significant; ****p&lt;0.0001.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>FACS sorting strategy and the viability of sorted cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) FACS sorting strategy of DFV-B infected primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. (<bold>B</bold>) Viability of sorted cells under different conditions. (<bold>C</bold>) The percentage of single GFP-positive cells in DFV-B infected CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. Data shown from three biological replicates (mean ± SD). (<bold>D</bold>) qPCR quantification of GFP-DNA and mCherry-DNA in the sorted single GFP positive cell population. DNA of GFP and mCherry were quantified relative to cellular GAPDH. Data shown from three biological replicates (mean ± SD). p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ns, not significant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig2-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>DFV-B infection confirms effector-to-memory transitioning (EMT) CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are the primary targets for latency establishment</title><p>The latent HIV-1 reservoir mainly resides in resting memory CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Chun et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Finzi et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chomont et al., 2009</xref>), but they are normally not the direct targets for infection, due to the blocks in reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Korin and Zack, 1998</xref>), integration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bukrinsky et al., 1992</xref>) and host restriction by SAMHD1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Baldauf et al., 2012</xref>). It has been recently demonstrated that HIV-1 latency was preferentially established in EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Shan et al., 2017</xref>). Therefore, we investigated whether DFV-B infection in EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells recapitulated the tendency of latency establishment. We first confirmed the primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were in the process of EMT after 5–7 days in CFM culture, as the expression of CD25/CD69/HLA-DR and T cell exhaustion markers (PD-1 and TIM-3) had been greatly reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A and B</xref>). mC cells expressed significantly lower levels of activation markers and exhaustion markers than DP cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C and D</xref>), again supporting our results that mC cells were latently infected. The infection profiles were then analyzed when infection was administered independently at different time points indicated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). In general, EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were less permissive to DFV-B infection; however, the ratio of mC cells to total infected cells (mC+DP) steadily increased from 15.7% (day 0 infection) to 64.8% (day 10 infection) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>). This data strongly supports that infection during EMT process of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells is most likely to generate latent infection, which also highlights the significance and applicability of our DFV-B system as a viable cell model for HIV-1 latency.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Effector-to-memory transitioning CD4<sup>+ </sup>T cells are the primary targets for HIV-1 latency establishment.</title><p>(<bold>A and B</bold>) Expression of activation markers (CD25, CD69, HLA-DR; panel <bold>A</bold>) and exhaustion markers (LAG-3, TIM-3, PD-1; panel <bold>B</bold>) of the DFV-B infected primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. Primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were infected as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref> and the surface markers were measured by FACS at indicated time points. Data indicate mean ± SD for three different donors. p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ns, not significant; **p&lt;0.01; ***p&lt;0.001. (<bold>C and D</bold>) Expression of activation markers and exhaustion markers in the DN, DP, and mC population from <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold> of this figure. Panel <bold>C</bold> only shows the results of day 8 post-infection. Red dots represented marker-positive cells; blue dots represented negative cells. Panel <bold>D</bold> shows quantified values of markers expression. Data indicate mean ± SD for three different donors. (<bold>E</bold>) Infection profile of EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells when infected by DFV-B at indicated time points. Top panel depicts scheme of experimental procedure. Bottom panel shows the flow cytometric chart of infected EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells on day 5 post-infection. (<bold>F</bold>) Infected EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are more likely to become latently infected cells. The ratios of DP cells or mC cells to total infected cells were calculated using data from panel <bold>E</bold>. Data represents the average of three donors.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Generation of a stable cell line model of HIV-1 latency</title><p>Although some cell line models of HIV-1 latency (such as the widely used J-Lat model) have been reported, all of which are derived from single-cell clones, and therefore with identical integration sites, which significantly underrepresented the heterogenous nature of latently infected cells in vivo. Here, by taking the advantage of direct labeling of latently infected cells with DFV-B infection, we generated a Jurkat-based cell line model of HIV-1 latency (J-mC), which were derived from random infection events, and therefore should harbor diverse integration sites. We found that DFV-B infection in Jurkat cells closely resembled primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. Latently infected cells were readily identifiable on day 7 p.i. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>). Then the DN, DP, and mC Jurkat T cells were sorted by flow cytometry and stimulated by 10 ng/ml TNF-α for 3 days in CFM. Over 80% of mC cells were converted to DP cells following the treatment, but DP and DN cells were not affected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref>), confirming DFV-B infection could directly identify latent infection in Jurkat cells.</p><p>The process of model generation is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>. Thirty days after the first sorting, a small dose of TNF-α (5 ng/ml) was added to the culture to activate those unstable cells that were probably in the borderline state of latency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A and B</xref>). To assess the activatability of J-mC cells, we stimulated them with different stimuli. As expected, J-mC cells were activated efficiently by all stimuli to express both fluorescent proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C and D</xref>). The potent induction of cell-associated HIV-1 mRNA after PMA treatment further confirmed the integrated proviruses were reactivated in this model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>). Besides, mRNA expression levels and DNA levels of GFP and mCherry remained relatively stable over the course of a year (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F and G</xref>). Together, these results demonstrated that J-mC cells were indeed a stable group of latently infected cells and could be reactivated efficiently upon stimulation, suggesting that this would become a useful cell line model to study HIV-1 latency.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Generation of a novel cell line model of HIV-1 latency.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The experimental procedure of generating a Jurkat-based cell line model of HIV-1 latency (J-mC). Jurkat cells were infected by DFV-B at day 0 in CFM. (<bold>B</bold>) Flow cytometric charts during the process of J-mC model generation. Detailed steps can be found in ‘Generation of J-mC cells’ in the Materials and methods section. (<bold>C</bold>) Reactivation of J-mC cells by different stimuli. J-mC cells were stimulated, respectively, with 1 μM JQ1, 1 μM SAHA, 10 ng/ml TNF-α, 50 ng/ml PMA, and 50 ng/ml PMA and 1 μM ionomycin for 48 hr prior to analysis by flow cytometry. (<bold>D</bold>) Data from panel <bold>C</bold> are displayed graphically. Data indicate mean ± SD for three different treatments. (<bold>E</bold>) Cell-associated HIV-1 mRNA in J-mC cells after reactivation. J-mC cells were treated with DMSO or 50 ng/ml PMA for 48 hr. HIV-1 <italic>gag</italic>, <italic>tat</italic>, <italic>vif</italic>, and <italic>LTR</italic> mRNAs were quantified relative to cellular GAPDH, and values within each group were normalized to the DMSO treatment. Error bars represent SDs of three technical replicates. p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ***p&lt;0.001; ****p&lt;0.0001. (<bold>F</bold>) Long-term tracking of the phenotype of J-mC cells. J-mC cells were cultured in CFM and the expression of GFP and mCherry were monitored over the course of a year. (<bold>G</bold>) Long-term tracking of the integrated DNA level of GFP and mCherry in J-mC cells. J-mC cells were collected on the date indicated, and then total DNA were isolated. The DNA of GFP and mCherry were quantified relative to cellular GAPDH, respectively. Data shown from three biological replicates (mean ± SD).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>FACS sorting strategy and reactivation of the DP, DN, and mC Jurkat cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Jurkat cells were infected with DFV-B incorporating VSV-G in CFM. On day 7 post-infection, DP, DN, and mC Jurkat cells were sorted by flow cytometry. (<bold>B</bold>) Reactivation of DP, DN, and mC cells. DN, DP, and mC Jurkat cells were sorted according to panel <bold>A</bold>, purities of DN, DP, and mC population were measured by FACS. Then the sorted cells were stimulated by 10 ng/ml TNF-α for 3 days and the percentages of double positive subpopulations were measured by FACS.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig4-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>The integration landscape of HIV-1 in J-mC cells</title><p>To verify whether J-mC cells harbored diverse HIV-1 integration sites, we adopted a method called linear amplification–mediated high-throughput genome-wide sequencing (LAM-HTGTS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Hu et al., 2016</xref>) to analyze HIV-1 integration sites. We first tested the applicability of the method on J-Lat 8.4 and J-Lat 15.4, which had been reported to have only one HIV-1 integration site respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Symons et al., 2017</xref>). J-Lat 8.4 and 15.4 were mixed in equal amounts and then subjected to LAM-HTGTS. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A and B</xref>, 49.09% of the integration sites were located in the same position 77946384 of chromosome 1% and 46.92% counts were located in the same position 34441293 of chromosome 19 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>), which were exactly the integration sites of J-Lat 8.4 and J-Lat 15.4, suggesting that LAM-HTGTS was a robust method for analyzing HIV-1 integration sites. For J-mC cells, all integration sites recovered were diffusely distributed on 24 chromosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). Chromosome 17 harbored the most abundant integration sites, which at the same time were extremely diverse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref>). We also noticed that more than 70% of the integration sites were distributed on intronic regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>), which is consistent with previous reports on integration sites recovered from ART-treated HIV-1 infected individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Han et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Cohn et al., 2015</xref>). We performed gene ontology (GO) and GO pathway analysis on the genes at all integration sites, and found that the proviruses were enriched in genes related to ‘Regulation of transcription’, ‘Membrane’, and ‘Binding’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref>). In addition, HIV-1 integrated more frequently in cancer-related pathways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5G</xref>), which is also consistent with previously reported ex vivo data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wagner et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Cohn et al., 2015</xref>). Together, these data clearly demonstrated that J-mC cells harbored tremendously diverse HIV-1 integration sites, which were highly physiologically relevant, suggesting this cell line model as a valuable tool to study HIV-1 latency.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>The integration landscape of HIV-1 in J-mC cells.</title><p>(<bold>A and B</bold>) Validation of integration sites of J-Lat cell lines by LAM-HTGTS. J-Lat 8.4 and J-Lat 15.4 were mixed in equal amounts and subjected to LAM-HTGTS. <bold>A</bold>: Chromosome distribution of all integration sites. <bold>B</bold>: Integration sites analysis of J-Lat 8.4 and J-Lat 15.4. (<bold>C and D</bold>) Diversity of HIV-1 integration sites in J-mC cells. <bold>C</bold>: Chromosome distribution of all integration sites. A total of 5154 identified integration sites were obtained from J-mC cells. <bold>D</bold>: Distribution of integration sites on chromosome 17. The percentage of top 10 integration sites was shown. A total of 499 identified integration sites were obtained from chromosome 17. (<bold>E</bold>) Proportion of integration sites of J-mC cells in the indicated genomic regions. (<bold>F</bold>) The gene ontology analysis of HIV-1 integration sites detected in J-mC cells. (<bold>G</bold>) The GO pathway enrichment analysis of HIV-1 integration sites in J-mC cells.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>High-throughput screening of small compound library in J-mC cells discovers ACY-1215 as a potent latency reversing agent</title><p>To test the applicability of our J-mC model, we performed a high-throughput screening of a small-molecule library containing 1700 FDA-approved compounds to discover novel LRAs. The screening was performed from high concentrations to low concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1A</xref>), and with this system we successfully identified several previously reported LRAs, including SAHA, panobinostat, and romidepsin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). A new compound, ricolinistat (ACY-1215), was discovered in this screen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A and B</xref>), displaying excellent potential to reactivate latent HIV-1 in a dose-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Viral transcription was induced eight fold in average after 24 hr of ACY-1215 treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). In addition, we found that ACY-1215 showed better latency reversing activities in J-mC cells than in different J-Lat cell lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1C–E</xref>), which probably explained why it was not discovered in previous drug screenings. Besides, we observed that ACY-1215 displayed a synergistic effect with several other LRAs, but not disulfiram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1F</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>High-throughput screening with the J-mC model identifies ACY-1215 as a potent latency reversing agent.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Summary of screening results in J-mC cells. The results were shown as the percentage of the double positive cells and were normalized to the reactivation level of 50 ng/ml PMA. Each bar represents the average value of triplicates. (<bold>B</bold>) The chemical structure of ricolinostat (ACY-1215). (<bold>C</bold>) Reactivation effects of ACY-1215 on J-mC cells at the indicated concentrations. 0.5 million J-mC cells were stimulated with ACY-1215 for 3 days in each condition. Error bars represent SDs of three technical replicates. (<bold>D</bold>) Cell-associated HIV-1 mRNA expression of J-mC cells after ACY-1215 treatment. Data are representative of at least three independent experiments (mean ± SD). (<bold>E</bold>) ACY-1215 induced HIV-1 transcription in a primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells model of HIV-1 latency. (<bold>F</bold>) Data from panel <bold>E</bold> are displayed graphically. Histograms show quantification of the percent population in the active gate. Values represent the mean ± SD, N = 3. **p&lt;0.01. Results were analyzed by unpaired t-tests. (<bold>G</bold>) Quantification of ACY-1215 induced transcription of cell-associated HIV-1 mRNA in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from ART-suppressed infected individuals. HIV-1 transcription was measured by HIV-1 viral quality assurance assay. 1 million CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were analyzed per condition. Data indicate mean ± SD for three technical replicates. p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, **p&lt;0.01. (<bold>H</bold>) Fold induction of cell-associated HIV-1 mRNA was shown relative to the negative control (DMSO). Data indicate mean ± SD for three technical replicates. p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, **p&lt;0.01.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6sdata1"><label>Figure 6—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Characteristics of ART-suppressed, aviremic people living with HIV-1 (PLWH) in this study.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig6-data1-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig6-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Reactivation effects of ACY-1215 on J-mC cells and J-Lat cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic layout of the compound screening. (<bold>B</bold>) Reactivation effects of ACY-1215 on J-mC cells at the indicated concentrations. (<bold>C</bold>) Reactivation potency of ACY-1215 in a series of J-Lat cell lines. Error bars represent SDs of three technical replicates. (<bold>D</bold>) Reactivation effects of ACY-1215 and other LRAs on J-mC cells. Error bars represent SDs of three technical replicates. (<bold>E</bold>) Reactivation effects of ACY-1215 and other LRAs on J-Lat A2 cells. Error bars represent SDs of three technical replicates. (<bold>F</bold>) Reactivation effects of ACY-1215 are synergistically enhanced by co-treatment with other LRAs in J-mC cells. Data are representative of three independent experiments. Error bars represent SDs of three technical replicates, p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, *p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig6-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>ACY-1215 did not cause apparent cytotoxicity.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) ACY-1215 did not significantly induce expression of apoptotic markers. Representative flow chart shows the expression of annexin V and propidium iodide (PI) in PBMCs. (<bold>B</bold>) Data from panel <bold>A</bold> is displayed graphically. Histograms show the percentage of positive cells. Error bars represent SDs of three technical replicates. p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ns, not significant; *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01. (<bold>C</bold>) CCK-8 assays were used to determine cell viability in the ACY-1215 treated primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. Error bars represent SDs of three technical replicates.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig6-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Effects of ACY-1215 on T cell biomarkers and function.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) ACY-1215 did not induce global activation of primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. Expressions of CD25, CD69, and HLA-DR were measured by flow cytometry. Data shown from three biological replicates (mean ± SD). p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ns, not significant; ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001. (<bold>B and C</bold>) ACY-1215 did not upregulate HIV-1 co-receptor CCR5 (<bold>B</bold>) and CXCR4 (<bold>C</bold>) expression. Data shown from three biological replicates (mean ± SD). p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ns, not significant; ***p&lt;0.001. (<bold>D and E</bold>) Effects of ACY-1215 on the cytokine secretion of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. PBMCs isolated from HIV-1 naïve individuals were exposed to indicated treatment for 4 hr. Cells were then washed and cultured in fresh medium with PMA and ionomycin for 5 hr in the presence of brefeldin A. IFN-γ or TNF-α production in CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells was measured by intracellular cytokine staining. Data is shown from three biological replicates (mean ± SD). p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ns, not significant. (<bold>F and G</bold>) Effects of ACY-1215 on the cytokine secretion of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. PBMCs isolated from HIV naïve individuals were exposed to indicated treatment for 4 hr. Cells were then washed and cultured in fresh medium with PMA and ionomycin for 5 hr in the presence of brefeldin A. IFN-γ or TNF-α production in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells was measured by intracellular cytokine staining. Data shown from three biological replicates (mean ± SD). p-values calculated using unpaired t-test, ns, not significant.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-fig6-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>ACY-1215 is an oral HDAC6-selective inhibitor, and our data suggested that it was less toxic than SAHA as measured by annexin-V/propidium iodide (PI) staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2A and B</xref>) and CCK-8 assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2C</xref>). ACY-1215 does not induce upregulation of classic T cell activation markers on freshly isolated primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3A</xref>). In addition, ACY-1215 had no significant effect on CCR5 and CXCR4 expression of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3B and C</xref>). No significant induction of IFN-γ and TNF-α was detected in CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from the same donors following ACY-1215 treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3D–G</xref>). Taken together, these data indicated that ACY-1215 does not cause global T cell activation, T cell dysfunction, or cytotoxicity to CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells.</p><p>To further verify the physiological relevance of the J-mC model, we tested the latency reversal activities of ACY-1215 in a primary cell model of HIV-1 latency and in primary cells from ART-treated infected individuals. Average 20 million of GFP<bold><sup>-</sup></bold> Bcl-2-transduced CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were obtained from one healthy donor according to the protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Kim et al., 2014</xref>). At 48 hr post-treatment, we found that ACY-1215 worked as well as SAHA, reactivating over 80% of latent HIV-1 when comparing to PMA and ionomycin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E and F</xref>). We collected five PBMC samples from ART-suppressed, HIV-1 infected individuals (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig6sdata1">Figure 6—source data 1</xref>) and isolated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. As shown in the <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6G and H</xref>, ACY-1215 robustly induced the level of cell-associated HIV-1 mRNA by an average of 50-fold comparing to the negative controls. Taken together, our data strongly supports that ACY-1215 is a promising LRA candidate and J-mC is a highly physiological relevant cell model for HIV-1 latency.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we presented a newly designed dual fluorescent virus, DFV-B. With DFV-B infection, latently infected cells can be easily distinguished from productively infected or uninfected cells. Compared with the previously reported infection models, DFV-B displayed a better infection profile with a clearer cell population and a lower percentage of single GFP positive cells (&lt;1%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>) than RGH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dahabieh et al., 2013</xref>), Duo-Fluo I (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Calvanese et al., 2013</xref>), mdHIV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hashemi et al., 2016</xref>), and HIV<sub>GKO</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Battivelli et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>More than 50% of the latently infected primary cells by DFV-B were reactivated by PMA and ionomycin in CFM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), while only 5% were reactivatable in the HIV<sub>GKO</sub> model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Battivelli et al., 2018</xref>), indicating the robustness of the DFV-B system to research the mechanism of HIV-1 latency maintenance and reactivation in vitro. A small fraction of single GFP positive cells existed after DFV-B infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>), but compared with Duo-Fluo I or HIV<sub>GKO</sub> infected cells, the proportion of the cells was extremely small (&lt;1%). The eGFP and mCherry have 20–30 bp regions of homology at the C- and N-termini (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Salamango et al., 2013</xref>), which may cause genomic deletion due to homologous recombination. However, our data showed that the absence of GFP production was due to viral latency but not genomic deletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>). Nevertheless, the risk of recombination still exists between GFP and mCherry, which may need further optimizations. Based on sequence similarity of fluorescent proteins that have been reported, E2 crimson/mKO2 may be a good choice to replace mCherry, which have been used previously to construct a dual-fluorescence reporter system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Battivelli et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Kim et al., 2019</xref>). Besides, the insertion location of the fluorescent protein in the construct needs to be considered, because there was a big difference in protein expression depending on whether 31 bp <italic>nef</italic> was retained or not, or two fluorescent proteins were connected or not in DFV-B.</p><p>How HIV-1 latency is established is still not fully understood. A widely accepted view is that after infection occurs in activated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, a tiny fraction of the infected cells survive viral cytopathic effect and host immune elimination and revert to a more resting and memory phenotype, becoming latently infected cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Sengupta and Siliciano, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Margolis et al., 2020</xref>). Our data here was in line with the mainstream view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B and C</xref>). It is also suggested that latent infection is preferentially established in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells undergoing EMT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Chavez et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Shan et al., 2017</xref>). Our results from DFV-B infection indicated that EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were less permissive to infection, but once infected were much more likely to establish latency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E and F</xref>), which supports that EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are the primary targets for latent infection, and highlights the feasibility of our DFV-B system.</p><p>Some primary cell models of HIV-1 latency have been developed in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells or thymocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Sahu et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Burke et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Marini et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bosque and Planelles, 2009</xref>). However, the limited source and poor long-term viability of primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells preclude their extensive use. Yang et al reported a Bcl-2-transduced primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell model of HIV-1 latency, which could obtain a large amount of viable resting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells long term and mimic the process of latency establishment in vitro. However, the over-expression of Bcl-2 may alter the global transcriptional profile and affect the physiological characteristics of the latently infected cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Yang et al., 2009</xref>). In addition, the in vitro cell line model of latency, such as the J-Lat cell lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jordan et al., 2003</xref>), was derived from single-cell clone with identical HIV-1 integration sites, which significantly underrepresented the heterogeneous nature of latently infected cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Golumbeanu et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Ait-Ammar et al., 2019</xref>). Our novel model of J-mC cells harbored extremely diverse HIV-1 integration sites, with a majority of them located in intronic regions, which was in line with data recovered from infected individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Han et al., 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Craigie and Bushman, 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Cohn et al., 2015</xref>). In general, our DFV-B model system in primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells or Jurkat cells circumvented the problems mentioned above, and therefore could be utilized as a robust model to study the characteristics and mechanisms of HIV-1 latent infection.</p><p>By applying the J-mC model, we discovered a novel compound ricolinistat (ACY-1215) that can reactivate latent HIV-1 efficiently in different cell models and primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from ART-treated infected individuals. ACY-1215, an orally bioavailable HDAC6-selective inhibitor, had previously completed Phase 1 and 2 clinical trials for treatment of multiple myeloma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Santo et al., 2012</xref>). In vitro, ACY-1215 selectively increased acetylated a-tubulin (a marker of HDAC6 inhibition) without altering acetylated histone H4 (a marker of global HDAC inhibition) at biologically relevant concentrations (&lt;10 μM) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carew et al., 2019</xref>). In osteoarthritis chondrocytes, the function of ACY-1215 was investigated at concentrations of 1–10 μM, and decreased cell viability was observed at a concentration of 50 μM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cheng et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Li et al., 2019</xref>). In the present study, we used 3 μM ACY-1215 in all additional assays to achieve selective inhibition of HDAC6 activity, which was in line with the studies mentioned above and was in the achievable range for clinical trials.</p><p>HDAC6 belongs to class II b HDACs and is a cytosolic microtubule-associated deacetylase. Selective HDAC6 inhibition stops aggresome formation, thence inhibiting the degradation leading to accumulation of misfolded proteins within cells, and may reduce the toxicity related to the off-target effects of pan-HDAC inhibitors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Amengual et al., 2021</xref>). Besides, HDAC6-KO mice were normal, as opposed to the lethal effect of genetic ablation of class I HDACs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Haberland et al., 2009</xref>). ACY-1215 and ACY-241 (another HDAC6-selective inhibitor) can downregulate Th2 cytokine production, decrease T-cell exhaustion, increase T-cell killing ability, and augment the proportion of central memory cells and expression of cytolytic markers in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Laino et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bae et al., 2018</xref>). ACY-1215 can also change the chromatin accessibility of T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Laino et al., 2019</xref>). Besides, ACY-1215 has anti-inﬂammatory eﬀect and is considered a potential anti-inflammatory drug (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cheng et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Zhang et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Zhang et al., 2019</xref>). A recent study reported that ACY-1215 could prevent the neurotoxicity of HIV-1 envelope protein gp120 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Wenzel et al., 2019</xref>). Our data suggested that ACY-1215 was less toxic than SAHA as described clinically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Santo et al., 2012</xref>), did not elevate the expression of classic T cell activation markers, and had no significant effect on HIV-1 co-receptors. Taken together, ACY-1215 could become a promising LRA for future AIDS functional cure studies.</p><p>In summary, our study designed and put forward a new dual fluorescent reporter virus, DFV-B, infection of which can directly mark latently infected primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. We have also developed a stable latently infected cell line model based on DFV-B infection, which can be utilized as a valuable tool to study HIV-1 latency. We further identified a novel small compound ACY-1215 that can effectively reactivate latent HIV-1 and will be of great importance for the future applications of HIV-1 functional cure strategy.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Reagent type (species) or resource</th><th valign="top">Designation</th><th valign="top">Source or reference</th><th valign="top">Identifiers</th><th valign="top">Additional <break/>information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human CD4-FITC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 317408; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_571951">AB_571951</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human CD8-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 301049; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2562054">AB_2562054</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human Bcl2-AF647 (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 658706; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2563280">AB_2563280</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human CD69-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 310910; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_314845">AB_314845</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human CD25-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 302610; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_314280">AB_314280</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human HLA-DR-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 307610; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_314688">AB_314688</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human PD-1-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 329908; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_940475">AB_940475</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human LAG-3-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 369212; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2728373">AB_2728373</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human CCR5-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 359122; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2564073">AB_2564073</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human CXCR4-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 306510; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_314616">AB_314616</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human IFN-γ-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 502512; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_315237">AB_315237</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-human TNF-α-APC (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 502912; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_315264">AB_315264</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-HIV-1 p24 antibody (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">ABcam</td><td valign="top">Cat# ab9071; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_306981">AB_306981</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-HIV-1 Vif antibody (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">ABcam</td><td valign="top">Cat# ab66643; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_1139534">AB_1139534</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-β-actin antibody (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">ABcam</td><td valign="top">Cat# ab8226; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_306371">AB_306371</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Goat Anti-Mouse IgG H and L (Alexa Fluor 680) preadsorbed</td><td valign="top">ABcam</td><td valign="top">Cat# ab186694</td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:20000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Purified anti-human CD3 Antibody (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 300302; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_314038">AB_314038</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Purified anti-human CD28 Antibody (mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 302902; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_314304">AB_314304</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Dilution 1:1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Strain, strain background (<italic>Escherichia coli</italic>)</td><td valign="top">Stbl3 <italic>E. coli</italic></td><td valign="top">ThermoFisher</td><td valign="top">Cat#C7381201</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Biological sample (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">Blood samples</td><td valign="top">Guangzhou Blood Center, Guangzhou</td><td valign="top"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gzbc.org/">http://www.gzbc.org/</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Blood samples from healthy individuals</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Biological sample (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">Blood samples</td><td valign="top">The Fifth Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University, Zhuhai, China</td><td valign="top"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zsufivehos.com/">http://www.zsufivehos.com/</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Blood samples from HIV-1- infected individuals</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Tissue culture media</td><td valign="top">RPMI 1640</td><td valign="top">GIBCO</td><td valign="top">Cat# 11875093</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Tissue culture media</td><td valign="top">DMEM</td><td valign="top">GIBCO</td><td valign="top">Cat# 11995065</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Tissue culture media</td><td valign="top">Penicillin-Streptomycin Solution</td><td valign="top">BBI Life Sciences</td><td valign="top">Cat# E607011</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Tissue culture media</td><td valign="top">1 M Hepes Solution</td><td valign="top">BBI Life Sciences</td><td valign="top">Cat# E607018</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">DMSO</td><td valign="top">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# D2650-100ML</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Disulfiram</td><td valign="top">Selleckchem</td><td valign="top">Cat# S1680</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Bryostatin-1</td><td valign="top">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# B7431</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Panobinostat</td><td valign="top">Selleckchem</td><td valign="top">Cat# S1030</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">ACY-1215</td><td valign="top">Selleckchem</td><td valign="top">Cat# S8001</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">(<sup>+</sup>)-JQ-1</td><td valign="top">Selleckchem</td><td valign="top">Cat#S7110</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">SAHA</td><td valign="top">Selleckchem</td><td valign="top">Cat#S1047</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Approved Drug Library</td><td valign="top">TargetMOI</td><td valign="top">Cat# L1000</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA)</td><td valign="top">Selleckchem</td><td valign="top">Cat#S7791</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Ionomycin</td><td valign="top">MERCK</td><td valign="top">at#407952–5 MG</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Phytohemagglutinin-M(PHA-M)</td><td valign="top">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat#11082132001</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">TRIzol Reagent</td><td valign="top">ThermoFisher</td><td valign="top">Cat#15596018</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Propidium Iodide (PI)</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 421301</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Chemical compound, drug</td><td valign="top">Annexin-V-APC</td><td valign="top">Biolegend</td><td valign="top">Cat# 640941; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2616657">AB_2616657</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant proteins</td><td valign="top">Recombinant Human TNF-a</td><td valign="top">PeproTech</td><td valign="top">Cat#300-01A</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant proteins</td><td valign="top">Recombinant Human IL-2</td><td valign="top">R and D Systems</td><td valign="top">Cat#202-IL-500</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Critical commercial assays</td><td valign="top">Human CD4<sup>+</sup>T Lymphocyte Enrichment Set-DM</td><td valign="top">BD Biosciences</td><td valign="top">Cat#557939</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Critical commercial assays</td><td valign="top">HIV-1 p24 ELISA Kit</td><td valign="top">Abcam</td><td valign="top">Cat#ab218268</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Critical commercial assays</td><td valign="top">Cell Counting Kit-8</td><td valign="top">MedChemExpress</td><td valign="top">Cat# HY-K0301</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Critical commercial assays</td><td valign="top">Plasmid Mini Kit</td><td valign="top">OMEGA</td><td valign="top">Cat# D6943-02</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Critical commercial assays</td><td valign="top">Endo-free Plasmid Mini Kit</td><td valign="top">OMEGA</td><td valign="top">Cat# D6950-02</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Critical commercial assays</td><td valign="top">Gel Extraction</td><td valign="top">OMEGA</td><td valign="top">Cat# D2500-02</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Critical commercial assays</td><td valign="top">Cycle-Pure Kit</td><td valign="top">OMEGA</td><td valign="top">Cat# D6492-02</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Critical commercial assays</td><td valign="top">Tissue DNA kit</td><td valign="top">OMEGA</td><td valign="top">Cat# D3396-02</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">HEK293T</td><td valign="top">ATCC</td><td valign="top">CRL-3216; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_0063">CVCL_0063</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">J-Lat 6.3</td><td valign="top">NIH AIDS Reagents Program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jordan et al., 2003</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Cat# 9846; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_8280">CVCL_8280</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">J-Lat 8.4</td><td valign="top">NIH AIDS Reagents Program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jordan et al., 2003</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Cat#9847; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_8284">CVCL_8284</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">J-Lat 9.2</td><td valign="top">NIH AIDS Reagents Program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jordan et al., 2003</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Cat# 9848; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_8285">CVCL_8285</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">J-Lat 10.6</td><td valign="top">NIH AIDS Reagents Program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jordan et al., 2003</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Cat#9849; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_8281">CVCL_8281</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">J-Lat 15.4</td><td valign="top">NIH AIDS Reagents Program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jordan et al., 2003</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Cat# 9850; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_8282">CVCL_8282</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td valign="top">J-Lat A2</td><td valign="top">NIH AIDS Reagents Program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jordan et al., 2003</xref>)</td><td valign="top">Cat#9867; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CVCL_1G43">CVCL_1G43</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software</td><td valign="top">Prism 6</td><td valign="top">GraphPad</td><td valign="top"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.graphpad.com/scientific-software/prism/">https://www.graphpad.com/scientific-software/prism/</ext-link>; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_002798">SCR_002798</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software</td><td valign="top">BD LSRFortessa cell analyzer</td><td valign="top">BD Biosciences</td><td valign="top"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bdbiosciences.com/in/instruments/lsr/index.jsp">http://www.bdbiosciences.com/in/instruments/lsr/index.jsp</ext-link>; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_018655">SCR_018655</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software</td><td valign="top">FlowJo V10</td><td valign="top">Tree Star</td><td valign="top"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.flowjo.com/">https://www.flowjo.com/</ext-link>; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_008520">SCR_008520</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Software</td><td valign="top">GloMax 96 Microplate Luminometer Software</td><td valign="top">Promega</td><td valign="top"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.promega.com/resources/softwarefirmware/">https://www.promega.com/resources/softwarefirmware/</ext-link>; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_018614">SCR_018614</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-VQA-F</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">CAGATGCTGCATATAAGCAGCTG</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-VQA-R</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">TTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTGAAGCAC</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-VQA-Probe</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top">FAM-<named-content content-type="sequence">CCTGTACTGGGTCTCTCTGG</named-content>-MGB</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">qPCR-GFP-F</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">GTGCAGTGCTTCAGCCGCTACC</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">qPCR-GFP-R</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">ACCTCGGCGCGGGTCTTGTA</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">qPCR-mCherry-F</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">GTGGTGACCGTGACCCAGGACT</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">qPCR-mCherry-R</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">TGGTCTTGACCTCAGCGTCGTAGTG</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">qPCR-GAPDH-F</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">CTCTGCTCCTCCTGTTCGAC</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">qPCR-GAPDH-R</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">AGTTAAAAGCAGCCCTGGTGA</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-gag-F</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">ACATCAAGCAGCCATGCAAAT</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-gag-R</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">TCTGGCCTGGTGCAATAGG</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-tat-F</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">ATGGAGCCAGTAGATCCTAGAC</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-tat-R</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">CGCTTCTTCCTGCCATAGG</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-vif-F</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">CACACAAGTAGACCCTGACCT</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-vif-R</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">CCCTACCTTGTTATGTCCTGCT</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-LTR-F</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">CCACAAAGGGAGCCATACAATG</named-content></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sequence-based reagent</td><td valign="top">HIV-1-LTR-R</td><td valign="top">This paper</td><td valign="top">PCR primers</td><td valign="top"><named-content content-type="sequence">TTATGGCTTCCACTCCTGCC</named-content></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Cell lines</title><p>HEK293T and Jurkat cells were obtained from ATCC. HEK293T cells were cultured in DMEM supplemented with 1% penicillin–streptomycin (ThermoFisher), 1% L-glutamine (ThermoFisher), and 10% FBS (ThermoFisher). Jurkat T cells were cultured in CFM (RPMI 1640 supplemented with 1% penicillin–streptomycin, 1% L-glutamine, and 10% FBS). J-Lat 6.3, J-Lat 8.4, J-Lat 9.3, J-Lat 10.6, J-Lat 15.4, and J-Lat A2 cell lines were derived from the human Jurkat T cell line and were gifts from Dr. Robert F. Siliciano (Department of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD) Laboratory, which were originally generated from Dr. Eric Verdin (The Buck Institute for Research on Aging, Novato, CA). All the J-Lat cell lines were cultured in CFM. All cells have been tested for mycoplasma using a PCR assay and confirmed to be mycoplasma-free. All cells were cultured in a sterile incubator at 37°C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Plasmids and vector construction</title><p>DFV-B was derived from the original NL4-3 strain of HIV-1, which contains an HIV-1 genome. To construct DFV-B, GFP (Fragment 2) and EF-1α-mCherry (Fragment 3) were obtained by cloning in the respective plasmids. A 347 bp sequence (Fragment 1) was amplified from pNL4-3 plasmid using primers F1: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">ATTAGTGAACGGATCCTTAGCACTTATCTGGGACG</named-content>-3’ and R1: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">GCCCTTGCTCACCATCTTATAGCAAAATCCTTTCCA</named-content>-3’. A 3’LTR sequence (Fragment 4) was amplified from pNL4-3 plasmid using primers F2: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CTTAGCCACTTTTTAAAAGAAA</named-content>-3’ and R2: 5’- <named-content content-type="sequence">ACCCTGCACTCCATGGATCAGCTGGCACCCCCGGA</named-content>-3’. Next, a skeleton sequence was obtained from pNL4-3 using the <italic>BamH</italic> I and <italic>Nco</italic> I restriction sites. Finally, Fragment 1, GFP (Fragment 2), EF-1α-mCherry (Fragment 3), and Fragment 4 were cloned into the skeleton sequence by a modified SLIC technique (Li and Elledge, 2012). Of note, a portion of <italic>env</italic> was deleted for a single round of infection of the virus, and the <italic>vpr</italic> gene had a frameshift mutation to reduce the toxicity of the pseudovirus. Most of the <italic>nef</italic> sequence was replaced by GFP- EF-1α-kozak-mCherry, and the remaining 31 bp of nef sequence was reserved in order not to disturb the function of LTR.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Virus stock production</title><p>Pseudotyped viral stocks were produced in HEK293 T cells by co-transfecting 2.2 μg of VSV-G glycoprotein-expression or pCXCR4 HIV-1 envelope-expression vector, 4.4 μg of packaging vector pC-Help, and 4.4 μg pEB-FLV or pDFV-B construct using a polyethylenimine (Invitrogen) transfection system according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Supernatants were harvested after 48 hr, centrifuged (10 min, 500 × g, room temperature), and filtered through a 0.45 μm pore size membrane to remove the cell debris. Viruses were concentrated by centrifuging with a 25% vol of 50% polyethylene glycol 6000 and a 10% vol of 4 M NaCl. Concentrated virions were resuspended in complete medium and stored at −80°C.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Generation of J-mC cells</title><p>The cell line model of HIV-1 latency was generated as described (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A and B</xref>). Briefly, Jurkat cells were infected by DFV-B incorporating a VSVG envelope at 250 ng virus per million cells on day 0 in CFM. At day 7, the single mCherry positive cells were sorted according to the red gate in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>. The purity of single mCherry positive cells was greater than 99%. Next, the cells were cultured for another 30 days in CFM. At day 37, a small dose of TNF-α (5 ng/ml) was added to the culture and maintained for 7 days to further activate those unstable cells that were probably in the borderline state of latency. At day 44 the second sorting of single mCherry positive cells was performed by the red gate. Similarly, the third and fourth sorting of single mCherry positive cells were performed at days 58 and 72. J-mC cells were finalized at day 86. Each sorting was performed by the red gate in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Generation of latently HIV-1 infected Bcl-2–transduced cells</title><p>This primary cell of HIV-1 latency was generated as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Kim et al., 2014</xref>). In brief, primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were isolated from PBMCs with Human CD4<sup>+</sup> T lymphocyte Enrichment Set-DM (BD, USA) according to manufacturer’s instructions. CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were co-stimulated with anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 antibodies and were transduced with EB-FLV at the MOI of 5–10 by spinoculation of cells at 1200 g at room temperature for 2 hr. Following 3–4 weeks of culture, viable cells were isolated using Ficoll density gradient centrifugation. Activated Bcl-2-transduced cells were then infected with reporter virus NL4-3-Δ6-drEGFP at a MOI of less than 0.1. The infected cells were maintained in IL-2 and T cell growth factor–enriched medium for 3 days after infection, and then the medium was changed to RPMI 1640 with 10% FBS and 1% penicillin/streptomycin without exogenous cytokines and cultured for more than 1 month. Finally, the GFP-negative cells were sorted to more than 99.9% purity using fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS Aria II, BD).</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Infection of primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells</title><p>Primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were isolated from HIV naïve individuals. CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were co-stimulated with anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 antibodies for 3 days. Activated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were then infected with DFV-B incorporating a CXCR4-tropic Env at a MOI of 0.05–0.1. The infected cells were maintained in STCM for 3 days after infection, then the medium was changed to CFM, and cultured for 1 week.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Flow cytometry and cell sorting</title><p>GFP and mCherry fluorescence were measured in a BD LSR Fortessa cell analyzer and sorted in a FACS Aria II (BD). Data were analyzed using Flowjo (version 10.4.0).</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>DNA, RNA extraction, and qPCR</title><p>Total DNA was extracted with tissue DNA kit (OMEGA). Cells were incubated with different drugs for different time intervals, total RNA was extracted using TRIzol (Invitrogen) and chloroform, and then precipitated with isopropyl alcohol. RNA reverse transcription to cDNA was done according to the procedure of the SuperScript IV Control Reactions (ThermoFisher). Relatively quantitative PCR was performed using SYBR qPCR Master Mix (Vazyme) on the QuantStudio 3 (Thermo Fisher Scientific) using a standard two-step procedure (denatured: 95°C/10 s, annealed/extended: 60°C/30 s, 40 cycles). The RT-PCR primer sequences used were shown in Key resources table. The 2<sup>−ΔΔCT</sup> method was adopted to analyze the relative expression of mRNAs, using GAPDH as the reference gene.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Viral quality assurance</title><p>Total cellular RNA was extracted from 1 million CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells after 24 hr of stimulation followed by reverse transcription. Real-time PCR was performed using the TaqMan (Life Technologies) gene expression assay. HIV-1 mRNAs were detected using the following primers and probe, modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Shan et al., 2013</xref>. Forward (5′→3′) <named-content content-type="sequence">CAGATGCTGCATATAAGCAGCTG</named-content> (9501–9523), Reverse (5′→3′) <named-content content-type="sequence">TTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTGAAGCAC</named-content> (9629-poly A), and Probe (5′→3′) FAM-<named-content content-type="sequence">CCTGTACTGGGTCTCTCTGG</named-content>-MGB (9531–9550). The cycling parameters were as follows: 2 min at 50°C, 10 min at 95°C, and 45–50 cycles at 95°C for 15 s and then 60°C for 60 s. Molecular standard curves were generated using serial dilutions of a TOPO plasmid containing the last 352 nucleotides of viral genomic RNA plus 30 deoxyadenosines (pVQA). Results for each drug treatment were presented as fold change relative to DMSO control (mean ± SD).</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Protein extraction and western blot</title><p>After treatment, cells were lysed in RIPA lysis buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl buffered at pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 0.5 % NP-40, 1% Triton X-100, 10% glycerol, 2 mM EDTA, 1 mM NaF, 1 Mm Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub>, 1× protease and phosphatase inhibitor cocktail) and incubated in ice for 30 min, followed by centrifugation at 12,000 g for 10 min at 4°C. The supernatants were collected as a whole protein extract. Protein samples were stored at −80°C or directly used for western blotting analysis. The protein extract was denatured by addition of NuPAGE running buffer (ThermoFisher), followed by denaturation at 100°C for 10 min, 50 μg of total protein were electrophoresis for 1.5 hr on a 10% polyacrylamide gel to separate the proteins, transferred onto PVDF membranes (Biorad), and co-incubation with primary and secondary antibodies. The antibodies were diluted by 5% BSA. Subsequently, Blots were imaged on an infrared (IR) laser-based fluorescence imaging system (LI-COR Odyssey).</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Linear amplification–mediated high-throughput genome-wide sequencing (LAM-HTGTS)</title><p>Genomic DNA is sheared by sonication, and the HIV-1-human genome junctions are then amplified by LAM-PCR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Schmidt et al., 2007</xref>), using directional primers lying on HIV-1 LTR. LAM-PCR with a single 5′ biotinylated primer amplifies across the HIV-1 LTR into the unknown human genome. Junction-containing single-stranded DNAs (ssDNAs) are enriched via binding to streptavidin-coated magnetic beads. After washing, bead-bound ssDNAs are unidirectionally ligated to a bridge adapter. Adapter-ligated, bead-bound ssDNA fragments are then subjected to nested PCR to incorporate a barcode sequence that is necessary for demultiplexing. A final PCR step fully reconstructs Illumina Miseq adapter sequences at the ends of the amplified HIV-1-human junction sequence. Samples are then separated on an agarose gel, and the resulting population of 0.5–1 kb fragments is collected and quantified before Miseq paired-end sequencing, with a typical 2 × 250 bp HTGTS library. The sequence of the matched read pairs after the LTR or adapter were trimmed to 50 base pairs and subsequently the trimmed read pairs were grouped according to 100% sequence match. Well-represented sequences were used for chromosomal alignment which was determined using the Blat-UCSC Genome Browser (GRCH38/hg38). An HIV integration site was identified if the position had ≥10 counts.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Drug screening</title><p>We screened a library of 1700 drugs from the FDA-approved drug library. 1 × 10<sup>5</sup> J-mC cells were resuspended in 200 μl of medium in round-bottom 96-well plates. For the first round of screening, J-mC cells were treated with compounds (10 μM) for 48 hr and were analyzed by FACS. Then drugs with less than 30% of live cells are selected from the result of the first round of screening for a second round of screening with 5 μM drug concentration. Each plate contained cells treated with 50 ng/ml PMA, PBS and DMSO as controls. After 48 hr at 37°C, reactivation of latent HIV-1 was detected as above.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Cytotoxicity assays</title><p>Cell death radio was evaluated by Annexin V/propidium iodide (PI) double staining assay. The cells incubate Annexin V-FITC at room temperature for 15 min. Then add PI before analyzing the stained cells by flow cytometry. Cell viability was measured by a Cell Count Kit-8 (MCE). PBMCs plated as 1 million cells per well in a 96-well plate were incubated with drugs for 48 hr. Then 10 μl of CCK-8 reagent was added to 100 μl of cell culture mixture and incubated for an additional 4 hr. Optical density (OD) was recorded at a wavelength of 450 nm on a microplate reader (Mοlecular Devices). The cell viability was calculated as follows. (OD treatment – OD blank control) / (OD untreatment – OD blank control) × 100%.</p></sec><sec id="s4-14"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All experiments were repeated at least three times. Statistics were performed with GraphPad Prism 8 (GraphPad), and all data are presented as mean values ± SD. p-values were calculated based on the Mann–Whitney U-test or Student’s t-test (large sample size) using SPSS software. * denotes p&lt;0.05, ** denotes p&lt;0.01, *** denotes p&lt;0.001, **** denotes p&lt;0.0001, and NS denotes non-significant.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank all the volunteers who donated blood samples for this study. This work was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (32070159 and 81672024), the National Special Research Program of China for Important Infectious Diseases (2018ZX10302103 and 2017ZX10202102), Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province of China (2017A030306005), and Guangdong Innovative and Entrepreneurial Research Team Program (2016ZT06S638) to KD. </p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Data curation, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Data curation, Methodology</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Data curation, Validation, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Data curation, Validation, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Data curation, Validation, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Data curation, Validation, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>Data curation, Validation, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>Resources, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con9"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Project administration, Writing - review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1"><p>Human subjects: The use of PBMCs from healthy individuals was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Guangzhou Blood Center (Guangzhou, Guangdong, China). We did not have any interaction with the healthy individuals or protected information, and therefore no informed consent was required. Chronically HIV-1-infected participants sampled by this study were recruited from The Fifth Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University (Zhuhai, Guangdong, China). This study was approved by the Ethics Review Boards of the Fifth Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University (2018K41-1). All the participants were given written informed consent with approval of the Ethics Committees. The enrollment of HIV-1-infected individuals was based on the criteria of prolonged suppression of plasma HIV-1 viremia on cART, which is undetectable plasma HIV-1 RNA levels (less than 50 copies/ml) for a minimum of 12 months, and having high CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell count (at least 350 cells/mm<sup>3</sup>). All HIV-1-infected participants provided written informed consent for their participation in the study and agreed with the publication of the scientific results.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>HIV-1 integration sites of J-Lat 8.4 and J-Lat 15.4.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-63810-supp1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp2"><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>HIV-1 integration sites of J-mC cells.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-63810-supp2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-63810-transrepform-v2.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in the manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ait-Ammar</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kula</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Darcis</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdikt</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>De Wit</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallon</surname> <given-names>PWG</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcello</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohr</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Lint</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Current status of latency reversing agents facing the heterogeneity of HIV-1 cellular and tissue reservoirs</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>3060</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.03060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32038533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amengual</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lue</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cremers</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawas</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>First-in-Class selective HDAC6 inhibitor (ACY-1215) Has a highly favorable safety profile in patients with relapsed and refractory lymphoma</article-title><source>The Oncologist</source><volume>26</volume><elocation-id>184-366</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/onco.13673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33458921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hideshima</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tai</surname> <given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Raje</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Munshi</surname> <given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitor ACY241 enhances anti-tumor activities of antigen-specific central memory cytotoxic T lymphocytes against multiple myeloma and solid tumors</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>1932</fpage><lpage>1947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41375-018-0062-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29487385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldauf</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Erikson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Daddacha</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Burggraf</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenkova</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambiel</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wabnitz</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramberg</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Panitz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Flory</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Landau</surname> <given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sertel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutsch</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasitschka</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>König</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fackler</surname> <given-names>OT</given-names></name><name><surname>Keppler</surname> <given-names>OT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>SAMHD1 restricts HIV-1 infection in resting CD4(+) T cells</article-title><source>Nature Medicine</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1682</fpage><lpage>1688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.2964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22972397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battivelli</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahabieh</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Mohsen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Svensson</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tojal Da Silva</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohn</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramatica</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deeks</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillai</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdin</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Distinct chromatin functional states correlate with HIV latency reactivation in infected primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e34655</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29714165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosque</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Planelles</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Induction of HIV-1 latency and reactivation in primary memory CD4+ T cells</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2008-07-168393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18849485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bukrinsky</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharova</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dempsey</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanwick</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukrinskaya</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Haggerty</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>Active nuclear import of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 preintegration complexes</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>6580</fpage><lpage>6584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.89.14.6580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1631159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burke</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsden</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bristol</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vatakis</surname> <given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zack</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Primary cell model for activation-inducible human immunodeficiency virus</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>7424</fpage><lpage>7434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02838-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17475639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvanese</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavez</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurent</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdin</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Dual-color HIV reporters trace a population of latently infected cells and enable their purification</article-title><source>Virology</source><volume>446</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2013.07.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24074592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carew</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Espitia</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Visconte</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Anwer</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawrocki</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Rational cotargeting of HDAC6 and BET proteins yields synergistic antimyeloma activity</article-title><source>Blood Advances</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>1318</fpage><lpage>1329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/bloodadvances.2018026484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31015208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chavez</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvanese</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdin</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>HIV latency is established directly and early in both resting and activated primary CD4 T cells</article-title><source>PLOS Pathogens</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1004955</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26067822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>ACY-1215 exhibits anti-inflammatory and chondroprotective effects in human osteoarthritis chondrocytes via inhibition of STAT3 and NF-κB signaling pathways</article-title><source>Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>2464</fpage><lpage>2471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2018.11.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30551507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chomont</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Far</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ancuta</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautmann</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Procopio</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassine-Diab</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Boucher</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulassel</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghattas</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenchley</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schacker</surname> <given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Douek</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Routy</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sékaly</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>HIV reservoir size and persistence are driven by T cell survival and homeostatic proliferation</article-title><source>Nature Medicine</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>893</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.1972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19543283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chun</surname> <given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Carruth</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Finzi</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>DiGiuseppe</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermankova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chadwick</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolick</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Brookmeyer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeiger</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barditch-Crovo</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Quantification of latent tissue reservoirs and total body viral load in HIV-1 infection</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>387</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/387183a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chun</surname> <given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nickle</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Justement</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Roby</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallahan</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kottilil</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moir</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mican</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullins</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannon</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauci</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Persistence of HIV in gut‐associated lymphoid tissue despite long‐term antiretroviral therapy</article-title><source>The Journal of Infectious Diseases</source><volume>197</volume><fpage>714</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/527324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18260759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohn</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname> <given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosales</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrish</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Learn</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Czartoski</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>McElrath</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Caskey</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jankovic</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussenzweig</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>HIV-1 integration landscape during latent and active infection</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>160</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.01.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25635456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craigie</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bushman</surname> <given-names>FD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>HIV DNA integration</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Medicine</source><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>a006890</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a006890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22762018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahabieh</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooms</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadowski</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>A doubly fluorescent HIV-1 reporter shows that the majority of integrated HIV-1 is latent shortly after infection</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>4716</fpage><lpage>4727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.03478-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23408629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finzi</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermankova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierson</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carruth</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaisson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chadwick</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolick</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brookmeyer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallant</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Markowitz</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Richman</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Identification of a reservoir for HIV-1 in patients on highly active antiretroviral therapy</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>1295</fpage><lpage>1300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.278.5341.1295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9360927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golumbeanu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cristinelli</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rato</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavassini</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beerenwinkel</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciuffi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Single-Cell RNA-Seq reveals transcriptional heterogeneity in latent and reactivated HIV-Infected cells</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>942</fpage><lpage>950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.03.102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29694901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haberland</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname> <given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>The many roles of histone deacetylases in development and physiology: implications for disease and therapy</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19065135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Monie</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedaghat</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimoji</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierson</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolick</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Resting CD4+ T cells from human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1)-infected individuals carry integrated HIV-1 genomes within actively transcribed host genes</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><volume>78</volume><fpage>6122</fpage><lpage>6133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.78.12.6122-6133.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15163705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashemi</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Barreto</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashemi</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomness</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadowski</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>HIV provirus stably reproduces parental latent and induced transcription phenotypes regardless of the chromosomal integration site</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>5302</fpage><lpage>5314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02842-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26984732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Panchakshari</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alt</surname> <given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Frock</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Detecting DNA double-stranded breaks in mammalian genomes by linear amplification-mediated high-throughput genome-wide translocation sequencing</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>871</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27031497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisgrove</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdin</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>HIV reproducibly establishes a latent infection after acute infection of T cells in vitro</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1868</fpage><lpage>1877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/cdg188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12682019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosmane</surname> <given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullen</surname> <given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Capoferri</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A primary CD4(+) T cell model of HIV-1 latency established after activation through the T cell receptor and subsequent return to quiescence</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>2755</fpage><lpage>2770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2014.188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25375990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname> <given-names>PU</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewin</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Limitations of dual-fluorescent HIV reporter viruses in a model of pre-activation latency</article-title><source>Journal of the International AIDS Society</source><volume>22</volume><elocation-id>e25425</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jia2.25425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31855322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korin</surname> <given-names>YD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zack</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Progression to the G1b phase of the cell cycle is required for completion of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 reverse transcription in T cells</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>3161</fpage><lpage>3168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.72.4.3161-3168.1998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9525642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laino</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Betts</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Veerapathran</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolgalev</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarnaik</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Quayle</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>HDAC6 selective inhibition of melanoma patient T-cells augments anti-tumor characteristics</article-title><source>Journal for ImmunoTherapy of Cancer</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e0517-0</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40425-019-0517-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Ricolinostat (ACY-1215) inhibits VEGF expression via PI3K/AKT pathway and promotes apoptosis in osteoarthritic osteoblasts</article-title><source>Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy</source><volume>118</volume><elocation-id>109357</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2019.109357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31548177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margolis</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Archin</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eron</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrari</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname> <given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gay</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goonetilleke</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanstrom</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname> <given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Curing HIV: seeking to target and clear persistent infection</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>181</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32220311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marini</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Romerio</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>An in vitro system to model the establishment and reactivation of HIV-1 latency</article-title><source>The Journal of Immunology</source><volume>181</volume><fpage>7713</fpage><lpage>7720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.181.11.7713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahu</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Braciale</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cloyd</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>A novel in vitro system to generate and study latently HIV-infected long-lived normal CD4+ T-lymphocytes</article-title><source>Virology</source><volume>355</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2006.07.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16919704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salamango</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baluyot</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlong</surname> <given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Recombination can lead to spurious results in retroviral transduction with dually fluorescent reporter genes</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>13900</fpage><lpage>13903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02524-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24067983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hideshima</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kung</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamang</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarpe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Duzer</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazitschek</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogier</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cirstea</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodig</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eda</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Scullen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Canavese</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradner</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Raje</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Preclinical activity, Pharmacodynamic, and pharmacokinetic properties of a selective HDAC6 inhibitor, ACY-1215, in combination with bortezomib in multiple myeloma</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>119</volume><fpage>2579</fpage><lpage>2589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2011-10-387365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzwaelder</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartholomae</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaoui</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilz</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Glimm</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>von Kalle</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>High-resolution insertion-site analysis by linear amplification-mediated PCR (LAM-PCR)</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth1103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18049469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sengupta</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Targeting the latent reservoir for HIV-1</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2018.04.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29768175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabi</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laird</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisele</surname> <given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolick</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>A novel PCR assay for quantification of HIV-1 RNA</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>6521</fpage><lpage>6525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00006-13</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Capoferri</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabi</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laird</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosmane</surname> <given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolick</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ke</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Flavell</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Transcriptional reprogramming during Effector-to-Memory transition renders CD4<sup>+</sup> T Cells Permissive for Latent HIV-1 Infection</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2017.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29045905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Symons</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chopra</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malatinkova</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Spiegelaere</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Leary</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Abana</surname> <given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezaei</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandekerckhove</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallal</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewin</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname> <given-names>PU</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>HIV integration sites in latently infected cell lines: evidence of ongoing replication</article-title><source>Retrovirology</source><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>2</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12977-016-0325-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garg</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname> <given-names>CYK</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Styrchak</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Edlefsen</surname> <given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullins</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Frenkel</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Proliferation of cells with HIV integrated into Cancer genes contributes to persistent infection</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>345</volume><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1256304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wenzel</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Speidell</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Flowers</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Avdoshina</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mocchetti</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Histone deacetylase 6 inhibition rescues axonal transport impairments and prevents the neurotoxicity of HIV-1 envelope protein gp120</article-title><source>Cell Death &amp; Disease</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e674</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-019-1920-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>H-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Connell</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinoso</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrum</surname> <given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolick</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Small-molecule screening using a human primary cell model of HIV latency identifies compounds that reverse latency without cellular activation</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Investigation</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>3473</fpage><lpage>3486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI39199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiao</surname> <given-names>FZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname> <given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Histone deacetylase 6 inhibitor ACY-1215 protects against experimental acute liver failure by regulating the TLR4-MAPK/NF-κB pathway</article-title><source>Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2017.10.103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29112935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiao</surname> <given-names>FZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname> <given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Inhibition of HDAC6 attenuates LPS-induced inflammation in macrophages by regulating oxidative stress and suppressing the TLR4-MAPK/NF-κB pathways</article-title><source>Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy</source><volume>117</volume><elocation-id>109166</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2019.109166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31255993</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.63810.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Symons</surname><given-names>Jori</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University Medical Center</institution><country>Netherlands</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>Peter Doherty Institute of Infection and Immunity</institution><country>Australia</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife publishes the most substantive revision requests and the accompanying author responses.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Acceptance summary:</bold></p><p>The authors demonstrate that their dual reporter virus is an efficient tool to determine latency and to test latency reversal agents. These findings will contribute to the armoury to study and combat HIV latency.</p><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Infection with a newly-designed dual fluorescent reporter HIV-1 effectively identifies latently infected CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by 3 peer reviewers, one of whom is a member of our Board of Reviewing Editors, and the evaluation has been overseen by Miles Davenport as the Senior Editor. The following individual involved in review of your submission has agreed to reveal their identity: Thomas Rasmussen (Reviewer #2).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>As the editors have judged that your manuscript is of interest, but as described below that additional experiments are required before it is published, we would like to draw your attention to changes in our revision policy that we have made in response to COVID-19 (https://elifesciences.org/articles/57162). First, because many researchers have temporarily lost access to the labs, we will give authors as much time as they need to submit revised manuscripts. We are also offering, if you choose, to post the manuscript to bioRxiv (if it is not already there) along with this decision letter and a formal designation that the manuscript is &quot;in revision at <italic>eLife</italic>&quot;. Please let us know if you would like to pursue this option. (If your work is more suitable for medRxiv, you will need to post the preprint yourself, as the mechanisms for us to do so are still in development.)</p><p>Summary:</p><p>In this paper, Cai and colleagues describe a dual fluorescent reporter virus, DFV-B, that was used to infect primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and Jurkat cells. In DFV-B infected primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, latently infected cells could be sorted out and in those more than 50% could be activated to produce GFP (under control of LTR) using PMA/ionomycin stimulation. In Jurkat cells the authors demonstrated the establishment of a latently infected cell line model of HIV latency that was used to identify ACY-1215, a selective inhibitor of HDAC6, as a potential latency-reversing agent.</p><p>The manuscript is well written and in general, data are clearly and soundly presented. As such, this work should be of interest for the field of HIV latency and cure, but there are a few outstanding issues that may require further clarification or modification:</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1. The results show that the ratio of mC cells tot total infected cells increased over prolonged culturing in CD4 T cells. However, as the mC signal also dropped 10 fold. Additionally, there seems to be cells that solely transcribe the productive reporter.</p><p>The drop in the latent reporter needs to be explained. My understanding is that this reporter should be continuously transcribed. A loss of signal of the latent reporter is a known problem with dual reporter viral systems. Why does this system show less efficiency in primary cells compared to cell lines.</p><p>2. Figure 2: I suggest including the PMA/ionomycin stimulation of DN and DP cells in the actual Figure 2 (currently in the supplement) as these are good controls and add further credibility to the conclusion.</p><p>3. Figure 4: The process of model generation is not quite clear from text and Figure 4. Please further clarify identification of latently infected (mCherry) and DP cells. In that process I recommend incorporating the gating plots from the supplementary figure to further clarify gating strategy and how this is different to the sorting plots shown in Figure 4B. It is also not clear at which time points in the model (shown in Figure 4B) cells were sorted and then subjected to the various stimuli.</p><p>4. The authors mention that previous J-Lat models are disadvantaged due to their identical integration sites, but that their J-mC model of DFB-V infection should harbour diverse integration sites. Yet, no data are presented to confirm this assumption.</p><p>5. The use of the developed model systems in the identification of ACY-1215 is</p><p>interesting and relevant, but several important pieces of information are missing, which will further strengthen the presentation of these data:</p><p>a. The dose-dependent activation of GFP expression with increasing concentration of ricolinistat looks consistent and credible, but information on how long cells were stimulated for should be included in the figure or figure text, as should the utilised concentration of SAHA. It would also strengthen the interpretation if the authors could relate the used concentrations of ricolinistat to therapeutic levels during clinical dosing, ie are these levels physiologically relevant?</p><p>b. Figure 5G: Given the significant variation among individuals in cell-associated HIV RNA in the absence of stimulation, it would useful to also display the actual measured levels across DMSO, PMA/ionomycin and ACY conditions in Figure 5G. Also, which concentration of ACY was used here and is this therapeutically relevant? Finally, how many isolated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were analysed per condition?</p><p>6. Depending on the above clarifications with regard to the most relevant concentration of ricolinistat for ex vivo and in vitro use, the compound looks like it could have similar potency to vorinostat, which is not overly impressive and may not offer any advantage compared to previously tested LRAs. One difference could be its HDAC6 selectivity, which may offer a better effect/toxicity index as hinted by the authors, but this is not really elaborated on any further. I recommend adding this aspect to the discussion of this compound by comparing clinically available data with this compound and selected pan-HDAC inhibitors.</p><p>7. Figure 1c demonstrates that the viability of the total cell population after day 6 of viral infection is rapidly decreasing. Was the viability of the mC cell population after 7 days (moment of reactivation) also reduced and if so, how does this impact latency and the subsequent reactivation of HIV.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.63810.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1. The results show that the ratio of mC cells tot total infected cells increased over prolonged culturing in CD4 T cells. However, as the mC signal also dropped 10 fold. Additionally, there seems to be cells that solely transcribe the productive reporter.</p><p>The drop in the latent reporter needs to be explained. My understanding is that this reporter should be continuously transcribed. A loss of signal of the latent reporter is a known problem with dual reporter viral systems. Why does this system show less efficiency in primary cells compared to cell lines.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewers for the helpful comment. In Figure 1B, as described by the reviewers that the ratio of mC cells to total infected cells increased over prolonged culturing in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, but DP cells to total infected cells decreased. We think this phenotype can be attributed to two factors: 1) the productive infected DP cells are more prone to apoptosis caused by the cytotoxicity of HIV-1 proteins; 2) a portion of survived DP cells gradually transform to mC cells because HIV-1 transcription is turned off during the culturing process, this is also evidenced by previous works on primary cell models of HIV-1 latency, as some infected cells gradually lost the fluorescent signal of the reporter viruses (Yang et al., JCI 2009; 119: 3473–3485, He et al., <italic>eLife</italic> 2019; 8: e46181 and Scandella et al., Scientific Reports 2020; 10: 14642). To further verify these DP cells are more prone to apoptosis, we monitored the percentage of apoptotic cells after DFV-B infection by Annexin V and Zombie (Cat#423105, Biolegend) staining. We found that DP cells had significantly higher proportion of Annexin V-positive cells than mC cells on 3-7 days post-infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="sa2fig1">Author response image 1</xref>), which clearly demonstrated that DP cells contained more early apoptotic cells, that contributed to the decreased ratio of DP cells in the total infected cell population.</p><fig id="sa2fig1"><label>Author response image 1.</label><caption><title>The expression of apoptotic markers on DP and mC cells during post-infection culturing of primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells.</title><p>(A) The expression of apoptotic markers on DP and mC cells at 3 days post-infection. Flow cytometry chart shows the representative measurement of annexin V and zombie in DFV-B infected primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. (B) Data from Day 3, 5, 7 post-infection are displayed graphically on each indicated time point. Histograms show the percentage of positive cells. Error bars represent SDs of three technical replicates. p-values calculated using unpaired t test. ns, not significant; *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-63810-resp-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><p>In Figure 3E, we showed that the level of mC cells dropped 10-fold from 3.09% to 0.33% as concerned by the reviewers. We apologize for not stating it clear enough in the original manuscript. In fact, this data here was not generated by one-time infection and follow-up (such as Figure 1B), but was generated by multiple independent infections administered at different indicated time points, which was not the case of loss of signal of the latent reporter. The purpose here was to further verify whether HIV-1 latency was preferentially established in EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, which our previous work had reported (Shan et al., Immunity 2017; 47: 766-775). Our data here showed that when the infection was administered at EMT stage (Day 6, 8, 10 after αCD3/28 stimulation), although the overall infectivity decreased, the percentages of directly generated latent infection (mC cells) significantly increased. This was demonstrated by the ratio of mC cells to total infected cells in Figure 3F, which was increased from 15.7% (Day 0 infection) to 64.8% (Day 10 infection). Our experiment confirmed that HIV-1 latency was preferentially established in EMT CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells.</p><p>Additionally, regarding the potential problem of loss of signal of the latent reporter, we indeed observed that a tiny portion of single GFP<sup>+</sup> cells existed after DFV-B infection (Figure 1B and Figure 3E). We traced and found that the proportion of single GFP<sup>+</sup> cells decreased from 0.7% to 0.2% (similar to uninfected cells) as the culture time increased (updated Figure 2—figure supplement 1C), which is significantly lower than the previous reported dual reporter viral systems (Calvanese et al., Virology 2013; 446: 283–292 and Kim Y et al., Journal of the International AIDS Society 2019; 22: e25425). Meanwhile, the integrated DNA levels of GFP and mCherry in this single GFP<sup>+</sup> cells were not different (updated Figure 2—figure supplement 1D), suggesting both reporters were still stably integrated. We speculated that this unlikely phenotype of single GFP<sup>+</sup> cells could be due to the differential dynamics of fluorescent protein degradation. We agree with the reviewer’s comment about the problem of potential loss of signal of the dual reporter viral systems, we have since added additional words (lines 287-294 in revised manuscript) in the Discussion section to address.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2. Figure 2: I suggest including the PMA/ionomycin stimulation of DN and DP cells in the actual Figure 2 (currently in the supplement) as these are good controls and add further credibility to the conclusion.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewers for the insightful suggestion. We have modified Figure 2 by adding the PMA/ionomycin stimulation of DN and DP cells (Figure 2B). This data showed DP and DN cells were not affected by PMA/ionomycin stimulation, but more than half of the mC cells were reactivated, again suggesting that infection of DFV-B in primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells could directly identify live latently infected cells.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3. Figure 4: The process of model generation is not quite clear from text and Figure 4. Please further clarify identification of latently infected (mCherry) and DP cells. In that process I recommend incorporating the gating plots from the supplementary figure to further clarify gating strategy and how this is different to the sorting plots shown in Figure 4B. It is also not clear at which time points in the model (shown in Figure 4B) cells were sorted and then subjected to the various stimuli.</p></disp-quote><p>We apologize for not stating it clear enough in the original manuscript about the process of J-mC cells generation. We have adopted the reviewer`s suggestion to show gating strategy in the modified Figure 4B. To clarify the process of J-mC generation, firstly, Jurkat cells were infected by DFV-B incorporating a VSVG envelope at 250 ng virus per million cells on Day 0 in CFM. At Day 7, the single mCherry positive cells were sorted according to the red-gated plots in Figure 4B, in which the purity of the single mCherry positive cells was greater than 99%. Next, the cells were cultured for another 30 days in CFM. At Day 37, 23.9% of the mC cells were converted to productive cells, probably due to spontaneous activation. At the same time, a small dose of TNF-α (5 ng/ml) was added to the culture and maintained for 7 days to further activate those unstable cells that were probably in the borderline state of latency. More than 70% of mC cells were reactivated at day 44. Meanwhile, the second sorting of single mCherry positive cells were performed, and subsequently the third and fourth sorting of single mCherry positive cells were performed at Day 58 and 72. J-mC cells were finalized at Day 86. Each sorting strategy was performed by the red-gated plots in Figure 4B. Besides, we have updated the experimental procedure in “Generation of J-mC cells” in the Materials and methods (lines 432-443 in revised manuscript).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4. The authors mention that previous J-Lat models are disadvantaged due to their identical integration sites, but that their J-mC model of DFB-V infection should harbour diverse integration sites. Yet, no data are presented to confirm this assumption.</p></disp-quote><p>We totally agree with the reviewers that this is an important point, so we have added a series of new data (the updated Figure 5) to show J-mC cells indeed harbored diverse integration sites. Briefly, we performed linear amplification–mediated high-throughput genome-wide sequencing (LAM-HTGTS) (Hu et al., Nature Protocol 2016; 11: 853-871) for HIV-1 integration site analysis on J-mC cells. We first confirmed that LAM-HTGTS was feasible for HIV-1 integration sites analysis by applying the method on J-Lat 8.4 and J-Lat 15.4 cells (updated Figure 5A and 5B). For J-mC cells, 30 days after they were obtained via multiple rounds of sorting, total DNA of the obtained J-mC cells was extracted with tissue DNA kit (OMEGA) and the genomic DNA was sheared by sonication, and subjected to LAM-HTGTS. Our data clearly demonstrated that the integration landscape of latent HIV-1 in J-mC cells was highly diverse, which represents a major strength of this cell model of HIV-1 latency comparing to the other existing cell line models. Updated descriptions of the new data have been added in the main text (lines 199-224 in revised manuscript).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5. The use of the developed model systems in the identification of ACY-1215 is</p><p>interesting and relevant, but several important pieces of information are missing, which will further strengthen the presentation of these data:</p><p>a. The dose-dependent activation of GFP expression with increasing concentration of ricolinistat looks consistent and credible, but information on how long cells were stimulated for should be included in the figure or figure text, as should the utilised concentration of SAHA. It would also strengthen the interpretation if the authors could relate the used concentrations of ricolinistat to therapeutic levels during clinical dosing, ie are these levels physiologically relevant?</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewers for pointing out this important issue. We have updated Figure 6 and added concentrations of SAHA and ACY-1215 used in the experiments. Briefly, 1 μM SAHA and 3 μM ACY-1215 were used in Figure 6 and the other supplementary figures. The recommended clinical dose of SAHA and ACY-1215 were 200-600mg once daily (QD) for 28 days (Richardson et al., Leuk Lymphoma 2008;49(3): 502–507 and Siegel et al., Blood Cancer J. 2014;4: e182) or 160 mg twice daily (BID) for 28 days (Vogl et al., Clin Cancer Res 2017; 23(13): 3307–3315 and Amengual et al., The Oncologist 2021; 10.1002/onco.13673), respectively. For in vitro system, ACY-1215 was administered at concentrations of 1–10 μM (Carew et al., Blood Advances 2018; 3:1318-1329 and Chneg et al., Biomedicine and Pharmacotherapy 2018; <italic>109</italic>, 2464–2471). Our application of 3 μM ACY-1215 here was in line with the other studies and was in the achievable range for clinical trials.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>b. Figure 5G: Given the significant variation among individuals in cell-associated HIV RNA in the absence of stimulation, it would useful to also display the actual measured levels across DMSO, PMA/ionomycin and ACY conditions in Figure 5G. Also, which concentration of ACY was used here and is this therapeutically relevant? Finally, how many isolated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were analysed per condition?</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewers for this helpful suggestion. We have now added the actual measured levels of cell-associated HIV-1 RNA in the updated Figure 6G, in which the absolute copies were quantified across DMSO, PMA/ionomycin and ACY-1215 treatments. The original Figure 5G has been changed to the updated Figure 6H. 3 μM of ACY-1215 was used in the experiment and 1 million of purified CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from each ART-treated patient were used per condition. The therapeutically relevant concentration for ACY-1215 was addressed in the response above.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>6. Depending on the above clarifications with regard to the most relevant concentration of ricolinistat for ex vivo and in vitro use, the compound looks like it could have similar potency to vorinostat, which is not overly impressive and may not offer any advantage compared to previously tested LRAs. One difference could be its HDAC6 selectivity, which may offer a better effect/toxicity index as hinted by the authors, but this is not really elaborated on any further. I recommend adding this aspect to the discussion of this compound by comparing clinically available data with this compound and selected pan-HDAC inhibitors.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewers for the insightful suggestion. We have adopted this suggestion and added another paragraph in the Discussion section to elaborate this important aspect (lines 341-358 in revised manuscript).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>7. Figure 1c demonstrates that the viability of the total cell population after day 6 of viral infection is rapidly decreasing. Was the viability of the mC cell population after 7 days (moment of reactivation) also reduced and if so, how does this impact latency and the subsequent reactivation of HIV.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewers for the comment. The viability shown in Figure 1C was monitored in primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, which were previously stimulated by αCD3/CD28. In the absence of IL-2 supplement, it was expected to see the viability of the infected cells decreased as the culturing time increased. As we stated in the response to Question 1 above, primary mC cells were significantly less apoptotic than DP cells, which also suggested that the cessation of HIV-1 protein production in mC cells improved survival. To further address the reviewer’s concern, we tested the viability of the mC, DP and DN cells at 12h post-sorting, 3 days post-DMSO and 3 days post-PMA treatment. As shown in the updated Figure 2—figure supplement 1B, the viabilities of DP, DN and mC cells were comparable between DMSO and PMA treatment, and the cells got activated by the stimulation of PMA, an indication for functional cellular response. The new data in the updated Figure 2B also demonstrated that the latency reversal effect was not affected by the viabilities of DP, DN and mC cells. Taken together, the viability of the mC cells should have minimal effect on latency and the subsequent reactivation of HIV-1.</p></body></sub-article></article>