<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">36268</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cytokinin transfer by a free-living mirid to <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> recapitulates a strategy of endophytic insects</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-109309"><name><surname>Brütting</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9698-4400</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">†</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-107663"><name><surname>Crava</surname><given-names>Cristina Maria</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3774-4567</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">†</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa1">‡</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-109935"><name><surname>Schäfer</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa2">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-1399"><name><surname>Schuman</surname><given-names>Meredith C</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3159-3534</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-42414"><name><surname>Meldau</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa3">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-109311"><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>Nora</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa4">¶</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-1013"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>Ian T</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5371-2974</contrib-id><email>baldwin@ice.mpg.de</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Molecular Ecology</institution><institution>Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Jena</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Leipzig</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>Joerg</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of British Columbia</institution><country>Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>Detlef</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>Max Planck Institute for Developmental Biology</institution><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa1"><label>‡</label><p>Department of Biology and Biotechnology, University of Pavia, Pavia, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa2"><label>§</label><p>Institute for Evolution and Biodiversity, University of Münster, Münster, Germany</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa3"><label>#</label><p>Research &amp; Development, Molecular Physiology, KWS SAAT SE, Einbeck, Germany</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa4"><label>¶</label><p>Research Group Sequestration and Detoxification in Insects, Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology, Jena, Germany</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="equal-contrib1"><label>†</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>17</day><month>07</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e36268</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-03-01"><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-07-05"><day>05</day><month>07</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018, Brütting et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Brütting et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-36268-v3.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.001</object-id><p>Endophytic insects provide the textbook examples of herbivores that manipulate their host plant’s physiology, putatively altering source/sink relationships by transferring cytokinins (CK) to create ‘green islands’ that increase the nutritional value of infested tissues. However, unambiguous demonstrations of CK transfer are lacking. Here we show that feeding by the free-living herbivore <italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> on <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> is characterized by stable nutrient levels, increased CK levels and alterations in CK-related transcript levels in attacked leaves, in striking similarity to endophytic insects. Using <sup>15</sup>N-isotope labeling, we demonstrate that the CK <italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-isopentenyladenine (IP) is transferred from insects to plants via their oral secretions. In the field, <italic>T. notatus</italic> preferentially attacks leaves with transgenically increased CK levels; plants with abrogated CK-perception are less tolerant of <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding damage. We infer that this free-living insect uses CKs to manipulate source/sink relationships to increase food quality and minimize the fitness consequences of its feeding.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>Many insects use plants for food and for shelter. To protect themselves, plants often develop defense mechanisms that deter or debilitate their attackers, such as producing toxins or storing nutrients away from the attacked tissues.</p><p>But some insects manage to counter the plants’ defense responses. Such species are often less mobile and spend a large part of their life in a restricted area of the plant, for example, inside plant tissues. Also known as ‘endophytic’ animals, these insects can even manipulate the signaling system in a plant, such as a class of plant hormones called cytokinins, which help plants to grow and to develop seeds and nutrient-storing fruits or young leaves.</p><p>Researchers have previously assumed that endophytic animals target cytokinins because they are restricted to living in certain areas within the plant, and – unlike ‘free-living’ insects – lack access to other, potentially more nutritious feeding sites. By modifying cytokinins, the location-bound insects could create their own ‘nutrient pool’. Until now, it was unclear how insects transfer cytokinins to a plant and if this ability was restricted to endophytic insects.</p><p>To investigate this further, Brütting, Crava et al. studied the response of coyote tobacco plants infested with a free-living insect, the sap-sucking bug <italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic>. The experiments revealed that the insects’ bodies contained large quantities of a type of cytokinin, even when insects were raised on artificial diets.</p><p>Brütting, Crava et al. then developed a method to clearly distinguish cytokinins present in the insects from those produced by the plants to test whether <italic>T. notatus</italic> can transfer these plant hormones during feeding. The results showed that similar to endophytic insects, <italic>T. notatus</italic> injects cytokinins into the attacked leaves, presumably to create a stable nutritious environment.</p><p>Insects represent the largest and most diverse group of organisms on Earth, including many crop pests. Despite their detrimental impact on the environment and the health of the farmers, pesticides are used predominantly for pest control. A better understanding of how insects use cytokinins to increase the nutritional value of the leaves may help us to find ways to increase the crop’s tolerance to insect attacks.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>tupiocoris notatus</kwd><kwd>nicotiana attenuata</kwd><kwd>cytokinins</kwd><kwd>herbivores</kwd><kwd>plant manipulation</kwd><kwd>effectors</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Other</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004189</institution-id><institution>Max-Planck-Gesellschaft</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Open-access funding</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Brütting</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><name><surname>Crava</surname><given-names>Cristina Maria</given-names></name><name><surname>Schäfer</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuman</surname><given-names>Meredith C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldau</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>Nora</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>Ian T</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000780</institution-id><institution>European Commission</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>ERC Advanced Grant no. 293926</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Brütting</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuman</surname><given-names>Meredith C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldau</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001659</institution-id><institution>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Collaborative Research Centre SFB 1127</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Crava</surname><given-names>Cristina Maria</given-names></name><name><surname>Schäfer</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Cytokinin-dependent manipulation of plant metabolism is a strategy employed not only by gallers and leaf-miners but also by a free-living insect, <italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic>, which directly transfers cytokinins at feeding sites to manipulate its host plant.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Insect herbivores are under constant pressure from their host plants: they must adapt to toxic or anti-digestive defense compounds whose levels often dramatically increase in response to insect feeding; and their food source has low nitrogen to carbon ratios and a dietary value which decreases as leaves mature and senesce. Some herbivorous insects have developed strategies to overcome the low nutritional contents of their host plants and have evolved specialized mechanisms to tolerate, or even co-opt toxic plant defense metabolites for their own uses, in an apparent evolutionary arms race (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Strong et al., 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Després et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Heckel, 2014</xref>).</p><p>Phytophagous insects can be categorized as either endophytic or free-living depending on the relationships that they establish with their host plant. This distinction is not binary and many transitional forms exist even within the same taxa. Consequently, the large differences in herbivorous lifestyles has selected for plant defense responses that counter different herbivory strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Kessler and Baldwin, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Schuman and Baldwin, 2016</xref>). Free-living insects are mobile on their host plants, moving among plants, and frequently among different plant species. As a consequence of this mobility, they can freely choose tissues that are most nutritious or least defended, but the most nutritious tissues are often highly defended, resulting in a potential trade-off for herbivores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ohnmeiss and Baldwin, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>). To avoid herbivore-induced defenses, free-living insects often move to other plant parts or even other host plants in response to defense activation, and the advantages of such movement are readily seen when induced defenses are abrogated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Paschold et al., 2007</xref>) or experimentally manipulated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">van Dam et al., 2000</xref>). In contrast, endophytic insects develop more intimate relationships with their host plants as they are sedentary and spend a large portion of their life cycle within plant tissues. They have evolved strategies to overcome many of the plant defenses by hijacking plant metabolism and reprogramming plant physiology in their favor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Giron et al., 2016</xref>). Often the only viable plant defense is the ‘scorched earth’ response, whereby infested tissues are abscised from the plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Fernandes et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>To date, the best-studied examples of endophytic plant-manipulating species, featured in most textbooks of plant physiology, are the gall-forming insects and leaf-miners. Gall-forming organisms, which include not only several orders of insects but also mites, nematodes and microbes, promote abnormal plant growth by reprogramming the expression of plant genes, to create novel organs that provide favorable environments for the exploiter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Stone and Schönrogge, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Shorthouse et al., 2005</xref>). Advantages for the gall-formers range from an improved nutritional value, with reduced defense levels, to protection from diseases, competitors, predators, parasitoids and unfavorable abiotic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hartley, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Stone and Schönrogge, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Allison and Schultz, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Harris et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Saltzmann et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Nabity et al., 2013</xref>). Manipulations of leaf-mining larvae do not result in the formation of new macroscopic structures like galls but they are often revealed during senescence of host tissues, where ‘green islands’ appear around the active feeding sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Engelbrecht, 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Engelbrecht et al., 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Giron et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kaiser et al., 2010</xref>). Such green islands maintain a high level of photosynthetic activity typical of non-senescent leaves, thus providing nutrition for the larvae which feed on them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Behr et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Body et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">Zhang et al., 2016</xref>). In this way, green islands reflect a battle between plant and infesting insect during the nutrient recovery phase that precedes abscission. The host plant tries to recover nutrients from the senescent leaf, whereas the insect tries to maintain a nutritious environment so as to complete its development.</p><p>The most likely effectors used by insects to manipulate a plant’s normal physiological response to wounding are phytohormones, since significant levels of some well-known wound-responsive phytohormones, including cytokinins (CKs), abscisic acid (ABA) and auxins, have been found in the body and salivary secretions of a number of gall-forming insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mapes and Davies, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Straka et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Tooker and De Moraes, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Yamaguchi et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Tanaka et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Takei et al., 2015</xref>), as well as in the bodies and labial glands of leaf-mining larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Engelbrecht et al., 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Body et al., 2013</xref>). Amongst these phytohormones, CKs deserve additional discussion due to their role in the formation of green islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Engelbrecht, 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Engelbrecht, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Engelbrecht et al., 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Giron et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kaiser et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Body et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>). CKs are adenine derivatives which play a key role in the regulation of plant growth and development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Sakakibara, 2006</xref>). They are known for their capacity to increase photosynthetic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Jordi et al., 2000</xref>), determine sink strength (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mok and Mok, 2001</xref>) and inhibit senescence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Richmond and Lang, 1957</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Gan and Amasino, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Ori et al., 1999</xref>). More recently, CKs have been shown to regulate herbivory-induced defense signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Schäfer et al., 2015b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Schäfer et al., 2015c</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>). The long history of investigating CKs in the formation of green islands dates back to the late 1960’s, to reports of increased levels of CKs in affected tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Engelbrecht, 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Engelbrecht et al., 1969</xref>). In the last decade, studies on the leaf-mining larvae of <italic>Phyllonorycter blancardella</italic> identified CKs as the causative factors for the ‘green island’ phenomenon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Giron et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kaiser et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Body et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>). These studies suggested that insects could be the source of phytohormones used to manipulate plant physiological responses. However, a clear demonstration of the ability of insects to transfer CKs to a host plant remains elusive.</p><p>To assess whether an insect actively transfers CKs to manipulate plant physiology, we studied the interactions between the well-established ecological model-plant <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> and one of its most abundant specialist herbivores, <italic>Tupiocoris notatus. N. attenuata</italic> is a wild diploid tobacco species native to southwestern North America. <italic>T. notatus</italic> is a free-living, 3–4 mm mirid bug (Miridae, Heteroptera) specialized to tobacco species and a few other solanaceous plants including <italic>Datura wrightii</italic>. It is a piercing-sucking cell-content feeder that damages the surface of the leaves without removing foliar material. Its feeding behavior is in sharp contrast with the feeding behavior of a well-studied specialist herbivore of <italic>N. attenuata</italic>, the lepidopteran <italic>Manduca sexta</italic>, whose chewing larvae cause extensive tissue damage and a well characterized defense response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Baldwin, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kessler and Baldwin, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Kessler et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Steppuhn et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">Zavala et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Schuman et al., 2012</xref>). When plants are attacked by <italic>M. sexta</italic>, specific insect-derived fatty acid-amino acid conjugates elicit a defense response regulated by a burst of jasmonic-acid (JA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Baldwin, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Halitschke et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Kessler et al., 2004</xref>). This jasmonate burst triggers the accumulation of defense metabolites like nicotine, caffeoylputrescine, diterpene-glycosides and tripsyin-proteinase inhibitors. It has also strong effects on the regulation of primary metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Voelckel and Baldwin, 2004</xref>): sugars, starch and total soluble proteins readily decrease in the attacked leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Ullmann-Zeunert et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Machado et al., 2015</xref>), as does photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Meza-Canales et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>In contrast, infestation with <italic>T. notatus</italic> in nature, surprisingly, does not decrease plant fitness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Kessler and Baldwin, 2004</xref>), despite resulting in damage to large portions of photosynthetically active leaf area. Tissues around <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding sites have increased rates of photosynthesis per chlorophyll content that may compensate for the damage caused by herbivore feeding, resulting from an active ingredient of the oral secretion of <italic>T. notatus</italic> which remains to be identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Halitschke et al., 2011</xref>). We previously observed increased damage by <italic>T. notatus</italic> in tissues that were enriched in CKs through the transgenic manipulation of <italic>N. attenuata</italic> CK metabolism, using plants expressing a dexamethasone (DEX)-inducible construct driving transcription of the CK biosynthesis gene, isopentenyltransferase (IPT, i-ov<italic>ipt</italic>). Individual DEX-treated leaves of field-grown plants suffered more damage from <italic>T. notatus</italic> than did mock-treated leaves. This led to the hypothesis that increased CK levels promote better nutritional quality, which in turn increases <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schäfer et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Here, we report that <italic>T. notatus</italic> adults and nymphs contain high concentrations of two CKs. When confined to feeding on single <italic>N. attenuata</italic> leaves, concentrations of CKs increase in attacked leaves throughout the feeding period, with consequences for nutrient concentrations. Using <sup>15</sup>N-labeled tracers, we demonstrate that <italic>T. notatus</italic> transfer CKs to the leaves on which they feed. Finally, we analyzed how changes to CK metabolism in plants affected <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding preferences. We conclude that CK-dependent manipulation of plant metabolism is not only a strategy used by gall-forming insects or leaf-miners, but also employed by this free-living insect, which directly transfers CKs at feeding sites to manipulate its host plant.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding induces the JA pathway and associated defenses in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic></title><p>To characterize the defensive response of <italic>N. attenuata</italic> to mirid attack, we analyzed jasmonate hormones and defense metabolites that are known to be induced by <italic>M. sexta,</italic> as well as <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Kessler and Baldwin, 2004</xref>). Continuous feeding by <italic>T. notatus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a</xref>) causes visible damage to <italic>N. attenuata</italic> leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1b</xref>) and triggers defense responses in attacked leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1c–j</xref>). Three days of <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding induced levels of the defense metabolites nicotine and caffeoylputrescine (CP), as well as trypsin proteinase inhibitor activity (TPI) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1c–e</xref>). <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding also elevated the levels of jasmonic acid (JA), its precursor <italic>cis</italic>-(+)−12-oxophytodienoic acid (OPDA) and its bioactive isoleucine conjugate (JA-Ile) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1f–h</xref>). Interestingly, there was also a significant increase in salicylic acid (SA), but no influence on abscisic acid (ABA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1i,j</xref>). JA and JA-Ile levels triggered by <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding remained elevated for up to six days when mirids were confined to feed on a single leaf (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1a–c</xref>). Their concentrations remained higher than controls even when <italic>T. notatus</italic> were free to move to other parts of the plant, although they steadily decreased over the six days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1d–f</xref>) These results demonstrate that <italic>N. attenuata</italic>’s response to <italic>T. notatus</italic> involves activation of JA signaling and downstream defense responses.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.003</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding induces JA-dependent defense responses in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) <italic>T. notatus</italic> adult. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative pictures of a control leaf of <italic>N. attenuata</italic> and a leaf after 3 d of continuous <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding. (<bold>C–J</bold>) Defense metabolites and stress-related phytohormone levels induced by 3 d of <italic>T. notatus</italic> attack (filled columns) compared with control leaves (open) from unattacked plants: (<bold>C</bold>) nicotine, (<bold>D</bold>) caffeoylputrescine (CP), (<bold>E</bold>) trypsin proteinase inhibitor (TPI) activity, (<bold>F</bold>) jasmonic acid (JA), (<bold>G</bold>) jasmonic acid-isoleucine conjugate (JA-Ile), (<bold>H</bold>) <italic>cis</italic>-(+)−12-oxophytodienoic acid (OPDA), (<bold>I</bold>) salicylic acid (SA) and (<bold>J</bold>) abscisic acid (ABA). Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney test was used to identify statistically significant differences between control and attacked leaves. (<bold>C</bold>) nicotine: N = 6, W = 5, p=0.022; (<bold>D</bold>) CP: N = 6, W = 0, p=0.001, (<bold>E</bold>) TPI: N = 7, W = 0, p&lt;0.001, (<bold>F</bold>) JA: N = 7, W = 0, p&lt;0.001, (<bold>G</bold>) JA-Ile: N = 7, W = 0, p&lt;0.001; (<bold>H</bold>) OPDA: N = 7, W = 0, p&lt;0.001; (<bold>I</bold>) SA: N = 7, W = 0, p&lt;0.001: (<bold>J</bold>) ABA: N = 7, W = 20, p=0.620. *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001, n.s.: not significant. Error bars depict standard errors. FM: fresh mass. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_1 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig1-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding increases levels of JA and JA-Ile.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental setup corresponding to (<bold>B</bold>) and (<bold>C</bold>). On each plant, we enclosed one leaf in a plastic clipcage with (clipcage+ <italic>T. notatus</italic>) or without (clipcage) 20 <italic>T. notatus.</italic> Additionally, we collected uncaged control leaves (control, dotted line). (<bold>B</bold>) Jasmonic acid (JA) and (<bold>C</bold>) jasmonic acid-isoleucine conjugate (JA-Ile) were monitored over 144 hr. Data were analyzed with ANCOVA on square root-transformed data with mirid as factor and time as continuous explanatory variable. (<bold>B</bold>) JA: time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 38.42, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 93.82, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 10.89, p=0.002. (<bold>C</bold>) JA-Ile: time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 10.17, p=0.002; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 110.10, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 1.292, p=0.261). Error bars depict standard errors (N ≥ 3). (<bold>D</bold>) Experimental setup corresponding to (<bold>E</bold>) and (<bold>F</bold>). A whole plant was caged in an insect cage with (cage+ <italic>T. notatus</italic>) or without (control cage) <italic>T. notatus</italic> adults. (<bold>E</bold>) JA and (<bold>F</bold>) JA-Ile kinetics were monitored over 144 hr after the start of herbivore exposure. Data were analyzed with generalized least squares (GLS) model with mirid as factor and time as continuous explanatory variable. (<bold>E</bold>) JA: time F<sub>1,44</sub> = 14.878, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 30.218, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 14.471, p&lt;0.001. (<bold>F</bold>) JA-Ile: time F<sub>1,44</sub> = 4.123, p=0.048; mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 33.920, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 3.978, p=0.052. Error bars depict standard errors (N = 4). FM: fresh mass. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_1_S1 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig1-figsupp1-v3"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title><italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding does not negatively affect the nutritional quality of the attacked leaves</title><p>Feeding by <italic>M. sexta</italic> is detrimental to <italic>N. attenuata</italic> fitness. It causes reduction of photosynthesis in attacked leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Halitschke et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Meza-Canales et al., 2017</xref>) and a decrease in sugar and total soluble protein (TSP) contents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Ullmann-Zeunert et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Machado et al., 2015</xref>). In contrast, <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding seems to increase photosynthetic activity in attacked leaves, when accounting for tissue damaged by the feeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Halitschke et al., 2011</xref>). We measured the impact of continuous <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding over several days on the nutritional quality of the attacked leaves. We analyzed TSPs, sugar and starch levels, as well as measuring photosynthetic rates and chlorophyll contents of leaves over a period of 144 hr.</p><p>Visibly heavily damaged leaves did not show significant decreases in nutrient levels when mirids were confined to feed on a single leaf with a small plastic cage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2a</xref>). TSP levels decreased with time in a clipcage but mirid feeding did not have a significant influence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2b</xref>). Furthermore, we did not observe any significant changes in starch, sucrose, glucose or fructose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2c–f</xref>). Although we did not observe changes in carbohydrate levels, photosynthesis was significantly reduced in attacked leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1b</xref>). In contrast, mirid feeding had no effect on chlorophyll contents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1c</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.005</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding on single leaves does not significantly change nutrient levels.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental setup: On each plant we enclosed one leaf in a plastic clipcage with (clipcage +<italic>T. notatus</italic>; solid line) or without (clipcage, dashed line) 20 <italic>T. notatus.</italic> Additionally, we collected uncaged control leaves (control, dotted line). (<bold>B</bold>) Total soluble proteins (TSP), (<bold>C</bold>) starch, (<bold>D</bold>) sucrose, (<bold>E</bold>) glucose and (<bold>F</bold>) fructose were analyzed in a time-kinetic from 1 to 144 hr. Statistically significant differences were identified with ANCOVA with mirid as factor and time as continuous explanatory variable. (<bold>B</bold>) TSP: log transformed time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 14.317, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 2.438, p=0.125; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.479, p=0.492. (<bold>C</bold>) log transformed starch: time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 137.376, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 3.749, p=0.058; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 2.651, p=0.110. (<bold>D</bold>) sucrose: time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 13.847, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 3.883, p=0.054; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 5.894, p=0.019. (<bold>E</bold>) glucose: time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 173.06, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.050, p=0.823; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.107, p=0.745. (<bold>F</bold>) fructose: log transformed time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.505, p=0.480; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.433, p=0.513; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 5.798, p=0.020. Error bars depict standard errors (N ≥ 3). FM: fresh mass. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_2 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig2-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.006</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding on single leaves decreases photosynthetic rates while not influencing chlorophyll contents.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental setup: On each plant we enclosed one leaf in a plastic clipcage with (clipcage +<italic>T. notatus</italic>; solid line) or without (clipcage, dashed line) 20 <italic>T. notatus.</italic> Additionally, we collected untreated control leaves (control, dotted line). (<bold>B</bold>) photosynthetic rates and (<bold>C</bold>) chlorophyll contents in a time-kinetic from 1 to 144 hr (120 hr). Statistically significant differences were identified with ANCOVA with mirid as factor and time as continuous explanatory variable. (<bold>B</bold>) photosynthetic rates: time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.846, p=0.362; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 41.466, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 10.802, p=0.002; (<bold>C</bold>) chlorophyll content: time F<sub>1,45</sub> = 2.423, p=0.127; mirid F<sub>1,45</sub> = 1.721, p=0.196; time*mirid F<sub>1,45</sub> = 1.670, p=0.203; Error bars depict standard errors (N ≥ 3). For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_2_S1 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig2-figsupp1-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.007</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding on whole plants only slightly alters nutrient levels in attacked leaves of <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic>, mainly decreasing protein contents.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental setup: whole plants were caged with (cage+ <italic>T. notatus</italic> attacked; solid line) or without (control cage, dotted line) <italic>T. notatus.</italic> <bold>B</bold>) Protein, (<bold>C</bold>) starch, (<bold>D</bold>) sucrose, (<bold>E</bold>) glucose and (<bold>F</bold>) fructose were monitored in a time-kinetic from 24 to 144 hr. Statistically significant differences were identified with ANCOVA with mirid as factor and time as continuous explanatory variable. (<bold>B</bold>) TSP: time F<sub>1,43</sub> = 25.145, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,43</sub> = 19.672, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>1,43</sub> = 0.102, p=0.75. (<bold>C</bold>) starch: time F<sub>1,44</sub> = 13.949, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 0.342, p=0.561; time*mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 4.932, p=0.031. (<bold>D</bold>) log transformed sucrose: time F<sub>1,43</sub> = 0.111, p=0.740; mirid F<sub>1,43</sub> = 3.834, p=0.057; time*mirid F<sub>1,43</sub> 0.721, p=0.401. (<bold>E</bold>) log transformed glucose: time F<sub>1,44</sub> = 0.672, p=0.417; mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 0.066, p=0.798; time*mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> 4.760, p=0.035. (<bold>F</bold>) fructose: time F<sub>1,44</sub> = 0.890, p=0.351; mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 0.229, p=0.634; time*mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> 1.83, p=0.183. Error bars depict standard errors. (N ≥ 3). FM: fresh mass. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_2_S2 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig2-figsupp2-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig2s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.008</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding on whole plants decreases photosynthetic rates and chlorophyll contents in attacked leaves of <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental setup: whole plants were caged with (cage+ <italic>T. notatus</italic>; solid line) or without (control cage, dotted line) <italic>T. notatus.</italic> (<bold>B</bold>) Photosynthetic assimilation rates and (<bold>C</bold>) chlorophyll contents were monitored in a time-kinetic from 24 to 144 hr (120 hr) after the start of herbivore exposure. Statistically significant differences were identified with ANCOVA with mirid as factor and time as continuous explanatory variable. (<bold>B</bold>) photosynthetic rates: time F<sub>1,44</sub> = 0.196, p=0.660; mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 102.063, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> 1.234, p=0.273. (<bold>C</bold>) chlorophyll content: time F<sub>1,36</sub> = 5.244, p=0.028; mirid F<sub>1,36</sub> = 40.128, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>1,36</sub> 7.215, p=0.011. Error bars depict standard errors (N = 4). For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_2_S3 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig2-figsupp3-v3"/></fig></fig-group><p>When entire plants were heavily infested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2a</xref>), changes in nutrient levels in the plant became apparent only for TSP levels, which decreased after mirid feeding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2b</xref>). Conversely, levels of starch, sucrose, glucose and fructose were not affected by mirid feeding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2c–f</xref>). Both chlorophyll contents and photosynthetic rates significantly decreased after <italic>T. notatus</italic> whole-plant attack (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3a–c</xref>).</p><p>In summary, when only twenty mirids were allowed to feed on a single leaf the overall nutritional quality was not altered, although the feeding damage was visibly severe. In contrast, during a more extreme mirid infestation in which entire plants were severely attacked, TSP levels of attacked leaves decreased, but sugar and starch contents remained unchanged. However, no overall apparent increased photosynthetic activity was observed. An allocation of nutrients from unattacked to attacked tissue may explain the observation that even heavy <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding only marginally influenced nutrient levels in attacked leaves. If this inference is correct, then mirid feeding likely influences the source/sink relationships of the host plant.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title><italic>T. notatus</italic> attack increases the levels of cytokinins and transcripts responsible for cytokinin degradation</title><p>Cytokinins (CKs) are known to regulate source/sink relationships and stabilize nutrient levels in tissues fed on by endophytic insects. Recently, we showed that these phytohormones also play a role in plant defense, since <italic>M. sexta</italic> herbivory, wounding, and JAs can increase the levels of <italic>c</italic>Z-type CKs in <italic>N. attenuata</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Schäfer et al., 2015c</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>). As we did not see a strong decrease in nutrients after mirid feeding, it was especially interesting to investigate CK metabolism during <italic>T. notatus</italic> attack.</p><p>When entire plants were attacked, mirid feeding significantly increased the accumulation of <italic>NaCKX5</italic> transcripts, which code for a CK oxidase/dehydrogenase responsible for CK degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3a</xref>). Transcript levels of <italic>NaZOG2</italic>, which codes for a CK glucosyltransferase responsible for CK inactivation, as well as transcripts of <italic>NaLOG4</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1b</xref>), which is involved in CK biosynthesis, also increased after mirid feeding. In contrast, transcript levels of the isopentenyltransferase <italic>NaIPT5,</italic> which catalyzes the rate-limiting step of CK biosynthesis, were reduced after mirid feeding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1c</xref>). <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding did not change levels of the CK response regulator <italic>NaRRA5</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1d</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.009</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> contain large amounts of CKs in their bodies and their feeding alters <italic>Nicotiana attenuata’s</italic> cytokinin (CK) metabolism.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Transcript accumulations of <italic>NaCKX5</italic>: cytokinin oxidase/dehydrogenase 5 (which inactivates CKs by oxidation) and (<bold>B</bold>) CK levels in leaves: sum of <italic>cis</italic>-zeatin (<italic>c</italic>Z), <italic>trans</italic>-zeatin (<italic>t</italic>Z), <italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-isopentenyladenine (IP) and their ribosides (<italic>c</italic>ZR, <italic>t</italic>ZR, IPR) in leaves exposed to <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding (cage +<italic>T. notatus</italic>, solid line) and control leaves (control cage, dotted line) at different times after herbivore exposure. (<bold>C</bold>) Single CK types in leaves after 144 hr of exposure to <italic>T. notatus</italic> and in the insect bodies. Two-way ANOVA on log<sub>2</sub>-transformed data followed by Welch t-test with Bonferroni corrections between control and <italic>T. notatus</italic> cage for each harvest time were used to analyze <bold>A</bold>) (mirid F<sub>1,13</sub> = 158.2, p&lt;0.001; time F<sub>3,13</sub> = 12.52, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>3,13</sub> 7.015, p=0.005). ANCOVA with mirid as factor and time as continuous explanatory variable was used to analyze <bold>B</bold>) (log<sub>2</sub> transformed data: time F<sub>1,44</sub> = 7.335, p=0.010; mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 8.609, p=0.005; time*mirid F<sub>1,44</sub> = 15.243 <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). (<bold>C</bold>) was analyzed with Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney test between control and attacked leaves for each CK type. • p&lt;0.1, *p&lt;0.05. Error bars depict standard errors (<bold>A</bold>): N ≥ 2; (<bold>B, C</bold>): N = 4). FM: fresh mass. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_3 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig3-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.010</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding alters transcript levels of cytokinin inactivation and biosynthetic genes in attacked leaves of <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic>.</title><p>Relative transcript accumulations (<italic>NaActin</italic> as reference gene) in leaves infested with <italic>T. notatus</italic> (cage+ <italic>T. notatus</italic>, solid line) and control leaves (control cage, dotted line) at different harvest times after the start of herbivore exposure. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>NaZOG2</italic>: zeatin-<italic>O</italic>-glucosyltransferase 2. (<bold>B</bold>) log<sub>2</sub> transformed <italic>NaLOG4</italic>: cytokinin riboside 5'-monophosphate phosphoribohydrolase LOG (LONELY GUY) 4. (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>NaIPT5</italic>: isopentenyltransferase 5. (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>NaRRA5</italic>: CK response regulator 5. Statistically significant differences were identified by two-way ANOVAs with factors mirid and time followed by Welch t-test with Bonferroni corrections between control and <italic>T. notatus</italic> cage for each harvest time. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>NaZOG2</italic>: time F<sub>3,13</sub> = 10.45, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,13</sub> = 49.36, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>3,13</sub> 12.83, p&lt;0.001; <bold>B</bold>) <italic>NaLOG4</italic>: time F<sub>3,13</sub> = 2.092, p=0.151; mirid F<sub>1,13</sub> = 28.28, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>3,13</sub> 5.372, p=0.013; (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>NaIPT5</italic>: time F<sub>3,13</sub> = 4.274, p=0.026; mirid F<sub>1,13</sub> = 41.21, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>3,13</sub> 3.030, p=0.068; (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>NaRRA5:</italic> time F<sub>3,13</sub> = 0.996, p=0.426; mirid F<sub>1,13</sub> = 0.039, p=0.847; time*mirid F<sub>3,13</sub> 0.643, p=0.601. • p&lt;0.1, *p&lt;0.05. Error bars depict standard errors (N ≥ 2). For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_3_S1 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig3-figsupp1-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.011</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding on whole plants alters cytokinin (CKs) levels in attacked <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> leaves.</title><p>Whole plants were caged with (cage+ <italic>T. notatus</italic>, solid line) or without (control cage, dotted line) <italic>T. notatus</italic> and CK concentrations in attacked leaves were quantified in a time kinetic from 24 to 144 hr after herbivore exposure. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>cis</italic>-Zeatin (<italic>c</italic>Z), (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>trans</italic>-zeatin (<italic>t</italic>Z), (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-isopentenyladenine (IP) and their ribosides (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>c</italic>ZR, (<bold>E</bold>) <italic>t</italic>ZR, (<bold>F</bold>) IPR. Statistically significant differences were identified by two-way ANOVAs (TWA) followed by TukeyHSD <italic>post hoc</italic> test (<bold>C</bold>), (<bold>D and F</bold>) or by generalized least squares (GLS) model followed by Wilcoxon–Mann–Whitney tests with Bonferroni corrections between control and <italic>T. notatus</italic> cage for each harvest time (<bold>A, B and E</bold>). (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>c</italic>Z: time F<sub>5,36</sub> = 3.046, p=0.021; mirid F<sub>1,36</sub> = 44.561, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>5,36</sub> = 2.688, p=0.037. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>t</italic>Z: time F<sub>5,36</sub> = 4.347, p=0.003; mirid F<sub>1,36</sub> = 18.392, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>5,36</sub> = 4.898, p=0.002. (<bold>C</bold>) IP: time F<sub>5,36</sub> = 1.351, p=0.266; mirid F<sub>1,36</sub> = 2.249, p=0.142; time*mirid F<sub>5,36</sub> = 0.579, p=0.716. (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>c</italic>ZR: time F<sub>5,36</sub> = 3.097, p=0.020; mirid F<sub>1,36</sub> = 9.234, p=0.004; time*mirid F<sub>5,36</sub> = 3.985, p=0.006. (<bold>E</bold>) <italic>t</italic>ZR: time F<sub>5,36</sub> = 9.421, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,36</sub> = 11.277, p=0.002; time*mirid F<sub>5,36</sub> = 6.177, p&lt;0.001. (<bold>F</bold>) IPR: time F<sub>5,36</sub> = 3.490, p=0.011; mirid F<sub>1,36</sub> = 20.016, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>5,36</sub> = 1.141, p=0.357. • p&lt;0.1, *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01. Error bars depict standard errors (N = 4). FM: fresh mass. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_3_S2 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig3-figsupp2-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig3s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.012</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Influence of <italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> single-leaf feeding on cytokinin levels of attacked and unattacked leaves.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental setup: a single leaf was enclosed in a plastic clipcage with (clipcage+ <italic>T. notatus</italic>; solid line) or without 20 <italic>T. notatus</italic> (clipcage, dashed line). Additionally, unenclosed control leaves (control, dotted line) were also collected. (<bold>B</bold>–<bold>H</bold>) CK values in leaves at different time-points after the start of herbivore exposure: (<bold>B</bold>) sum of <italic>cis</italic>-zeatin (<italic>c</italic>Z), <italic>trans</italic>-zeatin (<italic>t</italic>Z), <italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-isopentenyladenine (IP) and their ribosides (<italic>c</italic>ZR, <italic>t</italic>ZR, IPR). (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>c</italic>Z, (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>t</italic>Z, (<bold>E</bold>) IP, (<bold>F</bold>) <italic>c</italic>ZR, (<bold>G</bold>) <italic>t</italic>ZR and <bold>H</bold>) IPR. Statistically significant differences were identified by two-way ANOVAs (<bold>C, E</bold>) or by ANCOVA with mirid as factor and time as continuous explanatory variable (<bold>B, D, F, G, H</bold>). (<bold>B</bold>) sum of CKs: time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.041, p=0.841; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 1.934, p=0.170; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 5.270, p=0.026. (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>c</italic>Z: time F<sub>7,39</sub> = 5.855, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,39</sub> = 31.43, p&lt;0.001; time*mirid F<sub>7,39</sub> = 1.596, p=0.166. (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>t</italic>Z: log transformed time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 3.024, p=0.088; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.986, p=0.325; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 2.572, p=0.115. (<bold>E</bold>) IP: time F<sub>7,39</sub> = 11.538, p&lt;0.001; mirid F<sub>1,39</sub> = 7.134, p=0.011; time*mirid F<sub>7,39</sub> = 2.279, p=0.048. (<bold>F</bold>) <italic>c</italic>ZR: log transformed time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 1.083, p=0.303; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 5.066, p=0.03; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.256, p=0.615. (<bold>G</bold>) square root transformed <italic>t</italic>ZR: log transformed time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 9.910, p=0.003; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 1.164, p=0.286; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 0.688, p=0.411 <bold>hr</bold> IPR: log transformed time F<sub>1,51</sub> = 11.909, p=0.001; mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 1.484, p=0.229; time*mirid F<sub>1,51</sub> = 1.813, p=0.184. Error bars depict standard error (N ≥ 3). FM: fresh mass. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_3_S3 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig3-figsupp3-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig3s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.013</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> contains large amounts of <italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-isopentenyladenine (IP) in their bodies independently of stage, sex or food source.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) IP and IPR (<italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-isopentenyladenosine) in <italic>T. notatus</italic> nymphs and adult males and females. One-way ANOVAs with Tukey HSD <italic>post hoc</italic> test (N ≥ 3). IP: F<sub>2,10</sub> = 17.92, p&lt;0.001; IPR, F<sub>2,10</sub> = 0.89, p=0.441. (<bold>B</bold>) IP and IPR in <italic>T. notatus</italic> adults reared on plants or on artificial diet. Green dotted lines present representative levels of IP and IPR in leaf tissues on which the insects had fed. Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney test. IP: N = 7; W = 38, p=0.281; IPR N = 7; W = 35, p=0.463 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4b</xref>). n.s, not significant. Error bars depict standard errors (N = 7). FM: fresh mass. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_3_S4 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig3-figsupp4-v3"/></fig></fig-group><p>The levels of the different types of CKs varied depending on time and whether mirids attacked single leaves or entire plants. When entire plants were infested with <italic>T. notatus</italic>, overall leaf CK contents gradually increased over time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3b</xref>). Levels of <italic>cis</italic>-zeatin (<italic>c</italic>Z) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2a</xref>), <italic>cis</italic>-zeatin riboside (<italic>c</italic>ZR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2d</xref>), <italic>trans</italic>-zeatin (<italic>t</italic>Z) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2b</xref>) and <italic>trans</italic>-zeatin riboside (<italic>t</italic>ZR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2e</xref>) were significantly higher after <italic>T. notatus</italic> attack. In contrast, levels of <italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-isopentenyladenine (IP) remained unaffected by mirid feeding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2c</xref>) and levels of <italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-isopentenyladenosine (IPR) decreased in attacked leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2f</xref>). This decrease was significant in the first 24 hr after the initiation of mirid attack and disappeared at later harvest times (p&lt;0.05 in TukeyHSD <italic>post hoc</italic> test).</p><p>When mirids were only allowed to feed on a single leaf, we did not observe changes in levels of summed CKs over the whole time series (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3b</xref>). However, Bonferroni-corrected t-tests of single time point revealed increased levels at the last time point harvested, after 144 hr of feeding (tt: p=0.026). The changes in individual CKs only partially overlapped with those observed during whole-plant feeding. There was a significant increase in <italic>c</italic>Z (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3c</xref>), but levels of <italic>c</italic>ZR decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3f</xref>). IP levels, which did not change during whole-plant feeding, were significantly higher overall after single-leaf feeding, although pairwise comparisons for each time point did not reveal significant changes at any given time point. <italic>t</italic>Z, <italic>t</italic>ZR and IPR remained unaffected by mirid feeding when only single leaves were attacked (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3d,g,h</xref>).</p><p>Interestingly, in both experiments overall CK levels remained unchanged or were increased, despite the concomitant increases in transcripts of genes related to CK degradation. From these results, we infer that CKs are involved in the observed nutritional stability during mirid feeding; this hypothesis prompted a more detailed analysis of the origin of these CKs.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title><italic>T. notatus</italic> contains high levels of IP</title><p>Mirid attack enhanced the levels of <italic>c</italic>Z and <italic>c</italic>ZR as was previously found for <italic>M. sexta</italic> herbivory, wounding, and JA application (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Schäfer et al., 2015c</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>); but in contrast to these other types of elicitations, long-term mirid feeding and the associated JA accumulation did not decrease IP levels. This was particularly surprising given that CK degradation and inactivation processes appeared to have been activated by mirid feeding. We analyzed CK levels in <italic>T. notatus</italic> to determine whether these insects could themselves provide a source of CKs. We found very high levels of IP and IPR in extracts from the insect bodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3c</xref>). While concentrations of IPR were comparable to those in leaves (around 1 pmol per g fresh mass (FM)), concentrations of IP exceeded those of leaves by up to three orders of magnitude: while levels in leaves ranged from 0.01 to 0.1 pmol g FM<sup>−1</sup>, levels in insects were usually between 1 and 5 pmol g FM<sup>−1</sup> and attained values as high as 16 pmol g FM<sup>−1</sup>. Insects collected from <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants in their natural habitat at a field site in Utah, USA, also contained high amounts of IP: in a pooled sample of ten insects, we measured 18.26 pmol IP per g FM<sup>-1</sup>.</p><p>Mirids contained high IP and IPR levels in their bodies independently of their sex, developmental stage, or food source (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4</xref>). The sole significant difference was that IP concentration in nymphs was about half as high as in adult males and females, but nymphs still had concentration several times those found in leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4a</xref>). To evaluate if CKs levels remained stable when <italic>T. notatus</italic> was no longer feeding on its host plant, we reared insects for five days either on artificial diet (containing no CKs) or on plants. Insects raised on artificial diet had IP levels in their body that were not different from levels in insects raised on plants; IPR levels were also unchanged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4b</xref>).</p><p>Although the source of CKs in <italic>T. notatus</italic> remains unknown, we hypothesize that IP and IPR found in <italic>T. notatus</italic> body could be used by the mirid to counter the decrease in IP levels in attacked leaves that is commonly observed in response to long-term JA elicitation or <italic>M. sexta</italic> feeding.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title><italic>T. notatus</italic> transfers IP to the plant via its oral secretions</title><p>To evaluate whether <italic>T. notatus</italic> could transfer CKs to the plant, we conducted <sup>15</sup>N- labeling experiments. We grew plants in hydroponic culture with <sup>15</sup>N-labeled KNO<sub>3</sub> as the only source of nitrogen. We furthermore created a stock of <italic>T. notatus</italic> insects that were <sup>15</sup>N-labeled by raising them for an entire generation on <sup>15</sup>N-grown plants. We then performed two different types of experiments to trace the origin of CKs in <italic>T. notatus</italic> attacked leaves: we either used <sup>15</sup>N-grown plants that we exposed to <sup>14</sup>N-labeled insects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>) or we used <sup>14</sup>N-grown plants and exposed them to <sup>15</sup>N-labeled insects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplements 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s3">3</xref>). CKs are adenine derivatives that contain five nitrogen atoms. Therefore, CKs produced by <sup>15</sup>N-labeled plants or insects harbored five <sup>15</sup>N and are readily distinguished from <sup>14</sup>N-labeled CKs by mass spectrometry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s4">Figure 4—figure supplements 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s5">5</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.014</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> transfers IP to leaves of its host plant.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>) Experimental setup and chromatograms of IP: (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>T. notatus</italic> raised on <sup>14</sup>N-grown hydroponic plants grown contain only [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP in their bodies. (<bold>B</bold>) Plants raised on a hydroponic medium containing only a <sup>15</sup>N containing N-source have only [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP in leaves. <sup>15</sup>N labeled plants and <sup>14</sup>N labeled insects were placed in the same cage for 5 days. Ratio of [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP (originating from insects, blue) and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP (from host plant, yellow) were determined in attacked leaves. (<bold>C</bold>) Chromatograms of [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP in the leaves of 5d attacked plants. (<bold>D</bold>) Ratio of [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP at different harvest times after the start of exposure to <italic>T. notatus</italic> (N = 5). For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_4 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig4-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.015</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> transfers IPR to leaves of its host plant.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) and <bold>B</bold>) Experimental setup and chromatograms of IPR: (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>T. notatus</italic> raised on <sup>14</sup>N-grown hydroponic plants contain only [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR in their bodies. (<bold>B</bold>) Plants raised on a hydroponic medium containing only a <sup>15</sup>N containing N-source contain only [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR in their leaves. <sup>15</sup>N labeled plants and <sup>14</sup>N labeled insects were placed in the same cage for 5 days. Ratio of [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR (originating from insects, blue) and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR (from host plant, orange) were determined in attacked leaves. (<bold>C</bold>) Chromatograms of [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR in the leaves of 5d attacked plants. (<bold>D</bold>) Ratio of [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR at different harvest times after start of the exposure to <italic>T. notatus</italic> (N = 5). For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_4_S1 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig4-figsupp1-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.016</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Twenty <italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> individuals transfer detectable amounts of IP to leaves.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>) Experimental setup and chromatograms of IP: (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>T. notatus</italic> raised on <sup>15</sup>N-grown hydroponic plants contain only [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP in their bodies. (<bold>B</bold>) Plants raised on a hydroponic medium containing only <sup>14</sup>N containing N-source contain only [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP in leaves. 20 <sup>15</sup>N-labeled insects were placed in small cages on one leaf of <sup>14</sup>N-grown plants for 5 days. Ratio of [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP (originating from insects, yellow) and [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP (from host plant, blue) were determined in attacked leaves. (<bold>C</bold>) Chromatograms of [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP and [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP in the leaves that were attacked for 5d. (<bold>D</bold>) Ratio of [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP and [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP at different harvest times after the start of exposure to <italic>T. notatus</italic> (N ≥ 3). For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_4_S2 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig4-figsupp2-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig4s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.017</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Twenty <italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> individuals transfer detectable amounts of IPR to leaves.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>) Experimental setup and chromatograms of IP: (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>T. notatus</italic> raised on <sup>15</sup>N-grown hydroponic plants contain only [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR in their body. (<bold>B</bold>) Plants raised on a hydroponic medium containing only <sup>14</sup>N containing N-source contain only [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR in leaves. 20 <sup>15</sup>N labeled insects were placed in small cages on one leaf of <sup>14</sup>N-grown plants for 5 days. Ratio of [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR (originating from insects, orange) and [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR (from host plant, blue) were determined in attacked leaves. (<bold>C</bold>) Chromatograms of [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR and [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR in the leaves that were attacked for 5d. (<bold>D</bold>) Ratio of [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR and [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR at different harvest times after the start of exposure to <italic>T. notatus</italic> (N ≥ 3). For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_4_S3 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig4-figsupp3-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig4s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.018</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Chromatograms of IP, [D<sub>6</sub>]-IP, [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP.</title><p>Dashed lines show the retention-time shifts between unlabeled [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP, [D<sub>6</sub>]-IP (internal standard) and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP. Color coding follows that of the chromatograms. The monitored parental → daughter ion transitions are given in the top right of each chromatogram.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig4-figsupp4-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig4s5" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.019</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 5.</label><caption><title>Chromatograms of IPR, [D<sub>6</sub>]-IPR and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR.</title><p>Dashed lines show the retention-time shifts between unlabeled [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP, [D<sub>6</sub>]-IP (internal standard) and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP. Color coding follows that of the chromatograms. The monitored parental → daughter ion transitions are given in the top right of each chromatogram.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig4-figsupp5-v3"/></fig></fig-group><p>In the first approach, we used a low-infestation setup by placing 20 <sup>15</sup>N-labeled <italic>T. notatus</italic> adults in a small cage on the leaf of a <sup>14</sup>N-grown plant for five days. After four days of continuous feeding, we found detectable amounts of <sup>15</sup>N-labeled IP (and IPR) in the leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplements 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s3">3</xref>): around 2.35 fmol [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP per g FM, which represent the 3.3% of the [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]/[<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP ratio (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2d</xref>). [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-labelled IP and IPR could only have originated from the insects, as the natural abundance of <sup>15</sup>N is below 0.4%, and IP (or IPR) with five <sup>15</sup>N would occur about once in a trillion molecules. From these values, one mirid feeding on a leaf for five days could account for a transfer of at least 0.12 fmol IP per g FM<sup>−1</sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>), assuming that CK transport, degradation or conversion to other CK forms can be excluded.</p><p>In the reverse experiment, we used <sup>15</sup>N-grown plants and insects raised on <sup>14</sup>N-grown plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). We placed <sup>15</sup>N-grown plants in cages where <italic>T. notatus</italic> were reared on <sup>14</sup>N-grown plants. These <sup>15</sup>N-grown plants were switched to a new cage with infested <sup>14</sup>N-grown plants once per day to ensure that they were always attacked by <sup>14</sup>N-labeled insects and to prevent the accumulation of <sup>15</sup>N in the <sup>14</sup>N-labeled insects. After 5 days, an average of 48% of the [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]/[<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP ratio was <sup>14</sup>N labeled and therefore originating from the insects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). In this stronger induction setup, IPR transfer from the insect to the plant was also already detected after 24 hr and accounted to 19% of the [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]/[<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP ratio after 5 d (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>To evaluate how IP and IPR were transferred to the leaf during feeding, we analyzed the CK contents of the oral secretions and frass of <italic>T. notatus</italic>, which we considered the most likely means of transfer. Mirids were fed on sugar solutions covered with parafilm, which allowed the insects to penetrate the film with their stylets while preventing evaporation and preventing either insects or their frass from being immersed in the liquid. We then measured CKs in the sugar solution, which contained substances transferred by the oral secretions, as well as in the surface wash, which contained insect excretions (frass). We found large amounts (high signal intensity) of IP mainly from the oral secretions (from the sugar solution that mirids had fed on) and much lower amounts in the frass of the mirids (from the surface wash) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). IPR was found in oral secretions and in frass in similar amounts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.020</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> contain large quantities of IP in their saliva and small amounts in their frass.</title><p>Chromatograms showing the signal intensity of an MS/MS- trace for IP (204.1 → 136.0). (<bold>A</bold>) IP signal of pure sugar solution (black line) or sugar solution fed upon by <italic>T. notatus</italic> for 5 days (red line). The sugar solution was covered with a thin layer of parafilm that allowed piercing and feeding on the solution and prevented contamination by <italic>T. notatus</italic> frass. (<bold>B</bold>) Chromatograms of the surface wash of the parafilm covering the sugar solution after <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding (red line, covered with visible frass spots) or without (control wash, black line). Chromatograms shown represent one out of six replicates.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig5-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.021</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> contain IPR in their saliva and frass.</title><p>Chromatograms showing the signal intensity of a MS/MS- trace for IPR (336.1 → 204.1). (<bold>A</bold>) IPR signal of pure sugar solution (black line) or sugar solution that has been used as diet for <italic>T. notatus</italic> for 5 days (red line). The sugar solution was covered with a thin layer of parafilm that allowed piercing and feeding on the solution and prevented contamination with <italic>T. notatus</italic> frass. (<bold>B</bold>) Chromatograms of the surface wash of the parafilm covering the sugar solution after <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding (red line, covered with visible frass spots) or without (control wash, black line). Chromatograms shown represent one out of six replicates.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig5-figsupp1-v3"/></fig></fig-group><p>These results clearly demonstrate that <italic>T. notatus</italic> is able to transfer CKs (mainly IP) to its host plant. The most likely means of transfer would be via the salivary secretion produced during feeding, although we cannot rule out a smaller contribution of feces, which are sticky and tend to cover infested leaves.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Altered CK metabolism in <italic>N. attenuata</italic> affects its interaction with <italic>T. notatus</italic></title><p>In nature, <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeds on young <italic>N. attenuata</italic> tissues, such as younger stem leaves and young growing leaves. This feeding pattern was inferred from the damage distributions observed on plants in both nature and the glasshouse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1a</xref>), as well as in two-choice assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1b</xref>). The young leaves preferred by <italic>T. notatus</italic> are typically rich in CKs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>). To evaluate how CK metabolism affects the interaction of <italic>N. attenuata</italic> with <italic>T. notatus</italic>, we used transgenic <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants that were either enhanced in CK production (i-ov<italic>ipt</italic>) or silenced in CK perception (ir<italic>chk2/3</italic>). Transgenic i-ov<italic>ipt</italic> plants that contain a dexamethasone (DEX)-inducible promotor system coupled to an IPT gene were produced as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schäfer et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Schäfer et al., 2015b</xref>), and allowed a DEX-mediated induction of CK overproduction. ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants, fully characterized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Schäfer et al., (2015b)</xref> are silenced for two of three CK receptors.</p><p><italic>T. notatus</italic> prefers leaves of i-ov<italic>ipt</italic> plants which have been treated with DEX and therefore have higher levels of CKs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6a</xref>). If <italic>T. notatus</italic> is given the choice between empty vector (EV) and ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants, mirids show a strong preference for EV plants, as shown in the lower damage levels on ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6b</xref>). Furthermore, we found pronounced differences in the reaction of the plants to the damage caused by <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding. Mirid attack caused necrotic lesions in ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants, comparable to a pathogen-induced hypersensitive response, whereas this did not occur in WT, EV or i<italic>-</italic>ov<italic>ipt</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6c</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.022</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Cytokinin-regulated traits mediate <italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> feeding preferences and alter leaf responses to feeding.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>): Surface damage on <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants after 10 d of <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>T. notatus</italic> could choose between dexamethasone-inducible isopentenyltransferase-overexpressing plants (i-ov<italic>ipt</italic>) treated with dexamethasone-containing lanolin paste (+DEX) or lanolin paste without dexamethasone as control (+LAN; figure based on data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schäfer et al., 2013</xref>). Statistically significant differences were identified with pairwise t-test: N = 7, p=0.032. (<bold>B</bold>) Choice between empty vector (EV) and ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants silenced in the two cytokinin receptor genes <italic>NaCHK2</italic> and <italic>NaCHK3</italic> (ir<italic>chk2/3</italic>). Pairwise t-test: N = 6, p&lt;0.001. Error bars depict standard errors. *p&lt;0.05, ***p&lt;0.001. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative pictures of leaves of EV or ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants with or without <italic>T. notatus</italic> damage. Magnifications show necrotic lesions occurring only in ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants after several days of mirid feeding. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_6 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig6-v3"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.023</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic> prefers to feed on young leaves.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Distribution of <italic>T. notatus</italic> damage in flowering <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> plants grown in the field and glasshouse. Upper panel: picture 1) field plot at Lytle Preserve, Utah, 2) a typically damaged leaf, 3) glasshouse and plants in the glasshouse. Lower panel: Damaged leaf area in % in field and in glasshouse. Leaves were classified as rosette leaves, lower to mid stem leaves and upper stem leaves and side branches as indicated in the schematic drawing (left). One-way ANOVAs followed by Tukey HSD <italic>post hoc</italic> tests were used to identify statistically significant differences. Field plants: N = 21, F<sub>2,33</sub> = 5.729, p=0.007; glasshouse plants: N = 4, F<sub>2,9</sub> = 45.5, p&lt;0.001. Different letters indicate significant differences (p&lt;0.01), error bars depict standard errors. (<bold>B</bold>) Choice assay: 10 mirids were placed in an arena with two tubes connected to either a fully-grown leaf or young growing leaves with an apical stem. Number of mirids on each side was counted after 12 hr. Pairwise t-test: N = 12, p=0.026. Error bars depict standard errors. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_6_S1 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig6-figsupp1-v3"/></fig></fig-group><p>To better understand the feeding preferences of <italic>T. notatus</italic>, we measured nutrient levels in ir<italic>chk2/3,</italic> DEX-induced i-ov<italic>ipt</italic> plants and EV plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>). Starch and sucrose did not differ among the lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7c,f</xref>). However, i-ov<italic>ipt</italic> plants had higher concentrations of protein, free amino acids, glucose and fructose than did ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7a,b,d,e</xref>). The i-ov<italic>ipt</italic> plants tended to have higher nutrient levels than did EV plants but the results were only statistically significant for glucose concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7d</xref>). In contrast, ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants tended to have lower nutrient levels compared to EV, but these were only significantly lower for fructose concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7e</xref>).</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.024</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Transgenic <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> plants altered in their cytokinin metabolism are also altered in their nutrient contents.</title><p>We compared nutrient contents of empty vector (EV) plants, plants silenced in the two cytokinin receptor genes <italic>NaCHK2</italic> and <italic>NaCHK3</italic> (ir<italic>chk2/3</italic>) and dexamethasone-inducible isopentenyltransferase-overexpressing plants (i-ov<italic>ipt</italic>) treated with dexamethasone-containing lanolin paste (DEX) leading to spatially-regulated increased CK levels. Concentrations were determined in untreated rosette leaves of <italic>N. attenuata:</italic> (<bold>A</bold>) protein, (<bold>B</bold>) free amino acids, (<bold>C</bold>) starch, (<bold>D</bold>) glucose, (<bold>E</bold>) fructose and (<bold>F</bold>) sucrose. Significant differences were identified with one-way ANOVAs followed by Tukey HSD <italic>post hoc</italic> tests. (<bold>A</bold>) protein: F<sub>2,9</sub> = 10.74, p=0.004; (<bold>B</bold>) free amino acids: F<sub>2,9</sub> = 4.27, p=0.050; (<bold>C</bold>) log<sub>2</sub> transformed starch: F<sub>2,9</sub> = 2.208, p=0.166; <bold>D</bold>) glucose: F<sub>2,9</sub> = 18.89, p&lt;0.001; (<bold>E</bold>) fructose: F<sub>2,9</sub> = 15.43, p=0.001; (<bold>F</bold>) sucrose: F<sub>2,9</sub> = 0.375, p=0.698. Error bars depict standard errors (N = 4). FM: fresh mass. For raw data see Raw_data_FIGURE_7 (Dryad: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brütting et al., 2018</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-36268-fig7-v3"/></fig><p>From these results, we conclude that CKs play a dual role in the <italic>T. notatus-N. attenuata</italic> interaction: as important determinants of tissue palatability for <italic>T. notatus</italic> by enhancing nutrient contents, but also as important tolerance factors that allow plants to suffer negligible or lower fitness consequences of mirid attack than they would otherwise.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Gall-formers and leaf-miners have long been known for their ability to manipulate plant’s physiology, likely via phytohormones such as CKs. It is commonly thought that CK-dependent manipulation of plant metabolism is a trait typical of endophytic insects that has been shaped by the sedentary and intimate relationships that these insects establish with their host plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Giron et al., 2016</xref>). Here, we provide evidence that a free-living insect, the mirid <italic>T. notatus,</italic> transfers CKs to its host plant <italic>N. attenuata</italic> and likely manipulates the host plant’s metabolism for its own benefit. This strategy, not previously described for any free-living insects, indicates that CK-mediated manipulation of plant metabolism by insects could be a mechanism more widespread than previously thought.</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>Transfer of CKs from <italic>T. notatus</italic> to its host plant</title><p>We unambiguously demonstrated that <italic>T. notatus</italic> transfers two types of CKs, IP and its riboside IPR, to <italic>N. attenuata</italic> providing the first clear demonstration of CK transfer from an insect to a plant. IP has been generally considered one of the most active natural CKs based on classical activity assays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Gyulai and Heszky, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Sakakibara, 2006</xref>) and high concentrations of IP have been previously reported in plant-manipulating endophytic insects, like leaf miners and gall-formers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Engelbrecht, 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Engelbrecht et al., 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mapes and Davies, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Straka et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Yamaguchi et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Body et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Tanaka et al., 2013</xref>). We also showed that oral secretions, and in much lower amounts, frass of <italic>T. notatus</italic>, contained IP and IPR, thus providing a possible means of transfer.</p><p>Concentrations of total CK content of <italic>N. attenuata</italic> leaves steadily increased during long-term <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding, consistent with the observation that mirids transferred CKs to plants. The overall reconfiguration of the transcriptional activity of genes involved in CK degradation, inactivation, and biosynthesis upon <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding did not correlate with the apparent changes in CK concentrations. This suggests that <italic>N. attenuata</italic> might activate a type of CK detoxification in response to mirid feeding and CK introduction. Additional support for the existence of a mechanism that counter-balances mirid-injected CKs comes from the observation that the leaf concentration of IP and IPR, the two CKs transferred by <italic>T. notatus</italic>, were unaffected or only slightly changed in plants by mirid feeding. This was surprising, considering that we estimated that after five days of whole-plant infestation, roughly half of the total IP in attacked leaves originated from mirids.</p><p>Understanding to what extent the observed changes in cytokinin signaling result from mirid-mediated CK transfer is further complicated by the fact that CK levels respond as part of the herbivory-inducible defense signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Schäfer et al., 2015a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Schäfer et al., 2015c</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>). The dual role of CKs in plant growth and defense highlights the complexity of the fine regulation of CKs needed to regulate plant physiological responses. Not only CK quantities, but also CK structures, and the hormonal balance with other phytohormones may influence changes in metabolism upon insect feeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Giron et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title><italic>T. notatus</italic>-induced effects in <italic>N. attenuata</italic></title><p>Demonstrable effects on host plants induced by endophytic insects include alterations of plant morphology, changes in the nutritional quality of the affected tissues and the inactivation of plant defenses surrounding the attack sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Giron et al., 2016</xref>). Whereas alterations of plant morphology are associated with only some endophytic insects, for example gall-formers, control of the nutritional quality of the infested tissues seems to be a common feature of all endophytic insect-plant interactions.</p><p><italic>N. attenuata</italic> leaves maintain their nutritional quality despite being heavily damaged by <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding: only total soluble proteins (TSPs) decreased with heavy infestation, as in the whole-plant experiments, whereas concentrations of glucose, fructose, sucrose and starch remained unchanged. Previous studies in <italic>N. attenuata</italic> showed that wounding and application of oral secretions (OS) of <italic>M. sexta</italic> as well as <italic>M. sexta</italic> feeding reduced glucose and fructose concentrations by inhibiting soluble invertases. Such reductions are JA-dependent, and abrogated in transgenic lines impaired in JA production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Machado et al., 2015</xref>). A negative influence of jasmonates on plant primary metabolism has also been suggested by studies in a number of other plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Babst et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Skrzypek et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">van Dam and Oomen, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hanik et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Tytgat et al., 2013</xref>). Hence, the fact that <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding activated JA-signaling, but did not negatively influence soluble monosaccharide concentrations, suggested that an additional counterbalancing alteration in the primary metabolism of <italic>N. attenuata</italic> occurs during <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding. Similar to what has been observed for carbohydrates, wounding and <italic>M. sexta</italic> OS application results in a 91% reduction of total soluble proteins (TSPs) in young rosette leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Ullmann-Zeunert et al., 2013</xref>), the same leaf stage used in this study. After 144 hr of continuous <italic>T. notatus</italic> infestation, during which proteins should be heavily depleted by mechanical cell-content damage – in contrast to the minor damage associated with OS elicitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Halitschke et al., 2001</xref>) – TSP reductions were only ca. 75%. More surprisingly, a smaller <italic>T. notatus</italic> infestation (twenty mirids confined on a single leaf) did not change TSP contents at all during 144 hr of continuous feeding. These results are consistent with microarray analysis that compared expression patterns induced by <italic>T. notatus</italic> and <italic>M. sexta</italic>, which revealed that mirid-specific transcriptional responses occurred largely in primary metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Voelckel and Baldwin, 2004</xref>). Thus, during <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding, plant’s primary metabolism seems to be influenced by mechanisms different from the classical JA-mediated herbivory and wound responses.</p><p>In contrast to the apparent sugar and starch homeostasis observed during <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding and to the observations of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Halitschke et al. (2011)</xref>, we observed a decrease in photosynthetic rates during continuos mirid feeding. Reduced photosynthetic rate is a general response observed in a number of plant-insect interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Zhou et al., 2015</xref>) as well as in <italic>N. attenuata</italic>. Wounding and elicitation with <italic>M. sexta</italic> OS rapidly decrease photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation and this reduction is mediated by the JA-precursor OPDA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Meza-Canales et al., 2017</xref>). We think that the discrepancy between our work and results from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Halitschke et al. (2011)</xref> likely results from differences in the experimental protocols used: (1) we used a very heavy infestation, (2) the leaf area used to measure the photosynthetic rates of mirid-attacked leaves included both damaged and undamaged areas, (3) we did not normalize photosynthetic rates to intact undamaged leaf tissue. In any case, the reduction in the overall photosynthetic rates observed during <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding was not consistent with unchanged starch and sugar levels and, together with the observation that <italic>T. notatus</italic> transfers CK during feeding, suggests the inhibition of senescence and/or transport of nutrients to the attacked leaves.</p><p>Manipulation of plant defenses is another phenomenon often observed in endophytic insect-host plant interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Giron et al., 2016</xref>). We showed that <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding activated <italic>N. attenuata</italic> JA-dependent defense pathways in a way consistent with previous studies; the increases in defense metabolites induced by <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding were comparable to those elicited by <italic>M. sexta</italic> attack (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Kessler and Baldwin, 2004</xref>). <italic>T. notatus</italic> is well-adapted to the specialized metabolism of <italic>N. attenuata</italic>; it prefers wild-type plants which are less susceptible to invasion by other herbivores, rather than those impaired in JA biosynthesis with reduced defense metabolites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Fragoso et al., 2014</xref>). Insects counter the presence of toxic metabolites in their host plants by detoxification or sequestration of toxic substances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Heckel, 2014</xref>), and the detoxification ability of <italic>T. notatus</italic> is suggested by the observation that it accumulates transcripts encoding detoxification enzymes in response to JA-dependent defenses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Crava et al., 2016</xref>). This fact, togheter with the finding that defense pathways were not down-regulated during the <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding, point out that down-regulation of plant defense may not benefit <italic>T. notatus</italic> as much as its manipulation of its host’s nutritional status.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Changes in the CK metabolism of the host plant alters <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding preferences</title><p>Choice assays demonstrated that <italic>T. notatus</italic> is attracted to plant tissues with enhanced CK levels, both when CK levels were naturally higher, as in young plant tissues, and when CKs are experimentally increased using DEX-inducible transgenic plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schäfer et al., 2013</xref>). When CK perception was impaired as in the ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> line, mirids preferred WT or EV plants over the transgenic plants as shown by their different damage levels. This preference for higher CK levels and against ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants could either be a direct effect of CKs or – more likely – an indirect effect of CK-related processes. A direct attraction to CKs in insects has been discussed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Robischon, 2015</xref>) but to our knowledge there is no direct evidence that insects perceive CKs. Consistent with the second hypothesis, CK levels were not reduced in ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants compared to those of the EV line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Schäfer et al., 2015c</xref>). Thus, we infer that <italic>T. notatus</italic> prefers metabolites positively associated with the CK pathway. These might be molecules produced either by <italic>N. attenuata</italic> primary or specialized metabolism. For example, <italic>T. notatus</italic> is attracted to quercetin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Roda et al., 2003</xref>), and some related phenolic compounds are influenced by CK levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Schäfer et al., 2015b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>). Consistent with the primary metabolism hypothesis, we showed that nutrient levels of transgenic lines correlated with <italic>T. notatus</italic> preference. This inferred preference for nutrients is also consistent with <italic>T. notatus</italic> damage distribution on whole plants, which is concentrated on young, CK-rich and nutrient-rich tissues. These tissues are also better defended (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>) suggesting a possible trade-off between palatability and anti-digestive effects of the diet. However, specialized detoxification mechanisms likely allow <italic>T. notatus</italic> to feed with impunity on otherwise well-defended tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Crava et al., 2016</xref>), thus allowing <italic>T. notatus’s</italic> feeding choice to reflect the nutritional quality, rather than the defensive status, of its host.</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Manipulation of the host plant physiology: a mechanism shared with free-living insects?</title><p>Our results provide evidence that a free-living insect transfers CKs which manipulates its host plant’s metabolism, likely for its own benefit. CK-mediated plant manipulation strategies have only been known so far from endophytic insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Giron et al., 2016</xref>). The low mobility and intimate associations of endophytic insects with their host plants provides the selective environment for the evolution of mechanisms that allow them to manipulate host plant physiology and/or morphology.</p><p>Species known for CK-dependent manipulation of host plants are not closely related to each other, and span several orders: Lepidoptera, Hymenoptera, Hemiptera and Diptera. The most studied examples are Lepidopteran leaf-miners which cause the green island phenomenon, like <italic>Phyllonorycter blancardella</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Giron et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kaiser et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Body et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>) or <italic>Stigmella argentipedella</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Engelbrecht, 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Engelbrecht, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Engelbrecht et al., 1969</xref>). Among gall-forming organisms, two species of the genus <italic>Bruggmannia</italic> are also capable of producing green islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Fernandes et al., 2008</xref>). Other gallers that manipulate plant morphology can be found among hymenopterans, such as gall-wasps, dipterans such as gall-midges and gall-flies, and hemipterans such as psyllids and gall-aphids. Among these, a role for CKs in gall formation has been shown for the dipterans <italic>Eurosta solidaginis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mapes and Davies, 2001</xref>) and <italic>Rhopalomyia yomogicola</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Tanaka et al., 2013</xref>), the hymenopteran <italic>Dryocosmus kuriphilus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Matsui et al., 1975</xref>) and sawflies of the genus <italic>Pontania</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Yamaguchi et al., 2012</xref>) and the hemipterans <italic>Pachypsylla celtidis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Straka et al., 2010</xref>) and the galling-aphid <italic>Tetraneura nigriabdominalis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Takei et al., 2015</xref>). The fact that species from different orders have developed similar mechanism of plant manipulation suggests either an ancient evolutionary origin or a convergent evolutionary trait. We propose that such CK-dependent manipulation is more widespread than previously thought, and is also shared with free-living insects like <italic>T. notatus</italic>.</p><p>CKs transferred by <italic>T. notatus</italic> could originate from its host plant and be sequestered by the insect but also they could be synthesized by the insect itself or its associate endosymbionts. In fact, CKs are also produced by organisms other than plants, like fungi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Chanclud et al., 2016</xref>), bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Costacurta and Vanderleyden, 1995</xref>) and nematodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Siddique et al., 2015</xref>). It is thought that IP and IPR can be derived from tRNA, and this suggests that the substrate for CK biosynthesis is shared by all organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Persson et al., 1994</xref>), virtually enabling insects to produce CKs. The most recent studies on CK-mediated manipulation of plant physiology by insects suggested a role of endosymbiotic bacteria in CK production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kaiser et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Giron et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>). Antibiotic feeding experiments have revealed that endosymbionts like <italic>Wolbachia</italic> are the most likely producers of CKs in the leaf-miner <italic>P. blancardella</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kaiser et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Body et al., 2013</xref>). Yet, this bacterium is unlikely responsible for CK production in <italic>T. notatus</italic>, as <italic>Wolbachia</italic> was not be detected in mirids from the same glasshouse colony used in our experiments, and was identified only very rarely from insects collected from the field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adam et al., 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Free-living phytophagous insects are thought not to manipulate their host plant’s physiology to enhance the nutritional quality of their diet, as they are free to move to the best feeding locations on a plant. This work provides evidence of the ability of a free-living insect to introduce CKs into their host during feeding to maintain a better nutritional environment. We suggest that this mechanism may be commonly found in other free-living species and that it combines the benefits of the two different lifestyles: the ability to move, hide and choose the best feeding locations, and to manipulate the host plant via CK-transfer. Clarifying the details of the origins of the <italic>T. notatus</italic>-transferred CKs and studying their role in nature will provide new insights into the complex interactions that occur during plant-herbivore interactions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Chemicals</title><p>All chemicals used were obtained from Sigma‐Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, US) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com/">http://www.sigmaaldrich.com/</ext-link>), Merck (Darmstadt, Germany) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.merck.com/">http://www.merck.com/</ext-link>), Roth (Karsruhe, Germany) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.carlroth.com/">http://www.carlroth.com/</ext-link>) or VWR (Radnor, PE, US) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vwr.com">http://www.vwr.com</ext-link>), if not mentioned otherwise in the text. CK standards were obtained from Olchemim (Olomuc, Czech Republic) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.olchemim.cz">http://www.olchemim.cz</ext-link>), dexamethasone (DEX) from Enzo Life Sciences (Farmingdale, NY, US) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.enzolifesciences.com/">http://www.enzolifesciences.com/</ext-link>), HCOOH for ultra-performance LC from Fisher Scientific (Hampton, NH, US) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fisher.co.uk/">http://www.fisher.co.uk/</ext-link>) or from Honeywell Riedel-de Haën<sup>TM</sup> (Morris Plains, NJ, US) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.riedeldehaen.com/">http://www.riedeldehaen.com/</ext-link>), and GB5 from Duchefa (Haarlem, The Netherlands) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.duchefa-biochemie.nl/">http://www.duchefa-biochemie.nl/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Plant cultivation and transgenic plants</title><p>We used the 31st inbred generation of <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> (T<sc>orr</sc>. ex S. Wats.) originating from the ‘Desert Inn’ population from the Great Basin Desert (Washington County, UT, US) as wild-type (WT) plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Baldwin et al., 1994</xref>). Transgenic plants were generated from WT <italic>N. attenuata,</italic> as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Krügel et al., 2002</xref>) by <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation. Empty vector transformed plants (EV) (line A-04-266-3) were used as controls in experiments that included other transgenic lines.</p><p>The transgenic line ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> was transformed with a construct harboring inverted-repeat gene fragments to silence the expression of two of the three known CK receptor homologs <italic>NaCHK2</italic> and <italic>NaCHK3</italic> (<sc>Chase Domain Containing Histidine Kinase</sc> 2 and 3) and was previously characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Schäfer et al., 2015b</xref>). We used line A-12–356, which had a silencing efficiency of about 50%. The i-ov<italic>ipt</italic> line (A-11–92 x A-11–61) contains a gene encoding the rate-limiting step of CK biosynthesis, the isopentenyltransferase (IPT) from <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> (<italic>Tumor morphology root; Tmr</italic>). The IPT gene is controlled by the pOp6/LhGR expression system, which allows transcriptional up-regulation in a specific tissue by the application of DEX (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schäfer et al., 2013</xref>). Application of DEX to the leaves of the plant induces the transcription of <italic>IPT</italic> which locally increases CK levels. DEX was dissolved in lanolin paste with 1% DMSO at a final concentration of 5 µM. For control treatments, we used 1% DMSO in lanolin. The lanolin paste was applied to the petioles of the leaves 24 hr prior to other treatments as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schäfer et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Seeds were sterilized and germinated on Gamborg B5 media as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Krügel et al. (2002)</xref> with modifications as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>). For soil growth conditions, ten days after germination, plants were first transplanted to TEKU pots and 10 days later into 1 L pots. For hydroponic growth conditions, the plants were transferred after 12 days into 50 mL hydroponic culture single pots and 10 days later into 1 L hydroponic containers. Conditions for hydroponic culture were previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Ullmann-Zeunert et al., 2012</xref>) as were conditions for soil growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>). For the damage determination experiment in the glasshouse, single plants were grown in 4 L pots. Plants were maintained under glasshouse conditions (22–27°C; ca. 60% RH, 16:8 light:dark regime) as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adam et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>To prevent <italic>T. notatus</italic> infestation of the main glasshouse facility of the MPI-COE, we maintain the colony in a separate glasshouse located in Isserstedt, Germany, approximately 7 km from the main glasshouse facility. Plants were germinated in the main glasshouse facility and transferred to the Issersted glasshouse just before plants began to flower, when plants had main stems about 25 cm tall. In both glasshouses, plants were maintained at comparable growth conditions. After transferring plants to the Isserstedt glasshouse, we allowed for at least two days of acclimation before initiating experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Insect colony</title><p>The colony of <italic>T. notatus</italic> (Distant, 1893) <sc>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1,1A</xref></sc>) originated from insects caught in the vicinity of the Brigham Young University/Max Planck field station at Lytle Ranch Preserve in the Great Basin Desert (Washington County, UT, US) and was annually refreshed with insects caught from the same field site. The colony was maintained in cages made of acrylic glass (2 × 1 × 1 m) with a fine mesh for air circulation. Cages were maintained under the same glasshouse growth conditions that were used for the cultivation of <italic>N. attenuata</italic> (27°C; ca. 60% RH, 18:8 light:dark regime). We fed insects with hydroponically grown WT <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants. Fresh plants were provided weekly and remained in the cages for several weeks to allow nymphs to hatch from eggs laid in the older plants. Insects were collected from the cage for experiments using an insect exhauster. Prior to being clip-caged onto <italic>N. attenuata</italic> leaves, insects were anaesthetized with CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title><italic>T. notatus</italic> rearing on artificial diet</title><p>For the artificial diet we dissolved amino acids (<sub>L</sub>-alanine, 50 mg; <sub>L</sub>-arginine, 30 mg; <sub>L</sub>-cysteine, 20 mg; glycine, 20 mg; <sub>L</sub>-histidine, 30 mg; <sub>L</sub>-leucine, 30 mg; <sub>L</sub>-lysine, 20 mg; <sub>L</sub>-phenylalanine, 30 mg; <sub>L</sub>-proline, 80 mg; <sub>L</sub>-serine, 100 mg; <sub>L</sub>-tryptophan, 500 mg; <sub>L</sub>-tyrosine, 10 mg; <sub>L</sub>-valine, 40 mg; <sub>L</sub>-asparagine, 200 mg; <sub>L</sub>-aspartic acid, 200 mg; <sub>L</sub>-glutamine, 500 mg; <sub>L</sub>-glutamic acid, 300 mg; <sub>L</sub>-isoleucine, 20 mg; <sub>L</sub>-methionine, 10 mg; <sub>L</sub>-threonine, 100 mg), sugars (glucose, 400 mg; fructose, 150 mg; sucrose, 800 mg) and vitamins (Vanderzant Vitamin Mix, 650 mg) in 40 mL water and sterile filtered the solution. Additionally, we prepared an agar solution (1 g Agar-Agar in 60 mL water) which was sterilized by autoclaving. After cooling the liquid agar solution to approximately 60°C in a water bath, we added the nutrient solution and aliquoted the diet under sterile conditions in single 0.5 mL micro-centrifuge tubes, where it solidified. These tubes were stored at 4°C until use.</p><p>For experiments, <italic>T. notatus</italic> were placed in plastic boxes (10 × 6 × 6 cm) covered with paper tissue and sealed with a perforated lid. In each box, 15 to 20 mirids were placed with a tube containing the artificial diet as the sole food source in addition to a source of water. The diet was exchanged with fresh diet every day. The shaded boxes were kept in the glasshouse. After 5 days the surviving mirids were collected, flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C until CK extraction.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Collection of oral secretions and frass of <italic>T. notatus</italic></title><p><italic>T. notatus</italic> oral secretions were collected as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Halitschke et al., 2011</xref>) with minor modifications. In brief, we placed 15 to 20 mirids in a single plastic box (10 × 6 × 6 cm) covered with paper tissue and sealed with a perforated lid. In each box, we placed an inverted scintillation vial lid filled to the brim with sugar solution (~3 mL, 40 mM glucose) as the sole food and water source. Lids were covered by a stretched thin layer of Parafilm (Neenah, WI, US) which allowed for stylet penetration. After 24 hr, we collected the lids, removed the sugar solution with a syringe and carefully dissolved (with MeOH) the frass spots deposited on the parafilm. As a control, similarly packaged sugar solutions in boxes lacking mirids maintained under the same conditions were used. Frass and sugar solution samples originating from the exposure to approximately 100 mirids were pooled. Pooled sugar solutions were freeze-dried overnight. Prior to CK extraction, extraction buffer was used to dissolve the evaporated sugar solution.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Herbivory treatment</title><p>To measure the defense responses of <italic>N. attenuata</italic> to <italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding, whole plants were exposed to mirid attack in the <italic>T. notatus</italic> rearing cages and damaged lamina from the first (lowest) stem leaf were collected after three days of feeding. Control plants were placed in a similar but mirid-free cage under same conditions. Collected lamina pieces were flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C until analysis.</p><p>For kinetic analysis of CKs, JA, JA-Ile, primary metabolites and photosynthetic rates during <italic>T. notatus</italic> attack, we used two different experimental setups which differed in the area damaged by <italic>T. notatus</italic>, and the number of <italic>T. notatus</italic> used to inflict the damage to the <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants. In the first setup, only one leaf per plant was exposed to <italic>T. notatus.</italic> We enclosed twenty adults on the first (lowest) stem leaf in a round plastic clip-cage (7 cm dimeter, 5 cm height). Clip-cages had holes covered with a fine mesh for air ventilation. Control plants received empty clip-cages to control for the effects of caging leaves. We also sampled leaves from plants without clip-cages. Before sampling, mirid mortality was scored, and samples with more than 50% mortality were discarded. Control and damaged leaf lamina were harvested at nine time-points from separate plants (0, 1, 3, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120 and 144 hr), flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen and kept at −80°C until analysis. In the second setup, the entire aboveground plant was exposed to mirids, by placing the plants directly into the <italic>T. notatus</italic> rearing cage; control plants were placed in a similar, empty cage. Damaged lamina from the first (lowest) stem leaf were sampled at seven time-points from separate plants (0, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120 and 144 hr). Both experiments were started in the morning (09:00 – 12:00) and each harvest time represented at least three replicate plants. For each experiment, phytohormone concentrations (CKs, JA and JA-Ile), sugars (sucrose, fructose and glucose), starch, total soluble proteins, photosynthetic rates and chlorophyll contents were measured.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Measurement of caffeoylputrescine and nicotine</title><p>Caffeoylputrescine and nicotine were extracted and determined by UHPLC-ToF-MS by analyzing extracted ion chromatograms as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Schäfer et al., 2015c</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brütting et al., 2017</xref>). For extraction, 80% MeOH (v/v) was used for approximately 100 mg of frozen and ground leaf material from each sample (exact tissue masses were recorded). Values are presented as peak area * g FM<sup>−1</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Trypsin proteinase inhibitor (TPI) assay</title><p>TPI activity was determined using a radial diffusion assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Jongsma et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">van Dam et al., 2001</xref>) with approximately 50 mg of frozen and ground leaf lamina (exact tissue masses were recorded). TPI activity was normalized to leaf protein content. The protein content of the extracts used for the TPI assay was determined using a Bradford-assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bradford, 1976</xref>) on a 96-well microtiter plate.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Quantification of total soluble proteins</title><p>Total soluble proteins were extracted from 50 mg of frozen ground leaf lamina (exact tissue masses were recorded) in 0.5 ml 0.1 M M Tris-HCl (pH 7.6) following the protocol described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Ullmann-Zeunert et al. (2012)</xref>. Protein concentrations were measured using a Bradford assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bradford, 1976</xref>) on a 96-well microtiter plate using bovine serum albumin (BSA) as standard.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Quantification of free amino acids</title><p>Free amino acids were extracted from leaf lamina by acidified MeOH extraction [MeOH:H<sub>2</sub>O:HCOOH 15:4:1 (v/v/v)] and analyzed by liquid chromatography coupled to a triple quadrupole MS (Bruker EVOQ Elite, Bruker Daltonics, Bremen, Germany; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bruker.com">www.bruker.com</ext-link>), as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Schäfer et al., 2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Measurement of starch, glucose, fructose and sucrose with a hexokinase assay</title><p>Glucose, fructose, sucrose and starch were determined following the protocol described by Machado and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Machado et al., 2015</xref>). Briefly, 100 mg plant tissues (exact tissue masses were recorded) were extracted first with 80% (v/v) ethanol and later twice with 50% (v/v) ethanol, each by incubation for 20 min at 80°C. Supernatants from all extractions were pooled, and sucrose, glucose and fructose were quantified enzymatically as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Velterop and Vos, 2001</xref>). The remaining pellets were used for an enzymatic determination of starch content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Smith and Zeeman, 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Photosynthetic measurements</title><p>Net CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate was measured with a LI-COR LI-6400/XT portable photosynthesis system (LI-COR Inc., Lincoln, NE, US). All measurements were conducted using a 2 cm<sup>2</sup> chamber, at constant CO<sub>2</sub> (400 µmol CO<sub>2</sub> mol air<sup>−1</sup>), light (300 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> PAR), temperature (25–26°C) and relative humidity (20–40%). Measurements of photosynthetic rates of leaves with clip-cage were specifically done on the area included in the clip-cage. We measured photosynthetic rates of control leaves and leaves damaged by <italic>T. notatus</italic>. Leaves with clip-cages were analyzed in the covered area shortly after removal of the clip cage.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Chlorophyll measurement</title><p>Chlorophyll was quantified using a Minolta SPAD Chlorophyll meter 502. Chlorophyll content is displayed in arbitrary SPAD units. Each sample value is the mean of chlorophyll content measured at three different random spots from each analyzed leaf. Leaves with clip cages were analyzed in the covered area shortly after the removal of the clip cage.</p></sec><sec id="s4-14"><title>qPCR quantification of cytokinin-related transcripts</title><p>RNA was extracted with TRIzol (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, US), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. cDNA was synthesized by reverse transcription using oligo(dT) primer and RevertAid reverse transcriptase (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Real-time qPCR was performed using actin as a standard on a Mx3005P qPCR machine (Stratagene, San Diego, CA, US) using a qPCR Core kit for SYBR Green I No ROX mix (Eurogentec, Seraing, Belgium). The primer sequences are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-15"><title>Measurement of phytohormones</title><p>Levels of defense signaling compounds after three days of <italic>T. notatus</italic> herbivory were quantified as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kallenbach et al., 2010</xref>). JA, JA-Ile, OPDA and SA were analyzed as described by Kallenbach and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kallenbach et al., 2010</xref>) and ABA as described by Dinh and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">Ðinh et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Kinetics of CKs, JA and JA-Ile during 144 hr of <italic>T. notatus</italic> attack was measured as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Schäfer et al., 2016</xref>). In brief, phytohormones were extracted from ca. 100 mg of fresh ground leaf material (exact sample masses were recorded) using acidified methanol and purified on reversed phase and cation exchange solid-phase extraction columns. The measurements were done via liquid chromatography coupled to a triple quadrupole MS (Bruker EVO-Q Elite) equipped with a heated electrospray ionization source. The method was extended for the detection of <sup>15</sup>N-labeled CKs. The parent → product ion transitions for <sup>15</sup>N labeled CKs are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp3">Supplementary file 3</xref>. Chromatograms of IP, [D<sub>6</sub>]-IP, [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IP as well as IPR, [D<sub>6</sub>]-IPR and [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-IPR are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s4">Figure 4—figure supplement 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s5">5</xref>. The same extraction method was used for CK extraction from <italic>T. notatus</italic>, using approximately 10 mg of ground material (five pooled samples of ca. 20 adults; exact sample masses were recorded).</p></sec><sec id="s4-16"><title>Cytokinin transfer experiment</title><p><italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants with more than 98% of their total nitrogen content as <sup>15</sup>N were obtained following the protocol described by Ullmann-Zeunert and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Ullmann-Zeunert et al., 2012</xref>). Briefly, twelve days after germination, plants were transferred into individual 50 mL hydroponic culture containers with Ca(<sup>15</sup>NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> as the sole nitrogen source. Ten days later, the plants were transferred to 1 L hydroponic culture chambers with the same <sup>15</sup>NO<sub>3</sub>- concentration as of K<sup>15</sup>NO<sub>3</sub>. Once per week, the plants were fertilized with 1 mM K<sup>15</sup>NO<sub>3</sub> and the containers were maintained at 1 L with distilled water.</p><p>To generate <sup>15</sup>N labeled <italic>T. notatus,</italic> we reared insects for an entire generation on fully <sup>15</sup>N-labelled <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants. Two-hundred adult females were transferred to a 47.5 × 47.5 × 93 cm insect cage with four <sup>15</sup>N-labelled <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants in the early elongation stage of growth. Females were allowed to lay eggs for four days and subsequently removed. <sup>15</sup>N-labelled plants were fertilized once a week (as described above), and after three weeks two fresh <sup>15</sup>N-labelled plants were added to the insect cage. One week after the first adults emerged, the <sup>15</sup>N labeled mirids were collected and used for the cytokinin transfer experiment.</p><p>Two types of experiments were conducted to quantify the transfer of cytokinins from mirids to <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants. In the first, twenty <sup>15</sup>N-labelled <italic>T. notatus</italic> adults were quickly anesthetized with CO<sub>2</sub> prior to clip-caging on a lower stem leaf of a <sup>14</sup>N-grown plant, with one clip-cage per plant. We collected and froze in liquid nitrogen the leaf lamina corresponding to the area included in the clip-cage and thus damaged by mirids at different time-points: 0, 3, 6, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 120 hr. Each harvest time included at least three replicate plants. Samples were stored at −80°C until analysis.</p><p>In the second type of experiment, five <sup>15</sup>N-labelled <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants were placed in the mirid rearing cage. One lower stem or rosette leaf per plant was harvested at 0, 3, 6, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 120 hr, thus each harvest time represented five replicate plants. Plants were transferred once per day to a different cage to ensure that mirids did not accumulate <sup>15</sup>N-labeled metabolites. We separated the leaf lamina from the mid-rib and froze the lamina in liquid nitrogen, and stored the samples at −80°C until analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s4-17"><title>Damage distribution of WT plants under field and glasshouse conditions</title><p>In the field, the damaged area on different leaf types was estimated as % of the total leaf area. The proportion of damaged leaf area for each leaf was visually estimated and the leaves were grouped into three different types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1a</xref>). Finally, we calculated average leaf damage for all leaf types: rosette leaves, the first (oldest) three stem leaves and all younger stem leaves and side branches. Similarly, <italic>T. notatus</italic> damage distribution within the plant was evaluated under controlled conditions in the glasshouse. In this experiment, a total of seven WT plants were used to form four replicates. The replicates consisted of three pairs of WT plants and one single plant, where each replicate was placed in one cage, meaning that one cage represented one replicate with no matter if there were one or two plants inside the cage. The plants in each cage were exposed to adults of <italic>T. notatus</italic> (n = 10 insects/plant) for one week. <italic>T. notatus</italic> infestations continued for an additional two weeks, where in the last week, five insects/plant were added to each cage. <italic>T. notatus</italic> damage was estimated from high resolution pictures of 15 leaves per plant at standardized rosette, mid stem, and young stem positions. Using Photoshop (Adobe), the damage was evaluated and expressed as a percentage of total damage per plant.</p></sec><sec id="s4-18"><title>Choice assays</title><p>For choice assays conducted in the field between young and fully mature leaves, we collected insects from native populations at our field station in Utah, USA. Ten to fifteen <italic>T. notatus</italic> adults were placed in a plastic cup. The cup was connected to two other plastic cups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1b</xref>), one enclosing a fully mature stem leaf and the other enclosing young, growing leaves (apical meristem and young leaves which had not yet completed the sink-source transition). To prevent desiccation, leaf petioles were submerged in water in a 2 mL plastic microcentrifuge tube. As the insects are night-active, after one night (12 hr) during which the insects could choose between the two containers, we counted the number of mirids in each.</p><p>For choice assays between WT and ir<italic>chk2/3</italic> plants, we placed plants in a large mesh-enclosed cage in the glasshouse (3 × 4 × 1.6 m) into which 500 <italic>T. notatus</italic> were released. The damage on each plant (as described above) was estimated 10 days later.</p><p>Data from choice assays on i-ov<italic>ipt</italic> plants were taken from a previously published dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schäfer et al., 2013</xref>). Plants were either treated with pure lanolin (LAN) as a control or with DEX-containing lanolin as described above. We treated the first (oldest) ten stem leaves of a flowering plant and placed one DEX- and one LAN-treated plant in one 47.5 × 47.5×93 cm insect cage. About 100 <italic>T. notatus</italic> adults were added to the cage, and the damaged leaf area was estimated after 10 days. The average damage level from all 10 treated leaves from each plant was counted as one replicate.</p></sec><sec id="s4-19"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Data were analyzed using R 3.3.1 (2016-06-21; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>). Statistical tests and number of replicates, as well as transformations to data in order to meet assumptions of a test (homoscedasticity, normality), are provided in the figure legends. Normality of data sets was assessed by Shapiro–Wilk tests and homoscedasticity by Levene's test. If not mentioned otherwise, time course data were analyzed with ANCOVA with mirid feeding as factor and time as continuous explanatory variable. If the response variable was not linearly dependent on time we used two-way ANOVAs (TWA) with mirid feeding and time as factors. In all the analyses of experiments with the data from clip-cages, we only used data from control clip-cages and clip-cages with mirids. Differences were considered significant when p&lt;0.05.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was funded by the Max-Planck-Society. In addition, Christoph Brütting, Stephan Meldau and Meredith C Schuman were funded by ERC Advanced Grant no. 293926 from the European Research Council to Ian T Baldwin. Martin Schäfer and Cristina Crava were funded by Collaborative Research Centre ‘Chemical Mediators in Complex Biosystems - ChemBioSys’ (SFB 1127) from the DFG. We thank Brigham Young University for the use of their Lytle Preserve field station, Mario Kallenbach, Matthias Schöttner, Thomas Hahn, Antje Wissgott, Wibke Kröber, Celia Diezel, and Eva Rothe for technical assistance, Claire Poore, Thomas Steier, Anja Hartmann, Spencer Arnesen and Katrina Welker for help with sample processing, Tamara Krügel, Andreas Weber, Andreas Schünzel and the entire glasshouse team for plant cultivation, and Rayko Halitschke for helpful discussions.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf2"><p>Senior editor, <italic>eLife</italic></p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Conceptualization, Investigation, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Conceptualization, Supervision, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Conceptualization, Project administration</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Formal analysis, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>Conceptualization, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Project administration, Writing—review and editing</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.025</object-id><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Calculations of the minimum amount of IP transferred by a single mirid in clip-cage experiment and estimation of the number of feeding mirids required to transfer the measured amount of IP in the whole-plant experiment.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36268-supp1-v3.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.026</object-id><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>Sequences of primers used for real-time qPCR.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36268-supp2-v3.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.027</object-id><label>Supplementary file 3.</label><caption><title>Multi-reaction monitoring settings for the quantification of [<sup>14</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]-, [<sup>15</sup>N<sub>5</sub>]- and deuterated cytokinins in positive ionization mode.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36268-supp3-v3.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.028</object-id><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36268-transrepform-v3.docx"/></supplementary-material><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are available on Dryad Digital Repository</p><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><related-object content-type="generated-dataset" id="dataset1" source-id="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.hq48044" source-id-type="uri"><collab collab-type="author">Brütting C</collab><collab collab-type="author">Crava CM</collab><collab collab-type="author">Schäfer M</collab><collab collab-type="author">Schuman MC</collab><collab collab-type="author">Meldau S</collab><collab collab-type="author">Adam N</collab><collab collab-type="author">Baldwin IT</collab><year>2018</year><source>Data from: Cytokinin transfer by a free-living mirid to Nicotiana attenuata recapitulates a strategy of endophytic insects</source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.hq48044">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.hq48044</ext-link><comment>Available at Dryad Digital Repository under a CC0 Public Domain Dedication</comment></related-object></p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adam</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Erler</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallenbach</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaltenpoth</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunert</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuman</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Sex ratio of mirid populations shifts in response to hostplant co-infestation or altered cytokinin signaling </article-title><source>Journal of Integrative Plant Biology</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jipb.12507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27862998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allison</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Biochemical responses of chestnut oak to a galling cynipid</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-005-0981-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15839487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babst</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrieri</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerdau</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlyer</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schueller</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Orians</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Jasmonic acid induces rapid changes in carbon transport and partitioning in <italic>Populus</italic></article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><volume>167</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01388.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15948830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Staszak-Kozinski</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Up in smoke: I. Smoke-derived germination cues for postfire annual <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> torr. Ex. Watson</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>2345</fpage><lpage>2371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02033207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24242811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Jasmonate-induced responses are costly but benefit plants under attack in native populations</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>8113</fpage><lpage>8118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.14.8113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9653149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behr</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Humbeck</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hause</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Deising</surname> <given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirsel</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The hemibiotroph <italic>Colletotrichum graminicola</italic> locally induces photosynthetically active green islands but globally accelerates senescence on aging maize leaves</article-title><source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interactions</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>879</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-23-7-0879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20521951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Body</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubreuil</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Casas</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Giron</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Leaf-miners co-opt microorganisms to enhance their nutritional environment</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>969</fpage><lpage>977</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-013-0307-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23807431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1976">1976</year><article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title><source>Analytical Biochemistry</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(76)90527-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="data"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brütting</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Crava</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schäfer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuman</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><data-title>Data from: cytokinin transfer by a free-living mirid to Nicotiana attenuata recapitulates a strategy of endophytic insects</data-title><source>Dryad</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5061/dryad.hq48044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brütting</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schäfer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanková</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gase</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Changes in cytokinins are sufficient to alter developmental patterns of defense metabolites in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic></article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27557345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chanclud</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisiala</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname> <given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalvon</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ducasse</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Romiti-Michel</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gravot</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroj</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Cytokinin production by the rice blast fungus is a pivotal requirement for full virulence</article-title><source>PLoS Pathogens</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e1005457</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1005457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26900703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costacurta</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanderleyden</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Synthesis of phytohormones by plant-associated bacteria</article-title><source>Critical Reviews in Microbiology</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10408419509113531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7576148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crava</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brütting</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Transcriptome profiling reveals differential gene expression of detoxification enzymes in a hemimetabolous tobacco pest after feeding on jasmonate-silenced <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> plants</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>1005</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-3348-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27931186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Després</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallet</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>The evolutionary ecology of insect resistance to plant chemicals</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2007.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17324485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engelbrecht</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Orban</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Heese</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1969">1969</year><article-title>Leaf-miner caterpillars and cytokinins in the “Green Islands” of autumn leaves</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>223</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/223319a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engelbrecht</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1968">1968</year><article-title>Cytokinins in the green islands of autumnal leaves</article-title><source>Flora Oder Allg. Bot. Zeitung</source><volume>159</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0367-1836(17)30103-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engelbrecht</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1971">1971</year><article-title>Cytokinin activity in larval infected leaves</article-title><source>Biochemie und Physiologie der Pflanzen : BPP</source><volume>162</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0015-3796(17)31102-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>De Marco Júnior</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schönrogge</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Plant organ abscission and the green island effect caused by gallmidges (Cecidomyiidae) on tropical trees</article-title><source>Arthropod-Plant Interactions</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11829-008-9031-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fragoso</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothe</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Root jasmonic acid synthesis and perception regulate folivore-induced shoot metabolites and increase <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> resistance</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><volume>202</volume><fpage>1335</fpage><lpage>1345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24580101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Inhibition of leaf senescence by autoregulated production of cytokinin</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>270</volume><fpage>1986</fpage><lpage>1988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.270.5244.1986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8592746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giron</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Frago</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Glevarec</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname> <given-names>CMJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicke</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Cytokinins as key regulators in plant-microbe-insect interactions: connecting plant growth and defence</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2435.12042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giron</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huguet</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname> <given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Body</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Insect-induced effects on plants and possible effectors used by galling and leaf-mining insects to manipulate their host-plant</article-title><source>Journal of Insect Physiology</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinsphys.2015.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26723843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giron</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Imbault</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Casas</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Cytokinin-mediated leaf manipulation by a leafminer caterpillar</article-title><source>Biology Letters</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsbl.2007.0051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17412674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gyulai</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Heszky</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Auxin and cytokinin bioassays: A short review</article-title><source>Acta Agron. Hungarica</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halitschke</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Herbivore-specific elicitation of photosynthesis by mirid bug salivary secretions in the wild tobacco <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic></article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><volume>191</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2011.03701.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halitschke</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schittko</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohnert</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Molecular interactions between the specialist herbivore <italic>Manduca sexta</italic> (Lepidoptera, Sphingidae) and its natural host <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic>. III. Fatty acid-amino acid conjugates in herbivore oral secretions are necessary and sufficient for herbivore-specific plant responses</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>125</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.125.2.711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11161028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanik</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gómez</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schueller</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orians</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrieri</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Partitioning of new carbon as ¹¹C in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> reveals insight into methyl jasmonate induced changes in metabolism</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>1058</fpage><lpage>1067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-010-9835-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20842413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname> <given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohfritsch</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Virulent hessian fly (Diptera: cecidomyiidae) larvae induce a nutritive tissue during compatible interactions with wheat</article-title><source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0013-8746(2006)099[0305:VHFDCL]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartley</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>The chemical composition of plant galls: are levels of nutrients and secondary compounds controlled by the gall-former?</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004420050401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28308028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heckel</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><chapter-title>Insect detoxification and sequestration strategies</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Voelckel</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jander</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>Annual Plant Reviews</source><volume>47</volume><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</publisher-name><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9781118829783.ch3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jongsma</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiekema</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Trypsin inhibitor activity in mature tobacco and tomato plants is mainly induced locally in response to insect attack, wounding and virus infection</article-title><source>Planta</source><volume>195</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00206288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordi</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schapendonk</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Davelaar</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoopen</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pot</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>De Visser</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhijn</surname> <given-names>JAV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Increased cytokinin levels in transgenic PSAG12-IPT tobacco plants have large direct and indirect effects on leaf senescence, photosynthesis and <italic>N</italic> partitioning</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3040.2000.00544.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaiser</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Huguet</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Casas</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Commin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Giron</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Plant green-island phenotype induced by leaf-miners is mediated by bacterial symbionts</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><volume>277</volume><fpage>2311</fpage><lpage>2319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2010.0214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20356892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kallenbach</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alagna</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonaventure</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title><italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> SIPK, WIPK, NPR1, and fatty acid-amino acid conjugates participate in the induction of jasmonic acid biosynthesis by affecting early enzymatic steps in the pathway</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>152</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.149013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Defensive function of herbivore-induced plant volatile emissions in nature</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>291</volume><fpage>2141</fpage><lpage>2144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.291.5511.2141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11251117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Plant responses to insect herbivory: the emerging molecular analysis</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.53.100301.135207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12221978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Herbivore-induced plant vaccination. Part I. The orchestration of plant defenses in nature and their fitness consequences in the wild tobacco <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic></article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02076.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15125770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Halitschke</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Silencing the jasmonate cascade: induced plant defenses and insect populations</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>305</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1096931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15232071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krügel</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gase</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Halitschke</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title><italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic>, a model ecological expression system</article-title><source>Chemoecology</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/PL00012666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Machado</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arce</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrieri</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Erb</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Jasmonate-dependent depletion of soluble sugars compromises plant resistance to <italic>Manduca sexta</italic></article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><volume>207</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25704234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mapes</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Cytokinins in the ball gall of <italic>Solidago altissima</italic> and in the gall forming larvae of <italic>Eurosta solidaginis</italic></article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><volume>151</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1469-8137.2001.00158.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsui</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Torikata</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Munakata</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1975">1975</year><article-title>Studies on the resistance of chestnut trees (<italic>Castanea</italic> spp.) to chestnut gall wasps (<italic>Dryocosmus kuriphilus</italic> YASUMATSU)</article-title><source>Journal of the Japanese Society for Horticultural Science</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2503/jjshs.43.415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meza-Canales</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zavala</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Herbivore perception decreases photosynthetic carbon assimilation and reduces stomatal conductance by engaging 12-oxo-phytodienoic acid, mitogen-activated protein kinase 4 and cytokinin perception</article-title><source>Plant, Cell &amp; Environment</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.12874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27925291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mok</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mok</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Cytokinin metabolism and action</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.52.1.89</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11337393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nabity</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Haus</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Berenbaum</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLucia</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Leaf-galling phylloxera on grapes reprograms host metabolism and morphology</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>16663</fpage><lpage>16668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1220219110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24067657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohnmeiss</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Optimal defense theory predicts the ontogeny of an induced nicotine defense</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>1765</fpage><lpage>1783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/0012-9658(2000)081[1765:ODTPTO]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ori</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Juarez</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Banowetz</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Leaf senescence is delayed in tobacco plants expressing the maize homeobox gene <italic>knotted1</italic> under the control of a senescence-activated promoter</article-title><source>The Plant Cell Online</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.11.6.1073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10368178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paschold</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Halitschke</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Co(i)-ordinating defenses: NaCOI1 mediates herbivore- induced resistance in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> and reveals the role of herbivore movement in avoiding defenses</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03119.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17561925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Persson</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Esberg</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Olafsson</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Björk</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Synthesis and function of isopentenyl adenosine derivatives in tRNA</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>1152</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0300-9084(94)90044-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7748950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richmond</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1957">1957</year><article-title>Effect of kinetin on protein content and survival of detached <italic>Xanthium</italic> Leaves</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>125</volume><fpage>650</fpage><lpage>651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.125.3249.650-a</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robischon</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Do cytokinins function as two-way signals between plants and animals?</article-title><source>BioEssays</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.201400099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roda</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldham</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Svatos</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Allometric analysis of the induced flavonols on the leaf surface of wild tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic>)</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(02)00608-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12620365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Cytokinins: activity, biosynthesis, and translocation</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.57.032905.105231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16669769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saltzmann</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovanini</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Virulent Hessian fly larvae manipulate the free amino acid content of host wheat plants</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>1401</fpage><lpage>1410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-008-9544-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18841417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuman</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>The layers of plant responses to insect herbivores</article-title><source>Annual Review of Entomology</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-010715-023851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26651543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuman</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthel</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Herbivory-induced volatiles function as defenses increasing fitness of the native plant <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> in nature</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>e00007</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.00007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23066503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schäfer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brütting</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallenbach</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>High-throughput quantification of more than 100 primary- and secondary-metabolites, and phytohormones by a single solid-phase extraction based sample preparation with analysis by UHPLC-HESI-MS/MS</article-title><source>Plant Methods</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13007-016-0130-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27239220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schäfer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brütting</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gase</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichelt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>'Real time' genetic manipulation: a new tool for ecological field studies</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23906159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schäfer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brütting</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meza-Canales</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Großkinsky</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vankova</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015a</year><article-title>The role of cis-zeatin-type cytokinins in plant growth regulation and mediating responses to environmental interactions</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>4873</fpage><lpage>4884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erv214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25998904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schäfer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meza-Canales</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Brütting</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015b</year><article-title>Cytokinin concentrations and Chase-domain containing his kinase 2 (NaCHK2)- and NaCHK3-mediated perception modulate herbivory-induced defense signaling and defenses in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic></article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><volume>207</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25919325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schäfer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meza-Canales</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro-Quezada</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brütting</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanková</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015c</year><article-title>Cytokinin levels and signaling respond to wounding and the perception of herbivore elicitors in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Integrative Plant Biology</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jipb.12227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24924599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shorthouse</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wool</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Raman</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Gall-inducing insects – Nature's most sophisticated herbivores</article-title><source>Basic and Applied Ecology</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.baae.2005.07.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddique</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Radakovic</surname> <given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>De La Torre</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chronis</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Novák</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramireddy</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Holbein</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matera</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hütten</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutbrod</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Anjam</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozanska</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Habash</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Elashry</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobczak</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakimoto</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Strnad</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmülling</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchum</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundler</surname> <given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A parasitic nematode releases cytokinin that controls cell division and orchestrates feeding site formation in host plants</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>12669</fpage><lpage>12674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1503657112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26417108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skrzypek</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saniewski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Jasmonates are essential factors inducing gummosis in tulips: mode of action of jasmonates focusing on sugar metabolism</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Physiology</source><volume>162</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2004.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15940867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeeman</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Quantification of starch in plant tissues</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>1342</fpage><lpage>1345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2006.232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steppuhn</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gase</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krock</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Halitschke</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Nicotine's defensive function in nature</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e217</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0020217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15314646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname> <given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schönrogge</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>The adaptive significance of insect gall morphology</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(03)00247-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Straka</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname> <given-names>RJN</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Gall-inducing <italic>Pachypsylla celtidis</italic> (Psyllidae) infiltrate hackberry trees with high concentrations of phytohormones</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Interactions</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17429145.2010.484552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strong</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawton</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Southwood</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1984">1984</year><source>Insects on Plants: Community Patterns And Mechanisms</source><publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawai</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Adaptive significance of gall formation for a gall-inducing aphids on Japanese elm trees</article-title><source>Journal of Insect Physiology</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinsphys.2014.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25437243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Phytohormones in Japanese mugwort gall induction by a gall-inducing gall midge</article-title><source>Bioscience, Biotechnology, and Biochemistry</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>1942</fpage><lpage>1948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1271/bbb.130406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24018692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tooker</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>De Moraes</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Feeding by a gall-inducing caterpillar species alters levels of indole-3-acetic and abscisic acid in <italic>Solidago altissima</italic> (Asteraceae) stems</article-title><source>Arthropod-Plant Interactions</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11829-010-9120-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tytgat</surname> <given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoeven</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Raaijmakers</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakx-Schotman</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntyre</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Putten</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Biere</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dam</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Plants know where it hurts: root and shoot jasmonic acid induction elicit differential responses in <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic></article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>65502</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23776489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ullmann-Zeunert</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Muck</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wielsch</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hufsky</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanton</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartram</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Böcker</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Groten</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Svatoš</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Determination of ¹⁵N-incorporation into plant proteins and their absolute quantitation: a new tool to study nitrogen flux dynamics and protein pool sizes elicited by plant-herbivore interactions</article-title><source>Journal of Proteome Research</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>4947</fpage><lpage>4960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr300465n</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22905865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ullmann-Zeunert</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanton</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wielsch</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartram</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hummert</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Svatoš</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Groten</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Quantification of growth-defense trade-offs in a common currency: nitrogen required for phenolamide biosynthesis is not derived from ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase turnover</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>75</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23590461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Dam</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadwich</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Induced responses in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> affect behavior and growth of the specialist herbivore <italic>Manduca sexta</italic></article-title><source>Oecologia</source><volume>122</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004420050043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28308288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Dam</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mares</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Ontogeny constrains systemic protease inhibitor response in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1010341022761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11441445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Dam</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oomen</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Root and shoot jasmonic acid applications differentially affect leaf chemistry and herbivore growth</article-title><source>Plant Signaling &amp; Behavior</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.3.2.5220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19516980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Velterop</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vos</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>A rapid and inexpensive microplate assay for the enzymatic determination of glucose, fructose, sucrose, L-malate and citrate in tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>) extracts and in orange juice</article-title><source>Phytochemical Analysis</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pca.598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11705256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voelckel</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Herbivore-induced plant vaccination. Part II. Array-studies reveal the transience of herbivore-specific transcriptional imprints and a distinct imprint from stress combinations</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>650</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02077.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15125771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walters</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>McRoberts</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitt</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Are green islands red herrings? Significance of green islands in plant interactions with pathogens and pests</article-title><source>Biological Reviews</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-185X.2007.00033.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18093233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokuda</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Phytohormones and willow gall induction by a gall-inducing sawfly</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><volume>196</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04264.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22913630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zavala</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Patankar</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gase</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Constitutive and inducible trypsin proteinase inhibitor production incurs large fitness costs in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic></article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>1607</fpage><lpage>1612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0305096101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14757829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dugé de Bernonville</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Body</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Glevarec</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichelt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Unsicker</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruneau</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Renou</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Huguet</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubreuil</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Giron</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Leaf-mining by <italic>Phyllonorycter blancardella</italic> reprograms the host-leaf transcriptome to modulate phytohormones associated with nutrient mobilization and plant defense</article-title><source>Journal of Insect Physiology</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinsphys.2015.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26068004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiguet</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubreuil</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisiala</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreas</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname> <given-names>RJN</given-names></name><name><surname>Huguet</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Body</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giron</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Dynamics and origin of cytokinins involved in plant manipulation by a leaf-mining insect</article-title><source>Insect Science</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1065</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1744-7917.12500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28636152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lou</surname> <given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzin</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jander</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Alteration of plant primary metabolism in response to insect herbivory</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>169</volume><fpage>1488</fpage><lpage>1498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.01405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26378101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ðinh</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Gális</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>UVB radiation and 17-hydroxygeranyllinalool diterpene glycosides provide durable resistance against mirid (<italic>Tupiocoris notatus</italic>) attack in field-grown <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> plants</article-title><source>Plant, Cell &amp; Environment</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2012.02598.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22897424</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.032</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>Joerg</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of British Columbia</institution><country>Canada</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Cytokinin transfer by a free-living mirid to <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> recapitulates a strategy of endophytic insects&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>.</p><p>Your article has been reviewed by an external peer reviewer, and the evaluation has been overseen by Joerg Bohlmann as the Reviewing Editor and Detlef Weigel as the Senior Editor. The external reviewer, Enric Frago, agreed to reveal his identity. We discussed the review and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Overall, the external review was positive. Based on this assessment and based on the Reviewing Editor's reading of the paper and our discussion, we believe the work presented in this manuscript will be of considerable interest to the broad audience of <italic>eLife</italic>. This paper has strong potential to impact how people view plant herbivore interactions. There are, however, a few issues that will require revisions. First, there are questions about the origin of the cytokinins. Preferentially, you will provide additional data that clearly document the insect origin of cytokinins. In their absence, please be more circumspect in your discussion of cytokinin origin. Additional work to test the plant fitness consequences is needed to substantially improve the paper.</p><p>External Reviewer's Comments</p><p>In this study Brütting, Crava and co-authors study how an herbivorous mirid bug manipulates the physiology of its host plant using plant hormone cytokinins (CKs). These hormones are important regulators of source-sink nutrient balances in plants, so that a potential benefit of increasing CKs in the local area the insect feeds on is an increase in the nutritional value of that area. This strategy has already been suggested as important in endophytic insects because their larvae are spatially constrained and cannot look for areas with an optimal nutritional value (particularly after plant defences are triggered). Several studies have shown that CK levels are higher in bodies of endophytic insects as well as in plant areas in which they feed, but direct CK production by insects remains elusive. This manuscript is thus very exciting because it shows for the first time (to my knowledge) that a CK, which is quite likely produced by the insect is incorporated into the plant, leading to transcriptomic changes and to associated nutritional changes. In addition, this effect is shown in a non-endophytic insect, which suggests that the mechanism reported here can be widespread in insects. The manuscript is well written and will be of interest to a large audience. The experiments are well designed because they follow a sequence of discoveries and novel hypotheses, which are subsequently tested. I have, however, few concerns regarding the interpretation of results that I detail below. I am not an expert on CK metabolism, so I will have minor comments in this regard.</p><p>One of the main concerns I have is that in the Results and Discussion sections authors speculate too much when interpreting their results. I have the feeling that the authors try to build a nice story, and they often interpret their results in a way that they point too directly to the following experiment.</p><p>For example, an important conclusion of this study is that thanks to CK manipulation, mirids can feed on their host plants without altering the nutritional quality of the plant. It is true that several metabolites like sugars were not altered, but proteins were, and the authors still state that &quot;mirid feeding did not dramatically affect the overall nutritional quality of leaves&quot; (subsection “<italic>T. notatus</italic> feeding does not negatively affect the nutritional quality of the attacked leaves”). It seems that authors are just picking the results they are interested in to keep the flow of the story. To what extent are protein contents important for this insect species, for instance? Most phloem feeders, for example, are strongly affected by protein contents in phloem, while sugars are in fact meaningless in terms of their consequences for insect fitness.</p><p>Related to my previous comment, the authors speculate about the benefits insects can gain from CK manipulation (e.g. Discussion section) but no formal test is performed. This study reports a suite of really complicated experiments, and I find very surprising that the authors did not perform such a simple experiment. Testing how insects perform on the two mutant plants that constitutively express or do not express CKs would be a quite simple and highly informative experiment. Alternatively, can they explain why this experiment is not needed to support their conclusions?</p><p>Also related to my first comment, I am still a bit puzzled by the enigmatic effect of mirids on plant fitness (e.g. subsection “Altered CK metabolism in <italic>N. attenuata</italic> affects its interaction with <italic>T. notatus</italic>”, Discussion section). As far as I know, CKs can alter nutrient balances among different parts of the plant, but how is it possible that an insect takes biomass from the plant without imposing any fitness cost? I am aware of the studies published by some of the authors of the present study in which overcompensation is suggested as a plant strategy to minimise damage when herbivory occurs. However, to my taste, the authors rely too much on these previous studies to argue that plants do not suffer from these mirids. In fact, the authors found in one of their experiments that plants indeed suffer when large insect densities are present. I think the authors should cling a bit less on their previous results and argue that maybe, plants can resist a certain level of herbivory, but they suffer when a certain threshold is reached. Why not test plant fitness consequences when insects feed on mutant plants that constitutively express CKs? This would unequivocally prove the costs of being able of triggering defences or not. If not possible, please de-emphasise discussions on the null effect of mirid feeding on plant fitness.</p><p>I find the arguments that CKs originate from the insect a bit unconvincing. The authors argue that CKs come from the insect because (i) CK concentration in the insect was ten times larger than in the plant (subsection “<italic>T. notatus</italic> contains high levels of IP” and Discussion section), and because (ii) these CK levels remained stable after five days of rearing on artificial diet. However, insects were reared on natural plants, then fed 5 days artificial diet, and then CKs measured. To my view, this experiment does not really demonstrate that CKs are synthesised by the insect as it is possible they are sequestered from the plant (as happens in other insects that sequester defensive plant metabolites). I wonder what would happen with CK levels if insects were reared since early instars on artificial diet.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36268.033</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>External Reviewer's Comments</p><p>In this study Brütting, Crava and co-authors study how an herbivorous mirid bug manipulates the physiology of its host plant using plant hormone cytokinins (CKs). These hormones are important regulators of source-sink nutrient balances in plants, so that a potential benefit of increasing CKs in the local area the insect feeds on is an increase in the nutritional value of that area. This strategy has already been suggested as important in endophytic insects because their larvae are spatially constrained and cannot look for areas with an optimal nutritional value (particularly after plant defences are triggered). Several studies have shown that CK levels are higher in bodies of endophytic insects as well as in plant areas in which they feed, but direct CK production by insects remains elusive. This manuscript is thus very exciting because it shows for the first time (to my knowledge) that a CK, which is quite likely produced by the insect is incorporated into the plant, leading to transcriptomic changes and to associated nutritional changes. In addition, this effect is shown in a non-endophytic insect, which suggests that the mechanism reported here can be widespread in insects. The manuscript is well written and will be of interest to a large audience. The experiments are well designed because they follow a sequence of discoveries and novel hypotheses, which are subsequently tested. I have, however, few concerns regarding the interpretation of results that I detail below. I am not an expert on CK metabolism, so I will have minor comments in this regard.</p><p>One of the main concerns I have is that in the Results and Discussion sections authors speculate too much when interpreting their results. I have the feeling that the authors try to build a nice story, and they often interpret their results in a way that they point too directly to the following experiment.</p></disp-quote><p>Thanks for this insightful point. We agree that in parts we may have forced transitions and in reworking the text we have tried to find a more natural, less forced, flow for the experimental narrative and have reworked the explanatory text that we thought was helping readers follow our experimental logic. Throughout this work, we have strived to consider alternative hypotheses at each step in the process; and in parts, we may have overdone it, and confounded the logical flow with a heterogeneous consideration of the mountain of data that was collected in the process. We hope that this revision has been successful regarding this important point.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>For example, an important conclusion of this study is that thanks to CK manipulation, mirids can feed on their host plants without altering the nutritional quality of the plant. It is true that several metabolites like sugars were not altered, but proteins were, and the authors still state that &quot;mirid feeding did not dramatically affect the overall nutritional quality of leaves&quot; (subsection “T. notatus feeding does not negatively affect the nutritional quality of the attacked leaves”). It seems that authors are just picking the results they are interested in to keep the flow of the story. To what extent are protein contents important for this insect species, for instance? Most phloem feeders, for example, are strongly affected by protein contents in phloem, while sugars are in fact meaningless in terms of their consequences for insect fitness.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with the reviewer’s point. We do not know how and if protein content is important for <italic>T. notatus</italic> which unlike aphids, is not an exclusive phloem feeder, but we recognize that nitrogen is often a constraint for the diets of many herbivorous insects. Our results revealed that the decrease in total soluble proteins (TSPs) was only significant when we exposed the entire plant directly to our mirid colony and not when we confined twenty mirids to a single leaf (even when, in this latter case, feeding damage was clearly apparent). This was surprising because wounding and application of <italic>M. sexta</italic> oral secretions significantly decreases total soluble proteins in elicited <italic>N. attenuata</italic> leaves. We have revised the text in the Results session as follows to temper our conclusions:</p><p>“In summary, when only twenty mirids were allowed to feed on a single leaf the overall nutritional quality was not altered, although the feeding damage was visibly severe. In contrast, during a more extreme mirid infestation in which entire plants were severely attacked, TSP levels of attacked leaves decreased, but sugar and starch contents remained unchanged”.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Related to my previous comment, the authors speculate about the benefits insects can gain from CK manipulation (e.g. Discussion section) but no formal test is performed. This study reports a suite of really complicated experiments, and I find very surprising that the authors did not perform such a simple experiment. Testing how insects perform on the two mutant plants that constitutively express or do not express CKs would be a quite simple and highly informative experiment. Alternatively, can they explain why this experiment is not needed to support their conclusions?</p></disp-quote><p>We agree completely with the reviewer that, at least on paper, this experiment should provide the cleanest test of our hypothesis. However, constitutive CK over-expression or silencing is well known to result in such severe developmental abnormalities that the analysis of the effects of CKs on herbivore performance would be confounded by the accompanying morphological and developmental consequences of the CK manipulations. These vast pleiotropic effects of CKs are likely the reason why the plant-herbivore community has been slow to realize the importance of CKs in mediating responses to attack. The work presented in this paper was motivated by an observation published in previous paper (Schäfer et al., 2013), in which we developed a DEX-inducible system for <italic>N. attenuata</italic>, and as a proof of concept, used it to over-express a CK biosynthetic gene (IPT). When we planted these plants into the field and elicited particular leaves with DEX, the treated leaves were heavily attacked by mirids. This was the first direct evidence that mirids preferred high CK levels. In this paper, we use the same DEX-inducible system to over-express IPT and a transgenic line silenced in two of three CK receptors to manipulate CK levels in fully developed leaves to partially disentangle the pleiotropy. By quantifying damage levels, we show that mirids prefer leaves that over-express CKs compared to WT leaves, and that they prefer WT leaves to leaves impaired in CK perception. These data point to the importance of CKs in the mirid performance or at least feeding behavior.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Also related to my first comment, I am still a bit puzzled by the enigmatic effect of mirids on plant fitness (e.g. subsection “Altered CK metabolism in N. attenuata affects its interaction with T. notatus”, Discussion section). As far as I know, CKs can alter nutrient balances among different parts of the plant, but how is it possible that an insect takes biomass from the plant without imposing any fitness cost? I am aware of the studies published by some of the authors of the present study in which overcompensation is suggested as a plant strategy to minimise damage when herbivory occurs. However, to my taste, the authors rely too much on these previous studies to argue that plants do not suffer from these mirids. In fact, the authors found in one of their experiments that plants indeed suffer when large insect densities are present. I think the authors should cling a bit less on their previous results and argue that maybe, plants can resist a certain level of herbivory, but they suffer when a certain threshold is reached. Why not test plant fitness consequences when insects feed on mutant plants that constitutively express CKs? This would unequivocally prove the costs of being able of triggering defences or not. If not possible, please de-emphasise discussions on the null effect of mirid feeding on plant fitness.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with the reviewer that in one of the two experimental designs used in this study, when we exposed entire <italic>N. attenuata</italic> plants to our glasshouse mirid colony, plants were heavily attacked and clearly suffered. We chose this heavy infestation setup because attack from large number of mirids was advantageous to clearly trace the transfer of labeled CKs from mirids into the CK pools of plants. As we had used this experimental setup for the labeling experiments, we were compelled to use the same setup with the same high herbivore load to examine effects on nutrient contents. We ran a parallel lower infestation setup and found no significant differences between the two setups for all nutrients examined except for TSPs which were significantly depleted under the heavy infestation condition. However, in our three decades of field work with <italic>N. attenuata</italic>, such high mirid densities do not commonly occur (in most years, plants in the field host between 3 to 20 individuals and not hundreds as was the case for these glasshouse experiments). Hence drawing conclusions about the fitness consequences from unrealistically high heavy infestation rates does not seem appropriate to us. Therefore, we rely more on the previous published data from our group (Kessler et al., 2004) because this work was conducted under field conditions at our field site in Utah. We think that these were the best possible circumstances in which to quantify plant fitness cost. Fitness data from field experiments should always hold sway over those from glasshouse experiments, which are frequently confounded by all sorts of artifacts (lack of AMF interactions, pot-bound roots, no UVB fluence, to name a few). Moreover, published experiments with the same mirid species attacking <italic>Datura wrightii</italic> conducted by other researchers reported similarly neutral fitness effects of <italic>T. notatus</italic> attack (see Elle and Hare, 2000; Hare and Elle, 2002).</p><p>We agree with reviewer that a formal analysis of the fitness effects of mirid attack on <italic>N. attenuata</italic> is beyond the scope of this paper and hence we have deleted discussions of the neutral effects of mirid feeding on plant fitness.</p><p>As noted above, while the proposed experiments using mutant plants that constitutively express CKs sound good on paper, they would not be illuminating due to the strong development effects of over-expressing CKs.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>I find the arguments that CKs originate from the insect a bit unconvincing. The authors argue that CKs come from the insect because (i) CK concentration in the insect was ten times larger than in the plant (subsection “T. notatus contains high levels of IP” and Discussion section), and because (ii) these CK levels remained stable after five days of rearing on artificial diet. However, insects were reared on natural plants, then fed 5 days artificial diet, and then CKs measured. To my view, this experiment does not really demonstrate that CKs are synthesised by the insect as it is possible they are sequestered from the plant (as happens in other insects that sequester defensive plant metabolites). I wonder what would happen with CK levels if insects were reared since early instars on artificial diet.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with the reviewer that the experiments have not rigorously ruled out the possibility that CKs found in mirids could have originated from host plant and were subsequently sequestered by the insect. Unfortunately, we not been successful (despite many attempts) in rearing <italic>T. notatus</italic> entirely on artificial diet and as a consequence, we have not been able to rigorously test this hypothesis. We have removed the text where we speculated about the origins of the CKs transferred by <italic>T. notatus</italic> in both the Results and Discussion sessions.</p></body></sub-article></article>