<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="article-commentary" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">36662</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.36662</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Insight</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Developmental Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Structural Biology and Molecular Biophysics</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sub-display-channel"><subject>Gastrulation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>May the force be with you</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-110321"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>Shinuo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><bio><p><bold>Shinuo Weng</bold> is in the Department of Molecular Biosciences, The University of Texas at Austin, Austin, United States</p></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-7351"><name><surname>Wallingford</surname><given-names>John B</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6280-8625</contrib-id><email>wallingford@austin.utexas.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><bio><p><bold>John B Wallingford</bold> is in the Department of Molecular Biosciences, The University of Texas at Austin, Austin, United States</p></bio></contrib><aff id="aff1"><institution content-type="dept">Department of Molecular Biosciences</institution><institution>University of Texas at Austin</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Austin</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>24</day><month>04</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e36662</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-04-17"><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-04-17"><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018, Weng et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Weng et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-36662-v1.pdf"/><related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="ra1" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.26944"/><abstract><p>Understanding the coordination of the forces generated in embryos by two processes, convergent extension and convergent thickening, is key to understanding how a hollow sphere of cells develops into an elongated embryo.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>biomechanics</kwd><kwd>force</kwd><kwd>convergent extension</kwd><kwd>gastrulation</kwd><kwd>blastopore closure</kwd><kwd>convergent thickening</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd><italic>Xenopus</italic></kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Understanding the coordination of the forces generated in embryos by two processes, convergent extension and convergent thickening, is key to understanding how a hollow sphere of cells develops into an elongated embryo.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text><p><bold>Related research article</bold> Shook DR, Kasprowicz EM, Davidson LA, Keller R. 2018. Large, long range tensile forces drive convergence during Xenopus blastopore closure and body axis elongation. <italic>eLife</italic> <bold>7</bold>:e26944. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.26944">10.7554/eLife.26944</ext-link></p></boxed-text><p>Gastrulation is a key embryonic event during which the three-dimensional framework of an animal is established. Indeed, it has been said that ‘it is not birth, marriage or death, but gastrulation which is truly the most important time in your life’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Slack, 1991</xref>). Generally speaking, the process of gastrulation accomplishes two goals. First, it positions the precursors of the internal organs inside the embryo and surrounds them with cells that will go on to form skin. Second, it converts an essentially spherical ball of cells into the elongated form with the defined head-to-tail axis that is found in animals as diverse as insects, worms and vertebrates. Not surprisingly, achieving these two goals involves the robust movement of cells and tissue.</p><p>After more than a century of study, well-defined maps of these tissue movements have been established for many animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Stern, 2004</xref>), and more recent work has focused on understanding how the forces responsible for tissue movement are generated and transmitted in a coordinated manner between individual cells.</p><p>A popular model for the study of gastrulation and tissue mechanics is the frog <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Keller et al., 2003</xref>). The large size of <italic>Xenopus</italic> cells makes them amenable to live imaging, and the even distribution of yolk throughout all the cells allows <italic>Xenopus</italic> tissue to survive and develop well in explant cultures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Davidson and Keller, 2007</xref>). However, the mechanisms by which the forces that move tissues are generated and directed have remained unclear. Now, in eLife, David Shook of the University of Virginia and co-workers – Eric Kasprowicz (Thomas Jefferson University Hospital), Lance Davidson (University of Pittsburgh) and Raymond Keller (Virginia) – report new insights into the generation of long-range forces during gastrulation in <italic>Xenopus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Shook et al., 2018</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Force generating 'engines' during gastrulation in <italic>Xenopus</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) During gastrulation a hollow sphere of cells (left) is transformed into an elongated embryo (right). This starts with cells on the dorsal (upper) side of the embryo rolling over a structure called the blastopore (red circle) and moving to the inside of the sphere. This reduces the size of the blastopore. Cell-autonomous convergence forces (purple) then cause the sphere to elongate, leading to the formation of the anterior–posterior axis. (<bold>B</bold>) The process by which tissue elongates along the anterior-posterior (AP) axis, and becomes narrower along the medio-lateral (ML) axis, is called convergent extension. (<bold>C</bold>) Shook et al. discovered that a process called convergent thickening – which involves the tissue becoming thicker in the direction at right angles to the convergent extension – is also important during gastrulation. (<bold>D</bold>). Sketch showing how the convergence force (y-axis) increases through gastrulation, and then plateaus (during early neurulation) before increasing again (during late neurulation).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-36662-fig1-v1"/></fig><p>Very early embryos are made up of three germ layers: the outer layer or ectoderm, the middle layer or mesoderm, and the inside layer or endoderm. During gastrulation in <italic>Xenopus</italic>, a ring of cells that later forms the mesoderm (called the presumptive mesoderm) rolls inwards over a structure called the blastopore lip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). This process is called involution. The presumptive mesoderm cells then rearrange to form a narrower and longer embryo in a process called axis elongation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Shindo, 2018</xref>). Convergent extension has long been considered to be the sole source of convergence force in embryos and has been well characterized in animals ranging from insects to amphibians, fish and mammals.</p><p>Shook et al. identified a central role for another process, called convergent thickening, in which the cells rearrange themselves in order to increase the thickness of the tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). Curiously, convergent thickening had been identified decades ago, but was previously thought to play only a relatively minor role in gastrulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Keller and Danilchik, 1988</xref>). Shook et al. found that the entire ring of presumptive mesoderm undergoes convergent thickening before involution, thus adding new layer of mechanical complexity to this long-studied process.</p><p>So how do embryos co-ordinate the processes of convergent extension and convergent thickening? The transition from convergent thickening before involution to convergent extension after involution suggests that there is a mechanical connection between these two processes that generates a driving force across the whole embryo throughout gastrulation. To explore this question Shook et al. used an experimental set-up called the 'tractor pull' to study samples of tissue taken from the presumptive mesoderm. This approach involves attaching two plastic strips to the ends of the tissue to control its position, and an optical fiber to pull the tissue; forces generated in the tissue cause the optical fiber to bend, and its deflection can be used to calculate the force.</p><p>Shook et al. found that the convergence force increased throughout gastrulation, then plateaued during a stage known as early neurulation (during which the central nervous system is formed), and then increased again during late neurulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). Since convergent extension occurs dominantly in the dorsal tissue (that is, the upper side or back of the animal), and convergent thickening lasts longer on the ventral side (the lower side or front), Shook et al. tried to unravel the origin of the behavior shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref> by changing the proportion of ventral and dorsal tissue. When just ventral tissue was studied, the second increase during late neurulation did not happen; and when just dorsal tissue was studied, there was no plateau phase. This suggests that the convergence force before involution is mostly driven by convergent thickening across the whole tissue, and that after involution convergence force results solely from convergent extension in the dorsal tissue.</p><p>Shook et al. also performed experiments in which the tractor pull set-up was used to apply forces to tissue. They found that dorsal tissues under convergent extension are capable of generating and transmitting higher forces than tissues under convergent thickening. Therefore, when the transition from thickening to extension occurs in the dorsal tissue and spreads to the ventral tissue, regions of ventral tissue that have not yet undergone thickening-to-extension transition will limit the generation and transmission of force in the medio-lateral direction.</p><p>The work of Shook et al. provides new insights into the mechanics of gastrulation, while raising new questions and invigorating old ones. For example, while the mechanisms of convergent extension are well defined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Shindo, 2018</xref>), the mechanisms that drive convergent thickening remain essentially unknown. Since convergent thickening relies on radially-directed cell movement, it is tempting to speculate that it uses similar mechanisms to other recently defined radial migration events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Sedzinski et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Szabó et al., 2016</xref>). Moreover, while planar cell polarity signaling, a conserved genetic network that controls the position of cells within a population, is known to direct convergent extension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Butler and Wallingford, 2017</xref>), its role in convergent thickening is unknown; this issue warrants further examination because the disruption of planar cell polarity in ventral tissues where convergent thickening predominates substantially disrupts gastrulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Ewald et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>Ultimately, this work is significant because gastrulation in most animals relies on the complex interplay of multiple force-generating 'engines' (such as convergent extension and convergent thickening) yet how such engines work in concert remains largely unexplored in other animals, including mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Nowotschin and Hadjantonakis, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Solnica-Krezel, 2005</xref>). The results reported by Shook et al. should motivate others to attack similarly complex processes in other animals.</p></body><back><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallingford</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Planar cell polarity in development and disease</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm.2017.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28293032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Measuring mechanical properties of embryos and embryonic tissues</article-title><source>Methods in Cell Biology</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0091-679X(07)83018-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17613319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewald</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyrot</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyszka</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallingford</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Regional requirements for Dishevelled signaling during Xenopus gastrulation</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>131</volume><fpage>6195</fpage><lpage>6209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15548584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Danilchik</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year><article-title>Regional expression, pattern and timing of convergence and extension during gastrulation of Xenopus laevis</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3197629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shook</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>How we are shaped: the biomechanics of gastrulation</article-title><source>Differentiation</source><volume>71</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1432-0436.2003.710301.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12694202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nowotschin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadjantonakis</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Cellular dynamics in the early mouse embryo: from axis formation to gastrulation</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Genetics &amp; Development</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gde.2010.05.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20566281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sedzinski</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannezo</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Biro</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallingford</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Emergence of an apical epithelial cell surface in vivo</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2015.12.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26766441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shindo</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Models of convergent extension during morphogenesis</article-title><source>Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Developmental Biology</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e293</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wdev.293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shook</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasprowicz</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Large, long range tensile forces drive convergence during <italic>Xenopus</italic> blastopore closure and body axis elongation</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e26944</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.26944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29533180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slack</surname> <given-names>JMW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><source>From Egg to Embryo</source><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/CBO9780511525322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solnica-Krezel</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Conserved patterns of cell movements during vertebrate gastrulation</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>R213</fpage><lpage>R228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2005.03.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15797016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stern</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><source>Gastrulation</source><publisher-name>CSHL Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szabó</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobo</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Omara</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McLachlan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayor</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>The molecular basis of radial intercalation during tissue spreading in early development</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2016.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27165554</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>