<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">88466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.88466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi" specific-use="version">10.7554/eLife.88466.3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Developmental Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>E3 ubiquitin ligase Deltex facilitates the expansion of Wingless gradient and antagonizes Wingless signaling through a conserved mechanism of transcriptional effector Armadillo/β-catenin degradation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-314755"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Vartika</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6642-4277</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-314758"><name><surname>Sachan</surname><given-names>Nalani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-314756"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>Bappi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-314831"><name><surname>Mutsuddi</surname><given-names>Mousumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-314753"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>Ashim</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3523-7089</contrib-id><email>amukherjee@bhu.ac.in</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04cdn2797</institution-id><institution>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Varanasi</named-content></addr-line><country>India</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/046rm7j60</institution-id><institution>Department of Integrative Biology and Physiology, University of California Los Angeles</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Los Angeles</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/005dvqh91</institution-id><institution>Department of Cell Biology, NYU Langone Medical Center</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">New York</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Roger J</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0464eyp60</institution-id><institution>University of Massachusetts Medical School</institution></institution-wrap><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Araújo</surname><given-names>Sofia J</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/021018s57</institution-id><institution>University of Barcelona</institution></institution-wrap><country>Spain</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="publication"><day>20</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>RP88466</elocation-id><history><date date-type="sent-for-review" iso-8601-date="2023-05-21"><day>21</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a preprint.</event-desc><date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2023-06-07"><day>07</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date><self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.06.06.543920"/></event><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a reviewed preprint.</event-desc><date date-type="reviewed-preprint" iso-8601-date="2023-08-03"><day>03</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date><self-uri content-type="reviewed-preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.88466.1"/></event><event><event-desc>The reviewed preprint was revised.</event-desc><date date-type="reviewed-preprint" iso-8601-date="2024-04-26"><day>26</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date><self-uri content-type="reviewed-preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.88466.2"/></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2023, Sharma et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sharma et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-88466-v1.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="figures-pdf" xlink:href="elife-88466-figures-v1.pdf"/><abstract><p>The Wnt/Wg pathway controls myriads of biological phenomena throughout the development and adult life of all organisms across the phyla. Thus, an aberrant Wnt signaling is associated with a wide range of pathologies in humans. Tight regulation of Wnt/Wg signaling is required to maintain proper cellular homeostasis. Here, we report a novel role of E3 ubiquitin ligase Deltex in Wg signaling regulation. <italic>Drosophila dx</italic> genetically interacts with <italic>wg a</italic>nd its pathway components. Furthermore, Dx LOF results in a reduced spreading of Wg while its over-expression expands the diffusion gradient of the morphogen. We attribute this change in Wg gradient to the endocytosis of Wg through Dx which directly affects the short- and long-range Wg targets. We also demonstrate the role of Dx in regulating Wg effector Armadillo where Dx down-regulates Arm through proteasomal degradation. We also showed the conservation of Dx function in the mammalian system where DTX1 is shown to bind with β-catenin and facilitates its proteolytic degradation, spotlighting a novel step that potentially modulates Wnt/Wg signaling cascade.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>Armadillo/β-catenin</kwd><kwd>deltex</kwd><kwd>E3 ubiquitin ligase</kwd><kwd>endocytosis</kwd><kwd>ubiquitination</kwd><kwd>Wnt/Wingless signaling</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd><italic>D. melanogaster</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002742</institution-id><institution>Institute of Eminence Scheme, Banaras Hindu University, India and Department of Science and Technology, Ministry of Science and Technology, India.</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CRG/2021/006975</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>Ashim</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection, and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Genetic and molecular analysis shows that Deltex modulates the Wingless gradient and counters Wingless signaling by promoting Armadillo/β-catenin degradation through a conserved regulatory mechanism.</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>publishing-route</meta-name><meta-value>prc</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Morphogens play a key role in cell-fate determination in a concentration-dependent manner, and their functions are indispensable to tissue patterning during development. These molecules elicit long-range signaling by forming a concentration gradient and cells differentiate based on these positional cues. The roles of morphogens such as Wingless (Wg), Hedgehog (Hh), and Decapentaplegic (Dpp) during the development of <italic>Drosophila</italic> appendages have been extensively studied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Cadigan and Nusse, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lecuit et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Nellen et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tabata, 2001</xref>).</p><p>Wg signaling is an evolutionarily conserved pathway and has multiple roles in the regulation of a variety of developmental processes, including cell-fate specification, cell proliferation, cell survival, and migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cadigan and Waterman, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Logan and Nusse, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">MacDonald et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Valenta et al., 2012</xref>). Any aberration in the expression of candidates in the Wg signaling cascade often leads to human diseases including cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Clevers, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Coombs et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>In the developing wing disc, Wg is secreted from the dorsal–ventral (D/V) boundary, and a gradient of Wg is formed to elicit long-range Wg signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Baena-Lopez et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Diaz-Benjumea and Cohen, 1995</xref>). Secreted Wg, consecutively induces the expression of its target Senseless (Sens) and Distal-less (Dll). High threshold Wg target gene <italic>senseless</italic> is responsible for the formation of margin sensory bristles of adult wings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Couso et al., 1994</xref>), whereas the low threshold Wg target gene <italic>distal-less</italic> is required for proper wing growth and is expressed in a graded manner, declining toward the edges of the wing pouch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Couso et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Neumann and Cohen, 1997</xref>). Wg also induces the expression of Cut by activating Notch in the D/V boundary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">de Celis and Bray, 1997</xref>).</p><p>Wg exercises its effect by regulating the transcription of the target genes in the responding cells. Armadillo (vertebrate homolog β-catenin) plays a pivotal role in the transduction of Wg signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Dierick and Bejsovec, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Städeli et al., 2006</xref>). In the absence of the Wg ligand, a protein complex comprising of APC (Adenomatous polyposis coli), Axin, GSK3-β (Shaggy), and Casein Kinase-I (Cki) mediates Armadillo (Arm) phosphorylation, and ubiquitination, followed by its degradation via the proteasome pathway. On the contrary, binding of the ligand Wg to its receptor Frizzled (Fz), at the cell surface, initiates a signaling cascade that inhibits the function of the destruction complex via adaptor protein Dishevelled (Dsh), leading to the stabilization of Arm. Arm then translocates to the nucleus thereby activating the transcription of the downstream target genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mosimann et al., 2009</xref>). In canonical Wg signaling, Arm plays a dual role. The cytosolic Arm, as mentioned, is used for the transduction of the Wg signals, whereas the Arm localized at the adherens junctions together with α-catenin and cadherin homologs is required for cell adhesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Peifer et al., 1993</xref>).</p><p>We have earlier reported that <italic>deltex</italic> (<italic>dx</italic>), a known Notch signaling regulator, modulates Decapentaplegic morphogen gradient formation and affects Dpp signaling in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sharma et al., 2022</xref>). Here, in the present study, we report that <italic>deltex</italic> genetically interacts with the genes that encode Wg pathway components during wing development. Immuno-cytochemical analysis revealed that Dx facilitates the spreading of the morphogen, thereby directly affecting the expression of the short- and long-range target genes, Senseless and Vestigial. This change in the Wg gradient is attributed to the role of Dx in Wg trafficking. Here, we speculate that Dx, like in the case of Dpp and Notch, aids in the vesicular trafficking of Wg to facilitate its gradient formation. Furthermore, Dx was also seen to reduce the expression of the Wg effector Arm through proteasomal degradation. We also investigate the conservation of Dx function in β-catenin stability and degradation in cultured human cells. Here, we show that human DTX1 binds with β-catenin and facilitates its degradation. This study thus presents a whole new avenue of Dx function in the regulation of Wg signaling.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title><italic>dx</italic> genetically interacts with Wg pathway components</title><p>Wg controls the growth and patterning of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing and aberrant Wg signaling interferes with normal wing development. In order to ascertain the role of <italic>dx</italic> in Wg signaling, first, we tried to check if <italic>dx</italic> genetically interacts with <italic>wg</italic> alleles. It is interesting to note that both the wg loss-of-function alleles tested (<italic>wg<sup>CX3</sup></italic> and <italic>wg<sup>CX4</sup></italic>) showed lethality in homozygous condition; however, in heterozygous condition, they do not exhibit any phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B1, C1</xref>). The two mutant alleles of <italic>dx</italic> (a null allele <italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic> and a loss-of-function allele <italic>dx</italic>) show wing vein thickening phenotype in hemizygous condition, however, <italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic> and <italic>dx</italic> heterozygote female flies exhibit normal wings. When the loss-of-function allele of <italic>wg</italic> (<italic>wg<sup>CX3</sup></italic> and <italic>wg<sup>CX4</sup></italic>) was brought in heterozygous condition with either <italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic> or <italic>dx</italic> mutant alleles, they showed wings that were indistinguishable from the wild type (data not shown). However, when the dosage of <italic>wg</italic> was reduced in <italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic> and <italic>dx</italic> mutant alleles in the hemizygous background, an increased wing vein thickening phenotype was observed which is indicative of an enhanced phenotype relative to controls (<italic>n</italic> = 100). Moreover, an appreciable number of flies show notching in the wing margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B1–C3</xref>), suggesting that a complete absence of <italic>dx</italic> creates a sensitized background, which is more responsive to a lower dosage of <italic>wg</italic> during wing development. Furthermore, the expression of Cut, a downstream target of Wg signaling activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Katanaev et al., 2008</xref>) at the D/V boundary of the wing disc, was found to be reduced in wing discs from these larvae. Third instar larval wing discs displayed an interrupted Cut expression at the intersection of A/P and D/V boundary from individuals carrying heterozygous <italic>wg</italic> loss-of-function allele in <italic>dx</italic> hemizygous null background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1H1–H4</xref>). These results clearly indicate that <italic>dx</italic> may play a role in <italic>Drosophila</italic> Wg signaling activity.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title><italic>dx</italic> genetically interacts with Wg pathway components.</title><p>(<bold>A1–F3</bold>) Representative wings from males with the indicated genotypes. <italic>dx</italic> (<bold>A2</bold>) and <italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic> (<bold>A3</bold>) hemizygote show extra vein material at the distal end of the wing compared to wild-type flies (<italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic>) (<bold>A1</bold>). (<bold>B2, B3, C2, C3</bold>) Both the <italic>dx</italic> allele show an enhancement of wing vein thickening along with wing notching in hemizygous combination with different alleles of wg (<italic>wg<sup>CX3</sup></italic> and <italic>wg<sup>CX4</sup></italic>) heterozygotes. (<bold>D2, D3, E2</bold>, <bold>E3</bold>) Different alleles of <italic>fz</italic> (<italic>fz<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic>fz<sup>MB07478</sup></italic>) in trans-heterozygous conditions show enhanced vein thickening and wing nicking phenotype with <italic>dx</italic> hemizygotes. (<bold>F2, F3</bold>) <italic>dx</italic> alleles show strong genetic interaction with the Wg target gene <italic>sens,</italic> where a loss-of-function allele of sens (<italic>sens<sup>E58</sup></italic>) shows wing nicking phenotype in flies that are homozygous for <italic>dx</italic> alleles. (<bold>G</bold>) Graph showing the frequency of wing notching phenotypes observed in indicated genetic combinations (<italic>n</italic> = 100). (<bold>H1–H4</bold>) Representative image of Cut in wing imaginal disc in different genetic combinations. (<bold>H2</bold>) The expression of Cut in <italic>wg<sup>CX4</sup></italic> heterozygote is similar to the wild-type Cut expression (<bold>H1</bold>). (<bold>H3</bold>) <italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic> hemizygotes show a reduction in Cut expression in the dorsal–ventral (D/V) boundary of the wing disc. (<bold>H4</bold>) Wing disc from <italic>dx<sup>152</sup>/Y; wg<sup>CX4</sup>/+</italic> genotype shows a further reduction in Cut expression when compared to <italic>dx<sup>152</sup>/Y</italic> wing discs. Images in H1–H4 are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Scale bar: A1–F3: 200 µm. H1–H4: 50 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig1-v1.tif"/></fig><p>Furthermore, we tried to elucidate if the receptor of <italic>wg</italic>, <italic>frizzled</italic> (<italic>fz</italic>), does exhibit any interaction with <italic>dx</italic>. When the hypomorphic allele of <italic>fz</italic> (<italic>fz<sup>1</sup></italic>), was brought in heterozygous condition with <italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic> null<italic>,</italic> the male flies displayed wing notching phenotype in addition to wing vein thickening (<italic>n</italic> = 100) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D1–E3</xref>). <italic>senseless</italic> (<italic>sens</italic>), a short-range target of Wg signaling also displayed a strong genetic interaction with <italic>dx</italic>. A loss-of-function allele of <italic>sens (sens<sup>E58</sup></italic>) is recessive lethal in homozygous condition; however, in heterozygous condition, they do not display any phenotype. On the contrary, on reducing the dosage of <italic>sens</italic> in <italic>dx</italic> null and <italic>dx</italic> loss-of-function allele in hemizygous condition, an enhanced wing phenotype with marked serration in the wing margin was observed (<italic>n</italic> = 100) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F1–F3</xref>). These results displayed a strong genetic interaction between <italic>dx</italic> and Wg pathway components, suggesting that Dx may have functional implications in <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing development.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Loss of <italic>dx</italic> reduces Wg signaling</title><p>To better understand the role of <italic>dx</italic> in Wg signaling regulation, we studied the expression of Wg and its target genes in <italic>dx</italic> null wing discs. It was found that in <italic>dx</italic> null third instar larval wing discs, the gradient of Wg at the D/V boundary was shortened. High-magnification pictures revealed a significant decrease in the amount of Wg emanating from the Wg-producing cells at the D/V boundary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A2</xref>). Thus, Dx is required for the proper Wg gradient formation, as the range of Wg expression and the number of Wg puncta was significantly reduced in <italic>dx</italic> null condition. Similar interruption in Wg gradient was also observed by Hori et al., where <italic>dx<sup>24</sup></italic> allele showed a reduction in Wg expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hori et al., 2004</xref>), however, the study focuses on the indispensable role of <italic>dx</italic> in Notch signaling.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Loss of Dx reduces Wg signaling gradient and target gene expression.</title><p>(<bold>A2</bold>) <italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic> wing disc shows a narrow Wg expression gradient compared to wild-type third instar larval wing discs (<bold>A1</bold>). (<bold>A1”, A2”</bold>) show Wg-lacZ staining in the mentioned genotype. (<bold>B2</bold>) A constricted expression of Sens was observed in dx null discs (<italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic>) (marked by arrowhead) compared to the control wild-type wing imaginal discs (<bold>B1</bold>). (<bold>C1</bold>) The expression of Vg in the wild-type disc. (<bold>C2</bold>) dx null discs showed a broadened Vg expression, marked by arrowheads. (<bold>A1’–C2’</bold>) Show the average fluorescence intensity of images in A1–C2. (<bold>D1, D2</bold>) Expression of the RNAi targeting Dx by <italic>en-GAL4</italic> or <italic>ap-GAL4</italic> results in morphological aberrations in the expressing regions. (<bold>E</bold>) Graph showing the percentage of flies showing respective phenotypes in the mentioned genotype (<italic>n</italic> = 100). Images in A–C are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Scale bar: A1–A2: 10 µm. B1–C2: 50 µm. D1, D2: 200 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig2-v1.tif"/></fig><p>We also analyzed the expression of Wg target genes in <italic>dx</italic> null discs. The domain of Vestigial, the long-range target of Wg was found to be significantly broadened in <italic>dx</italic> null discs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C2</xref>). This is in contrast to the reported partial suppression of Vg expression in <italic>ptc-GAL4</italic> expressed Dx dominant negative discs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hori et al., 2004</xref>). Moreover, in another set of experiments, we found that the expression of the short-range target Sens showed slight deformity in the expression pattern with a constricted expression at the D/V boundary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B2</xref>).</p><p>Expression of the short-range target such as Sens needs a higher threshold of Wg morphogen gradient than the long-range target like Vestigial which often requires a less concentrated Wg gradient. Thus, our results show that a proper Wg gradient is not formed in the absence of Dx, and this supports that Dx may have a profound role in regulating Wg signaling through its gradient formation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Dx regulates Wg signaling</title><p>Based on the loss-of-function genetic interaction studies between <italic>dx</italic> and <italic>wg</italic> mutant alleles that suggest the role of Dx in Wg signaling, we further tried to investigate the gain-of-function effect of Dx on Wg signaling activity. For this, <italic>UAS-GAL4</italic> binary system was exploited. We over-expressed FLAG-tagged <italic>UAS-Dx</italic>, with <italic>engrailed-GAL4</italic> (<italic>en-GAL4</italic>) driver strain<italic>,</italic> that drives the expression of the transgene in the posterior compartment of the wing imaginal disc, and in turn in the adult wing. Over-expression of <italic>Dx</italic> with <italic>en-GAL4</italic> shows pupal lethality at 25°C, however, at 18°C, the flies emerge with massive morphological defects. The wing displayed blisters along with vein loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplements 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">A2</xref>). Besides, Dx over-expression with <italic>apterous-GAL4</italic> (<italic>ap-GAL4</italic>) also resulted in abnormal wings that failed to appose properly and show large blisters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1–A3</xref>), and since Wg signaling modulates the expression of cell adhesion molecules in <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing imaginal disc cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bienz, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Wodarz et al., 2006</xref>) such phenotypes are often associated with impaired Wg signaling.</p><p>To check if Dx is involved in Wg pathway regulation in other developmental contexts, we over-expressed Dx in the primordia of the dorsal thorax using <italic>ap-GAL4</italic> and <italic>pnr- GAL4</italic>. Dx over-expression in the thorax leads to reduced and disoriented macrochaetae and reduction in scutellar bristles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplements 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">B2–B3</xref>). A reduced tarsal segment along the proximodistal axis and dorsoventral shift of the sex combs was observed when Dx was over-expressed with <italic>distal-less-GAL4</italic> (<italic>dll-GAL4</italic>) in the leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplements 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">C2</xref>). All these phenotypes are characteristics of reduced Wg signaling as also shown earlier for ectopic expression of another gene required for epithelial planar polarity, <italic>nemo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Zeng and Verheyen, 2004</xref>). Dx shows a similar phenotype when over-expressed in flies suggesting that like <italic>nemo</italic>, Dx may antagonize the Wg signaling activity.</p><p>To further test whether Dx affects the Wg signaling output we tried to analyze the expression of the Wg target genes in the wing imaginal discs of the third instar larvae. Wg activates the expression of the proneural gene <italic>senseless</italic> (<italic>sens</italic>) in the sensory organ precursor, which later develops into bristles of the adult wing margin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Blair, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Couso et al., 1994</xref>). The expression of Senseless, a canonical target normally activated by high Wg levels in two discrete stripes at the D/V boundary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Nolo et al., 2000</xref>) was found to be significantly reduced in the posterior compartment where Dx was over-expressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A2</xref>). It is known that Wg can also indirectly induce the expression of Cut. A positive feedback loop between Wg expressing cells along the D/V boundary and Serrate and Delta expressing cells in adjacent cells maintains the Notch signaling activity along the D/V boundary, which consecutively induces the expression of Cut (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">de Celis and Bray, 1997</xref>). Similar to Sens, we found that the expression of Cut was also drastically abolished upon Dx over-expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B2</xref>). Moreover, to the contrary, the expression of Vestigial (Vg), which is activated in response to low ligand concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Neumann and Cohen, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Zecca et al., 1996</xref>) was found to be expanded in the posterior domain of the wing imaginal disc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C2</xref>), indicating that Dx reduces the Wg gradient. These results strongly suggest that Dx modulates Wg signaling output.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>With two supplements<bold>:</bold> Dx modulates the expression of the Wg target genes.</title><p>(<bold>A1–A3</bold>) Over-expression of Dx using posterior domain-specific <italic>en-GAL4</italic> results in a complete loss of Senseless (<bold>A2</bold>). Third instar larval wing discs of the indicated genotypes were immunostained to detect FLAG (green) and Senseless (red). (<bold>B1–B3</bold>) A reduction in expression of Cut was observed in the posterior domain of the wing disc upon Dx over-expression with <italic>en-GAL4</italic>. (<bold>C1–C3</bold>) Expression of Vestigial (Vg), on the contrary, was found to be expanded in the posterior compartment. Arrowheads indicate the expansion of Vg expression close to the anterior–posterior (A/P) boundary of the wing imaginal disc (<bold>C2</bold>). (<bold>D1–E3</bold>) Over-expression of caspase inhibitor p35 together with Dx does not show any rescue in the expression of Senseless (<bold>D2</bold>) and Cut (<bold>E2</bold>) suggesting the event is independent of apoptosis. The white line marks the boundary of FLAG expression. Images in A–E are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Scale bar: A1–E3: 50 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig3-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Ectopic Dx mimics Wg loss-of-function phenotype.</title><p>(<bold>A1</bold>) Representative image of wild-type adult wing. Over-expression of Deltex (Dx) in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing by <italic>en-GAL4</italic> (<bold>A2</bold>) or <italic>ap-GAL4</italic> (<bold>A3</bold>) shows a smaller wing with severe morphological defects. (<bold>B1</bold>) A wild-type notum. (<bold>B2</bold>) Dx expression with <italic>ap-GAL4</italic> shows the loss of macrochaetae on the notum. Loss of scutellar bristles was also noted. (<bold>B3</bold>) Dx expression with <italic>pnr-GAL4</italic> shows similar defects in the notum region with a marked reduction in the macrochaetae and scutellar bristles. (<bold>C2</bold>) A reduced tarsal segment and dorsal–ventral shift of the sex combs were observed upon Dx over-expression with <italic>distal-less GAL4</italic>. (<bold>D</bold>) Graph in D represents the percentage of reduction in tarsal segments in Dx over-expressed flies with <italic>dll-GAL4</italic> compared to wild-type flies. ****p &lt; 0.0001; unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test. Scale bar: A1–C2: 200 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig3-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Dx-mediated Wg regulation is independent of Notch.</title><p>(<bold>A1–A4</bold>) Notch target Deadpan (Dpn) remains unaltered upon Dx over-expression. Over-expression of Dx by posterior domain-specific <italic>en-GAL4</italic> does not cause any appreciable change in the expression of Notch target Deadpan. (<bold>B1–B4</bold>) <italic>en-GAL4</italic> driven expression of <italic>UAS-FLAG-Dx</italic> results in a punctate Notch response element (NRE) expression, marked by GFP. Images in A and B are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6).Scale bar: A1–B4: 50 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig3-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Also, in our earlier reports, we demonstrated the role of Dx in inflicting apoptosis. Dx synergizes with JNK (c-Jun N-terminal Kinase) pathway ligand Eiger and triggers caspase-dependent cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Dutta et al., 2018</xref>). Similar synergistic action of Dx was also reported with TRAF6 where the association triggers JNK activation in an Eiger-independent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Sharma et al., 2021a</xref>). Thus, we tried to dissect if the loss of these markers (Sens and Cut) is due to cell death. We inhibited apoptosis with caspase inhibitor protein p35 in Dx over-expression background and no rescue in the level of Sens and Cut expression was observed in the posterior compartment of the wing disc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D1–E4</xref>) suggesting the loss of Sens and Cut is independent of cell death.</p><p>It is worth mentioning here that similar to our findings, the expression of Sens was found to be down-regulated when Reggie-1, a component of the membrane micro-domain was up-regulated. The reduction in Sens and Cut expression, in their studies, was attributed to an enhanced spreading of the morphogen, Wg (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Katanaev et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p><italic>Drosophila</italic> Dx interacts with the ankyrin-rich repeats of the Notch intracellular domain and regulates Notch signaling positively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Matsuno et al., 1995</xref>). Moreover, negative regulation of Dx in association with non-visual β-arrestin, Kurtz was reported earlier, where polyubiquitination-mediated degradation of Notch by Dx was attributed to this loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Mukherjee et al., 2005</xref>). A similar reduction of Notch and its targets was reported lately when Dx synergistically interacts with TRAF6 and Hrp48 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Dutta et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mishra et al., 2014</xref>). Human Deltex (DTX1) was also shown to regulate NOTCH1/HES1 signaling negatively in osteosarcoma cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Zhang et al., 2010</xref>). It was reported earlier that in D/V boundary of the wing disc, the regulation of Wg is Notch dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Neumann and Cohen, 1996</xref>), we tried to elucidate if the regulation of Wg via Dx is through Notch. Thus, we examined the status of Deadpan (Dpn) and NRE (Notch response element), a direct target of Notch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Zacharioudaki and Bray, 2014</xref>). In contrast to reduced levels of Sens and Cut, the expression of Dpn was found to remain unaltered in Dx over-expressed conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2A1–A4</xref>), suggesting that Dx can possibly regulate the two signaling cascades, viz. Notch and Wg independent of each other. Furthermore, we also checked the status of the Notch response element (NRE-GFP) in Dx over-expression background and found a punctate NRE expression in the posterior domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2B1–B4</xref>). The role of Dx in Notch regulation is evident however if Dx regulates Wg through Notch or if the two events are independent is still a crucial aspect to investigate. Our results however indicate an independent role of Dx in Wg signaling regulation. We however do not rule out the alternate possibility of Wg regulation through Dx via Notch.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Over-expression of Dx expands the Wg diffusion gradient</title><p>In the third instar wild-type wing discs, Wg is secreted from the producing cells at the D/V boundary, which diffuses on either side to form a concentration gradient. Over-expression of Dx, by the A/P boundary-specific <italic>ptc-GAL4</italic>, results in an erosion of the Wg gradient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A2 and B2</xref>). Wg expression can be visualized as spreading far into the disc from the site of production. A high-magnification picture further revealed far-spreading punctate Wg expression more significantly in the ventral compartment. It is interesting to note that the number of Wg puncta and their apparent size is also significantly increased when Dx was over-expressed using <italic>ptc-GAL4</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hori et al., 2004</xref>). Similar diffusion of Wg gradient was also observed when Dx was over-expressed with posterior domain-specific <italic>en-GAL4</italic> driver (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Over-expression of Dx expands the Wg diffusion gradient.</title><p>(<bold>A1–B4</bold>) Over-expression of Dx by anterior–posterior (A/P) domain-specific <italic>ptc-GAL4</italic> results in the broadening of the Wg diffusion domain (<bold>A2</bold>). Grayscale images are for better contrast (<bold>A3</bold>). (<bold>B2</bold>) High-magnification picture shows increased Wg puncta at the A/P–dorsal–ventral (D/V) junction with more significant expression in the ventral portion of the disc (marked by arrowhead) (<bold>B2, B3</bold>). The white line marks the Ptc domain, respectively. (<bold>C1–C3</bold>) Dx over-expression with <italic>en-GAL4</italic> results in a diffused Wg expression in the posterior domain of the wing disc. (<bold>D1–D3</bold>) A marked increase in extracellular Wg (eWg) was observed upon Dx over-expression with <italic>en-GAL4</italic>. (<bold>E3</bold>) Representative image of wild-type Wg expression. Images in A–D are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Scale bar: A1–A4, C1–D3, and E: 50 µm. B1–B4: 10 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig4-v1.tif"/></fig><p>We also observed a significant increase in the extracellular Wg expression upon Dx over-expression further corroborating our initial results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D2</xref>). Earlier it was shown that Swim (Secreted Wg interacting molecule) promotes long-range Wg signaling by maintaining Wg solubility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mulligan et al., 2012</xref>). The report postulates that Swim reduction results in an increase in extracellular Wg which consequently increases the expression of long range Wg target, Dll (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mulligan et al., 2012</xref>). We have observed a very similar phenotype with another long range Wg target, Vg in increased Dx expression condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C2</xref>). Here, we do not rule out the possibility that Dx potentially aids in Wg mobilization from the adherens junction. Several models from studies in <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryonic epidermis and wing disc have been put forward to explain Wg movement across the cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Cadigan, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Tabata and Takei, 2004</xref>). Our result indicates that Dx facilitates Wg spreading which flattens its gradient. This, in turn, results in the reduction of the short-range Wg targets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A1–A3</xref>), which often require high levels of Wg. On the contrary, the long-range Wg target showed an expansion in their expression domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C1–C3</xref>), suggesting that Dx affects the Wg gradient formation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Dx-mediated Wg signaling is regulated by endocytosis</title><p>Extensive evidence suggests that signaling and endocytosis are intricately linked. Classically, endocytosis has been thought to reduce the number of accessible receptors, either through its sequestration in the endosomal vesicles or degradation in lysosomes, which consecutively down-regulates the signaling. However, some reports support the notion that endocytosis can also positively regulate the signaling cascade, its initiation, and propagation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Hupalowska and Miaczynska, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Seto and Bellen, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Different mechanisms have been suggested for the role of endocytosis in various signaling cascades. Notch is continuously internalized into early endosomes and followed by its internalization, Notch is sorted to other endocytic compartments including multivesicular bodies/late endosomes, and lysosomes, or recycling endosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Fortini and Bilder, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sachan et al., 2023</xref>). Thus, this step helps to maintain a quantitative as well as a qualitative pool of Notch. Once endocytosed, Notch follows a vesicular trafficking pathway that determines its final fate. In the canonical pathway, Notch gets internalized after binding to its ligand. However, during the non-canonical pathway, Notch can be internalized in the absence of ligand interaction. Once internalized, the Notch protein faces almost the same pathway that begins with its incorporation into the early endosomal vesicles. From here, it is either recycled back to the cell membrane, or it becomes a part of late endosomal vesicles/mature endosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Fortini and Bilder, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Vaccari et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Wilkin et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Yamada et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>In Notch trafficking and endocytosis, Dx plays a key role. Dx facilitates the trafficking of Notch receptors from the cell membrane into the early and then to the late endosomal vesicles in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hori et al., 2004</xref>). It was observed that Dx, directly or indirectly, increased the half-life of these accumulated Notch proteins in the endosomal vesicles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hori et al., 2004</xref>). If the transport of Notch into the late endosome was blocked, it hampered Dx-mediated Notch signal activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hori et al., 2004</xref>). Further study, using a similar approach, showed that Dx genetically interacts with the components of HOPS and AP-3 endocytic complexes that, successively, have a significant influence on Notch signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Wilkin et al., 2008</xref>). Dx has also been shown to play a critical role in Dpp endocytosis and trafficking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sharma et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>Like Notch and Dpp, evidence supporting Wg endocytosis has been reported earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Seto and Bellen, 2006</xref>). Wg is found to co-localize with Rab5 and Rab7 in the early and late endosomes, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Marois et al., 2006</xref>). We also observed a significant co-localization of Wg with Dx in Rab5-positive vesicles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A1–A4</xref>). Rab5 is a small GTPase that is required for endosome fusion to form early endosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Clague and Urbé, 2001</xref>). Impaired endocytosis affects Wg trafficking and in turn the signaling. Expression of a Dominant negative form of Rab5 (Rab5<sup>S43N</sup>) blocks the early steps of endocytosis, including internalization and early-endosome fusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Entchev et al., 2000</xref>), and significantly affects the Wg signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Seto and Bellen, 2006</xref>). A more punctate Wg expression was observed when the endocytosis is blocked by over-expressing a GDP-bound Rab5 (Rab5DN or Rab5<sup>S43N</sup>) with a D/V boundary-specific <italic>C96-GAL4</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C1</xref>). A further reduction in Wg puncta was observed when Dx was over-expressed in the same background, suggesting the role of Dx in Wg trafficking (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Dx-mediated Wg signaling is regulated by endocytosis.</title><p>(<bold>A1–A5</bold>) Dx (blue) co-localizes with Rab5 (green) and Wg (red) in the same subcellular compartment. The arrows mark the co-localized spots. (<bold>A5</bold>) High-magnification image of (<bold>A4</bold>). (<bold>C1</bold>) Over-expression of a Dominant Negative Rab5 with <italic>C96-Gal4</italic> inhibits the endosomal fusion at the dorsal–ventral (D/V) boundary, enhancing the Wg diffusion gradient. (<bold>C2</bold>) Co-expression of Dx with Rab5DN shows a further enhancement of the Rab5DN phenotype in the Wg diffusion gradient. (<bold>B1, B2</bold>) Representative adult wing image of the mentioned genotype (<italic>n</italic> = 50). (<bold>B1</bold>) Over-expression of Rab5DN results in wing tissue loss consistent with decreased Wg signaling. (<bold>B2</bold>) A further reduction in wing size is observed upon co-expressing Dx with Rab5DN. (<bold>B3</bold>) The graph shows the wing area percentage of the mentioned genotypes (<italic>n</italic> = 6). ****p &lt; 0.0001; unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test. (<bold>E1, F1</bold>) Over-expression of Rab7 with <italic>C96-GAL4</italic> renders no significant change in Wg expression. (<bold>E2, F2</bold>) Rab7 when co-expressed with Dx enhances the Wg spreading. (<bold>D1, D2</bold>) Representative adult wing of defined genotype (<italic>n</italic> = 50). Note the notching phenotype in the wing upon over-expression of FLAG-Dx together with UAS-Rab7 (<bold>D2</bold>). (<bold>D3</bold>) The graph shows the percentage of flies showing notching phenotype (<italic>n</italic> = 100). (<bold>G, H</bold>) Representative adult wing image of <italic>UAS-FLAG-Dx</italic> over-expressed with <italic>C96-GAL4</italic>. (<bold>H</bold>) Wg expression in <italic>UAS-FLAG-Dx&gt;C96</italic> GAL4 discs. Images in C and E are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Scale bar: A1–A4: 5 µm. C1, C2 and E1, E2: 50 µm. F1, F2: 20 µm. B1, B2 and D1, D2: 200 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig5-v1.tif"/></fig><p>Additionally, <italic>C96-GAL4</italic>-mediated over-expression of Rab5DN, results in a loss of wing tissue similar to the loss of Wg, implying the role of endocytosis in Wg signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Baker, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Couso et al., 1994</xref>). This loss of wing tissue was further aggravated when Dx was over-expressed along with Rab5DN suggesting a more diffused Wg expression at the D/V boundary, which further limits the threshold required to form the adult wing margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B2</xref>). This synergism brings about 90% lethality, further implicating the role of Dx in Wg regulation via endocytosis. In addition to Rab5, the late endosome protein Rab7, when over-expressed with Dx, showed a punctate Wg expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F2</xref>), suggesting an important role of Dx in Wg trafficking. Rab7 targets the endocytic cargo from the early endosome to the late endosome and then to the lysosome for degradation. Over-expression of a wild-type Rab7 increases trafficking toward the lysosome. This is due to enhanced vesicle fusion, resulting in enlarged late endosomal structures, prone to lysosomal degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Entchev et al., 2000</xref>). When UAS-Rab7 was co-expressed with Dx, a more punctate Wg expression was observed evincing that Dx might facilitate the functions of Rab7. Our study suggests the involvement of Dx in Wg endocytosis, however, further analysis is required to unravel the detailed mechanistic aspect in Wg endocytosis and trafficking via Dx.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Dx modulates Wg signal transduction</title><p>Armadillo, the <italic>Drosophila</italic> ortholog of mammalian β-catenin has a dual function. It acts as a nuclear transcription factor that transduces the Wg signaling on one hand and maintains the cell integrity on the other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Coombs et al., 2008</xref>). Within the wing disc, Arm concentrates apically where it binds with the transmembrane cadherins to build up the adherens junction that connects the actin filaments across polarized epithelial cells, thereby acting as a bridge between E-cadherin and the actin cytoskeleton. To investigate the functional aspect of Dx in Wg signaling regulation, we analyzed the status of this key effector of Wg signaling. Upon Dx over-expression with <italic>en-GAL4,</italic> the accumulation of Arm was strongly reduced in the whole posterior compartment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A2</xref>), and most evidently at the D/V boundary. A similar reduction in Arm expression was observed in the eye disc in the GMR domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1B1</xref>) indicating that Dx might disrupt the cell-fate specification in the eye tissue. Moreover, confocal Z stack analysis revealed a reduction of apical Arm accumulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B2</xref>). The reduction of the apical Arm is consistent with the decline of cell adhesion, leading to the structural reorganization of the cytoskeleton (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Wodarz et al., 2006</xref>). Higher magnification pictures further revealed a disorganized cell morphology upon Dx over-expression. Moreover, it was also observed that Dx co-localizes with endogenous Arm (marked by arrow) and is in the same vesicle upon Dx over-expression, suggesting that the two proteins might physically interact (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C3, C4</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>With 2 supplements: Dx modulates Wg Signal transduction.</title><p>(<bold>A1–C4</bold>) Dx over-expression with <italic>en-GAL4</italic> in the wing imaginal disc results in a reduction of endogenous Armadillo throughout the disc with a more pronounced reduction at the dorsal–ventral (D/V) boundary. (<bold>B1–B3</bold>) Confocal Z stack Intensity profiling shows a reduced Arm level in the posterior compartment of the disc. (<bold>C1–C4</bold>) A higher magnification picture shows a significant overlap between FLAG-tagged Dx and endogenous Arm (marked by arrowhead). Note the reduction of Arm in the posterior compartment of the disc. (<bold>C5</bold>) Graph shows the average Arm fluorescence intensity (a.u., arbitrary units) (<italic>n</italic> = 7). ****p &lt; 0.0001; unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test. (<bold>D1–D3</bold>) Show the average FLAG and Arm fluorescence intensity profiles for the representative wing disc. (<bold>E1–E6</bold>) Representative adult wing of defined genotype (<italic>n</italic> = 50). (<bold>E1, E2</bold>) Over-expression of the activated form of Arm (Arm<sup>S10</sup>) with <italic>C96-GAL4</italic> shows ectopic hairs more significantly along the wing margin of the adult wing. (<bold>E3, E4</bold>) Dx over-expression in the wing shows no ectopic hairs. (<bold>E5, E6</bold>) Co-expression of Dx with ArmS<sup>10</sup> results in the suppression of Arm gain-of-function effect and a relative reduction in the number of ectopic bristles was observed. (<bold>E7</bold>) Graph shows the number of bristles in each combination. ****p &lt; 0.0001; one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA)/Turkey’s multiple comparisons test. (<bold>F1–F6</bold>) Representative adult eye and eye imprint of defined genotype (<italic>n</italic> = 10). (<bold>F1, F2</bold>) GMR-specific expression of an activated form of Arm produces a severely reduced eye with diffused ommatidia. (<bold>F3, F4</bold>) Dx over-expression renders no significant phenotype. (<bold>F5, F6</bold>) Arm over-expression phenotype gets dramatically suppressed when Dx was co-expressed in the same background. (<bold>F7</bold>) Graph represents the phenotypic score of the eye size (<italic>n</italic> = 6). ****p ,0.0001; one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA)/Turkey’s multiple comparisontest. Images in A–C are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Scale bar: A1–A3: 10 µm. C1–C3: 2 µm. E1–E6 and F1–F6: 200 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig6-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Dx modulates Arm expression in the eye tissue.</title><p>A diffused expression of Arm was observed in the eye disc upon Dx over-expression in the <italic>GMR</italic> domain (<bold>B1-B3</bold>) in contrast to a wild-type Arm expression (<bold>A1-A3</bold>). Images in A and B are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Scale bar: A1–B3: 2 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig6-figsupp1-v1.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Dx might facilitate the cytoplasmic retention of Arm.</title><p>(<bold>A1–A10</bold>) High-magnification picture of Arm in the anterior (A) and posterior (P) domain of the wing imaginal disc. Note (<bold>A8–A10</bold>) showed a significant co-localization of Arm with nucleus stained with DAPI [4’,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (blue)], (<bold>A5–A7</bold>) however showed no such co-localization, suggesting that Dx might facilitate the nuclear retention of Arm. Images are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Scale bar: A1–A4: 2 µm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig6-figsupp2-v1.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Furthermore, upon over-expressing activated Arm (Arm<sup>s10</sup>), with the wing margin-specific <italic>C96-GAL4</italic>, ectopic hairs were observed throughout the wings, and this is more evident near the wing margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E1, E2</xref>). This is reported ro be a Wg gain-of-function phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Vuong et al., 2018</xref>). The ectopic hair phenotype, however, was significantly reduced when Dx was over-expressed in the same background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E5, E6</xref>), corroborating with our immuno-staining results. A similar reduction in Arm gain-of-function phenotype was observed when the activated Arm was over-expressed together with Dx in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> eye. Over-expressing Arm<sup>s10</sup> with eye-specific <italic>GMR-GAL4</italic> renders flies with reduced eye size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Freeman and Bienz, 2001</xref>) and severely diffused ommatidia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6F1, F2</xref>). Moreover, upon over-expressing Dx in the same background, the Arm gain-of-function phenotype was found to be suppressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6F5, F6</xref>).</p><p>Interestingly, it was also observed that Dx co-localizes with endogenous Arm and is in the same vesicle upon Dx over-expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C3</xref>). Since Arm accumulation was reduced in the cytoplasm of Dx over-expressed cells in the disc, we also checked if there is any alteration of nuclear localization of Arm in these cells. To investigate this, we analyzed the nuclear versus cytoplasmic localization of Arm protein in the wing imaginal disc. High-magnification pictures gave us a hint of Arm being exclusively in cytoplasm in Dx over-expressed condition. This inference was made since no localization of Arm in the nucleus (DAPI-stained area) was observed in the posterior compartment of the wing disc, though the anterior compartment showed significant localization of Arm with DAPI (marked by arrow) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2A1–A10</xref>). The small size of cells in the wing disc made it difficult to draw a definite result and a more robust and facilitated assay system is required to visualize the changes i.e. cytoplasm versus nuclear localization.</p><p>Since Dx possesses an E3 ubiquitin ligase activity, so this down-regulation can be a consequence of ubiquitination-mediated degradation of Arm which needs to be determined.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Dx degrades Armadillo by the proteasome-mediated mechanism</title><p>The stabilization of Arm/β-catenin is critical in Wg/Wnt signaling regulation and the ubiquitination-dependent proteasomal degradation is considered to be a major mechanism for controlling its stability. β-TrCP, Jade1, casitas B-lineage lymphoma (c-Cbl), and SIAH1 [the human homolog of <italic>Drosophila</italic> seven in absentia (sina)], are known E3 ligases that mediate β-catenin ubiquitination in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Spiegelman et al., 2000</xref>). Moreover, β-catenin ubiquitination in the nucleus is mediated by c-Cbl and TRIM33 (tripartite-motif containing protein 33). C-Cbl is a RING finger E3 ubiquitin ligase that binds to the non-phosphorylated nuclear β-catenin via the armadillo repeat region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chitalia et al., 2013</xref>). Though the ubiquitination of β-catenin is not always linked with its degradation and there are reports where E3 ubiquitin ligases enhanced the stability of β-catenin by ubiquitinating through Lys-29- or Lys-11-linked ubiquitin chains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Hay-Koren et al., 2011</xref>). Thus, to elucidate if Arm down-regulation through Dx is a ubiquitination-dependent phenomenon, first, we tried to test if Dx physically interacts with Arm. Co-immunoprecipitation experiments using FLAG-tagged Dx revealed that FLAG-tagged Dx pulled down Arm when co-expressed in eye tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). Likewise, FLAG-tagged Dx was coimmunoprecipitated with Arm using an anti-Arm antibody when the two proteins were expressed together (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Dx degrades Arm by a proteasome-mediated mechanism.</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Co-immunoprecipitation of FLAG-Dx and Arm. Co-immunoprecipitation was carried out with lysate over-expressing Arm and FLAG-Dx using <italic>GMAR-GAL4</italic>. + symbol indicates the presence of lysate and the − symbol shows the absence of lysate. FLAG-Dx immunoprecipitated Arm was detected by anti-Arm antibody (<bold>A</bold>). Arm immunoprecipitated FLAG-Dx was detected by FLAG antibody. (<bold>C1–C3</bold>) Dx over-expressed discs treated with MG132 for 3 hr showed a rescue in Arm expression and a more intense Arm staining in the posterior compartment was found after proteasome inhibitor treatment. (<bold>D1–D3</bold>) Confocal Z stack Intensity profiling shows a comparable Arm level in the posterior compartment of the wing imaginal disc. (<bold>E1–E3</bold>) A higher magnification picture shows no significant change in the expression of Arm in the posterior compartment of the disc suggesting the rescue in Arm degradation. (<bold>F</bold>) Graph shows the average Arm fluorescence intensity (a.u., arbitrary units) (<italic>n</italic> = 7). <italic>ns</italic>; unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test. (<bold>G</bold>) Western blot analysis confirms the immunocytochemical studies where proteasome inhibitor MG132 increases Arm protein levels in Dx over-expressed tissue samples. (<bold>H</bold>) Graph G represents the intensity profiling of the Western blot. ***p &lt; 0.001; unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test. Images in A–F are representatives of three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Scale bar: A1–A4: 10 µm. C1–C4: 2 µm.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata1"><label>Figure 7—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Original file for the co-immunoprecipitation analysis of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref> (anti-Armadillo).</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig7-data1-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata2"><label>Figure 7—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Original scans of the relevant co-immunoprecipitation analysis (anti-Armadillo) with highlighted bands and sample labels for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig7-data2-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata3"><label>Figure 7—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Original file for the co-immunoprecipitation analysis of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref> (anti-FLAG).</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig7-data3-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata4"><label>Figure 7—source data 4.</label><caption><title>Original scans of the relevant co-immunoprecipitation analysis anti-FLAG with highlighted bands and sample labels for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig7-data4-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata5"><label>Figure 7—source data 5.</label><caption><title>Original file for the Western blot analysis in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7G</xref> (anti-Armadillo and anti-tubulin).</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig7-data5-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata6"><label>Figure 7—source data 6.</label><caption><title>Original scans of the relevant Western blot analysis (anti-Armadillo and anti-tubulin) with highlighted bands and sample labels for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7G</xref>.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig7-data6-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig7-v1.tif"/></fig><p>Furthermore, to investigate the role of Dx in Arm degradation we incubated the imaginal discs with MG312, a proteasome inhibitor, before performing Arm staining. A rescue in Arm loss post-MG132 treatment was observed in the posterior domain of the wing disc suggesting it to be a ubiquitination-dependent phenomenon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C1–E4</xref>). Moreover, Western blot reconfirmed our immunofluorescence studies where a decline in Arm expression was observed in Dx over-expression which was significantly rescued after MG132 treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7G, H</xref>). These results unravel a novel mechanistic aspect of Dx in Wg signaling regulation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Conserved mechanism of β-catenin degradation by human DTX1</title><p>In order to elucidate the conserved role of Dx in Wg signaling regulation across the phyla, we examined the status of β-catenin in human DTX1over-expressed HEK-293 cells. In the <italic>Drosophila</italic> system, we have observed that Arm physically interacts with Dx and proteasome inhibitor, MG132, treatment resulted in stabilization of Arm in Dx-over-expressed wing imaginal discs. Thus, to determine the functional conservation of human homolog of <italic>Drosophila</italic> Dx, DTX1 in the β-catenin degradation, first we checked the binding of human DTX1 with β-catenin in HEK-293 cells through co-immunoprecipitation experiment. Consistent with the <italic>Drosophila</italic> studies, the results here undoubtedly reveal the fact that DTX1 binds to β-catenin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A</xref>). In addition, as in the case of <italic>Drosophila</italic>, β-catenin also gets stabilized in the presence of MG132 in human HEK-293 cells over-expressing DTX1. Post-MG132 treatment, the HEK-293 cell lines transfected with HA-tagged DTX1 showed a rescue in β-catenin expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8B</xref>). These results clearly indicate that there is a conserved mechanism through which DTX1 degrades β-catenin and in turn regulates Wnt signaling.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>DTX1 physically interacts with β-catenin and facilitates its degradation.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) HA-tagged human DTX1 transfected in HEK-293 cell line was pulled down with an anti-HA antibody. Immunoblot was done with β-catenin. A prominent band at 92 kDa corresponding to β-catenin post-MG132 treatment was observed. GAPDH was used as an internal control. (<bold>B</bold>) A rescue in β-catenin level post-MG132 treatment was observed. GAPDH serves as an internal control. (<bold>C</bold>) Graph C represents the intensity profiling of the Western blot in C. **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001; one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA)/Turkey’s multiple comparisons test. Images in A–F are representatives of three independent experiments. (<bold>D</bold>) The cartoon explains the two plausible mechanisms of Wg regulation through Dx. Dx facilitates Wg gradient formation on the one hand and on the other it targets Arm for its degradation thereby regulating the signaling output.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig8sdata1"><label>Figure 8—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Original file for the co-immunoprecipitation analysis in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A</xref> (anti-β catenin, anti-HA, and anti-GAPDH).</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig8-data1-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig8sdata2"><label>Figure 8—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Original scans of the relevant co-immunoprecipitation analysis (anti-β catenin, anti-HA, and anti-GAPDH) with highlighted bands and sample labels for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A</xref>.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig8-data2-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig8sdata3"><label>Figure 8—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Original file for the Western blot analysis in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8B</xref> (anti-β catenin, anti-HA, and anti-GAPDH).</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig8-data3-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig8sdata4"><label>Figure 8—source data 4.</label><caption><title>Original scans of the relevant Western blot analysis (anti-β catenin, anti-HA, and anti-GAPDH) with highlighted bands and sample labels for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8B</xref>.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pptx" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig8-data4-v1.pptx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-88466-fig8-v1.tif"/><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024, BioRender Inc</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>BioRender Inc</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Figure 8D was created using <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorender.com/">BioRender</ext-link>, and is published under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND</ext-link> license. Further reproductions must adhere to the terms of this license.</license-p></license></permissions></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The diverse role of Wg in different developmental contexts depends on the Wg signaling activity. Endocytosis and intracellular trafficking regulate Wg signaling levels. Internalization and endosomal transport of Wg not only affect levels and distribution of Wg ligand but also regulates signal transduction through Arm stabilization. Regulation of Wg pathway is tightly monitored at multiple steps. Canonically, Wg exerts its effects by regulating the transcription of the target genes through the effector molecule, Arm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Dierick and Bejsovec, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Städeli et al., 2006</xref>). In the absence of the Wg signaling the multi-protein destruction complex (APC, Axin, GSK3-β, and Cki) phosphorylates and degrades Arm. However, in the presence of the ligand Wg, the cell surface primes a signaling cascade with the aid of the scaffold protein, Axin, which in turn inhibits the destruction complex through the adaptor molecule Dishevelled leading to the stabilization of Arm. The stabilized Arm thereby enters the nucleus to activate the transcription of the target genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bilic et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mosimann et al., 2009</xref>). The stabilization of Arm is therefore a critical step where Wg regulation can take place. An activated Wg signaling also can relocate Axin from intracellular vesicles to the plasma membrane, thereby inactivating the destruction complex and stabilizing Arm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Cliffe et al., 2003</xref>). Relocation of Axin through intracellular trafficking strengthens the fact that Wg signaling is equally regulated through a non-canonical mechanism. Intracellular trafficking affects the efficiency of Wg signaling significantly. For instance, Wg accumulates on the cell surface of Dynamin mutant clones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Strigini and Cohen, 2000</xref>). A Rab5 knockdown further down-regulates Wg signaling suggesting that an internalization and endosomal transport of Wg is critical for its regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Seto and Bellen, 2006</xref>). Wg internalization is proposed to occur via two spatially distinct routes: one on the apical, and one on the basal, side of the disc. It is therefore thought that the subcellular localization of Wg along the apical–basal axis of receiving cells could play a crucial role in molding the Wg gradient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Marois et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>Previously, Godzilla, a member of the RNF family of membrane-anchored E3 ligases is shown to be required for subsequent trafficking of Wg from early apical endosomes to the basolateral surface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Yamazaki et al., 2016</xref>). Here, we show that Dx plays an important role in the intracellular trafficking of Wg and consequently facilitates the spreading of the Wg gradient. Dx regulates Wg signaling activity both at the level of spreading of Wg ligand and directly at the level of Arm stabilization. We hypothesize that since Dx has an E3 ubiquitin ligase activity, it can directly degrade Arm through ubiquitination followed by proteasomal degradation and thus diminish Wg signaling. Dx is a cytoplasmic protein and is best known for its regulation of Notch signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hori et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Matsuno et al., 1995</xref>). Dx regulates Notch signaling in a non-canonical manner and in an over-expressed condition Dx depletes Notch from the cell surface and accumulates it in the endocytic vesicles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hori et al., 2004</xref>). Involvement of Dx in signaling cascade other than Notch has been reported from our earlier studies, where we show that Dx interacts with the TNF (Tumor Necrosis Factor) ligand Eiger, and regulates JNK signaling by facilitating the re-localization of Eiger from the cell membrane to the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Dutta et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, we have also reported that Dx synergizes with TRAF6, the adaptor molecule in the JNK cascade, and activates JNK signaling at a level downstream of the ligand–receptor interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Sharma et al., 2021a</xref>). A novel function of Dx in Toll pathway activation has also been reported lately, where we have reported a JNK-independent Toll pathway activation through Dx (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Sharma et al., 2021b</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we present evidence for the first time that <italic>dx</italic> genetically interacts with <italic>wg</italic> and other components of the Wg signaling cascade in particular the transcription factor, <italic>arm</italic>. Our loss-of-function and gain-of-function studies show that Dx is involved in the regulation of Wg signaling. We show that over-expression of Dx plays an important role in promoting the spreading of the morphogen Wg. This leads to an erosion of the Wg gradient which consecutively results in a loss of the short-range targets, Sens and Cut. We also observed that the loss of Wg downstream targets upon Dx over-expression is independent of Notch. On the contrary, reducing the dosage of Dx narrows the gradient of Wg expression, supporting further the direct role of Dx in Wg spreading. Moreover, on knocking down Rab5, the small GTPase required for early-endosome formation, along with Dx over-expression, a reduction in wing size was observed with a reduction in the Wg expression. A similar reduction in Wg expression was observed when Rab7 was over-expressed along with Dx. Rab7 facilitates the late endosome formation, and along with Dx it might facilitate Wg trafficking and in turn, maintains its proper gradient.</p><p>It has been shown previously that Arm associates with Notch near the adherens junctions and that it is rapidly endocytosed promoting the traffic of an activated form of Armadillo into endosomal compartments, where it may be degraded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Sanders et al., 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Acar et al., 2021</xref>). Notch signaling regulates the activity and the amount of active/oncogenic form of Arm/β-catenin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hayward et al., 2005</xref>). More specifically, in colon cancer cells Notch physically interacts with unphosphorylated β-catenin and negatively regulates the translational accumulation of active β-catenin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kwon et al., 2011</xref>). These studies contemplate the diverse range of mechanisms through which Arm and consequently, Wg signaling may be intricately controlled. Here, we propose a model of Wg regulation through Dx via down-regulation of Arm. Dx down-regulates Arm when it was over-expressed in the wing and eye tissue. Since Dx has an E3 ubiquitin ligase activity and therefore this down-regulation of Arm can be attributed to being a ubiquitination-dependent phenomenon. Indeed, our results support this hypothesis since post-MG132 treatment rescues the loss of Arm when Dx is over-expressed in the background. In addition, we have also shown that human Deltex (DTX1) also displays a conserved function of proteasomal degradation of β-catenin.</p><p>The importance of Wnt/Wg signaling is acknowledged by its implicit role in myriads of biological phenomena throughout development. Wnt/Wg signaling has been implicated in many physiological processes, including development, tissue homeostasis, and tissue regeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Wodarz and Nusse, 1998</xref>). Thus, it is no surprise that mutations in the Wnt pathway components are associated with many hereditary disorders and cancers such as colorectal cancer, Wilms tumor, Familiar Adenomatous Polyposis, and leukemia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kinzler et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Nishisho et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Polakis, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Zhan et al., 2017</xref>). Thus, understanding the mechanism of Wnt/Wg signal regulation is a potent area of investigation. Increased expression of DTX and its involvement in cell migration and invasiveness in different cancers such as follicular lymphomas, osteosarcoma, glioblastoma, and melanoma have also been reported earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gupta-Rossi et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Huber et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Zhang et al., 2010</xref>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bachmann et al., 2014</xref>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Thang et al., 2015</xref>). Here, we have uncovered an important function of the cytoplasmic protein Dx in the gradient formation of the morphogen Wg. These results strengthen the role of Dx in the trafficking of morphogens, thereby allowing the proper activation of the short- and long-range target genes. In addition, the E3 ubiquitin ligase activity of Dx further opens a new avenue of Wg signaling regulation by maintaining the critical concentration of the effector molecule Arm. A clear understanding of Dx-mediated regulation of Wg signaling will be very useful for future research in the field of therapeutic intervention of diseases involved in aberrant Wg signaling.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title><italic>Drosophila</italic> genetics</title><p>All fly stocks were maintained on standard cornmeal/yeast/molasses/agar medium at 25°C as per standard procedures. <italic>UAS-NICD</italic>, <italic>UAS-FLAG-Dx</italic>, <italic>dx</italic>, and <italic>dx<sup>152</sup></italic> were kindly provided by Prof. Spyros Artavanis Tsakonas. <italic>wg<sup>CX3</sup></italic> (BL-2977), <italic>wg<sup>CX4</sup></italic> (BL-6908), <italic>fz<sup>1</sup></italic> (BL-1676), <italic>fz<sup>MB07478</sup></italic> (BL-25554), <italic>Sens<sup>E58</sup></italic> (BL-5312), <italic>UAS-arm<sup>S10</sup></italic> (BL-4782), <italic>UAS-Rab5DN</italic> (BL-9771), <italic>UAS-Rab7-GFP</italic> (BL-42706), <italic>UAS-Dx-RNAi</italic> (BL-35677), <italic>NRE-GFP</italic> (BL-30728), <italic>UAS-p35</italic>, <italic>vg-lacZ</italic>, <italic>en-GAL4</italic>, <italic>dpp-GAL4</italic>, <italic>C96-GAL4</italic>, <italic>ap-GAL4</italic>, <italic>pnr-GAL4</italic>, <italic>dll-GAL4</italic>, and <italic>GMR-GAL4</italic> stocks were obtained from Bloomington Stock Center.</p><p>All crosses were performed at 25°C unless otherwise mentioned. To induce the expression of the gene in the specific domain GAL4–UAS binary system was used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brand and Perrimon, 1993</xref>). Combination stocks were made with the help of appropriate genetic crosses.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Immunocytochemistry and microscopy</title><p><italic>Drosophila</italic> third instar larval wing discs were dissected out in ice-cold 1× PBS (Phosphate-buffered saline), and tissues were fixed in a 1:1 mixture of 3% paraformaldehyde in PBS and at room temperature for 1 min, followed by a second fixation in 3% paraformaldehyde and 5% DMSO (dimethysulfoxide) for 20 min. Immunostaining was done as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Sharma et al., 2021a</xref>). For extra-cellular Wg staining permeabilization of tissue was omitted. Third instar larval wing discs were incubated in ice with thrice the antibody concentration before fixation. Conventional staining protocol was followed thereafter. To inhibit proteasomal degradation, imaginal discs were incubated with 10 mM of MG132 (Sigma M7449) dissolved in Schneider Culture Media for 3 hr before proceeding with immunostaining.</p><p>The following primary antibodies were used in this study Mouse anti-Cut (1:00, DSHB-Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank), Mouse anti-Wg (1:100, DSHB), Mouse anti-Arm (1:50, DSHB), Rabbit anti-Flag (1:00, Sigma), Guinea pig anti-Sens (1:10,000, kindly gifted by Prof. Hugo Bellen), Rabbit anti-Dpn (1:200, a generous gift from Prof. Yuh Nung Jan), guinea pig anti-Rab5 (1:1000; a generous gift from Prof. Akira Nakamura), Alexa488-, Alexa555-, or Alexa405-conjugated secondary antibodies (1:200, Molecular Probes) were used to detect the primary antibodies. Imaging was performed using a Carl Zeiss LSM 780 laser scanning confocal microscope and images were processed with Adobe Photoshop7.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Plasmid and construct generation</title><p>DNA fragments coding for full-length human Deltex1 (1863bps) was inserted into the pcDNA3.1-HA (Addgene #128034) mammalian expression vector with an N-terminal HA tag. Forward primer 5′ <named-content content-type="sequence">CGCAGGGTACCATGTCACGGCCAGGCCACGGTG </named-content>3′ and reverse primer 5′ <named-content content-type="sequence">GCGAGTCTAGACTATCAAGCCTTGCCTGCAGCCTC</named-content> 3′ were used for PCR (Polymerase chain reaction) amplification of full-length Deltex1 cDNA and inserted into pcDNA3.1-HA vector utilizing KpnI and XbaI restriction sites.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Cell culture and transfection</title><p>HEK-293 (ATCC CRL-1573) was maintained in DMEM (Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum and penicillin/streptomycin (Invitrogen). HEK293 (CRL-1573) cells were obtained from ATCC and tested for mycoplasma contamination. Detailed information about the cell line can be obtained from the ATCC site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.atcc.org/products/crl-1573#detailed-product-information">here</ext-link>). Cells were cultured according to the manufacturer’s instructions (ATCC). Plasmids transfection was done by Lipofectamine 2000 (Thermo Fisher Scientific) as described by the manufacturer.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Co-immunoprecipitation and Western blotting</title><p>FLAG-tagged Dx was over-expressed in the wing discs under the control of <italic>en-GAL4</italic> driver. Wing discs were dissected and homogenized in 1× RIPA (Radioimmunoprecipitation assay) buffer (Cell Signaling Technology) containing PMSF (Phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride) 1 mM (Sigma), and 1× Protease Inhibitor (Roche). For control, <italic>en-GAL4/+</italic> protein samples were used. To inhibit proteasomal degradation, discs were incubated with 10 mM of MG132 (Sigma M7449) dissolved in Schneider Culture Media for 3 hr before proceeding with sample preparation. Protein concentration was quantified by Nanodrop. 1 µg of protein was subjected to Western blotting using Immun-blot PVDF (Polyvinylidene fluoride) membrane (Bio-Rad). Mouse anti-Arm (1:1000), Mouse anti-β-tubulin (1:2000, DSHB), and anti-mouse IgG–AP conjugate (1:2000, Molecular probes) were used as primary and secondary antibodies to probe the blot. Color was developed, after washing the membrane three times in TBST (Tris-Buffered Saline), using Sigma FAST BCIP/NBT (Sigma).</p><p>For immunoprecipitation of Dx and Arm, protein lysates were prepared in 1× RIPA buffer (Millipore, #20-188) from <italic>Drosophila</italic> head tissue expressing <italic>UAS-FLAG-Dx</italic>, <italic>UAS-arm<sup>s10</sup></italic>, or both <italic>UAS-arm<sup>s10</sup></italic> and <italic>UAS- FLAG-Dx</italic> using a <italic>GMR-GAL4</italic> driver. Crude lysates containing 2 mg of total protein were mixed with 5 µl of rabbit anti-FLAG antibody or mouse anti-arm antibody and 30 µl of protein A/G beads before being incubated overnight with end-over-end rotation at 4°C. <italic>UAS-arm<sup>s10</sup></italic> or <italic>UAS-FLAG-Dx</italic> lysates were used as control samples. Beads were collected after washing thrice with 1× RIPA buffer and separated on a 12% denaturing SDS-PAGE (Sodium Dodecyl Sulphate-Polyacrylamide Gel) followed by transfer onto Immuno-blot PVDF membranes (Bio-Rad). Mouse anti-arm antibody at 1:1500 dilution or rabbit anti-FLAG antibody at 1:1000 dilution and goat anti-rabbit IgG–AP conjugate at 1:2000 or goat anti-mouse IgG–AP conjugate at 1:200 dilution (Molecular Probes) was used as primary and secondary antibodies to probe the blot. Colorimetric detection was performed using Sigma FAST BCIP/NBT.</p><p>For visualizing conservation across the phyla, human <italic>Deltex1</italic> was expressed in HEK- 293 cells by transient transfection as mentioned (see ). Proteasomal degradation was inhibited by subjecting the transfected cells to 50 µM MG132 for 4 hr. Protein samples were quantified for Western blotting. Immunoprecipitation was carried out as described by abcam immunoprecipitation kit (#ab206996). After washing the samples with IP buffer, samples were denatured and run in 4–20% Mini-PROTEAN TGX precast protein gels (Bio-Rad #4561098) followed by an overnight transfer onto a PVDF membrane. After blocking the membrane with 2.5% BSA (Bovine Serum Albumin) in TBST for 1 hr, the blots were charged with primary antibody followed by an HRP-conjugated secondary antibody. Signal was developed using Chemiluminescence (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Primary antibodies used for Immunoprecipitation and Immunoblotting were mouse monoclonal anti-HA (1:1000, Sigma), rabbit anti-β-catenin (1:1000, Cell Signaling), and Rabbit anti-GAPDH (1:1000, Cell Signaling). Images were obtained with Chemidoc XRS+ (Bio-Rad).</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Imaging of adult tissues and eye imprints</title><p>For adult eye imaging, the anesthetized flies of the desired genotype were kept on a bridge slide to maintain a proper angle. Documentation was done with the Leica MZ105 system. Eye imprints using nail polish were made for analyzing ommatidial defects and were examined under differential interference contrast optics in a Nikon Eclipse Ni microscope (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Arya and Lakhotia, 2006</xref>). For wing and leg wholemount preparation, adult tissues from the desired genotype were removed with the help of a needle and scalpel and cleaned with isopropanol before mounting under coverslips in the mounting media. The slides were observed under a bright-field microscope and imaging was done at proper magnification.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For measuring wing and tarsal segment size, the area of the wing and the tarsal region were measured in arbitrary units using ImageJ software. The size of the wild-type wing and leg was considered as 100% and the size of wing and legs from other genotypes were measured in percent ratio to the wild-type wings and legs. For Arm staining, intensity per unit area of the discs was measured along the anterior–posterior axis using ImageJ software, and the graphs were produced using GraphPad Prism 5 software. Each dataset was repeated at least three times. <italic>T</italic>-test and one-way analysis of variance with Tukey’s multiple comparison post-test were employed to determine the significance of the level of difference among the different genotypes. <italic>p</italic>-value  &lt;0.05 was accepted as statistically significant.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information" id="s5"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Validation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Data curation, Methodology, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Data curation, Methodology</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Supervision, Project administration, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Conceptualization, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Project administration, Writing – review and editing</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="mdar"><label>MDAR checklist</label><media xlink:href="elife-88466-mdarchecklist1-v1.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s7"><title>Data availability</title><p>We do not have any datasets associated with this article. Source data files have been provided for Figures 7 and 8.</p></sec><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors extend sincere thanks to Prof. Spyros Artavanis-Tsakonas (Harvard Medical School), Prof. Florencio Serras (University of Barcelona), Prof. Hugo Bellen (Baylor College of Medicine), Prof. Yuh Nung Jan (University of California, San Francisco), Prof. Akira Nakamura (Institute of Molecular Embryology and Genetics, Kumamoto, Japan), and the Bloomington Stock Centre for fly stocks and antibody. Some of the antibodies used in the work were obtained from Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, University of Iowa. We also acknowledge the confocal facility of DBT-BHU-ISLS, Banaras Hindu University. Artwork is created with BioRender (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorender.com/">BioRender.com</ext-link>).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hidalgo-Sastre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leverentz</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodcock</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Collu</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Inhibition of Wnt signalling by Notch via two distinct mechanisms</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>9096</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-88618-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33907274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakhotia</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>A simple nail polish imprint technique for examination of external morphology of <italic>Drosophila</italic> eyes</article-title><source>Current Science</source><volume>90</volume><elocation-id>9</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Frommel</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Camicia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassa</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>DTX3L and ARTD9 inhibit IRF1 expression and mediate in cooperation with ARTD8 survival and proliferation of metastatic prostate cancer cells</article-title><source>Molecular Cancer</source><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>125</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-13-125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24886089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baena-Lopez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nojima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Integration of morphogen signalling within the growth regulatory network</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Cell Biology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2011.12.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22257639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year><article-title>Transcription of the segment-polarity gene wingless in the imaginal discs of <italic>Drosophila</italic>, and the phenotype of a pupal-lethal wg mutation</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.102.3.489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3181031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bienz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>beta-Catenin: a pivot between cell adhesion and Wnt signalling</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>R64</fpage><lpage>R67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2004.12.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15668160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruciat</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Niehrs</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Wnt induces LRP6 signalosomes and promotes dishevelled-dependent LRP6 phosphorylation</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>316</volume><fpage>1619</fpage><lpage>1622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1137065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17569865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Notch and Wingless signals collide</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>271</volume><fpage>1822</fpage><lpage>1823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.271.5257.1822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8596948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>Targeted gene expression as a means of altering cell fates and generating dominant phenotypes</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.118.2.401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8223268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cadigan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Wnt signaling: a common theme in animal development</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>3286</fpage><lpage>3305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.11.24.3286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cadigan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Regulating morphogen gradients in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing</article-title><source>Seminars in Cell &amp; Developmental Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1084-9521(02)00014-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cadigan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>TCF/LEFs and Wnt signaling in the nucleus</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>a007906</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a007906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23024173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chitalia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Shivanna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martorell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>c-Cbl, a ubiquitin E3 ligase that targets active β-catenin: a novel layer of Wnt signaling regulation</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>288</volume><fpage>23505</fpage><lpage>23517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.473801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23744067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clague</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbé</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>The interface of receptor trafficking and signalling</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>114</volume><fpage>3075</fpage><lpage>3081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.114.17.3075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Wnt/beta-catenin signaling in development and disease</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.10.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17081971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cliffe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamada</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>A role of Dishevelled in relocating Axin to the plasma membrane during wingless signaling</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>960</fpage><lpage>966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0960-9822(03)00370-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12781135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Covey</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Virshup</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Wnt signaling in development, disease and translational medicine</article-title><source>Current Drug Targets</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/138945008784911796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18673238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Couso</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez Arias</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>The wingless signalling pathway and the patterning of the wing margin in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Development</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.120.3.621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8162860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Celis</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Feed-back mechanisms affecting Notch activation at the dorsoventral boundary in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>3241</fpage><lpage>3251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.124.17.3241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9310319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diaz-Benjumea</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Serrate signals through Notch to establish a Wingless-dependent organizer at the dorsal/ventral compartment boundary of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>4215</fpage><lpage>4225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.121.12.4215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8575321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dierick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bejsovec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>5 cellular mechanisms of wingless/Wnt signal transduction</article-title><source>Current Topics in Developmental Biology</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>190</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsuddi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Regulation of notch signaling by the heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein Hrp48 and Deltex in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>206</volume><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.116.198879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28396507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsuddi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Deltex interacts with Eiger and consequently influences the cell death in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Cellular Signalling</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cellsig.2018.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29775737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Entchev</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwabedissen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>González-Gaitán</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Gradient formation of the TGF-beta homolog Dpp</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>981</fpage><lpage>991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)00200-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11136982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fortini</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Endocytic regulation of Notch signaling</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Genetics &amp; Development</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gde.2009.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19447603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>EGF receptor/Rolled MAP kinase signalling protects cells against activated Armadillo in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> eye</article-title><source>EMBO Reports</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/embo-reports/kve019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11258709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta-Rossi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Six</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBail</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Logeat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chastagner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Olry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Israël</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Monoubiquitination and endocytosis direct gamma-secretase cleavage of activated Notch receptor</article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>166</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200310098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15240571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hay-Koren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Caspi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilberberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosin-Arbesfeld</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>The EDD E3 ubiquitin ligase ubiquitinates and up-regulates beta-catenin</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E10-05-0440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21118991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Balayo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>DasGupta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez Arias</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Notch modulates Wnt signalling by associating with Armadillo/beta-catenin and regulating its transcriptional activity</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>1819</fpage><lpage>1830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15772135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fostier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuwa</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Go</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Okano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> Deltex mediates Suppressor of Hairless-independent and late-endosomal activation of Notch signaling</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>131</volume><fpage>5527</fpage><lpage>5537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mäki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosanova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casarotto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Canali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Casali</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tononi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Massimini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Human cortical excitability increases with time awake</article-title><source>Cerebral Cortex</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhs014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22314045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hupalowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miaczynska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>The new faces of endocytosis in signaling</article-title><source>Traffic</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0854.2011.01249.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21752167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katanaev</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Solis</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Buestorf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katanayeva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrock</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuermer</surname><given-names>CAO</given-names></name><name><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Reggie-1/flotillin-2 promotes secretion of the long-range signalling forms of Wingless and Hedgehog in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7601981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18219274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinzler</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilbert</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>L-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Preisinger</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McKechnie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Finniear</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Markham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Groffen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boguski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Horii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishisho</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Identification of FAP locus genes from chromosome 5q21</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>253</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1651562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shenje</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nigam</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Notch post-translationally regulates β-catenin protein in stem and progenitor cells</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1244</fpage><lpage>1251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21841793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lecuit</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Calleja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Two distinct mechanisms for long-range patterning by Decapentaplegic in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>381</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/381387a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8632795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>The Wnt signaling pathway in development and disease</article-title><source>Annual Review of Cell and Developmental Biology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.20.010403.113126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15473860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Wnt/beta-catenin signaling: components, mechanisms, and diseases</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2009.06.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19619488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marois</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>The endocytic pathway and formation of the Wingless morphogen gradient</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>133</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.02197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16354714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Diederich</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Go</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaumueller</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Artavanis-Tsakonas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Deltex acts as a positive regulator of Notch signaling through interactions with the Notch ankyrin repeats</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>2633</fpage><lpage>2644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.121.8.2633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7671825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsuddi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>TRAF6 is a novel regulator of Notch signaling in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Cellular Signalling</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>3016</fpage><lpage>3026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cellsig.2014.09.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25280943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mosimann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Beta-catenin hits chromatin: regulation of Wnt target gene activation</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19305417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Veraksa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Camonis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Artavanis-Tsakonas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Regulation of Notch signalling by non-visual beta-arrestin</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>1191</fpage><lpage>1201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb1327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16284625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mulligan</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuerer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Willert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Secreted Wingless-interacting molecule (Swim) promotes long-range signaling by maintaining Wingless solubility</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1119197109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22203956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nellen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Struhl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Direct and long-range action of a DPP morphogen gradient</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>85</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81114-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8616891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>A hierarchy of cross-regulation involving Notch, wingless, vestigial and cut organizes the dorsal/ventral axis of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>122</volume><fpage>3477</fpage><lpage>3485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.122.11.3477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8951063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Long-range action of Wingless organizes the dorsal-ventral axis of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.124.4.871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9043068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishisho</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Horii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Utsunomiya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Mutations of chromosome 5q21 genes in FAP and colorectal cancer patients</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>253</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1651563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1651563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nolo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Senseless, a Zn finger transcription factor, is necessary and sufficient for sensory organ development in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)00040-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10975525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peifer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orsulic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loureiro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>A model system for cell adhesion and signal transduction in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Development</source><volume>119</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.119.Supplement.163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polakis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>The many ways of Wnt in cancer</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Genetics &amp; Development</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gde.2006.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17208432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sachan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsuddi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Notch signalling: multifaceted role in development and disease</article-title><source>The FEBS Journal</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/febs.16815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37166442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>PGT</given-names></name><name><surname>Muñoz-Descalzo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Balayo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz-Peitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Ligand-independent traffic of Notch buffers activated Armadillo in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>PLOS Biology</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e1000169</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19668359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Internalization is required for proper Wingless signaling in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>173</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200510123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16606693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsuddi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021a</year><article-title>Deltex cooperates with TRAF6 to promote apoptosis and cell migration through Eiger-independent JNK activation in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Cell Biology International</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbin.11521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33300258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsuddi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021b</year><article-title>Deltex positively regulates Toll signaling in a JNK independent manner in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Genes to Cells</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gtc.12837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33555648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsuddi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Deltex modulates Dpp morphogen gradient formation and affects Dpp signaling in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>135</volume><elocation-id>jcs259658</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.259658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35950520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Slaga</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Minamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Wnt/beta-catenin signaling induces the expression and activity of betaTrCP ubiquitin ligase receptor</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1097-2765(00)80327-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Städeli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Transcription under the control of nuclear Arm/beta-catenin</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>R378</fpage><lpage>R385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2006.04.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strigini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Wingless gradient formation in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0960-9822(00)00378-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10744972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Genetics of morphogen gradients</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Genetics</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>620</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35084577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Morphogens, their identification and regulation</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>131</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thang</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Yajima</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumasaka</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Deltex-3-like (DTX3L) stimulates metastasis of melanoma through FAK/PI3K/AKT but not MEK/ERK pathway</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>14290</fpage><lpage>14299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.3742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26033450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaccari</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanwar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortini</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Endosomal entry regulates Notch receptor activation in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>180</volume><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200708127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18299346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valenta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>The many faces and functions of β-catenin</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>2714</fpage><lpage>2736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2012.150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22617422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vuong</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Iomini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Balmer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Aaronson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mlodzik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Kinesin-2 and IFT-A act as A complex promoting nuclear localization of β-catenin during Wnt signalling</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>5304</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-07605-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30546012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tongngok</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gensch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Clemence</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Motoki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchi-Kanai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> HOPS and AP-3 complex genes are required for a Deltex-regulated activation of notch in the endosomal trafficking pathway</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>762</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2008.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19000840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wodarz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Mechanisms of Wnt signaling in development</article-title><source>Annual Review of Cell and Developmental Biology</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.14.1.59</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9891778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wodarz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Wingless signaling modulates cadherin-mediated cell adhesion in <italic>Drosophila</italic> imaginal disc cells</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>119</volume><fpage>2425</fpage><lpage>2434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.02973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16720643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuwa</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayukawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkin</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Roles of <italic>Drosophila</italic> deltex in Notch receptor endocytic trafficking and activation</article-title><source>Genes to Cells</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2443.2011.01488.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21299753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexandre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakugawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaugue</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Godzilla-dependent transcytosis promotes Wingless signalling in <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing imaginal discs</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb3325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26974662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zacharioudaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Tools and methods for studying Notch signaling in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Methods</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2014.03.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24704358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zecca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Struhl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Direct and long-range action of a wingless morphogen gradient</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81991-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8945511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Verheyen</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Nemo is an inducible antagonist of Wingless signaling during <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing development</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>131</volume><fpage>2911</fpage><lpage>2920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15169756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rindtorff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Wnt signaling in cancer</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>1461</fpage><lpage>1473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2016.304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27617575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zweidler-McKay</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>DPM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Regulation of NOTCH signaling by reciprocal inhibition of HES1 and Deltex 1 and its role in osteosarcoma invasiveness</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>2916</fpage><lpage>2926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2010.62</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20208568</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="sa0"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.88466.3.sa0</article-id><title-group><article-title>eLife assessment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Roger J</given-names></name><role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of Massachusetts Medical School</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="evidence-strength"><kwd>Solid</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="claim-importance"><kwd>Useful</kwd></kwd-group></front-stub><body><p>This is a <bold>useful</bold> study of the connection between the ubiquitin ligase protein deltex and the wingless signaling pathway. Two different links are inferred from genetic interactions in vivo between loss-of-function mutations and overexpression. While the genetic data are <bold>solid</bold>, the precise mechanism underlying either effect remains to be established.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="referee-report" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.88466.3.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Reviewer #1 (Public Review):</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><anonymous/><role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><p>This study presents a genetic and molecular analysis of the role of the cytoplasmic ub ligase Deltex (Dx) in regulating the <italic>Drosophila</italic> Wingless (Wg) pathway in the larval wing disc. The study exploits the strength of the fly system to uncover a series of genetic interactions between dx and wg and fz allele that support a role for Dx upstream of the Wg pathway. These are paired with molecular evidence that dx lof alleles lower Wg protein in 'source' cells at the DV margin, and that Dx associates with Arm and lowers its levels in a manner that can be rescued by pharmacological inhibition of the proteasome. The genetic data are solid but subject to alternative explanations based on the authors' model that Dx both inhibits and activates the pathway. The molecular data are suggestive, but need follow up tests of how Dx affects Wg spread, and how Dx mediates poly-ub of Arm, and the degree to which Dx shares this role with the validated Arm E3 ligase Slmb. Overall, the story is very interesting but has mechanistic gaps that lead to speculative models that require more rigorous study to clarify mechanism. Dx sharing a role in Arm degradation with the Slmb/APC destruction would have important implications for the many Wg/Wnt regulated processes in development and disease.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="referee-report" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.88466.3.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Reviewer #2 (Public Review):</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><anonymous/><role specific-use="referee">Reviewer</role></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><p>The manuscript investigates the connections between the ubiquitin ligase protein deltex and the wingless pathway. Two different connections are proposed, one is function of deltex to modulate the gradient of wingless diffusion and hence modulate the spatial patter of wingless pathway targets, which regulate at different thresholds of wingless concentration. The second is a direct interaction between deltex and armadillo, a downstream component of the wingless pathway. Deltex is proposed to cause the degradation of armadillo resulting in suppression of wingless pathway activity. The results and conclusions of the manuscript are interesting and for the most part novel, although previously published work linking Notch and deltex to wingless signal regulation, and endocytosis to wingless gradient formation could be more extensively discussed. However neither of the two parts to the manuscript seem, in themselves sufficiently complete, and combining both parts together therefore seems to lack focus.</p><p>The main issue with the manuscript is that much of the conclusions are inferred from genetic interactions in vivo between loss of function mutants and overexpression. While providing useful in vivo physiological context, this type of approach struggles to be able to make definitive conclusions on whether an interaction is due to direct or indirect mechanism, as the authors themselves conclude at the end of section 2.3. The problem is confounded by the fact that there is already documented much cross talk between the Notch signaling pathway and wingless at the transcriptional level, and deltex is already a Notch modulator that can alter wingless mRNA expression (See Hori et al 2004). Deltex in addition to promoting a ligand-independent Notch signal can also induce expression of Notch ligand, allowing further non-autonomous Notch activation and subsequent cell autonomous cis-inhibition of the initial deltex-induced signal. The dynamics and outcomes of the Notch signal response to deltex in vivo is therefore already very complicated to interpret before even considering to unravel indirect (via Notch) and direct interactions with wingless, although the two possibilities are not mutually exclusive. Whilst the revised manuscript does not completely overcome these limitations, further data and quantification have improved the support for the conclusions and there is a wider discussion of the relevant literature. The conclusions are interesting and add significantly to our understanding of the intersections between Wingless, Notch and trafficking regulators in an in vivo context.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="sa3"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.88466.3.sa3</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Vartika</given-names></name><role specific-use="author">Author</role><aff><institution>Banaras Hindu University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Varanasi</named-content></addr-line><country>India</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sachan</surname><given-names>Nalani</given-names></name><role specific-use="author">Author</role><aff><institution>NYU Langone Medical Center</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">New York</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>Bappi</given-names></name><role specific-use="author">Author</role><aff><institution>Banaras Hindu University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Varanasi</named-content></addr-line><country>India</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mutsuddi</surname><given-names>Mousumi</given-names></name><role specific-use="author">Author</role><aff><institution>Banaras Hindu University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Varanasi</named-content></addr-line><country>India</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>Ashim</given-names></name><role specific-use="author">Author</role><aff><institution>Banaras Hindu University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Varanasi</named-content></addr-line><country>India</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><p>The following is the authors’ response to the original reviews.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p><bold>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations For The Authors):</bold></p><p>(1) The description of the wing phenotype that results from combinations of wingless and delex alleles at the bottom of page 4 (figure 1) is quite confusing. Are the trans-hets suppressed to wt or enhanced? The images in the Fig look enhanced.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for this thoughtful observation regarding the wing phenotype description in combination with wg and dx alleles. We understand the confusion and appreciate the opportunity to clarify.</p><p>In response to the concern raised, the trans-heterozygous indeed enhanced rather than suppressed to wild type. We acknowledge that the description would have been clearer. We have revised the relevant section to explicitly state that trans-heterozygous exhibit an enhanced wing phenotype in the updated version of the manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>(2) Use of Cut as a Wg readout in Fig1 is problematic since it is also a Notch target. Perhaps a more direct measure of Arm activity would be a better choice here, e.g., naked-lacZ.</p></disp-quote><p>We appreciate the reviewer’s insightful comment regarding the use of Cut as a Wg readout. The point about being Cut as a Notch target raises a valid concern. To address this issue and provide a more direct measurement of Arm activity, we agree that incorporating a specific Arm readout, such as naked lacZ, would be a more suitable choice.</p><p>We will incorporate this valuable feedback into our future research endeavors to augment the comprehensiveness of our study.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>(3) The dx allele effects on Sens and Vg in Fig 2C appear greater at two points along the DV margin (arrows). Do these match the expression pattern of dx mRNA?</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for this thoughtful observation. We understand that the effect of the dx LOF allele on Sens and Vg seems more pronounced at two specific points along the D/V margin. As far as our understanding Dx shows a homogeneous expression pattern throughout the Wg disc which has been reported earlier (Busseau et al., 1994., Mukherjee et al., 2005).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>(4) It really looks to my eye that dx loss lowers Wg expression in source cells in Fig 2. To confirm the model that Dx controls the spread of Wg protein, it would be ideal to rule out txnal effects with a wg-lacZ reporter.</p></disp-quote><p>We appreciate the reviewer for raising this important point. In the revised version of the manuscript, we have introduced Wg-lacZ staining for both Wg-lacZ/+ and dx152/Y; Wg-lacZ/+ combination in Figure 2. This additional information eliminates the possibility of Deltex influencing Wg transcriptional regulation in source cells, thus reinforcing our hypothesis that the reduction of Deltex leads to a decline in Wg protein levels in the source cells, given Dx essential role in wingless gradient formation.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>(5) The drop in DV Wg and expansion of Vg domain in dx mutants seem paradoxical but could be explained by accelerated Wg spread and uptake. This could be tested by depleting the dally-like glypican that promotes long-range Wg diffusion in dx mutants, and seeing if this restores Wg levels at the DV margin.</p></disp-quote><p>This is indeed a very thoughtful comment and we thank the reviewer for this insightful suggestion for further exploration. We believe that depleting dally-like glypican in dx mutants could possibly restore Wg levels at the DV margin.</p><p>We recognize the importance of this experiment in providing a more comprehensive understanding of the underlying mechanisms, and we will give major emphasis on incorporating this suggestion in our future research.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>(6) The authors describe the effect of Dx over-expression as &quot;reducing&quot; the Wg gradient when they actually mean &quot;flattening&quot;. Please be careful with this word choice as they mean different things.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for the insightful feedback. The suggested modifications have been incorporated into the revised version of the manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>(7) The combined effects of Rab5dn and Dx o/e on Wg protein loc/levels are interesting but need to be followed up by testing whether the endogenous Dx/Rab5 show genetic interactions in control of Wg protein levels/localization.</p></disp-quote><p>We acknowledge the reviewer's comment and in addressing it, we wish to highlight that the over-expression of Dx with endogenous Rab5 or Rab7 does not affect Wg protein levels or localization. We have mentioned the supporting data for this control in Figure 5(G, H).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>(8) The ability of MG132 to restore Arm levels in en-Dx discs is very promising. However, MG132 will also block Arm degradation by the Slmb-APC destruction complex, so this result could be non-specific. Tests of whether Dx drives poly-ub of Arm, and how much Dx is redundant to Slmb in this role, would be needed to solidify the authors' conclusion.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for this insightful comment. We understand that the concern about MG132 blocking Arm degradation by Slmb-APC destruction complex adds an important layer of complexity to the interpretation of the results. We agree with the reviewer's comment that conducting these experiments will indeed offer valuable insight into the specificity of MG132 effects and further strengthen our conclusion.</p><p>We are interested to see how future experiments addressing the points raised by the reviewer will shape our understanding of the intricate mechanisms involved in Wg signaling and Arm/β-catenin degradation. Once again, we thank the reviewer for the thoughtful engagement with the research, and the comments will undoubtedly stimulate further investigation and discussion in this area.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p><bold>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations For The Authors):</bold></p><p>The work really needs more experiments to further provide a mechanistic understanding and distinguish between direct and indirect action (via Notch signaling) on Wingless, but instead switches in the second half to a second interaction with β-catenin, leaving the conclusions of the first part hanging. More mechanistic information on the cell biology of how Deltex might affect wingless endocytic trafficking directly would be beneficial, for example involving some cell culture experiments where the action of deltex on Notch and wingless could be more clearly separated and a more detailed study of the consequences on wingless trafficking could be explored.</p><p>Wingless is secreted into an extracellular compartment and so won't be accessible for a direct interaction with cytoplasmic deltex. Therefore are the authors proposing Deltex interacts with a membrane-bound wingless receptor such as frizzled in order to mediate its effects? These avenues could be explored further experimentally to derive a more mechanistic conclusion.</p><p>The colocalisation images are not high resolution and colocalisation is not quantified, and no differences ( +/- Deltex) in wingless subcellular localisation, which would aid mechanistic interpretation, are shown.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for the insightful feedback on our work. We appreciate the suggestion for more experiments to provide a mechanistic understanding and to distinguish between direct and indirect actions of Notch on Wingless signaling. We acknowledge the importance of clarifying these aspects and agree that further experiments could help separate the effects of Deltex on Notch and Wingless signaling, allowing for a more detailed examination of their respective trafficking and ubiquitination mechanisms.</p><p>We will consider your valuable input in our future research efforts to enhance the comprehensiveness of our study.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Other specific points</p><p>Figure 2: Narrowing and broadening of different marker gene expression patterns in dx mutants needs to be quantified so that variation is taken into account and the numbers of wings imaged should be clearly stated.</p></disp-quote><p>We greatly appreciate this valuable suggestion from the reviewer. As a response, we have incorporated quantification data to address the observed variations. We have also provided information regarding the number of wing discs that were imaged for the purpose of quantification.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Figure 3: The number of discs imaged in total should be mentioned</p></disp-quote><p>We express our appreciation to the reviewer for the input. We have taken their comment into account and have subsequently included details regarding the number of discs imaged in the figure legend section of the manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Figure 6: There is no description of (E5-E6) in the figure legend. F1 to F5 eye size phenotypes require quantification.</p></disp-quote><p>We are grateful to the reviewers for bringing this to our attention. In response, we have included a description of E5-E6 in the figure legend. Also, as per the reviewer’s suggestions, we have incorporated the quantification data of the eye size phenotype.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Discussion</p><p>Links between Notch and wingless pathway should be more comprehensively discussed, including previous work that has previously linked Notch/Deltex to β-catenin degradation e.g.</p><p>Acar et al. .Sci Rep 2021 Apr 27;11(1):9096. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-88618-5</p><p>Hayward et al. Development 2005 Apr;132(8):1819-30. doi: 10.1242/dev.01724;</p><p>Kwon et al Nat Cell Biol 2011 Aug 14;13(10):1244-51. doi: 10.1038/ncb2313.</p><p>Sanders et al. PLoS Biol 2009 Aug;7(8):e1000169. doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1000169. Epub 2009 Aug 11.</p><p>The links between endocytic trafficking and wingless gradient formation could also be further discussed eg.</p><p>Marois et al. Development 2006 Jan;133(2):307-17.doi: 10.1242/dev.02197. Epub 2005 Dec 14</p><p>Yamazaki et al Nat Cell Biol 2016 Apr;18(4):451-7. doi: 10.1038/ncb3325. Epub 2016 Mar 14.</p></disp-quote><p>We appreciate the reviewer's valuable suggestions and we have now included these references in the discussion section of the revised manuscript.</p></body></sub-article></article>