<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.2"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">81549</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.81549</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Tools and Resources</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Developmental Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Generation of a transparent killifish line through multiplex CRISPR/Cas9mediated gene inactivation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-285160"><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-2040-6460</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-304883"><name><surname>Perner</surname><given-names>Birgit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-285161"><name><surname>Albertz</surname><given-names>Carolin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-304884"><name><surname>Mörl</surname><given-names>Hanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-285162"><name><surname>Hopfenmüller</surname><given-names>Vera L</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9807-6403</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-94253"><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5931-3189</contrib-id><email>christoph.englert@leibniz-fli.de</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/039a53269</institution-id><institution>Molecular Genetics Lab, Leibniz Institute on Aging - Fritz Lipmann Institute (FLI)</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Jena</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/039a53269</institution-id><institution>Core Facility Imaging, Leibniz Institute on Aging – Fritz Lipmann Institute (FLI)</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Jena</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05qpz1x62</institution-id><institution>Institute of Biochemistry and Biophysics, Friedrich-Schiller-University Jena</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Jena</named-content></addr-line><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>Itamar</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03qxff017</institution-id><institution>The Hebrew University of Jerusalem</institution></institution-wrap><country>Israel</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Stainier</surname><given-names>Didier YR</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0165r2y73</institution-id><institution>Max Planck Institute for Heart and Lung Research</institution></institution-wrap><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="publication"><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e81549</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2022-07-01"><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2023-02-23"><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a preprint at .</event-desc><date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2022-07-04"><day>04</day><month>07</month><year>2022</year></date><self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.07.04.498720"/></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2023, Krug et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Krug et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-81549-v3.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="figures-pdf" xlink:href="elife-81549-figures-v3.pdf"/><abstract><p>Body pigmentation is a limitation for <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging and thus for the performance of longitudinal studies in biomedicine. A possibility to circumvent this obstacle is the employment of pigmentation mutants, which are used in fish species like zebrafish and medaka. To address the basis of aging, the short-lived African killifish <italic>Nothobranchius furzeri</italic> has recently been established as a model organism. Despite its short lifespan, <italic>N. furzeri</italic> shows typical signs of mammalian aging including telomere shortening, accumulation of senescent cells, and loss of regenerative capacity. Here, we report the generation of a transparent <italic>N. furzeri</italic> line by the simultaneous inactivation of three key loci responsible for pigmentation. We demonstrate that this stable line, named <italic>klara</italic>, can serve as a tool for different applications including behavioral experiments and the establishment of a senescence reporter by integration of a fluorophore into the <italic>cdkn1a (p21</italic>) locus and <italic>in vivo</italic> microscopy of the resulting line.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>killifish</kwd><kwd>pigmentation</kwd><kwd>transparency</kwd><kwd>senescence</kwd><kwd>mate choice</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Other</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Carl Zeiss Stiftung</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>IMPULS P2019-01-006</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Leibniz Institute on Aging</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Graduate Student Fellowship</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Using the short-lived turquoise killifish, a transparent <italic>in vivo</italic> reporter line named <italic>klara</italic> is established that will be a valuable tool to explore development, senescence, aging, and regeneration.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>In animals, pigments that can be found in specific cell types limit optical transparency and prevent the <italic>in vivo</italic> observation of processes like organogenesis, regeneration, or cancer metastasis. While mammals have only one pigment cell type, the melanocyte, other vertebrates including fish develop several chromatophores that produce different colors. In one of the best-studied models for vertebrate coloration, the zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>), the three main kinds of chromatophores are the melanophores (black), the iridophores (silvery or blue), and the xanthophores (yellow), all derived from neural crest cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Kelsh et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Singh and Nüsslein-Volhard, 2015</xref>). A fourth population of pigment cells, forming the retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) is derived from the optic neuroepithelium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bharti et al., 2006</xref>). Different combinations of naturally occurring mutants in pigmentation genes have been used to generate adult transparent zebrafish. The <italic>casper</italic> line lacks melanocytes and iridophores due to mutations in <italic>mitfa</italic> and <italic>mpv17</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">D’Agati et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">White et al., 2008</xref>). An additional mutation in the <italic>slc45a2</italic> gene is present in <italic>crystal</italic> zebrafish, which completely lack melanin and therefore possess a transparent RPE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Antinucci and Hindges, 2016</xref>). Transparent zebrafish have been used to study different aspects of cancer and stem cell biology, among others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">White et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Yan et al., 2019</xref>). In another model fish, the medaka (<italic>Oryzias latipes</italic>), transparent juvenile and adult animals have recently been generated through CRISPR/Cas9-mediated inactivation of <italic>oca2</italic> and <italic>pnp4a</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lischik et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>During the last decade the turquoise killifish, <italic>N. furzeri</italic>, has emerged as a new model for research on aging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Platzer and Englert, 2016</xref>). With a lifespan between three and seven months, <italic>N. furzeri</italic> is the shortest-lived vertebrate that can be kept in captivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Tozzini et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Valdesalici and Cellerino, 2003</xref>). Hatchlings grow rapidly and can reach sexual maturation already within two to three weeks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Blažek et al., 2013</xref>). <italic>N. furzeri</italic> shares many hallmarks of aging with mammals, including telomere shortening, mitochondrial dysfunction, cellular senescence, loss of regenerative capacity, and cognitive decline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Genade et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Graf et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Hartmann et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hartmann et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Terzibasi et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Valenzano et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Wendler et al., 2015</xref>). What makes the killifish an attractive model in addition, is the establishment of transgenesis and genome engineering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Allard et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Harel et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Hartmann and Englert, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Valenzano et al., 2011</xref>) as well as the availability of reference sequences for the <italic>N. furzeri</italic> genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reichwald et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Valenzano et al., 2015</xref>). The turquoise killifish is sexually dimorphic and dichromatic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Cellerino et al., 2016</xref>). Compared to females, males are larger and more colorful. The latter occurs in two color forms with red and yellow morphs that differ primarily in coloration of the caudal fin. Females have translucent fins and a pale grayish body with iridescent scales.</p><p>Here, we describe the generation of transparent juvenile and adult <italic>N. furzeri</italic> animals. We have used a single injection of three sgRNAs targeting <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic>, which are involved in pigment development in melanophores, iridophores, and xanthophores, respectively. With the method employed, we have achieved simultaneous and biallelic somatic gene disruptions of three genomic loci in a highly efficient manner. Already in the F<sub>0</sub> generation, a fraction of animals were fully transparent. Homozygous triple mutants showed normal behavior, fertility, and general health. In addition, we have used the transparent line, named <italic>klara</italic>, to modify additional genes, to study female and male mate choice, and to generate an <italic>in vivo</italic> senescence reporter. For the latter, we employed homology-directed repair-mediated integration of a <italic>GFP</italic> allele into the locus of the senescence marker <italic>cdkn1a (p21</italic>). Finally, we show that this reporter line can be used for <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Multiple genes can be simultaneously inactivated in <italic>N. furzeri</italic></title><p>For the generation of a transparent <italic>N. furzeri</italic> line, we selected the genes <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk</italic>, and <italic>csf1ra</italic> as targets to interfere with the formation of melanophores, iridophores, and xanthophores, respectively. This was based on known color mutants in <italic>D. rerio</italic>, namely <italic>casper</italic> (lack of melanophores), <italic>shady</italic> (lack of iridophores), and <italic>panther</italic> (lack of xanthophores) in which <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk</italic>, and <italic>csf1ra</italic> were shown to be inactivated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Lister et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lopes et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Parichy et al., 2000</xref>). The expression of those three genes was analyzed in skin tissue from fish of both sexes at the age of 1, 2, 3, and 6 weeks post-hatching (wph). In male fish, we observed a significant up-regulation of <italic>mitfa</italic> at the age of 6 wph, whereas <italic>mitfa</italic> expression did not change in female fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). The expression of <italic>ltk</italic> increased steadily with age in both, male and female fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). In contrast, <italic>csf1ra</italic> expression did not differ significantly over time in males and females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). Direct comparison of <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> expression between females and males did not reveal sex-specific differences except for <italic>mitfa</italic> at 6 wph (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A–C</xref>). To induce mutations in the selected genes, single guide RNAs were designed based on the genome sequence provided by the <italic>N. furzeri</italic> Genome Browser (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reichwald et al., 2015</xref>). Since three genes were planned to be inactivated at the same time, we used only one sgRNA per gene. To facilitate mutation detection PAM sequences were chosen that had a restriction site directly upstream, assuming that the restriction site would be lost upon the introduction of a mutation. After the characterization of different sgRNAs for each gene, sgRNAs were synthesized targeting <italic>mitfa</italic> in exon 6, <italic>ltk</italic> in exon 22, and <italic>csf1ra</italic> in exon 9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1D–F</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Simultaneous inactivation of genes involved in body pigmentation.</title><p>(<bold>A–C</bold>) Gene expression analysis of <italic>mitfa</italic> (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>ltk</italic> (<bold>B</bold>), and <italic>csf1ra</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) in the skin of male and female wild-type fish via quantitative real-time PCR. The expression of <italic>mitfa</italic> was only significantly up-regulated in male fish at the age of 6 weeks post-hatching (wph) (p: 0.048). For both sexes, the expression of <italic>ltk</italic> increased significantly over time (p<sub>male, 2wph</sub>: 0.028, p<sub>male, 3wph</sub>: 0.026, p<sub>male, 6wph</sub>: 0.002; p<sub>female, 2wph</sub>: 0.002, p<sub>female, 3wph</sub>: 0.019, p<sub>female, 6wph</sub>: 0.033), whereas no significant differences were observed for <italic>csf1ra</italic>. Expression levels were normalized to the expression at 1 wph in the respective sex. <italic>Rpl13a</italic> was used as housekeeping gene (n<sub>male_1wph</sub> = 3, n<sub>male_2wph</sub> = 4, n<sub>male_3wph</sub> = 4, n<sub>male_6wph</sub> = 4; n<sub>female_1wph</sub> = 3, n<sub>female_2wph</sub> = 4, n<sub>female_3wph</sub> = 4, n<sub>female_6wph</sub> = 4). Relative gene expression was calculated using the ΔΔCT method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Pfaffl et al., 2002</xref>). Student’s or Welch’s t-tests were computed to determine significant changes in gene expression. Horizontal line represents median. Whiskers show min. to max. values. (<bold>D</bold>) Phenotypical analysis of F<sub>0</sub> embryos revealed a reduction of melanophores in GFP-positive compared to GFP-negative embryos. (<bold>E,F</bold>) Male (<bold>E</bold>) and female (<bold>F</bold>) wild-type <italic>N. furzeri</italic>. (<bold>G–J</bold>) Males and females of the F<sub>0</sub> generation, display a mosaic loss of body pigmentation. Note that almost completely transparent individuals can be observed in (<bold>H–J</bold>), allowing a view on inner organs (o: ovary, s: stomach, sb: swim bladder). (<bold>J</bold>) Microscopic analysis of a female F<sub>0</sub> fish with a view on individual eggs within the ovary and blood vessels (cv: cardinal vein, e: egg). (<bold>K,K’</bold>) Male (<bold>K</bold>) and female (<bold>K’</bold>) fish at the age of 38 days post-hatching (dph) with the genotype <italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup>,ltk<sup>+/-</sup>,csf1ra<sup>-/-</sup></italic> showed a lack of melanophores and xanthophores, whereas iridophores were present. (<bold>L,L’</bold>) A lack of melanophores and iridophores was observed in male (<bold>L</bold>) and female (<bold>L’</bold>) <italic>N. furzeri</italic> with the genotype <italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup>, ltk<sup>-/-</sup>, csf1ra<sup>+/-</sup></italic>. Despite a homozygous mutation in <italic>ltk</italic> (<italic>ltk<sup>-/-</sup></italic>) individual scales with iridophores were detected in fish of both sexes. (<bold>M,M’</bold>) The presence of homozygous mutations in all the three genes <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> resulted in the loss of body pigmentation in males (<bold>M</bold>) and females (<bold>M’</bold>) allowing a view on inner organs.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata1"><label>Figure 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Gene expression data and N. furzeri images.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig1-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Targeting the <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> loci in <italic>N</italic>. <italic>furzeri</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A–C</bold>) Comparison of the <italic>mitfa</italic> (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>ltk</italic> (<bold>B</bold>), and <italic>csf1ra</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) expression in the skin of male and female wild-type fish at 1 (n<sub>male</sub> = 3, n<sub>female</sub> = 4), 2 (n<sub>male</sub> = 4, n<sub>female</sub> = 3), 3 (n<sub>male</sub> = 4, n<sub>female</sub> = 3) and 6 wph (n<sub>male</sub> =4, n<sub>female</sub> = 3) using qRT-PCR. A significant change in gene expression between females and males was detected for <italic>mitfa</italic> at 6 wph (p: 0.031). Expression levels were normalized to the ones in females at the respective age. <italic>Rpl13a</italic> was used as a housekeeping gene. Relative gene expression was calculated using the ΔΔCT method. Student’s or Welch’s t-tests were computed to determine significant changes in gene expression. Horizontal line represents median. Whiskers show min. to max. values. (<bold>D,E,F</bold>) Schematic representation of the <italic>mitfa</italic> (<bold>D</bold>), <italic>ltk</italic> (<bold>E</bold>), and <italic>csf1ra</italic> (<bold>F</bold>) loci in <italic>N. furzeri</italic>. One sgRNA was designed per gene targeting a sequence part in exon 6 of <italic>mitfa</italic>, exon 22 of <italic>ltk,</italic> and exon 9 of <italic>csf1ra</italic>. Recognition sites for restriction enzymes (<italic>mitfa: EcoRI</italic>, <italic>ltk: EcoNI</italic>, <italic>csf1ra: NcoI</italic>) directly upstream of the respective PAM sequence were used to check for the presence of mutations. (<bold>G</bold>) Injection mold stamp designed for the preparation of plates for microinjections. Using this mold, single slots were generated on an agarose plate that stabilizes and holds freshly fertilized <italic>N. furzeri</italic> eggs for microinjections (Picture showing oocyte injection was kindly provided by Annekatrin Richter, FLI Jena). (<bold>H</bold>) One day after injection (dpi), injected eggs (n=591) were screened for the presence of a GFP signal. 36% of injected eggs were GFP-positive (n=211), 30% were GFP-negative (n=179), and 34% were dead (n=201).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s1sdata1"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Gene expression data, genomic loci and microinjection.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig1-figsupp1-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig1-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Analyzing the <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> loci upon simultaneous injection of three single guide RNAs (sgRNAs).</title><p>(<bold>A–C</bold>) Restriction enzyme digests to analyze the presence of mutations in <italic>mitfa</italic> (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>ltk</italic> (<bold>B</bold>), and <italic>csf1ra</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) of eight randomly selected GFP-positive and six randomly selected GFP-negative embryos as well as a wild-type control. Non-cleaved products (<italic>mitfa</italic>: 956 bp, <italic>ltk</italic>: 1.105 bp, <italic>csf1ra</italic>: 926 bp) indicated the presence of a mutation in the respective locus. The occurrence of two smaller products (<italic>mitfa</italic>: 383 bp +573 bp, <italic>ltk</italic>: 276 bp +829 bp, <italic>csf1ra</italic>: 300 bp +625 bp) indicated the presence of the wild-type sequence. (<bold>D</bold>) Based on restriction enzyme digests, the occurrence of mutations in the <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> locus of 85 F<sub>0</sub> fish were analyzed. All fish (85/85) carried a mutation in <italic>mitfa</italic> (mosaic: 51.8%; biallelic: 48.2%), <italic>ltk</italic> (mosaic: 32.9%; biallelic: 67.1%), and <italic>csf1ra</italic> (mosaic: 76.5%; biallelic: 23.5%).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s2sdata1"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Control digest and mutation frequencies in F0 fish.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig1-figsupp2-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig1-figsupp2-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Analyzing the <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> loci in animals of the F<sub>1</sub> and F<sub>2</sub> generation.</title><p>(<bold>A–C</bold>) Via sequencing, indel mutations were identified in <italic>mitfa</italic> (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>ltk</italic> (<bold>B</bold>), and <italic>csf1ra</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) of F<sub>1</sub> fish, originating from an outcross of F<sub>0</sub> animals with wild-type fish. CLUSTALW was employed for sequence alignments. Each line represents one fish. Deletions are indicated by dashed lines. The sequence part targeted by the respective single guide RNA (sgRNA) is underlined. (<bold>D</bold>) Phenotypic analysis of F<sub>2</sub> embryos, resulting from an incross of two triple heterozygous (<italic>mitfa<sup>+/-</sup></italic>, <italic>ltk<sup>+/-</sup></italic>, <italic>csf1ra<sup>+/-</sup></italic>) fish. The absence of melanophores was detected in embryos #1 and #3. In contrast, melanophores were present in embryos #2 and #4. (<bold>E</bold>) Restriction enzyme digests to analyze the presence of mutations in <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> of 10 randomly selected F<sub>2</sub> embryos. Non-cleaved products (<italic>mitfa</italic>: 956 bp, <italic>ltk</italic>: 1.105 bp, <italic>csf1ra</italic>: 926 bp) indicated the presence of a mutation in the respective locus. Occurrence of two smaller products (<italic>mitfa</italic>: 383 bp +573 bp, <italic>ltk</italic>: 276 bp +829 bp, <italic>csf1ra</italic>: 300 bp +626 bp) indicated the presence of the wild-type sequence. (<bold>F</bold>) Assessment of genotypes based on the results from the restriction enzyme digests. Embryo #10 showed a homozygous mutation in all three analyzed loci (<italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>ltk<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>csf1ra<sup>-/-</sup></italic>).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s3sdata1"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Sequencing results, images of F2 embryos and control digests.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig1-figsupp3-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig1-figsupp3-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>To simultaneously inactivate <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic>, we injected <italic>Cas9</italic> mRNA, the three different sgRNAs, and <italic>GFP</italic> mRNA into one-cell-stage embryos of the long-lived <italic>N. furzeri</italic> strain MZCS-08/122 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Dorn et al., 2011</xref>). <italic>GFP</italic> mRNA was used to identify properly injected embryos one day after the injection. An injection mold, stabilizing the eggs during the injection procedure, has already been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Harel et al., 2016</xref>). To further improve the injection procedure, we developed a new type of injection mold having single slots for each embryo. Moreover, the wall of these slots pointing towards the direction of the injection needle is sloped facilitating the access of the needle to the egg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1G</xref>). Using this injection mold, we were able to inject close to 600 embryos within two days, which were sorted for a GFP signal one day post-injection. One-third of each of the embryos were GFP-positive, GFP-negative, or dead (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1H</xref>). Seven days after injection, GFP-positive eggs were transferred onto coconut coir plates, mimicking the dry phase <italic>N. furzeri</italic> eggs undergo in their natural habitat. Since it is possible to detect melanophores already in embryos, GFP-positive and GFP-negative embryos were phenotypically analyzed. While melanophores were clearly detected in GFP-negative embryos, a reduction or an almost complete loss of melanophores was observed on the head and along the body axis in a fraction of GFP-positive embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). Iridophores and xanthophores are not detectable at this stage of development.</p><p>In order to analyze if the sgRNAs targeting <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> had induced mutations, regions around the expected mutation sites were amplified via PCR using DNA extracts from eight randomly selected GFP-positive and six GFP-negative embryos. Those amplicons were used in restriction enzyme digests to determine the presence of mutations. For all three genes, we observed a non-cleaved PCR fragment in all samples of GFP-positive embryos, suggesting that mutations had been introduced that made the amplicons resistant to restriction enzyme digest. The analysis of mutations in the <italic>mitfa</italic> sequence revealed, that 75% (6/8) of the GFP-positive samples only showed one undigested fragment, whereas 25% (2/8) were mosaic, since they also showed two additional fragments that only occur in the presence of the wild-type sequence. For <italic>ltk</italic>, we observed mosaicism in 37.5% of embryos (3/8) and for <italic>csf1ra</italic> in 87.5% (7/8) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A–C</xref>). For the GFP-negative embryos, we identified digested fragments in all samples, as in the respective wild-type controls. However, the first two GFP-negative embryos also showed non-cleaved fragments, indicating the presence of mutations. This suggests that the sorting into GFP-positive and GFP-negative embryos are not fully stringent.</p><p>Next, we hatched and raised GFP-positive embryos from the F<sub>0</sub> generation. Compared to wild-type larvae and adult animals, most fish from the F<sub>0</sub> generation of successfully injected eggs showed a mosaic loss of pigment cells. However, in some of the fish we already observed an almost complete loss of pigment cells, resulting in the transparency of the animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E–J</xref>). This already allowed us to have a clear view of inner organs. At an age of 25 days post-hatching (dph), the stomach in those transparent fish showed an orange color due to nauplii of artemia, small crustaceans, which are used as food at this age. Moreover, the swim bladder and in females the ovaries were clearly visible. We also observed the blood flow in the cardinal vein and in the small vessels of the caudal fin. Additionally, we identified single follicles including lipid droplets in the ovaries. Besides this phenotypical analysis of fish from the F<sub>0</sub> generation, we also analyzed the mutation rates. Based on results from the previously mentioned restriction analysis, we observed that all 85 fish had a mutation in <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra,</italic> at least in a mosaic fashion. Moreover, this analysis revealed that already in the F<sub>0</sub> generation biallelic mutations were observed (<italic>mitfa</italic>: 48.2%, <italic>ltk</italic>: 67.1%, <italic>csf1ra</italic>: 23.5%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2D</xref>). These data indicate a high efficiency of the CRISPR/Cas9 tool in <italic>N. furzeri</italic> and show that it is possible to simultaneously induce mutations in three genes of interest.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Generation of a stable, transparent killifish line</title><p>For the generation of a stable, transparent <italic>N. furzeri</italic> line and to reduce potential off-target effects, we performed an outcross of selected F<sub>0</sub> fish with wild-type animals. As expected, all of the obtained F<sub>1</sub> progeny showed a normal pigmentation pattern and hence were phenotypically not distinguishable from wild-type animals. To assess the presence of mutations, we extracted DNA from fin biopsies for genotyping. Among 60 analyzed fish, 14 animals were triple-heterozygous (<italic>mitfa<sup>+/-</sup>, ltk<sup>+/-</sup>, csf1ra<sup>+/-</sup></italic>). The targeted loci in those fish were analyzed via sequencing. Various deletion mutations were detected, but two fish carried the same mutation at the <italic>mitfa</italic> (Δ11 bp), <italic>ltk</italic> (Δ4 bp), and <italic>csf1ra</italic> (Δ5 bp) locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A–C</xref>). Those animals were used for a subsequent incross, from which according to the Mendelian ratio 1/64 (1.56%) of the F<sub>2</sub> offspring was expected to be triple homozygous. We first checked whether triple homozygous embryos were viable and could be detected among the F<sub>2</sub> eggs. Hence, we randomly selected embryos to assess their genotype. We observed a lack of melanophores in a proportion of embryos. Those embryos carried a homozygous mutation in <italic>mitfa</italic>, whereas embryos with only a heterozygous <italic>mitfa</italic> mutation had melanophores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3D</xref>). The genotypes for <italic>ltk</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> could only be assessed via molecular analysis at this developmental stage. Notably, one triple homozygous embryo was detected, indicating that at least until the hatching stage those embryos were viable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3E and F</xref>). We then proceeded with the hatching of F<sub>2</sub> eggs. In this generation, different genotypes were observed to result in different phenotypical appearances. Female fish with a heterozygous mutation in <italic>ltk</italic> and homozygous mutations in <italic>mitfa</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> resembled wild-type females at first glance, whereas in male fish especially the lack of xanthophores resulted in a silver-blue appearance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1K and K’</xref>). In contrast to this, the lack of melanophores and iridophores in fish with the genotype <italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>ltk<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>csf1ra <sup>+/-</sup></italic>allowed a view on inner organs, particularly in females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1L and L’</xref>). In order to increase the likelihood to obtain transparent, triple homozygous fish, we crossed two fish with the genotype <italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>ltk<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>csf1ra<sup>+/-</sup></italic>. From this cross, we genotyped 50 individuals via high-resolution melting analysis (HRMA) and identified 13 triple homozygous fish. We named the resulting transparent <italic>N. furzeri</italic> line <italic>klara</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1M and M’</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Characterization of <italic>klara</italic> animals</title><p>To assess the health and survival of the <italic>klara</italic> line, we compiled data from our fish database, in which the date of birth and date of death for every fish is recorded. The data of the wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> fish that were hatched in 2020 and 2021 comprise 546 and 159 animals, respectively. The corresponding survival curves did not show any differences between the cohorts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A</xref>). This is supported by the fact that both <italic>klara</italic> and wild-type animals score indifferently upon daily inspection of swimming, feeding, and social behavior as well as body condition, appearance, and breathing. Finally, we have quantified size and weight until 5 weeks post-hatching in both cohorts. Except for a single time point in females, there were no significant differences between the cohorts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B</xref>). These data suggest that in terms of general physiology, <italic>klara</italic> animals are not different from wild-type fish.</p><p>In zebrafish, the role of <italic>csf1ra</italic> in xanthophore development has been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Parichy et al., 2000</xref>). In addition, <italic>csf1ra</italic> is also known to play a role in the immune system, in particular in the survival, proliferation, and differentiation of monocytes and macrophage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hume et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Tagoh et al., 2002</xref>). For this reason, we wondered whether the inactivation of <italic>csf1ra</italic> has an effect on the immune cell population of <italic>klara</italic>. Since the kidney is the primary hematopoietic organ in teleost fish, we analyzed the whole kidney marrow (WKM) of fish with homozygous mutations in <italic>mitfa</italic> and <italic>ltk</italic>, which had in addition either no mutation, a heterozygous or a homozygous mutation in <italic>csf1ra</italic>. Based on a published gating strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Sanz-Morejón et al., 2019</xref>), we identified four subpopulations in the WKM of <italic>N. furzeri</italic> using flow cytometry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1C and D</xref>). The strongest <italic>csf1ra</italic> expression was detected in the myeloid cell population, which contains macrophages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). Comparing the number of immune cells in the three sub-populations, we did not observe any differences among the <italic>csf1ra</italic> genotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Characterization of <italic>klara</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Expression of <italic>csf1ra</italic> was analyzed via RT-PCR using cDNA from FACS-sorted populations of lymphocytes, progenitors, and myeloid cells obtained from the whole kidney marrow (WKM) of a wild-type <italic>N. furzeri. Csf1ra</italic> was detected in all subpopulations, most strongly in myeloid cells. As a negative control, an RT-sample (no reverse transcriptase during cDNA synthesis) was used to exclude contaminations with genomic DNA. As loading control, <italic>rpl13a</italic> was used. (<bold>B</bold>) Comparison of cell numbers in the different subpopulations of the WKM of fish with the following genotypes: <italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup>, ltk<sup>-/-</sup>, csf1ra<sup>+/+</sup></italic> (n=2), <italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup>, ltk<sup>-/-</sup>, csf1ra<sup>+/-</sup></italic> (n=4), and <italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup>, ltk<sup>-/-</sup>, csf1ra<sup>-/-</sup></italic> (n=4). One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s post hoc test did not reveal any significant differences. Horizontal line represents median. Whiskers show min. to max. value. (<bold>C,C’</bold>) Male <italic>klara</italic> fish (<bold>C</bold>) showed an appearance of melanophores on fin appendages, which was not observed in females (<bold>C’). (D,D’</bold>) Occurrence of melanophores intensified with age resulting in black fins in male fish (<bold>D</bold>). In female <italic>klara</italic> animals (<bold>D’</bold>) black fins were not observed.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata1"><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>PCR, FACS analysis of the WKM and images of klara fish.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig2-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig2-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Characterization of <italic>klara</italic> fish.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The lifespan of wild-type (MZCS-08/122, n=546) and <italic>klara</italic> (n=159) fish did not differ (p: 0.1353). The median lifespan (50% survival) was 200 days for wild-type fish and 213 days for <italic>klara</italic> animals. The maximum lifespan (10% survival) was 311 days in wild-types and 305 days in <italic>klara</italic>. Lifespan curves were analyzed via a Log-rank test for statistical differences. (<bold>B</bold>) Analysis of body size and weight in male and female wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> fish at the age of 7 (n<sub>WT_male</sub> = 10, n<sub>WT_female</sub> = 5, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_male</sub> = 7, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_female</sub> = 9), 14 (n<sub>WT_male</sub> = 9, n<sub>WT_female</sub> = 3, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_male</sub> = 7, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_female</sub> = 5), 21 (n<sub>WT_male</sub> = 7, n<sub>WT_female</sub> = 3, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_male</sub> = 4, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_female</sub> = 6), 28 (n<sub>WT_male</sub> = 5, n<sub>WT_female</sub> = 5, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_male</sub> = 5, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_female</sub> = 4) and 35 (n<sub>WT_male</sub> = 5, n<sub>WT_female</sub> = 5, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_male</sub> = 5, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_female</sub> = 5) days post-hatching (dph). Within one age cohort, the body size and weight of wild-types and <italic>klara</italic> fish were only compared between animals of the same sex via Student’s or Welch’s t-test. Regarding size, there was no difference between wild-types and <italic>klara</italic> fish. Among male fish, there was no difference between wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> fish. Only at the age of 28 dph, female wild-type fish were significantly heavier than <italic>klara</italic> females (p: 0.014). Error bars represent standard deviation. (<bold>C,D</bold>) Forward scatter (FSC-A) versus side scatter (SSC-A) plot of the whole kidney marrow (WKM) of a <italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>ltk<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>csf1ra<sup>+/+</sup></italic> fish (<bold>C</bold>) and a <italic>mitfa<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>ltk<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>csf1ra<sup>-/-</sup></italic> fish (<bold>D</bold>).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2s1sdata1"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Lifespan data, size and weight measurements and gating strategy.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig2-figsupp1-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig2-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>During the raising of <italic>klara</italic> fish, we observed that around the age of approximately four weeks, i.e., at the time of sexual maturation, melanophores appeared in male fish, in particular on fin appendages. However, this was not detected in female <italic>klara</italic> fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C and C’</xref>). With age, the melanophores spread over the whole fins and resulted e.g., in a fully black caudal fin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D and D’</xref>). This, however, did not interfere with the overall body transparency of <italic>klara</italic> animals.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Males and females prefer pigmented mating partners</title><p>Besides its role as camouflage, protection from UV damage, or for recognition, body pigmentation also plays an important role in the choice of mating partners. We investigated whether the lack of body pigmentation affects the breeding behavior of <italic>klara</italic> fish. We set up three breeding groups consisting of one <italic>klara</italic> male and two <italic>klara</italic> females, at the age of 14 weeks, which had never been used for breeding before. <italic>Klara</italic> fish showed a normal mating behavior, whereby the male uses its caudal fin to push the female into the sand and thus induces egg laying (<xref ref-type="video" rid="fig3video1">Figure 3—video 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig3video2">Figure 3—video 2</xref>). We also assessed the quantity and quality of collected eggs, which did not differ from wild-type fish, so that we could maintain the <italic>klara</italic> line in a triple homozygous state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). Thus, <italic>klara</italic> and wild-type females do not show a difference in fecundity. To assess the role of body pigmentation for mate choice in killifish, we set up different combinations of breeding trios consisting of wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> fish, thus that a wild-type or a <italic>klara</italic> animal of each sex had the choice between a wild-type or a <italic>klara</italic> animal of the other sex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). For each of the four combinations, we analyzed three tanks. Fish were put together and a sand box, which is required for egg deposition, was put into the tank. After 10 days the sand box was removed for the following two days. Subsequently, the box was added again and for the following four weeks, we collected eggs once per week for further analysis. To identify who produced the egg or who had fertilized it, we determined the genotype of the fertilized eggs by HRMA. We observed that in the presence of a <italic>klara</italic> and a wild-type female fish, irrespective of whether the male was a wild-type or a <italic>klara</italic> animal, approximately 75% of fertilized eggs originated from the wild-type female (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). This indicated that both <italic>klara</italic> and wild-type males showed a preference for the pigmented wild-type female. This mate choice was not influenced by size or weight, since both parameters were not statistically different between wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). Similarly, in the breeding groups, in which a <italic>klara</italic> and a wild-type male were present, more than 90% of eggs were fertilized by the wild-type male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). Again, wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> males did not show a difference in size, although <italic>klara</italic> males had less weight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). Taken together, this competitive breeding experiments indicated that pigmented fish were the preferred mating partner for both sexes.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Pigmented fish are preferred mating partners.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) For the analysis of egg quantity, eggs were collected once per week for four weeks (coll. #1–4) from wild-type (n=3 tanks with one male and two females each) and <italic>klara</italic> (n=3 tanks with one male and two females each) fish. To assess egg quality, the number of alive eggs stored on coconut coir plates was determined one-week post-collection (wpc). Student's or Welch's t-tests were computed revealing no significant differences regarding egg quantity and quality. Error bars represent standard deviation. (<bold>B</bold>) Collected eggs obtained from breeding groups with a wild-type female and a <italic>klara</italic> female and either a wild-type male (group #1) or a <italic>klara</italic> male (group #2) were genotyped via HRMA. As a mating partner, male fish preferred wild-type females (group #1: 76.2%; group #2: 75.1%) over <italic>klara</italic> females (group #1: 23.8%; group #2: 24.9%). In the presence of a wild-type male and a <italic>klara</italic> male and either a wild-type female (group #3) or a <italic>klara</italic> female (group #4) the majority of analyzed eggs were fertilized by the wild-type male (group #3: 97.6%; group #4: 90.9%). (<bold>C</bold>) Within the same sex, wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> fish did not differ in size(n<sub>WT_male</sub> = 9 n<sub>WT_female</sub> = 9, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_male</sub> = 9, n<italic><sub>klara</sub></italic><sub>_female</sub> = 8). Wild-type males were significantly heavier than <italic>klara</italic> males (p: 0.0009). Student’s or Welch’s t-tests were computed to determine differences in size or weight. Error bars represent standard deviation.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata1"><label>Figure 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Egg quantity and quality data, genotyping of eggs and size and weight measurements.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig3-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig3-v3.tif"/></fig><media mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig3-video1.mp4" id="fig3video1"><label>Figure 3—video 1.</label><caption><title>Mating of wild-type <italic>N. furzeri</italic> animals.</title></caption></media><media mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig3-video2.mp4" id="fig3video2"><label>Figure 3—video 2.</label><caption><title>Mating of <italic>N. furzeri klara</italic> animals.</title></caption></media></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title><italic>Klara</italic> fish can serve as a platform for further genetic manipulation</title><p>The simultaneous inactivation of <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> resulted in a loss of body pigmentation, however, the eyes were still normally pigmented (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Transparent zebrafish from the <italic>casper</italic> line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">White et al., 2008</xref>) also still have pigmented eyes, while fish of the fully transparent <italic>crystal</italic> line lack those pigments. This was achieved via an inactivation of the <italic>slc45a2</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Antinucci and Hindges, 2016</xref>). To get rid of retinal pigmentation in <italic>klara</italic> animals we designed a sgRNA targeting the <italic>slc45a2</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>). We first tested this sgRNA in one-cell stage eggs from the wild-type strain. Compared to GFP-negative embryos, we observed a loss of pigmentation in the eye of GFP-positive embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). Notably, also the appearance of melanophores on the head and body of those embryos was reduced. This phenotypical analysis indicated the inactivation of <italic>slc45a2</italic>, which was subsequently confirmed via restriction enzyme digest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref>). We then performed microinjections using the sgRNA targeting <italic>slc45a2</italic> into <italic>klara</italic> one-cell stage embryos and hatched F<sub>0</sub> fish (n=7). Besides the transparent body, the black pigmentation of the eye was absent, while we still observed a silver-pigmented ring around the eye of the animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). The presence of a mutation in the <italic>slc45a2</italic> locus of all seven F<sub>0</sub> fish was confirmed via restriction enzyme digest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1C</xref>). Subsequently, we performed an outcross of F<sub>0</sub> fish with <italic>klara</italic> and identified the presence of various indel mutations in F<sub>1</sub> offspring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1D and E</xref>). This experiment showed that the <italic>klara</italic> line can serve as a platform for further genetic manipulations.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Partial loss of eye pigmentation.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Despite the inactivation of three genes involved in pigmentation, the eye pigmentation did not differ between <italic>klara</italic> and wild-type fish. (<bold>B</bold>) Targeting the <italic>slc45a2</italic> locus in wild-types resulted in a reduction of melanophores in the eye, but also on the whole body of injected embryos compared to wild-type controls. (<bold>C</bold>) A loss of melanophores in the retinal pigmented epithelium was observed in F<sub>0</sub> fish upon a microinjection of the sgRNA targeting <italic>slc45a2</italic> in <italic>klara</italic> embryos. A silver-pigmented ring around the eye was still present. (ctrl: control; dpi: days post-injection; dph: days post-hatching).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata1"><label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Images of embryos and fish.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig4-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig4-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Inactivation of the <italic>slc45a2</italic> locus.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of the <italic>slc45a2</italic> locus in <italic>N. furzeri</italic>. A sgRNA was designed to target a sequence part in exon 1. The <italic>HypCH4III</italic> recognition site upstream of the PAM sequence allowed checking for the presence of mutations via restriction enzyme digest. (<bold>B</bold>) All GFP-positive embryos (5/5) from microinjections of the <italic>slc45a2</italic> sgRNA into wild-type oocytes showed the presence of a non-cleaved fragment (652 bp) indicating the presence of a mutation. Cleaved fragments (152 bp +500 bp) were detected in uninjected and wild-type control samples. (<bold>C</bold>) Analyzing seven hatched F<sub>0</sub> animals via restriction enzyme digest revealed the presence of mutations in all (7/7) fish indicated by the non-cleaved product. One fish (#3) did not show the additional cleaved fragments (152 bp +500 bp) indicating a biallelic mutation in <italic>slc45a2</italic>. (<bold>D</bold>) Mutations in <italic>slc45a2</italic> were present in 27/31 F<sub>1</sub> fish originating from the outcross of an F<sub>0</sub> animal with a wild-type fish. (<bold>E</bold>) Various indel mutations were identified in F<sub>1</sub> fish via sequencing. CLUSTALW was used for sequence alignments, in which each line represents one fish. Deletions are indicated by dashed lines. The sequence part targeted by the used sgRNA is underlined.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s1sdata1"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>slc45a2 locus, control digests and sequencing results.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig4-figsupp1-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig4-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Generation of an <italic>in vivo</italic> senescence reporter</title><p>The accumulation of senescent cells is one of the hallmarks of the aging process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">López-Otín et al., 2013</xref>). We wanted to take advantage of the transparent <italic>klara</italic> line and generate a senescence reporter line. To this end, we inserted a reporter construct, consisting of a <italic>GFP</italic> and <italic>nitroreductase</italic> (<italic>NTR</italic>) cassette into the <italic>cdkn1a</italic> (<italic>p21</italic>) locus of <italic>klara</italic> via homology-directed repair (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). The <italic>cdkn1a</italic> gene is a senescence marker and upregulated in old killifish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Graf et al., 2013</xref>). With this reporter/NTR cassette, <italic>cdkn1a</italic> expressing cells can be labeled via GFP and can also be ablated via the NTR/Mtz system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Curado et al., 2007</xref>). To facilitate HDR, we added flanking arms of 903 bp and 901 bp on the 5’ and 3’ ends of the construct, respectively. Since it has been reported that 5’-modifications of double-stranded donor templates increase HDR efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Ghanta et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Gutierrez-Triana et al., 2018</xref>), we amplified the template using biotinylated oligonucleotides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). Subsequently, we performed microinjections into one-cell stage <italic>klara</italic> eggs using an injection solution with a sgRNA that induces a DNA double-strand break in close proximity to the intended insertion site and the biotinylated HDR donor template. In 1 out of 16 randomly selected GFP-positive (i.e. successfully injected) embryos, we detected the presence of the reporter cassette. Its proper insertion was verified via sequencing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A</xref>). We subsequently set up the remaining GFP-positive embryos for hatching and detected three fish with a proper insertion among 19 F<sub>0</sub> animals. To verify the proper insertion of the <italic>GFP/ntr</italic> cassette into the genome of <italic>klara</italic> animals and for subsequent genotyping, we employed PCR using two different pairs of primers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>CRISPR/Cas9-mediated insertion of a reporter construct.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The <italic>cdkn1a</italic> locus in <italic>klara</italic> was targeted via CRISPR/Cas9 to insert a reporter construct consisting of a GFP and an NTR cassette, separated by P2A self-cleavage sites, allowing the detection and ablation of senescent cells. (<bold>B</bold>) A 5’-biotinylated, double-stranded donor template flanked by two ~0.9 kb flanking arms was used for the target-specific insertion. (<bold>C,D</bold>) Function of the reporter construct was tested by exposing embryos (<italic>cdkn1a<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic>) to a γ-irradiation dose of 10 Gy. Representative images taken before irradiation showed autofluorescence originating from the yolk, which was observed in embryos of both genotypes (<bold>C</bold>). 24 hr post-irradiation (hpi), the presence of GFP-positive cells was detected only in <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic> embryos (<bold>D</bold>). (<bold>E</bold>) Gene expression analysis of <italic>cdkn1a</italic> in embryos (<italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic>) at 24 (n=12) and 48 hpi (n=12) compared to non-irradiated controls (n=6). Expression of <italic>cdkn1a</italic> increased significantly as revealed by Student's t-test (p<sub>24hpi</sub>: 0.011, p<sub>48hpi</sub>: 0.0004). (<bold>F,G</bold>) For the expression of <italic>GFP</italic> (<bold>F</bold>) and <italic>ntr</italic> (<bold>G</bold>) at 24 (n=8) and 48 hpi (n=6) compared to non-irradiated controls (n=2), <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>+/+</sup></italic> embryos were excluded due to the absence of the reporter construct. Expressions of <italic>GFP</italic> and <italic>ntr</italic> were significantly increased at 48 hpi (p<italic><sub>GFP</sub></italic>: 0.045, p<italic><sub>ntr</sub></italic>: 0.006) compared to controls. For all qRT-PCRs, <italic>rpl13a</italic> was used as a housekeeping gene. Relative gene expression was calculated using the ΔΔCT method. Student’s t-tests were computed to determine significant changes in gene expression. Error bars represent standard deviation. (<bold>H</bold>) Detection of GFP-positive cells in the liver of a young (4 wph) and an old (30 wph) <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> fish. A higher number of GFP<sup>+</sup> cells was detected in the old liver sample. Images are displayed as extended depth of focus projections. In the young liver tissue, small individual GFP-positive cells were detected, whereas in the old liver, a high prevalence of enlarged GFP-positive cells was identified (see zoom-in). (<bold>I</bold>) Analysis of kidney samples via flow cytometry from <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> fish at the age of 4.5 wph (n<sub>male</sub> = 5; n<sub>female</sub> = 4), 9.5 wph (n<sub>male</sub> = 5; n<sub>female</sub> = 5) and 20.5 wph (n<sub>male</sub> = 4; n<sub>female</sub> = 5). A significantly higher proportion of GFP-positive cells was detected in 20.5 wph versus 4.5 wph (p: 0.0009) and 9.5 wph (p: 0.0084) fish. One-Way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s post hoc test was computed to analyze for differences in cell number. Horizontal line shows mean value. Error bars represent standard deviation. (<bold>J–M</bold>) Representative images from light sheet microscopy show the presence of GFP-positive cells in living <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> fish (<bold>K, M</bold>) at 4 dph (<bold>K</bold>) and 17 dph (<bold>M</bold>). The panel displays representative 3D reconstructions from stacks of 31 (<bold>J,L</bold>) and 372 (<bold>K,M</bold>) optical slices. <italic>Klara</italic> fish at the same ages (<bold>J,L</bold>), which do not have any GFP + cells, were used as controls. The image processing settings for the <italic>klara</italic> fish were adjusted to make the background fluorescence visible in order to create comparable image pairs. While a high number of GFP-positive cells was present in the dorsal fin area of <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> fish at the age of 17 dph (<bold>M</bold>), only one cell (marked by the white arrowhead) was detected in the dorsal developing fin of the younger <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> animal (<bold>K</bold>).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata1"><label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label><caption><title>cdkn1a locus, images of embryos, gene expression data, immunofluorescence stainings, FACS analysis and images obtained by light sheet microscopy.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig5-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig5-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Analysis of embryos from the senescence reporter line.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Identification of the reporter constructs integration into the <italic>cdkn1a</italic> locus via PCR. A primer pair combination was selected in which one oligonucleotide binding site was located within the <italic>cdkn1a</italic> locus but outside of the sequence that was covered by the homology arm and the other one binding within the insert. In 1 out of 16 randomly selected GFP-positive embryos an amplicon indicating the insertion of the construct was detected. Proper insertion, i.e., lack of the endogenous STOP codon followed by the presence of the <italic>P2A-GFP-P2A-NTR</italic> sequence was verified via sequencing of the PCR amplicon. (<bold>B</bold>) Two primer pair combinations were used to verify the presence of the reporter constructs in the <italic>cdkn1a</italic> locus. Besides the primer pair combination described in (<bold>A</bold>) (black arrows; expected amplicon size: 1497 bp), the alternative primer pair (blue arrows) was used in addition to distinguish between <italic>cdkn1a<sup>+/+</sup></italic>, <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic>, and <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> animals. In the presence of a wild-type allele, an amplicon at the size of 393 bp was expected. The insertion of the reporter cassette caused an increase in the fragment size to 1893 bp. In <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic> fish, both amplicons were detected.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5s1sdata1"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Genotyping PCRs and sequencing results.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig5-figsupp1-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig5-figsupp1-v3.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Characterization of the senescence reporter line.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Workflow of the reporter construct activity test via γ-irradiation (10 Gy) in embryos (<italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic>). The image was created with biorender.com. (<bold>B</bold>) Experimental setup to test the NTR/Mtz system in primary cells (fibroblasts) isolated from a <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> fish. The image was created with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorender.com/">BioRender</ext-link>. (<bold>C</bold>) The expression of <italic>cdkn1a</italic>, <italic>gfp,</italic> and <italic>ntr</italic> was analyzed in irradiated and non-irradiated cells upon Mtz treatment (50 µM). For all qRT-PCRs, <italic>rpl13a</italic> was used as a housekeeping gene. Gene expression (relative to non-irradiated, DMSO-treated cells) was calculated using the ΔΔCT method. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s post hoc test did not reveal any significant differences in gene expression. Horizontal line represents median. Whiskers show min. to max. values.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5s2sdata1"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Schematic presentation of workflows and gene expression data.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig5-figsupp2-data1-v3.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig5-figsupp2-v3.tif"/></fig><media mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig5-video1.mp4" id="fig5video1"><label>Figure 5—video 1.</label><caption><title>This movie represents the z-stacks of optical slices from which the 3D projections of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5K</xref> were generated.</title><p>Microscopy has been done using a light sheet microscope and a 4-day-old <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> animal.</p></caption></media><media mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4" xlink:href="elife-81549-fig5-video2.mp4" id="fig5video2"><label>Figure 5—video 2.</label><caption><title>This movie represents the z-stacks of optical slices from which the 3D projections of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5M</xref> were generated.</title><p>Microscopy has been done using a light sheet microscope and a 17-day-old <italic>klara;cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> animal.</p></caption></media></fig-group><p>Next, we performed an outcross of the F<sub>0</sub> animals with <italic>klara</italic> fish. To assess whether the reporter was functional, the obtained F<sub>1</sub> embryos were exposed to a γ–irradiation dosage of 10 Gy. This should induce DNA damage and lead to the activation of TP53 and up-regulation of <italic>cdkn1a</italic>. To analyze, whether the up-regulated <italic>cdkn1a</italic> expression is linked to an up-regulation of <italic>GFP</italic>, we analyzed the embryos 1 hr before as well as 24 hr post irradiation (hpi) via fluorescence microscopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2A</xref>). Before irradiation, autofluorescence originating from the yolk was observed in <italic>cdkn1a<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic> embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). In contrast, at 24 hpi we observed GFP-positive cells in the optic tectum and other parts of the developing brain and fin buds of <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic> embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>). Gene expression analysis revealed an upregulation of endogenous <italic>cdkn1a</italic> as well as both <italic>GFP</italic> and <italic>ntr</italic> expression upon γ–irradiation in <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic> embryos, which further significantly increased at 48 hpi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E–G</xref>). Thus, we were able to insert a functional 1.5 kb reporter cassette into the <italic>cdkn1a</italic> locus of <italic>klara</italic> fish.</p><p>To verify the functionality of the <italic>nitroreductase</italic> gene, we employed cell culture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2B</xref>). We isolated skin cells from adult fish of the <italic>cdkn1a</italic>-reporter <italic>klara</italic> line. Several weeks after the primary cells had been taken in culture, they were treated with 50 µM metronidazole (Mtz) and subsequently exposed to 10 Gy γ–irradiation. After another 24 hr cells were harvested, and RNA was isolated and analyzed by qRT-PCR. We observed a consistent upregulation of <italic>cdkn1a</italic>, <italic>GFP</italic> as well as <italic>ntr</italic> upon irradiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2C</xref>). This upregulation was reversed by Mtz treatment. Although the data did not reach statistical significance, these results suggest that the <italic>ntr</italic> cassette is functional and leads to the decay of cells upon Mtz application.</p><p>After the initial characterization of the <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic> embryos, we raised them to adulthood and generated F<sub>2</sub> offspring. Subsequently, we used immunofluorescence and flow cytometry to detect and quantify the occurrence of GFP<sup>+</sup> cells and their potential accumulation upon aging. As organs for analysis, we selected liver and kidneys from young and old <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> animals. Staining for GFP revealed many more GFP<sup>+</sup> cells in the liver of a 30-weeks-old <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> fish than in a 4-weeks-old animal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5H</xref>). Of note, GFP<sup>+</sup> cells in older tissue were larger and often appeared clustered as opposed to smaller and scattered GFP<sup>+</sup> cells in young tissue. Using FACS, we detected a significant increase of GFP<sup>+</sup> cells in 20.5-weeks-old kidneys, compared to 4.5-and 9.5-weeks-old animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5I</xref>).</p><p>Finally, we performed light sheet microscopy on the dorsal fin area of live <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup> klara</italic> fish at 4 dph (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5K</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig5video1">Figure 5—video 1</xref>) and 17 dph (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5M</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="fig5video2">Figure 5—video 2</xref>) with <italic>klara</italic> animals as controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5J and L</xref>). While a significant number of GFP-positive cells was detected at the older stage, only a single cell was observed in the 4-days-old animal. These data suggest that the reporter that we have generated can be used to monitor <italic>cdkn1a (p21)-</italic>positive cells <italic>in vivo</italic> and that these cells accumulate upon aging.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Here, we report the generation of a transparent killifish line that is lacking melanophores, iridophores, and xanthophores. Based on published literature, we have selected the three genes <italic>mitfa</italic>, <italic>ltk,</italic> and <italic>csf1ra</italic> as targets for CRISPR/Cas9-mediated inactivation in <italic>N. furzeri (</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Lister et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lopes et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Parichy et al., 2000</xref>). We employed a single injection with three sgRNAs that had been pre-selected and characterized. The observation that some of the injected F<sub>0</sub> embryos showed a complete loss of melanophores demonstrated that the CRISPR/Cas9 system acts very efficiently in <italic>N. furzeri</italic>. This has been observed before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Harel et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Oginuma et al., 2022</xref>) and is most likely explained by the long duration of the one-cell stage in this species of 2–3 hr during which Cas9 can act (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dolfi et al., 2014</xref>). Cas9 efficiency was further confirmed by the fact that for all three genes, both alleles were inactivated in the F<sub>0</sub> animals, many of which showed an almost complete transparency. This efficiency is comparable to the one reported for zebrafish, whereby a codon-optimized Cas9 protein was employed to target a reporter transgene and four endogenous loci. In this case, mutagenesis rates reached 75–99% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jao et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>The <italic>klara</italic> animals did not show any anomalies regarding general health, lifespan, phenotype, and behavior and could be bred to homozygosity and kept as a stable line. While <italic>klara</italic> animals were initially fully transparent, male animals developed black pigments, particularly on fin appendages, which increased during their lifespan. While the re-appearance of pigmentation in male fin appendages limits the application of this line in the adult stages, it suggests that there is a second, <italic>mitfa</italic>-independent population of melanophores in killifish that appears in later life. In zebrafish, it has been shown that the paralogous gene, <italic>mitfb</italic> might fulfill this role by activating <italic>tyrosinase</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Lister et al., 2001</xref>). Whether or not this is also the case in killifish and whether <italic>mitfb</italic> might also be responsible for the remaining pigmentation in the retina remains to be determined. By inactivating <italic>slc45a2</italic> in <italic>klara</italic> fish, we obtained animals that were fully transparent regarding their body and the eye. This quadruple mutant might be particularly interesting for research on eye and retina regeneration and shows that <italic>klara</italic> animals can be used as a background for further gene inactivation.</p><p>We used the <italic>klara</italic> line for addressing mate choice in killifish. While breeding behavior was normal among <italic>klara</italic> animals, both wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> animals preferred pigmented mating partners in competitive breeding situations. Here, mate choice for pigmented partners was more pronounced in females (&gt;90%) than in males (approx. 75%). As we showed that there is no difference in fecundity between <italic>klara</italic> and wild-type females, this is most likely explained by the difference in appearance between wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> animals. This difference is much more distinct between males than between the respective females. The choice for pigmented males might also be influenced by the larger weight of wild-type males. As male mating success is driven by dominance, which is influenced by weight, it is likely that wild-type males have an advantage over <italic>klara</italic> males in getting access to females and their eggs. In this case, the strong selection for wild-type males would result from both female selection and male-dominant behavior.</p><p>Our observation is in line with an earlier report on the two-spotted gobies. In this case, males preferred to mate with more colorful females, which have bright yellow-orange bellies during the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Amundsen and Forsgren, 2001</xref>). It is very surprising that for mate choice <italic>N. furzeri</italic> seems to rely on visible cues, as their natural habitat is turbid with limited visibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Reichard and Polačik, 2019</xref>). It is tempting to speculate that mate choice in <italic>N. furzeri</italic> could also be influenced by other traits like chemical signals including pheromones.</p><p>The main motivation to generate a transparent killifish line was the possibility to perform longitudinal studies regarding aging and regeneration and to be able to observe respective processes in real-time without having to sacrifice cohorts of animals at distinct time points. One of the hallmarks of aging is the accumulation of senescent cells that are characterized by the expression of specific markers including <italic>cdkn1a (p21</italic>) and <italic>cdkn2a (p16</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">López-Otín et al., 2013</xref>). It is still a matter of debate whether senescent cells limit or extend lifespan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Grosse et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">van Deursen, 2014</xref>). To visualize and address the role of senescent cells, we have integrated a cassette encompassing a fluorescence reporter as well as a nitroreductase allele into the <italic>cdkn1a</italic> locus of <italic>klara</italic> animals. The respective HDR template was flanked by 0.9 kb homology arms and carried biotinylated 5’-ends, as those modifications of double-stranded DNA donor templates have been reported to increase HDR efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Ghanta et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Gutierrez-Triana et al., 2018</xref>). Out of 35 injected embryos, four showed proper integration of the construct, corresponding to 11%. At least three F<sub>0</sub> animals passed on the engineered allele to the next generation. Our analysis of <italic>klara</italic> embryos harboring the <italic>GFP</italic> allele in the <italic>cdkn1a</italic> locus had shown that the integrated reporter is functional and can be activated upon γ-irradiation. The characterization of respective adult animals demonstrated an accumulation of GFP<sup>+</sup> cells with age, as determined by flow cytometry, immunofluorescence, and <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging. Whether those cells are truly senescent cells remains to be determined. Since the reporter also encompasses an <italic>ntr</italic> allele, it shall be possible to ablate the GFP<sup>+</sup> and thus presumably senescent cells by administration of metronidazole, a prodrug that is converted to a cytotoxic agent by NTR. With the transparent senescence reporter line, it will be possible to further characterize the function of senescent cells in development, aging, and regeneration. The generation of additional reporters into different loci, e.g., <italic>cdkn2a/b</italic> or other senescent markers will also allow addressing the possible heterogeneity of senescent cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Cohn et al., 2023</xref>).</p><p>We consider the <italic>klara</italic> fish that we describe here a valuable and versatile tool for research on aging, regeneration, and behavior. This fish line will also be beneficial for colleagues interested in cancer biology and ecology. Beyond its potential to be used for the investigation of questions in biology <italic>klara</italic> animals can also contribute to the reduction of animal numbers, an aspect that gains increasing importance in biomedical research.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Fish husbandry</title><p>All the work reported here was performed in the background of the wild-type <italic>N. furzeri</italic> strain MZCS-08/122, which is originally derived from southern Mozambique (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Dorn et al., 2011</xref>), or the <italic>klara</italic> line. Fish are kept in single-housing at 26 °C on a light:dark cycle of 12 hr each. Adult fish are fed once a day <italic>ad libitum</italic> with red mosquito larvae, whereas juvenile fish (up to 5 weeks post-hatching) are fed with nauplii of artemia twice a day. To obtain a high number of fertilized wild-type oocytes for injections, multiple breeding groups consisting of ten fish ( two males, eight females) were set up in 40 liter tanks. To obtain oocytes from <italic>klara</italic> fish, breeding groups of one male and three females were set up in tanks containing approximately 8.5 l tank water. The sand box, which is necessary for the deposition of eggs, was always removed two days before and put back into the tank 2 hr before the injection. The eggs were collected with a sieve and were then used for microinjections. The routine collection of eggs for line maintenance was done on a weekly basis. Eggs were put on coconut coir plates and stored at 29 °C.</p><p>All fish were maintained in the Nothobranchius facility of the Leibniz Institute on Aging – Fritz Lipmann Institute Jena according to the German Animal Welfare Law. All performed experiments were covered by the animal licenses FLI-17–016, FLI-20–001, and FLI-20–102, which were approved by the local authorities (Thüringer Landesamt für Verbraucherschutz).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Lifespan analysis</title><p>The data for the lifespan of wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> fish were not obtained from a dedicated lifespan experiment. Those data were extracted from our fish database (a-tune tick@lab), in which date of birth and date of death are recorded. In the shown Kaplan-Meier curve, all wild-type and <italic>klara</italic> fish that hatched in 2020 and 2021 in our facility were included. Fish, which had to be euthanized due to human endpoint criteria or died already during raising before reaching 28 dph, were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Growth and weight measurements</title><p>The assessment of body size and body weight were performed on freshly euthanized fish (wild-type and <italic>klara</italic>) at the age of 7, 14, 21, 28, and 35 days post-hatching. Fish were briefly dried with a tissue and then placed onto a scale to determine body weight. Subsequently, fish were transferred onto a petri dish and placed on a millimeter of paper to assess body length. Body length was measured from the tip of the mouth to the end of the caudal fin. Since the sex of young fish cannot be distinguished phenotypically, a fin biopsy was taken from each fish as soon as the measurements were completed. This tissue sample was used for a PCR to identify the sex. The PCR was performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Richter et al., 2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Design and synthesis of single guide RNAs (sgRNAs)</title><p>SgRNAs were designed based on the genome sequence provided by the <italic>N. furzeri</italic> Genome Browser (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reichwald et al., 2015</xref>). Target sequences for sgRNAs had a length of 20 nucleotides followed by the PAM sequence -NGG. Only sequences containing a restriction site directly upstream of the PAM sequences were selected. A TAGG-overhang was added to the 5’-end of the forward sgRNA oligonucleotide and an AAAC-overhang to the 5’-end of the reverse complementary oligonucleotide (sg_<italic>mitfa</italic>_1: 5’-TAGG-<named-content content-type="sequence">AACATCAAAAGGGAATTCAC-3</named-content>’ sg_<italic>mitfa</italic>_2: 5’-AAAC- <named-content content-type="sequence">GTGAATTCCCTTTTGATGTT-3</named-content>’, sg_<italic>ltk</italic>_1: 5’- TAGG-<named-content content-type="sequence">TGAAATGGATTTCCTGATGG-3</named-content>’ sg_<italic>ltk</italic>_2: 5’-AAAC-<named-content content-type="sequence">CCATCAGGAAATCCATTTCA-3</named-content>’, sg_<italic>csf1ra</italic>_1: 5’-TAGG-<named-content content-type="sequence">CAGAGACACTTTTTCCATGG-3</named-content>’ sg_<italic>csf1ra</italic>_2: 5’-AAAC-<named-content content-type="sequence">CCATGGAAAAAGTGTCTCTG-3</named-content>’, sg_<italic>slc45a2</italic>_1: 5’- TAGG-<named-content content-type="sequence">TGACTACTGCCGCTCACAGT-3</named-content>’ sg_<italic>slc45a2</italic>_2: 5’- AAAC-<named-content content-type="sequence">ACTGTGAGCGGCAGTAGTCA-3’</named-content>). Complementary sgRNA oligonucleotides were annealed by heating them up to 95°C followed by gradually cooling by 1°C per 30s. The annealed oligonucleotides were ligated into the <italic>BsaI</italic>-linearized pDR274 vector (Addgene, plasmid #42250). After the ligation, <italic>E. coli</italic> TOP10 cells were transformed with this vector, containing the sgRNA sequence. Isolated plasmids were checked via sequencing for the correct presence of the sgRNA sequence. Using the <italic>DraI</italic> restriction enzyme a fragment of approximately 300bp was excised from the plasmid containing the sgRNA and the T7 promoter sequence. This fragment was used as a template for the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription, which was performed according to the manufacturer’s protocol of the mMESSAGE mMACHINE T7 Transcription Kit (Thermo Scientific Inc). The quality of <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed sgRNAs was controlled via RNA agarose gel electrophoresis.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Design and synthesis of DNA donor templates for HDR</title><p>The assembly of the donor template for the insertion of a <italic>P2A-GFP-P2A-NTR</italic> cassette into the <italic>cdkn1a</italic> locus of <italic>klara</italic> was done using the <italic>NEBuilder HiFi DNA Assembly Cloning Kit. P2A</italic> sites were added to the <italic>GFP</italic> (derived from the <italic>tol2</italic> kit plasmid #395) and the <italic>NTR</italic> sequence (obtained from plasmid: <italic>Myl7-LoxP-myctagBFP-LoxPNTRmCherry</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Zhou and Hildebrandt, 2012</xref>) via PCR. The <italic>NEBuilder Assembly Tool</italic> was used for the design of oligonucleotides containing overlap sequences, which are required for the assembly of individual PCR fragments. 0.05 pmol of each fragment (flanking arms, <italic>P2A-GFP</italic>, <italic>P2A-NTR</italic>, pGGC (pUC57-BsaI) backbone vector <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Geissler et al., 2011</xref>) were used together with 10μl of the <italic>NEBuilder HiFi DNA Assembly Master Mix</italic>. The NEBuilder assembly reaction was performed for 1 hr at 50°C. 5 µl of this reaction was used for a subsequent transformation into chemically competent TOP10 <italic>E. coli</italic>. Isolated plasmids were checked via sequencing for correct template assembly. 5’-biotinylated oligonucleotides (bio_<italic>cdkn1a</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TCTTACACCAAACACCACAA-3</named-content>’ bio_<italic>cdkn1a</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TAAAACATGCAGGATACCGG-3</named-content>’) were used to amplify the template from the isolated and then linearized plasmid. The amplicon with the expected size was excised from the agarose gel and purified using the <italic>NucleoSpin Gel and PCR clean-up</italic> kit (Macherey-Nagel). To induce a DNA double-strand break in close proximity to the intended site of insertion, the following oligonucleotides for sgRNA synthesis were used: sg_<italic>cdkn1a</italic>_1: 5’-TAGG-<named-content content-type="sequence">AATATCACTCCCCGGATTTC-3</named-content>’ sg_<italic>cdkn1a</italic>_2: 5’-AAAC-<named-content content-type="sequence">GAAATCCGGGGAGTGATATT-3</named-content>’. Synthesis of this sgRNA was done as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Microinjections into <italic>N. furzeri</italic> oocytes</title><p>For microinjections, an injection mold (manufactured by GT-Labortechnik, Arnstein, Germany) was used to form single slots of the size of an <italic>N. furzeri</italic> embryo. Injection plates were freshly prepared by dissolving 1.5 g of agarose in 50 ml of 0.3 x Danieau’s medium. This solution was boiled in a microwave oven and then poured into a petri dish (94 mm × 16 mm). The injection mold was inserted while the solution was still liquid. As soon as the agarose has hardened (after approximately 30 min), the stamp can be removed and the plate is ready to use. Fertilized embryos were individually inserted into the slots with the first cell facing the injection needle. 0.3 x Danieau’s medium was added to the plate until the eggs were completely covered. The injection was performed under a stereomicroscope using glass capillary needles, a pressure injector (World Precision Instruments), and a micromanipulator (Saur). The injection solution for the inactivation of target genes contained the sgRNAs (30 ng/µl each), <italic>Cas9</italic> mRNA (300 ng/µl), <italic>GFP</italic> mRNA (200 ng/µl), and phenol red. For knock-in approaches, the concentration of sgRNA and <italic>Cas9</italic> mRNA was kept the same, whereas <italic>GFP</italic> mRNA was reduced to 100 ng/µl and 20 ng/µl of the HDR template were added. After injections, the embryos remained on the plate and were stored at 29 °C until the next day. Using a fluorescence microscope, the injected embryos were sorted into GFP-positive and GFP-negative embryos. GFP-positive embryos were transferred into single wells of a 96-well plate containing 0.3 x Danieau’s medium.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>DNA sampling</title><p>DNA samples were obtained either from caudal fin biopsies or whole embryos. For fin biopsies, a small part of the caudal fin was cut off from the anesthetized fish. To extract DNA from whole embryos, the embryos were mechanically disrupted using a pipet tip. For fin, biopsy samples 100 µl and for embryos, 50 µl of NaOH (50 mM) was added to the sample and subsequently incubated at 95 °C for 45 min. Afterward, 1/10 volume of Tris-HCl (1 M, pH 8.0) was added.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Restriction enzyme digest</title><p>Restriction enzymes were used to check for the presence of mutations in the target genes. The region flanking the potential mutation site was amplified via PCR using the following oligonucleotides: <italic>mitfa</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TGCTTCACATACGTTTGCAG-3</named-content>’ <italic>mitfa</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CAAAGGTCTGAGGGCTTTCC-3</named-content>’, <italic>ltk</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TGTTCTGTCACCACCCTTGT-3</named-content>’ <italic>ltk</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">ACACTGCTATTACCAGGTTTGAC-3</named-content>’, <italic>csf1ra</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CATAGATACCGTGCAAGCCTG-3</named-content>’ <italic>csf1ra</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">AGCCCAGGTATGAAATCCGT-3</named-content>’, <italic>slc45a2</italic>_fw: 5’- <named-content content-type="sequence">GGATTTGGTGTTTTGGCCCT-3</named-content>’ <italic>slc45a2</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">GTAACTCGGCTCTAATCGTGC-3</named-content>’. For the restriction enzyme digest, 20 µl of the PCR reaction were incubated over night at 37 °C after adding 6.75 µl of ddH<sub>2</sub>O, 0.25 µl of the corresponding enzyme, and 3 µl of the respective enzyme buffer (<italic>mitfa: EcoRI</italic>, <italic>ltk: EcoNI</italic>, <italic>csf1ra: NcoI-HF</italic>, <italic>slc45a2: HypCH4III</italic>). Samples from the control digest were analyzed on a 1% agarose gel. In case of a mutation, the restriction enzyme is prevented from cleaving the PCR fragment. As a positive control, a PCR amplicon from a wild-type fish was always included in order to verify that the restriction enzyme digest worked properly.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>High-resolution melting analysis (HRMA)</title><p>After identifying the exact mutations in the targeted gene loci (from F<sub>2</sub> generation on), genotyping was performed via HRMA as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Krug et al., 2023</xref>). The following oligonucleotides were used for the HRM analysis: HRMA_<italic>mitfa</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CCTCACGAGTCTCTCTATCA-3</named-content>’ HRMA_<italic>mitfa</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">GCCCCATGAACCCAATATAA-3</named-content>’, HRMA_<italic>ltk</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CCACAGACTCTTCCAGAAAT-3</named-content>’ HRMA_<italic>ltk</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CTGATTATGAGGTGCGACTA-3</named-content>’, HRMA_<italic>csf1ra</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">AGTGTGTGGCTTTCAATTTG-3</named-content>’ HRMA_<italic>csf1ra</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TTTCTGGTGAGTGTTTGTTA-3</named-content>’. To assess the genotypes, melt curves were analyzed using the <italic>Precision Melt Analysis</italic> software (Bio-Rad).</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Isolation of nucleic acids</title><p>RNA isolation from fish tissues was done according to the manufacturer’s protocol of the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen). Tissue homogenization using ceramic beats was performed with the TissueLyser II (2 min at 30 Hz). The optional on-column DNase digestion step was included. 20 µl of DEPC H<sub>2</sub>O were used for final elution. RNA isolation from FACS sorted cells was done according to the protocol of the <italic>MagMaxTM-96 Total RNA Isolation Kit</italic>. Isolation of RNA and DNA from whole embryos was done via phenol-chloroform extraction. Using a pipette tip, the chorion of the embryos was mechanically ruptured before 500 µl of TRIzol was added. Homogenization of the embryos was performed with ceramic beats using the TissueLyser II (2 min at 30 Hz). After incubation at RT for 5 min, 200 µl chloroform was added. Samples were then mixed for 15 s, incubated at RT for 3 min, and then centrifuged at 12,000 × g for 20 min (4 °C). The upper, aqueous phase, containing the RNA, was transferred into a fresh tube, and 1.1 volumes of isopropanol, 0.16 volumes of NaAc (2 M, pH 4.0), and 1 µl of GlycoBlue (Thermo Fischer) were added. Samples were incubated at RT for 10 min and centrifuged at 12,000 × g for 20 min (4 °C). The supernatant was removed, and the pellet was washed with 1 ml of 80% EtOH and centrifuged at 7500 × g for 10 min (4 °C). The supernatant was discarded, and the pellet was air-dried. The RNA pellet was dissolved in 20 µl of DEPC-H<sub>2</sub>O and stored at –80 °C. The inter- and organic phases were used for the extraction of DNA (required for genotyping PCR). 300 µl of EtOH (100%) were added, samples were incubated at RT for 2–3 min and then centrifuged at 2000 × g for 5 min (4 °C). The supernatant was discarded, and the pellet was incubated in 1 ml of 0.1 M sodium citrate in 10% EtOH for 30 min before centrifugation at 2000 × g for 5 min (4 °C). The supernatant was discarded and 1 ml of EtOH (75%) was added 15 min before centrifugation at 2000 × g for 5 min (4 °C). Pellet was air-dried and dissolved in 15 µl NaOH (8 mM).</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>cDNA synthesis and gene expression analysis</title><p>For cDNA synthesis, 500 ng of RNA from fish tissues and whole embryos, 25 ng of RNA from FACS-sorted cells or 20 ng of RNA isolated from primary cells were used. cDNA synthesis was performed according to the instructions of the <italic>iScript cDNA Synthesis Kit</italic> (Bio-Rad). qRT-PCRs were performed in 384-well plates using 2 x SYBR Green Mix and the CFX384 Real-Time System (Bio-Rad). The reaction mix included 3 µl of cDNA (diluted 1:5 in DEPC H<sub>2</sub>O), 0.4 µl of each oligonucleotide, 1.2 µl DEPC H<sub>2</sub>O and 5 µl of 2 x SYBR Green Mix. Gene expression levels were determined using the following oligonucleotides: q_<italic>mitfa</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TGAAGCAAGTACTGGACAAG</named-content>-3’ q_<italic>mitfa</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TCCAGTAGAGTCAGAAGTCC</named-content>-3’, q_<italic>ltk</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CTGGGAGGAATCCGCTTA</named-content>-3’ q_<italic>ltk</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">AGTGAGACCAGTGCAGAG</named-content>-3’, q_<italic>csf1ra</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">AGTTCAAATGTATCAGAGACCT</named-content>-3’ q_<italic>csf1ra</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TATCCTGCTCCGAGAATCAT</named-content>-3’, q_<italic>gfp</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">AAGGGCATCGACTTCAAGGA</named-content>-3’ q_<italic>gfp</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">GGCGGATCTTGAAGTTCACC</named-content>-3’, q_<italic>ntr</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CTTTTGATGCCAGCAAGAAA</named-content>-3’ q_<italic>ntr</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">GAAGCCACAATAAAATGCCA</named-content> –3’, q_<italic>cdkn1a</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">ATGTGCAGAGGGATGGCTAC</named-content>-3’ q_<italic>cdkn1a</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CCTCCAGATCTTTACGCAG</named-content>-3’. For normalization the housekeeping gene <italic>rpl13a</italic> (q_<italic>rpl13a</italic>_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">ACTGTCAGAGGCATGCTTCC</named-content>-3’ q_<italic>rpl13a</italic>_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TGCTCTGAAAATTGTGCGCC</named-content>-3’) was used.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Whole kidney marrow (WKM) analysis via flow cytometry</title><p>Kidneys were dissected and immediately pushed through a 40 μm cell strainer (FALCON; placed on top of a 50 ml falcon tube) using a syringe plunger. Strainer and plunger were rinsed with 1 ml of PBS each. Cells were pelleted by centrifugation at 330 × g for 5 min (4 °C). The supernatant was discarded and the cell pellet was dissolved in 300 μl PBS. Analysis of the WKM was done using a BD FACS AriaTM IIIu. The gating strategy was chosen as described for the analysis of the WKM of zebrafish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Sanz-Morejón et al., 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Irradiation of <italic>N. furzeri</italic> eggs</title><p>For γ–irradiation of F<sub>1</sub> eggs from the <italic>cdkn1a</italic>-reporter line, eggs were placed into 12-well plates (one egg per well) containing 1 ml of 0.3 x Danieau’s medium. Eggs were irradiated in the 12-well plate with a dose of 10 Gy using a Gammacell 40 Exactor (Best Theratronics Ltd.). The presence of a GFP signal was checked using an Axio Zoom.V16 with ApoTome (Zeiss).</p></sec><sec id="s4-14"><title>Genotyping of eggs and fish from the <italic>cdkn1a</italic>-reporter line</title><p>DNA was extracted from eggs or fin biopsies as described above. To check for the presence of the reporter construct in the <italic>cdkn1a</italic> locus, the following primer pair was used: <italic>cdkn1a</italic>_insertion_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TATTTCTCTGGTGTTTGCCT</named-content>-3’ <italic>GFP</italic>_insertion_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">TGATATAGACGTTGTGGCTG</named-content>-3’. To discriminate between the three different genotypes, the following primer pair was used: <italic>cdkn1a</italic>_genotyping_fw: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CTACAGATCCAGCGTCATC</named-content>-3’ <italic>cdkn1a</italic>_genotyping_rv: 5’-<named-content content-type="sequence">CCAAGAGAACCAGACAAAGA</named-content>-3’. For <italic>cdkn1a<sup>+/+</sup></italic> animals, an amplicon with a size of 393 bp was expected, whereas a 1893 bp fragment occurred in <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic> fish. In <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup></italic> animals, both amplicons were expected. Genotyping PCRs were performed with the <italic>DreamTaq</italic> polymerase and 10 x DreamTaq Green buffer (Thermo Scientific). Cycling conditions were set according to the manufacturer’s manual with an annealing temperature of 60 °C and a cycle number of 35.</p></sec><sec id="s4-15"><title>Analysis of GFP-positive cells from the <italic>cdkn1a</italic>-reporter line</title><p>Kidneys were removed from freshly euthanized fish and placed into 1 x PBS on ice. Together with 1 ml PBS (with 1% FBS), the tissue was pushed through a 40 µm cell strainer (FALCON), using a syringe plunger. The cell strainer and plunger were rinsed twice with 1 ml of PBS each. After centrifugation at 250 × g for 5 min (4 °C), the pellet was resuspended in 200 µl PBS containing 1% FBS. The cell suspension was stained with 5 nM Sytox Red Dead Cell Stain (Invitrogen) to identify dead cells and was subsequently analyzed on a BD FACS AriaIIIu Cell Sorter using a 100 µm Nozzle. After doublet and dead cell exclusion, the GFP-positive cells were sorted in PBS. The GFP-positive gate was set according to the negative control obtained from the kidney of a <italic>klara</italic> fish. Data were analyzed using FlowJo v10 Software (BD).</p></sec><sec id="s4-16"><title>Immunofluorescence staining and imaging</title><p>Liver tissues were fixed overnight in 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS and subsequently washed three times in PBS-T (0.2% Tween in PBS). Tissues were placed for 5 min in 5% sucrose, then for 2 hr in 20% sucrose, and subsequently overnight in 30% sucrose. Tissues were embedded and shock frozen in molds filled with NEG-50 cryosection medium (Thermo Scientific). The tissue was cut into 20 µm slices. After defrosting for 25 min, the sections were washed four times for 10 min at RT in PBS-T (0.2% Tween) and were permeabilized by a short washing step with permeabilization solution (0.1% Tween, 0.3% Triton X 100 in PBS). Immediately afterward, the sections were washed again two times for 10 min at RT in PBS-T (0.2% Tween) and incubated in blocking buffer (2% BSA and 10% NGS in PBS-T (0.2% Tween)) for 1 hr at RT. Afterward, the samples were incubated overnight at 4 °C with an anti-GFP antibody (Thermo Scientific Inc, United States: A-11122, rabbit) diluted 1:200 in a blocking buffer. Sections were then washed four times for 10 min at RT in PBS-T (0.2% Tween) prior to incubation with bisbenzimide Hoechst 33258 and a secondary anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor 546 antibody (Thermo Scientific Inc, United States: A-11071, goat) diluted 1:500 in blocking solution for 1 hr at RT. After multiple washing steps in PBS-T (0.2% Tween), the slides were mounted with 70 µl ProLong Diamond antifade reagent (Thermo Scientific Inc). Before imaging, the samples were incubated at 4 °C overnight. Image stacks were recorded as optical sections with the Axio Imager 2 equipped with an ApoTome.2 slider (Zeiss, Germany). The ZEN 3.4 software (Zeiss, Germany) was used to process the images and to create extended depth of focus projections of the acquired z-stacks.</p></sec><sec id="s4-17"><title>Isolation and cultivation of skin cells from <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup> klara</italic> fish</title><p>Fish were euthanized with an overdose of Tricaine (1 g/l) and then immediately wiped with a paper towel containing 70% EtOH. After decapitation, the fish was briefly immersed three times in 0.16% NaOCl/PBS. Subsequently, scales and fins were removed with a scalpel. The skin was then pulled off using forceps, cut into small pieces, and transferred into 6 ml of HBSS (Gibco) containing 2 mg/ml collagenase type I (Fisher Scientific). After incubation for 2–3 hr with constant shaking of the reaction tubes every 15 min, the samples were centrifuged at 300 × g for 5 min followed by two wash steps using HBSS. The cells were seeded into cell culture flasks (50 ml; Greiner Bio-One). DMEM glucose (Gibco) supplemented with 10% FBS (Sigma), 0.1% MEM (1 mM; Sigma), 0.2% β-mercapto-ethanol (50 mM; Fisher Scientific), and 1 µg/ml Rh FGF (Immunotools) was used as basic medium. For the first eight days, this medium was additionally supplemented with 0.75% Pen./Strep. (Sigma), 1% Gentamicin (10 mg/ml; Sigma), and 0.3% Amphotericin B (0.25 mg/ml; Sigma). Afterward, the basic medium was supplemented with 1% Pen./Strep., 0.15% Gentamicin (10 mg/ml), 0.2% Amphotericin B (0.25 mg/ml). After 1–2 weeks, the composition of antibiotic and antifungal supplements changed to 1% Pen./Strep., 0.15% Gentamicin (10 mg/ml), and 0.1% Amphotericin B (0.25 mg/ml). As soon as 80% confluency was reached, skin cells were cultivated in a basic medium containing 1% Zellshield (Minerva Biolabs). The cells were constantly kept at 28 °C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-18"><title>Treatment of cells with metronidazole (Mtz)</title><p>24-well plates containing fibroblasts from the <italic>cdkn1a</italic>-reporter line (only <italic>cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup></italic>) were used. The medium was replaced by fresh medium containing either 0.2% DMSO (control) or 50 µM of Mtz (diluted in DMSO). Immediately afterward, cells were exposed to a γ–irradiation dosage of 10 Gy using a Gammacell 40 Exactor (Best Theratronics Ltd.). Non-irradiated cells served as controls. After the irradiation, cells were kept at 28 °C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. After 24 hr, the medium was removed and 350 µl lysis buffer RLT, supplemented with β-mercapto-ethanol (10 µl/ml buffer) from the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen) was added. The cell lysate was collected and homogenized using QIAshredder spin columns. Isolation of RNA was performed according to the manufacturer’s protocol. The optional on-column DNase digestion step was included. 20 µl of DEPC H2O were used for final elution.</p></sec><sec id="s4-19"><title>Sample preparation for light sheet microscopy</title><p>Throughout the preparation and the whole <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging process fish were constantly kept under anesthesia (200 mg/l Tricaine in system water). Depending on the age (and thus size), fish were mounted in the sample chamber either by embedding in a capillary with agarose (4 dph) or by fixing a small part of the caudal fin onto a capillary (17 dph).</p><p>The trunk and fins of fish at the age of 4 dph were completely embedded in 1% low melting agarose (in system water containing 200 mg/l Tricaine) tempered to 37 °C. The head and gills were not covered in agarose. Subsequently, the fish were sucked into a capillary tube with an inner diameter of 2.19 mm by pulling a plunger (with teflon tip) fitting into the capillary. Capillaries and matching plungers were provided in the Chamber &amp; Sample Holder Starter Kit Lightsheet Z.1 (Zeiss). The capillary with the fish was inserted into the sample holder and placed into the sample chamber filled with anesthesia solution (200 mg/l Tricaine in system water). After the agarose has solidified, the part of the agarose containing the fish was pushed out of the capillary (by the plunger) and the animal was imaged.</p><p>At the age of 17 dph, fish were too big to fit into the capillary. For this reason, a surface (diameter of about 3 mm) was modeled at the end of a capillary using a UV light curing resin (Bondic UV repair system). This modified capillary was placed into the sample holder and inserted into the microscope. Using the Bondic UV repair system a small part of the caudal fin was glued onto the shaped surface at the capillary. To prevent the fish from drying out, the sample chamber was then immediately filled with the anesthesia solution.</p><p>In order to ensure the vitality of the animals throughout the imaging procedure, the blood flow was constantly observed. Immediately after the images were acquired, the still anesthetized fish were euthanized with an overdose of Tricaine (1 g/l in system water).</p></sec><sec id="s4-20"><title><italic>In vivo</italic> light sheet imaging and image processing</title><p>Intravital imaging was performed with a Light sheet microscope (Z1, Zeiss) enabled for dual-side illumination. It was equipped with a 20 x detection objective (W Plan-Apochromat, numerical aperture of 1.0) and an sCMOS pco. edge 4.2 camera. Furthermore, the setup was temperature-controlled by the TempModule S1 and the TempModuleCZ-LSFM in combination with the PeltierBlock S and a Temperature Sensor, which were both assembled with the sample chamber. This allowed imaging at the optimal temperature for the fish (26 °C). Image processing, including dual side fusion, brightness/contrast adjustment, and image export was conducted using the Zen 3.1 software (blue edition, Zeiss). The 3Dxl rendering module (powered by arivis) was employed for three-dimensional reconstructions of the recorded z-stacks. Conversion of z-stacks into movies was performed using the arivis Vision4D software (arivis AG).</p></sec><sec id="s4-21"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed depending on the experimental setup via t-test or One-Way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s post hoc test. Equal or unequal variance was determined via F-Test followed by a Student’s or Welch’s t-test, respectively. The Kaplan-Meier curves (lifespan analysis) were analyzed via the Log-rank test. Significant changes are indicated by * if p≤0.05, ** if p≤0.01, and *** if p≤0.001.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information" id="s5"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf2"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Writing – original draft, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Investigation, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Data curation, Investigation, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Investigation, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Data curation, Investigation, Methodology, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Conceptualization, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing – original draft, Project administration, Writing – review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>All fish were maintained in the Nothobranchius facility of the Leibniz Institute on Aging - Fritz Lipmann Institute Jena according to the German Animal Welfare Law. The performed experiments reported here were covered by the animal license FLI-17-016, FLI-20-001, and FLI-20-102, which were approved by the local authorities (Thüringer Landesamt für Verbraucherschutz).</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="mdar"><label>MDAR checklist</label><media xlink:href="elife-81549-mdarchecklist1-v3.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s7"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files; Source Data files have been provided for all displayed items.</p></sec><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Hanna Reuter for suggesting the name <italic>klara</italic>, Nils Hartmann for the movie on wild-type killifish mating, Annekatrin Richter for providing the picture on oocyte injection, and Hakar Aliyas, Caglar Avci, Michelle Burkhardt, Christina Ebert, Gabriele Günther, Maleen Hofmann, Erik Hüttenrauch and Dagmar Kruspe for technical support. We are very grateful to members of FLI’s killifish facility, most notably to Simone Dunkel, Martin Neumann, Marcus Schmidt, Uta Naumann, and Beate Hoppe. We also thank members of the Core Facility Flow Cytometry, namely Johanna Schleep, Simone Tänzer, and Katrin Schubert for their contribution. This project was made possible by funding from the Carl Zeiss Foundation in the context of the IMPULS consortium (project number P2019-01-006) to CE. and a fellowship from the Leibniz Graduate School on Ageing and Age-Related Diseases (LGSA) to JK. The FLI is a member of the Leibniz Association and is financially supported by the Federal Government of Germany and the State of Thuringia.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Inducible transgenic expression in the short-lived fish nothobranchius furzeri</article-title><source>Journal of Fish Biology</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>1733</fpage><lpage>1738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jfb.12099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23639168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amundsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsgren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Male mate choice selects for female coloration in a fish</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>13155</fpage><lpage>13160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.211439298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11606720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antinucci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hindges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>A crystal-clear zebrafish for <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>29490</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep29490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27381182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>MTT</given-names></name><name><surname>Skuntz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertuzzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnheiter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>The other pigment cell: specification and development of the pigmented epithelium of the vertebrate eye</article-title><source>Pigment Cell Research</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0749.2006.00318.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blažek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Polačik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Rapid growth, early maturation and short generation time in african annual fishes</article-title><source>EvoDevo</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>24</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2041-9139-4-24</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24007640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzano</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>From the bush to the bench: the annual nothobranchius fishes as a new model system in biology</article-title><source>Biological Reviews of the Cambridge Philosophical Society</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/brv.12183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25923786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasek</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuchel</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>The heterogeneity of cellular senescence: insights at the single-cell level</article-title><source>Trends in Cell Biology</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcb.2022.04.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35599179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curado</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jungblut</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stainier</surname><given-names>DYR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Conditional targeted cell ablation in zebrafish: a new tool for regeneration studies</article-title><source>Developmental Dynamics</source><volume>236</volume><fpage>1025</fpage><lpage>1035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.21100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17326133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D’Agati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltre</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosimann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>A defect in the mitochondrial protein mpv17 underlies the transparent casper zebrafish</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>430</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2017.07.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28760346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolfi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Transition to annual life history coincides with reduction in cell cycle speed during early cleavage in three independent clades of annual killifish</article-title><source>EvoDevo</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>32</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2041-9139-5-32</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25276337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng’oma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Janko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichwald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Polačik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Platzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Phylogeny, genetic variability and colour polymorphism of an emerging animal model: the short-lived annual nothobranchius fishes from southern mozambique</article-title><source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2011.06.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21708276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geissler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholze</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Streubel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonas</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Boch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Transcriptional activators of human genes with programmable DNA-specificity</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e19509</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21625585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genade</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Terzibasi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Roncaglia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzano</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Annual fishes of the genus nothobranchius as a model system for aging research</article-title><source>Aging Cell</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1474-9726.2005.00165.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16164422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghanta</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dokshin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozturk</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Idrizi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gneid</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Edraki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera-Pérez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sontheimer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>5’-modifications improve potency and efficacy of DNA donors for precision genome editing</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e72216</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.72216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34665130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichwald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Absence of replicative senescence in cultured cells from the short-lived killifish nothobranchius furzeri</article-title><source>Experimental Gerontology</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2012.02.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22445733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grosse</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Emelyanov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacas-Gervais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulavin</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Defined p16<sup>high</sup> senescent cell types are indispensable for mouse healthspan</article-title><source>Cell Metabolism</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2020.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32485135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutierrez-Triana</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavhelidse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Thumberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittbrodt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Anlas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsingos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittbrodt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Efficient single-copy HDR by 5’ modified long dsdna donors</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e39468</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.39468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30156184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Benayoun</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pech</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzano</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Artandi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A platform for rapid exploration of aging and diseases in A naturally short-lived vertebrate</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>160</volume><fpage>1013</fpage><lpage>1026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.01.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25684364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzano</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Efficient genome engineering approaches for the short-lived african turquoise killifish</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>2010</fpage><lpage>2028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27658015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichwald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lechel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Terzibasi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Platzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Telomeres shorten while TERT expression increases during ageing of the short-lived fish nothobranchius furzeri</article-title><source>Mechanisms of Ageing and Development</source><volume>130</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mad.2009.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19428446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichwald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittig</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dröse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmeisser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lück</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gausmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Terzibasi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ristow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Platzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Mitochondrial DNA copy number and function decrease with age in the short-lived fish nothobranchius furzeri</article-title><source>Aging Cell</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>824</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1474-9726.2011.00723.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21624037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>A microinjection protocol for the generation of transgenic killifish (species: nothobranchius furzeri)</article-title><source>Developmental Dynamics</source><volume>241</volume><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.23789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22473915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hume</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollscheid-Lengeling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pridans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>The evolution of the macrophage-specific enhancer (FMS intronic regulatory element) within the CSF1R locus of vertebrates</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>17115</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-15999-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29215000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jao</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wente</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Efficient multiplex biallelic zebrafish genome editing using a CRISPR nuclease system</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>13904</fpage><lpage>13909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1308335110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23918387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelsh</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Heisenberg</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haffter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Odenthal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>van Eeden</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Furutani-Seiki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Granato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammerschmidt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Warga</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beuchle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelsang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nüsslein-Volhard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Zebrafish pigmentation mutations and the processes of neural crest development</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>123</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.123.1.369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9007256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Rapid genotyping of nothobranchius furzeri fish and larvae via high-resolution melt analysis (HRMA)</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Protocols</source><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>107744</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/pdb.prot107744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36828577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lischik</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittbrodt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Enhanced <italic>in vivo</italic>-imaging in medaka by optimized anaesthesia, fluorescent protein selection and removal of pigmentation</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e0212956</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30845151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Raible</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Nacre encodes a zebrafish microphthalmia-related protein that regulates neural-crest-derived pigment cell fate</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>3757</fpage><lpage>3767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.126.17.3757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10433906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Close</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raible</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Duplicate MITF genes in zebrafish: complementary expression and conservation of melanogenic potential</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>237</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/dbio.2001.0379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11543618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdow</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacoby</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Delfino-Machín</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haffter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Geisler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelsh</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Leukocyte tyrosine kinase functions in pigment cell development</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e1000026</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18369445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>López-Otín</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blasco</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The hallmarks of aging</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>153</volume><fpage>1194</fpage><lpage>1217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.05.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23746838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oginuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohmura-Adachi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogamino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishitani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Rapid reverse genetics systems for nothobranchius furzeri, a suitable model organism to study vertebrate aging</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>11628</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-15972-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35804091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parichy</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ransom</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Paw</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zon</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>An orthologue of the kit-related gene fms is required for development of neural crest-derived xanthophores and a subpopulation of adult melanocytes in the zebrafish, <italic>Danio rerio</italic></article-title><source>Development</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>3031</fpage><lpage>3044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.127.14.3031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10862741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfaffl</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Horgan</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dempfle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Relative expression software tool (REST) for group-wise comparison and statistical analysis of relative expression results in real-time PCR</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>30</volume><elocation-id>e36</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.9.e36</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Platzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Nothobranchius furzeri: a model for aging research and more</article-title><source>Trends in Genetics</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2016.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27427533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reichard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Polačik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Nothobranchius furzeri, an “instant” fish from an ephemeral habitat</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e41548</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.41548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30616713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reichwald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Petzold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Downie</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietsch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalopin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Felder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Szafranski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Taudien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Groth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arisi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Weise</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Priebe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liehr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Görlach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Than</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kestler</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Volff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schartl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Platzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Insights into sex chromosome evolution and aging from the genome of a short-lived fish</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>163</volume><fpage>1527</fpage><lpage>1538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.10.071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26638077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Molecular sexing of <italic>nothobranchius furzeri</italic> embryos and larvae</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Protocols</source><volume>2022</volume><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/pdb.prot107782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36167675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanz-Morejón</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>García-Redondo</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Galardi-Castilla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Große</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Manig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Langa</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Piragyte</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Botos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>González-Rosa</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Ortega</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salaices</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercader</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Wilms tumor 1B expression defines a pro-regenerative macrophage subtype and is required for organ regeneration in the zebrafish</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>1296</fpage><lpage>1306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2019.06.091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31365871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nüsslein-Volhard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Zebrafish stripes as a model for vertebrate colour pattern formation</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>R81</fpage><lpage>R92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.11.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25602311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tagoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Himes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leenen</surname><given-names>PJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hume</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonifer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Transcription factor complex formation and chromatin fine structure alterations at the murine c-fms (CSF-1 receptor) locus during maturation of myeloid precursor cells</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1721</fpage><lpage>1737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.222002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12101129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terzibasi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzano</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roncaglia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Domenici</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Large differences in aging phenotype between strains of the short-lived annual fish nothobranchius furzeri</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e3866</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19052641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tozzini</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng’oma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Polačik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blažek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichwald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Petzold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Watters</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Parallel evolution of senescence in annual fishes in response to extrinsic mortality</article-title><source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>77</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-13-77</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23551990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valdesalici</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Extremely short lifespan in the annual fish nothobranchius furzeri</article-title><source>Proceedings. Biological Sciences</source><volume>270 Suppl 2</volume><fpage>S189</fpage><lpage>S191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsbl.2003.0048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14667379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valenzano</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Terzibasi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Domenici</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Temperature affects longevity and age-related locomotor and cognitive decay in the short-lived fish nothobranchius furzeri</article-title><source>Aging Cell</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1474-9726.2006.00212.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16842500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valenzano</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Transposon-mediated transgenesis in the short-lived african killifish nothobranchius furzeri, a vertebrate model for aging</article-title><source>G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.111.001271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22384364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valenzano</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Benayoun</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Etter</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Clément-Ziza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Willemsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>The african turquoise killifish genome provides insights into evolution and genetic architecture of lifespan</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>163</volume><fpage>1539</fpage><lpage>1554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26638078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Deursen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>The role of senescent cells in ageing</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>509</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24848057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Age-dependent decline in fin regenerative capacity in the short-lived fish nothobranchius furzeri</article-title><source>Aging Cell</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>857</fpage><lpage>866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acel.12367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26121607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dovey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goessling</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zon</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Transparent adult zebrafish as a tool for <italic>in vivo</italic> transplantation analysis</article-title><source>Cell Stem Cell</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2007.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18371439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Iftimia</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Welker</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubash</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Drapkin</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Phat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Volorio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marvin</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ligorio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dershowitz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Karabacak</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sgroi</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Iafrate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maheswaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawls</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Langenau</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Visualizing engrafted human cancer and therapy responses in immunodeficient zebrafish</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>177</volume><fpage>1903</fpage><lpage>1914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31031007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hildebrandt</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Inducible podocyte injury and proteinuria in transgenic zebrafish</article-title><source>Journal of the American Society of Nephrology</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1047</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1681/ASN.2011080776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22440901</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="sa0"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.81549.sa0</article-id><title-group><article-title>Editor's evaluation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>Itamar</given-names></name><role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03qxff017</institution-id><institution>The Hebrew University of Jerusalem</institution></institution-wrap><country>Israel</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><related-object id="sa0ro1" object-id-type="id" object-id="10.1101/2022.07.04.498720" link-type="continued-by" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2022.07.04.498720"/></front-stub><body><p>This important work significantly simplifies our ability to observe and manipulate aging and senescence in a living vertebrate model. The evidence supporting the conclusions is compelling, with advanced genome editing, physiological assays, and state-of-the-art microscopy. The work will be of broad interest to biomedical and aging researchers, as well as to cell biologists.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.81549.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>Itamar</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03qxff017</institution-id><institution>The Hebrew University of Jerusalem</institution></institution-wrap><country>Israel</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Wittbrodt</surname><given-names>Joachim</given-names></name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/038t36y30</institution-id><institution>Heidelberg University</institution></institution-wrap><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Wang</given-names></name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00wksha49</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Biological Sciences, Beijing</institution></institution-wrap><country>China</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Reichard</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/053avzc18</institution-id><institution>The Czech Academy of Sciences</institution></institution-wrap><country>Czech Republic</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text id="sa2-box1"><p>Our editorial process produces two outputs: (i) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2022.07.04.498720">public reviews</ext-link> designed to be posted alongside <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.07.04.498720v1">the preprint</ext-link> for the benefit of readers; (ii) feedback on the manuscript for the authors, including requests for revisions, shown below. We also include an acceptance summary that explains what the editors found interesting or important about the work.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Generation of a transparent killifish line through multiplex CRISPR/Cas9-mediated gene inactivation&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by 3 peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor, Itamar Harel, and Didier Stainier as the Senior Editor. The following individuals involved in the review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Joachim Wittbrodt (Reviewer #1); Wang Wei (Reviewer #2); Martin Reichard (Reviewer #3).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed their reviews with one another, and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1. HDR-mediated integration: as there are concerns about PCR biases in the detection of HDR-mediated integration, the authors should use another pair of primers, and describe in detail the PCR amplification. Alternatively, it would be best to use Southern Blot.</p><p>2. Quality of figures: figure quality and assembly should be improved. This includes a symmetrical representation of both males and females at all steps, a single figure that describes the generation of the Klara line, the layout of figure S3, and clearer Figure 3F.</p><p>3. Kalra line: quantification of general physiology concerning health, growth rate, and survival of this triple mutation are required.</p><p>4. p21-GFP reporter line: to demonstrate that this line could be used as a resource for investigating adult biology, in-vivo imaging of either irradiated or young/old fish (2 time points) should be performed. This should then be followed by clearance of senescent cells.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>In the analysis of the integration, the authors should provide the exact PCR conditions, in particular the number of cycles. If they consider the statement of the perfect integration essential, this would be best supported by a Southern Blot analysis.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>Concerns:</p><p>1) Figures in this manuscript are not well-organized. For instance, it is difficult to find the phenotype for male and female Klara fish. In some figures, the authors show images of males, while in other figures I can only find females. Three figures were used to demonstrate the establishment of the Klara fish line, which is not necessary. One or two are more than enough. More figures should be used to characterize the Klara fish line. For example, a detailed characterization of this line during aging should be provided because the authors claim that this line will be useful for aging studies. Does the triple mutation influence the speed of aging? Would fish develop slower, faster, or normally? It is important to have these data because it will determine, to what extent, we can use the line for aging-, development-, and regeneration-related studies.</p><p>2) The crystal-clear mutants have been established in zebrafish; can authors generate a truly crystal-clear animal in African killifish? The re-appearance of pigmentation limits the application of this line in the adult stages.</p><p>3) One of the key goals of this manuscript is to establish a tool for <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging. But the authors did not use the important lines they have established to perform <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging. The cdkn1a (p21)-GFP line is very interesting, it can be informative if authors track GFP expression in the skin during aging for a single individual for a month or two. Imaging can be done weekly.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.81549.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1. HDR-mediated integration: as there are concerns about PCR biases in the detection of HDR-mediated integration, the authors should use another pair of primers, and describe in detail the PCR amplification. Alternatively, it would be best to use Southern Blot.</p></disp-quote><p>We fully understand and acknowledge that there are concerns regarding the specific integration of the GFP-NTR cassette into the killifish genome, which in the initial submission has only been demonstrated by PCR using a single primer pair. We have now used a second pair of primers to verify the site-specific integration of the cassette. The corresponding data are shown in Figure 5—figure supplement 1B. We would also like to point out that the ‘functionality’ of the cassette strongly suggests its proper integration.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2. Quality of figures: figure quality and assembly should be improved. This includes a symmetrical representation of both males and females at all steps, a single figure that describes the generation of the Klara line, the layout of figure S3, and clearer Figure 3F.</p></disp-quote><p>We have improved both the quality and assembly of the figures. This includes a balanced representation of males and females, the combination of all data regarding generation of the klara line in one figure and improving the quality/layout of figure 3. We have expanded the latter, which now also contains the scheme of former figure S3. We assume “3F” actually means “2F”. Here, we have added a female animal.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3. Kalra line: quantification of general physiology concerning health, growth rate, and survival of this triple mutation are required.</p></disp-quote><p>We have now included information on health, growth rate, and survival of the klara line. First, we have included a ‘survival’ curve of klara and corresponding wild-type animals (Figure 2—figure supplement 1A). Of note, this is not a dedicated survival curve but a compilation of data on the daily records from the fish facility regarding animals found dead. There is no significant difference between the two cohorts. Second, we have quantified size and weight until 5 weeks post-hatching in both cohorts (Figure 2—figure supplement 1B). Third, all fish in our fish facility are inspected and scored daily regarding swimming, feeding and social behavior as well as body condition, appearance and breathing. There is no parameter in which a difference between klara and wild-type animals have been observed. This is mentioned in the revised manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4. p21-GFP reporter line: to demonstrate that this line could be used as a resource for investigating adult biology, in-vivo imaging of either irradiated or young/old fish (2 time points) should be performed. This should then be followed by clearance of senescent cells.</p></disp-quote><p>We fully agree with the reviewers that the demonstration of the possibility of <italic>in vivo</italic> microscopy of klara animals carrying the GFP allele in the cdkn1a locus significantly adds to the impact of our work. We have performed light sheet microscopy on living klara animals at two different time points, namely at 4- and 17-days post-hatching and have included respective images and movies into the manuscript (Figure 5J-M and Figure 5-video1 and video2).</p><p>We would like to point out that both reviewer requests pertain animal experiments for which, at least initially, we did not have the appropriate licenses. Regarding microscopy we have applied for an amendment of an existing license, which made it possible to perform the light sheet experiments, albeit at restricted time points. Regarding the clearing experiment, however, we did not have any pre-existing license. Therefore, we performed those experiments in cell culture. The respective data are shown in Figure 5—figure supplement 2C.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>In the analysis of the integration, the authors should provide the exact PCR conditions, in particular the number of cycles. If they consider the statement of the perfect integration essential, this would be best supported by a Southern Blot analysis.</p></disp-quote><p>To show the integration of the reporter cassette into the cdkn1a locus, we initially performed a PCR using a forward primer that binds in the cdkn1a locus, but outside the sequence covered by the flanking arm, and a reverse primer binding within the GFP sequence. With this PCR, an amplicon was only obtained upon integration of the construct in the cdkn1a locus. In addition, we included an alternative PCR using a different primer pair combination (shown in in Figure 5—figure supplement 1B). With both primer pairs it was possible to verify the presence of the reporter cassette. In addition, the second primer pair also allows to distinguish between cdkn1a<sup>+/+</sup>, cdkn1a<sup>ki/+</sup> and cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup> fish and is thus suitable for genotyping of offspring.</p><p>The PCRs were performed using DreamTaq as Polymerase. The general PCR conditions were selected according to the manufacturer’s manual. We used 60°C as an annealing temperature and 35 cycles per PCR. Those conditions were included in the Methods and Materials section.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>Concerns:</p><p>1) Figures in this manuscript are not well-organized. For instance, it is difficult to find the phenotype for male and female Klara fish. In some figures, the authors show images of males, while in other figures I can only find females. Three figures were used to demonstrate the establishment of the Klara fish line, which is not necessary. One or two are more than enough. More figures should be used to characterize the Klara fish line. For example, a detailed characterization of this line during aging should be provided because the authors claim that this line will be useful for aging studies. Does the triple mutation influence the speed of aging? Would fish develop slower, faster, or normally? It is important to have these data because it will determine, to what extent, we can use the line for aging-, development-, and regeneration-related studies.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with the reviewer that a single figure about the generation of the klara line is more suitable. For this reason, Figure 1 and supplementary figure 1 summarize the line generation. We extended the characterization of klara fish by including a lifespan analysis (compared to the genetic background strain MZCS-08/122). It is important to mention, that this was not a dedicated lifespan experiment but a compilation of survival data obtained from our fish database (date of hatching vs date of death). Only fish that were found dead were included in the analysis, which revealed no difference in the survival of klara fish compared to respective wild-types (Figure 2—figure supplement 1A). In addition, we also included data concerning body size and weight of male and female klara as well as wild-type fish (Figure 2—figure supplement 1B) showing that klara fish develop normally.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) The crystal-clear mutants have been established in zebrafish; can authors generate a truly crystal-clear animal in African killifish? The re-appearance of pigmentation limits the application of this line in the adult stages.</p></disp-quote><p>We believe that it is in general possible to establish a fully transparent N. furzeri line by selecting different target genes. A potential inactivation of other genes involved in the formation of melanophores, such as tyrosinase or slc45a2, could be beneficial. In the meantime, the mutation causing the lack of iridophores in the casper line has been identified (D’Agati et al., 2017), so that an inactivation of mpv17 in N. furzeri could also be tested. However, these experiments are outside of the scope of this manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) One of the key goals of this manuscript is to establish a tool for in vivo imaging. But the authors did not use the important lines they have established to perform <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging. The cdkn1a (p21)-GFP line is very interesting, it can be informative if authors track GFP expression in the skin during aging for a single individual for a month or two. Imaging can be done weekly.</p></disp-quote><p>The aim to use the klara line for in vivo imaging, in form of the cdkn1a-reproter line, has been addressed now and data were included in Figure 5J-M and corresponding movies. We were able to get the approval for an animal license allowing us the <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging of living, anesthetized fish using light sheet microscopy at two different timepoints (4- and 17dph). With this technique, we were able to detect GFP-positive cells in cdkn1a<sup>ki/ki</sup> fish at both timepoints. Of note, the number of GFP-positive cells significantly increased from 4dph to 17dph.</p></body></sub-article></article>