<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">eLife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">16578</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Computational and Systems Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Lineage tracing of human B cells reveals the in vivo landscape of human antibody class switching</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-52866"><name><surname>Horns</surname><given-names>Felix</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5872-5061</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib">†</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="data-ro1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="data-ro2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-55276"><name><surname>Vollmers</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib">†</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-55280"><name><surname>Croote</surname><given-names>Derek</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4907-1865</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-55278"><name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>Sally F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-55279"><name><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>Gary E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-50728"><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>Cornelia L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-4879"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Mark M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-3886"><name><surname>Quake</surname><given-names>Stephen R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Biophysics Graduate Program</institution>, <institution>Stanford University</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Stanford</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Bioengineering</institution>, <institution>Stanford University</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Stanford</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Biomolecular Engineering</institution>, <institution>University of California Santa Cruz</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Santa Cruz</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Pediatrics</institution>, <institution>Stanford University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Stanford</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution content-type="dept">Stanford Prevention Research Center</institution>, <institution>Stanford University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Stanford</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Medicine</institution>, <institution>Stanford University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Stanford</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Microbiology and Immunology</institution>, <institution>Stanford University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Stanford</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><institution content-type="dept">Institute of Immunity, Transplantation and Infection</institution>, <institution>Stanford University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Stanford</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Applied Physics</institution>, <institution>Stanford University</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Stanford</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff10"><label>10</label><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Chevy Chase</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>Richard A</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff11"><institution>Max Planck Institute for Developmental Biology</institution>, <country>Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><email>quake@stanford.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con" id="equal-contrib"><label>†</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>02</day><month>08</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e16578</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>06</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016, Horns et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Horns et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-16578-v1.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.001</object-id><p>Antibody class switching is a feature of the adaptive immune system which enables diversification of the effector properties of antibodies. Even though class switching is essential for mounting a protective response to pathogens, the in vivo patterns and lineage characteristics of antibody class switching have remained uncharacterized in living humans. Here we comprehensively measured the landscape of antibody class switching in human adult twins using antibody repertoire sequencing. The map identifies how antibodies of every class are created and delineates a two-tiered hierarchy of class switch pathways. Using somatic hypermutations as a molecular clock, we discovered that closely related B cells often switch to the same class, but lose coherence as somatic mutations accumulate. Such correlations between closely related cells exist when purified B cells class switch in vitro, suggesting that class switch recombination is directed toward specific isotypes by a cell-autonomous imprinted state.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.001">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.001</ext-link></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>The human immune system comprises cells and processes that protect the body against infection and disease. B cells are immune cells that once activated produce antibodies, or proteins that help identify and neutralize infectious microbes and diseased host cells.</p><p>Antibodies fall into one of ten different classes, and each class has a different, specialized role. Certain antibody classes are responsible for eradicating viruses, while others recruit and help activate additional cells of the immune system.</p><p>B cells multiply quickly once they are activated. During this proliferation process, dividing B cells can switch from making one class of antibody to another. As such, a single activated B cell can yield a group of related B cells that produce distinct classes of antibodies. Although much has been learned about antibody class switching and its role in generating a diverse set of antibodies, the process of creating different antibody classes in humans remains unknown.</p><p>Horns, Vollmers et al. now reveal how antibodies of every class are created in living humans. By developing a way to reconstruct the B cell proliferation process and thereby trace the lineage of individual B cells, the occurrence of class switching events could be measured and mapped. This approach revealed that most antibodies are produced via a single dominant pathway that involves first switching through one of two antibody classes.</p><p>Horns, Vollmers et al. also determined that closely related B cells, which were recently born through division of a common ancestor, often switched to the same class. The shared fate is likely explained by the existence of similar conditions inside each cell, which are inherited during cell division and direct switching toward a particular class. All together, these new findings lay a foundation for developing techniques to direct antibody class switching in ways that support the immune system. Future work will aim to understand the conditions inside a cell that direct switching toward a particular class of antibody.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.002">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.002</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Author Keywords</title><kwd>antibody</kwd><kwd>class switching</kwd><kwd>repertoire</kwd><kwd>cell decisions</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research Organism</title><kwd>Human</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="par-2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000001</institution-id><institution>National Science Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Graduate Research Fellowship</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Horns</surname><given-names>Felix</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-4"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>U19A1057229</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Mark M</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>elife-xml-version</meta-name><meta-value>2.5</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>A comprehensive map of patterns of class switching reveals how antibodies of every class are created in humans.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The human immune system’s antibody repertoire provides broad protection against pathogen infection. The variable regions of antibodies have been the subject of intense study due to their central role in determining the amazing breadth of molecular recognition in the antibody repertoire. However, the constant regions of antibodies also display quite dynamic behavior through the phenomenon of class switching, which is also known as isotype switching. Different classes of antibodies with distinct Fc domains mediate specialized effector functions, including activation of complement, phagocytosis, cytotoxicity, and release of inflammatory mediators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kindt et al., 2007</xref>). The diversification of antibody functionality via class switching is essential for mounting a protective response to different pathogens. Conversely, dysregulation of antibody class switching has been implicated in autoimmune diseases, including allergic hypersensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Sugai et al., 2003</xref>), rheumatoid arthritis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Humby et al., 2009</xref>), systemic lupus erythematosus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bubier et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Mietzner et al., 2008</xref>), IgG4-related disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Stone et al., 2012</xref>), and hyperimmunoglobulin E syndrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Minegishi, 2009</xref>).</p><p>Class switching occurs during germinal center maturation and is linked to cell division and somatic hypermutation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hodgkin et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Liu et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Tangye et al., 2002</xref>). After antigen encounter, IgM+ and IgD+ naïve B cells can switch to expression of activated classes IgG, IgA, and IgE via genomic recombination of the immunoglobulin heavy chain constant region locus. Much of current knowledge about the mechanisms of class switching is derived from the analysis of B cells induced to undergo class switch recombination (CSR) in vitro. However, the patterns of antibody class switching in the natural setting within a living organism have remained largely uncharacterized.</p><p>How switch recombination is directed to distinct classes in individual cells is a longstanding question (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Esser and Radbruch, 1990</xref>). Cytokine signals, such as CD40 ligand, IL-4, IFNγ, and TGFβ, induce CSR and can direct switching toward specific classes in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Stavnezer, 1996</xref>). These signals likely originate from cognate Th cells and dendritic cells in vivo. Cytokine stimulation induces transcription and splicing of 'germline' transcripts from the switch region of the particular IGHC locus that is participating in CSR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Lorenz et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Stavnezer-Nordgren and Sirlin, 1986</xref>). These switch regions accumulate histone modifications that are associated with open chromatin conformations and high DNA accessibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jeevan-Raj et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Wang et al., 2009</xref>). Together, these experiments suggest a model in which epigenetic control of switch region accessibility directs CSR toward specific classes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Alt et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Stavnezer-Nordgren and Sirlin, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Vaidyanathan and Chaudhuri, 2015</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we mapped the landscape of human antibody class switching using high-throughput immune repertoire sequencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Boyd et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Weinstein et al., 2009</xref>). This method has previously yielded insights into how the immune system responds to pathogen challenge and vaccination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Jackson et al., 2014a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Jiang et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Parameswaran et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Racanelli et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Vollmers et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Wang et al., 2014</xref>) and changes with age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Jiang et al., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Wang et al., 2014</xref>). We developed an approach for reconstructing clonal histories of antibody lineages, including class switching events. We used this method to measure antibody class switching within clonal lineages across the entire repertoire in vivo in a cohort of healthy human twins. This comprehensive map identifies how antibodies of every class are created. Our analysis of class switching events within clonal lineages uncovered signatures of the cellular decision processes that direct CSR toward specific isotypes.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Antibody repertoire sequencing with subclass resolution</title><p>To investigate human antibody class switching in vivo, we conducted immune repertoire sequencing of immunoglobulin heavy chain (IGH) genes of 22 healthy young adult human twins, including 9 pairs of identical twins and 2 pairs of fraternal twins. Sequencing libraries were prepared of a ~430–480 bp fragment of the IGH gene using total RNA from peripheral blood B cells drawn from each subject. Libraries were sequenced with 300 bp paired-end reads on the Illumina Miseq platform. Individual RNA molecules were labeled with unique molecular barcodes during library preparation, enabling highly accurate measurement of genetic diversity by using a consensus read approach to correct PCR and sequencing errors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Vollmers et al., 2013</xref>). On average, ~261,000 raw reads were obtained from each individual at each time point, representing ~154,000 unique sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>). Molecular barcodes were used to enumerate unique sequences and identify distinct clones. Sequencing reads covered ~100 bp of the constant region, making it possible to determine antibody class and resolve subclasses (IgG1, IgG2, IgG3, IgG4, IgA1, and IgA2) with high accuracy. Across individuals, the most abundant class was IgM (75%), followed by IgG1 (10%) and IgA1 (8%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s4">Figure 1—figure supplement 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). For 14 of 22 subjects, the measurement was repeated 28 days after the initial sample as a biological replicate (Bio. Rep.). To test the robustness of these measurements, we used the Jensen-Shannon distance as a measure of similarity between distributions of antibody class abundance. As expected, the class distributions are essentially the same across replicates in nearly every subject (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s4">Figure 1—figure supplement 4A and B</xref>). Furthermore, V gene usage is highly similar across biological replicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s7">Figure 1—figure supplement 7</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.003</object-id><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Number of unique sequences of each class analyzed in this study.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.003">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.003</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Class</th><th>Sequences (Sample)</th><th>Sequences (Bio. Rep.)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgM</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2,423,262</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>1,899,952</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgD</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>70,169</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>60,510</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG3</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>16,981</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>15,625</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>117,025</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>143,053</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgA1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>276,189</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>231,477</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>213,574</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>176,484</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG4</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>6,751</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>9,672</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgE</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>278</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>262</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgA2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>63,374</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>62,251</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Reconstructing clonal history of antibody lineages</title><p>After activation by specific antigen, naïve B cells proliferate and undergo somatic hypermutation and class switching. This process gives rise to a clonally related lineage composed of antibody IGH sequences of distinct classes that also differ in the variable region due to accumulation of somatic mutations. To study class switching after B cell activation, we developed an approach for reconstructing the clonal history of antibody lineages by using the information contained in the accumulation of somatic mutations as a molecular clock, much as ribosomal 16S sequences are used to study the evolutionary relationships of life on earth. We identified sequences belonging to the same clonal lineage as those sharing a variable (V) and joining (J) gene combination, CDR3 length, and ≥95% sequence identity in both the CDR3 and the rest of the variable region with at least one other member of the lineage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s5">Figure 1—figure supplement 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s7">Figure 2—figure supplement 7</xref>, and Materials and methods). We reconstructed a minimum evolution tree for each clonal lineage by conducting a multiple sequence alignment of all sequences in the lineage and then identifying a minimum spanning tree which includes all the sequences and minimizes the total number of mutations across the tree.</p><p>CSR occurs through a genomic rearrangement of the IGH constant region locus that brings the gene segment encoding the new constant region closer to the VDJ locus. Gene segments between the old and new constant regions are looped out and deleted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Iwasato et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Schwedler et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Yoshida et al., 1990</xref>). Therefore, class switches are irreversible and must proceed from upstream classes to downstream classes, according to the order of the IGH constant region loci on the chromosome, which is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>. This provides a constraint on ancestry that we incorporated into our algorithm for clonal history reconstruction: for a sequence belonging to a given class, only sequences of upstream classes can be ancestors.</p><p>The lineage trees are rooted on the germline sequence of the V and J gene combination shared by the lineage. As expected, somatic mutations accumulate as one moves from the germline sequence toward the leaves of the trees (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s6">Figure 1—figure supplement 6A</xref>). We note that PCR and sequencing errors rarely give rise to sequences having different classes and therefore contribute minimally to error in measuring class switching. Because these errors terminate branches of the tree, they also do not affect our analysis of mutation accumulation and correlations in class switching patterns. Unlike previous approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Barak et al., 2008</xref>), our tree reconstruction approach enables direct measurement of class switching events in clonal lineages which are supported by observed sequences without the need to infer mutations or ancestral isotype states. The inference process is challenging and indirect due to the complex mutational spectrum of somatic hypermutation.</p><p>Examples of reconstructed clonal histories of activated B cell lineages from one subject are displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>. The ~154,000 unique sequences from each subject belonged to ~34,000 distinct clonal lineages on average (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref>). On average across all subjects, each sequence displays 99.2% identity in the VDJ variable region to its parent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s6">Figure 1—figure supplement 6B</xref>), suggesting that the repertoire has been sampled deeply enough to enable accurate, high-resolution reconstruction of lineage history, since most pairs of sequences are separated by at most a few sites of hypermutation.<fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.004</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Reconstructed clonal histories of B cell lineages.</title><p>Examples of reconstructed clonal histories of antibody lineages in the repertoire of Subject 1A. All lineages with ≥6 sequences, comprising 64% of unique sequences in the repertoire, are shown in the upper left. Four examples among these lineages are also shown. Circles indicate unique IGH sequences colored by class. Edges indicate the minimum evolution tree that spans the clonal lineage and are labeled with the number of substitutions separating the sequences. The tree is rooted on the germline V and J gene sequence, indicated by the small black circle.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.004">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.004</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.005</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Schematic of immune repertoire sequencing strategy and data processing.</title><p>Reads having identical molecular barcodes are combined to yield a consensus read, which corresponds to a single mRNA molecule whose sequence has been corrected for errors arising during PCR and sequencing. Next, molecules having the same VDJC sequence are combined and the molecular abundance of each unique sequence is counted. In our analysis, we considered only the unique sequences and ignored molecular abundance counts.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.005">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.005</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig1-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.006</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Number of unique sequences (<bold>A</bold>) and clonal lineages (<bold>B</bold>) identified in each subject.</title><p>Twins are indicated by subject identifiers having the same number, but different letters (e.g. 1A and 1B).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.006">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.006</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig1-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.007</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Schematic of human immunoglobulin heavy chain (IGH) locus.</title><p>Constant region loci are indicated by colored rectangles, with labels and colors corresponding to class, as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>. Recombination signal sequences are indicated by black diamonds. Because the intervening DNA is looped out and excised during class switch recombination, class switching can only proceed from left to right. This region is located on chromosome 14.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.007">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.007</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig1-figsupp3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.008</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Abundance of antibody classes.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Fraction of IGH sequences belonging to each class for each subject in sample and biological replicate. Median across subjects is indicated by red line. (<bold>B</bold>) Differences between distributions of antibody classes (measured by Jensen-Shannon distance). Lane 1 compares biological replicates for individual subjects. Lanes 2 and 3 compare pairs of subjects (identical twins or unrelated individuals). Median across comparisons indicated by red line.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.008">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.008</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig1-figsupp4-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s5" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.009</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 5.</label><caption><title>Determination of sequence identity cutoff for clonal lineages.</title><p>Distributions of sequence identity within groups of sequences sharing the same V and J genes and CDR3 length (a 'group') from the same repertoire are shown. For each sequence, we calculated the sequence identity with the most similar sequence in its group (its 'nearest neighbor'). Plot displays CDR3 length and identity to the nearest neighbor for all sequences in our data set. Color indicates the number of sequences per bin. This plot reveals two groups of sequences: (1) sequences for which the nearest neighbor has &gt;95% identity, implying that it belongs to a clonal lineage with the nearest neighbor; and (2) sequences for which the nearest neighbor has 40–80% identity, suggesting that it does not belong to a clonal lineage. This indicates that by using a cutoff of 95% sequence identity in the CDR3, one can stringently identify sequences belonging to the same clonal lineage.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.009">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.009</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig1-figsupp5-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s6" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.010</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 6.</label><caption><title>Features of reconstructed antibody lineages.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Somatic mutations accumulate in reconstructed antibody lineages. For every sequence, identity to the germline V gene is plotted against its depth,defined as the number of edges to the root of the tree (the germline sequence). Color indicates number of sequences per bin. (<bold>B</bold>) Distributions of sequence identity between variable region sequences of parent-child pairs in reconstructed antibody lineages.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.010">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.010</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig1-figsupp6-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s7" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.011</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 7.</label><caption><title>V gene usage is similar in biological replicates.</title><p>Fraction of sequences mapping to each V gene in the sample and biological replicate libraries is displayed. Squared Pearson correlation coefficient is shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.011">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.011</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig1-figsupp7-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Measuring the landscape of antibody class switching</title><p>To characterize the landscape of antibody class switching in living humans, we measured probabilities of class switching across the entire repertoire. We devised an algorithm that traverses the reconstructed tree for each lineage and counts switches between classes from ancestor to child. We then calculated the relative frequency of switching between every pair of classes. In total ~142,000 class switch events were observed and contributed to this data set.</p><p>To characterize the accuracy of this approach, we note that we detected ~35,000 pairs of sequences sharing identical VDJ sequences but having different classes, as indicated by differing constant region sequences. Since every molecule has a unique barcode associated with it, we are able to prove that these sequences are not due to PCR recombination artifacts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A</xref>). These sequence pairs arose from CSR without intervening hypermutation events and enable analysis of class switching rates on a subset of the data without the need for lineage identification or tree construction. When we conducted our analysis using only these sequences, we found that the patterns of class switching correlate extremely well with the landscape measured across the entire repertoire, showing that the full lineage tree approach faithfully measures class switching patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B and C</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). We further confirmed that the patterns of class switching measured using only sequences that inherited all of the germline mutations from their immediate ancestor are highly similar to those measured using the full lineage tree approach (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>), indicating that artifacts arising from imperfect sampling of ancestral sequences have not distorted our measurement. In addition, patterns of class switching measured using only sequences supported by at least three sequencing reads are highly similar to those measured using the full lineage tree approach, suggesting that PCR and sequencing error have not substantially distorted our measurement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3</xref>). Finally, we confirmed that patterns of class switching could not simply be explained by random switching in proportion to class abundance. After shuffling the classes of parent-child sequence pairs, the hierarchical class switching patterns that we observed vanished (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.012</object-id><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Counts of pairs of sequences sharing identical VDJ sequences, but different constant region sequences. Data from all subjects including both original and biological replicate samples are shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.012">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.012</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>IgM/IgD</th><th>IgG3</th><th>IgG1</th><th>IgA1</th><th>IgG2</th><th>IgG4</th><th>IgE</th><th>IgA2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG3</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>744</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>6440</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2234</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgA1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>6374</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>338</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>4676</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>3210</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>1325</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>5673</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2291</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG4</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>50</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>46</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>129</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>3</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>61</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgE</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>4</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgA2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>1619</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>30</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>427</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2581</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>1630</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0</p> </td><td valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>To confirm that we measured the antibody repertoire with sufficient depth to accurately characterize the class switching landscape, we performed rarefaction analysis using data from five subjects. This analysis revealed that the landscape asymptotes rapidly to the observed one as read sampling depth is increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s5">Figure 2—figure supplement 5</xref>). Since class switch intermediates that are missing from the data could contribute to error in our measurement, we performed additional rarefaction analysis to show that the fraction of class switches that occur via an intermediate also saturates as read sampling depth is increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s6">Figure 2—figure supplement 6</xref>). As further validation, we examined ~1500 sequences that were detected in both biological replicates of the same subject and found that in 99.9% of cases the class of the ancestor sequence was the same in both samples, indicating that the presence or absence of switch intermediates is reliably detected.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Landscape of antibody class switching</title><p>Our measurement of class switching patterns uncovered a hierarchy of pathways leading to the production of antibodies of specific classes, which we have summarized as a state transition diagram showing the relative rates of all possible switches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s8">Figure 2—figure supplement 8A</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). The dominant class switch pathway leads from IgM/IgD to IgG1 or IgA1. Specifically, IgM switched most commonly to IgG1, IgA1, and IgG2, which together account for ~85% of switches from IgM. Direct switches from IgM to downstream classes (IgG4, IgE, or IgA2) were rare (~14%). Instead, downstream classes are predominantly produced via indirect switches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), most often through IgG1 or IgA1 in a secondary hierarchy of pathways. For example, IgG1 frequently switched to IgA1 or IgG2, which together account for ~92% of switches from IgG1, but rarely switched directly to IgG4 or IgA2. Most IgA2 was produced by subsequent switches from IgA1 or IgG2 (~65%), instead of directly from IgG1. We also saw that IgG3 is more likely to switch to IgG1/2 (~87%) rather than IgA1/2, suggesting that IgG3 lies along a pathway for specific generation of IgG antibodies. These results delineate the class switch pathways that give rise to specific antibody classes. The class switching landscape and the penetrance of direct and indirect switches were highly reproducible across the biological replicates, which were separated by 28 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s8">Figure 2—figure supplement 8B</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s9">Figure 2—figure supplement 9</xref>), confirming the robustness of our measurements and suggesting that the landscape is a temporally invariant feature of the healthy human immune system.<fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.013</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Landscape of human antibody class switching.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) State transition diagram of class switching. Classes are indicated as circles and possible switches as arrows. The radius of each circle indicates the relative abundance of the labeled class. The width of each arrow indicates the relative frequency of the switch (also reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). Rare classes IgG4 and IgE have been omitted for clarity and are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s8">Figure 2—figure supplement 8A</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Penetrance of direct switches from IgM/IgD. For each class, the fraction of sequences created by direct switching from IgM is shown (mean ± s.d. across n = 22 subjects for Sample and n = 14 subjects for Bio. Rep.). (<bold>C</bold>) Rates of CSR. The rate constant of each switch path was estimated by fitting an exponential probability distribution to the distribution of the number of somatic mutations accumulated prior to CSR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s11">Figure 2—figure supplement 11</xref>). Distributions of rate constants for switch paths from IgM/IgD to activated classes (gray) and from an activated class to another activated class (white) having ≥500 examplesin both Sample and Bio. Rep. repertoires are shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.013">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.013</ext-link></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD1-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.014</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Counts of class switch events. </title><p>Number of events observed for each possible switch from the class indicated by the row to the class indicated by the column. Data from D0 and D28 are provided separately. These data were used to calculate the switching rates depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.014">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.014</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="zip" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-data1-v1.zip"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.015</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Patterns of class switching measured using sequences with identical VDJ sequences but different constant regions are highly similar to those measured using the full lineage reconstruction approach.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Origin of pairs of sequences having identical VDJ sequences but different constant region classes. PCR recombination artifacts (PCR chimeras) were detected by comparing the unique barcodes from each sequencing read. Specifically, a pair of sequences was identified as originating from PCR chimera if at least one V-region barcode was shared between the pair of sequences, accounting for ~5% of sequence pairs. (<bold>B</bold>) Landscape of antibody class switching measured using only pairs of sequences having identical VDJ sequences but different constant region classes, which did not originate from PCR chimeras. Top panels show the relative frequency of class switch events from the class indicated by the column to the class indicated by the row. Middle panels show the destination probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the column switches to the class indicated to the row. Bottom panels show the arrival probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the row arose via direct switch from the class indicated by the column. Sample (left) and biological replicate (right) are shown. (<bold>C</bold>) Comparison between the landscape of antibody class switching measured using only pairs of sequences having identical VDJ sequences but different constant region classes and the landscape measured using the full lineage reconstruction approach. The values that define the landscape (relative switch frequencies, destination probabilities, and arrival probabilities) are plotted against the values obtained using all parent-child sequence pairs. Squared Pearson correlation coefficient is shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.015">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.015</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.016</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Patterns of class switching measured using sequences inheriting all germline mutations from parent are highly similar to those measured using the full lineage reconstruction approach.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Landscape of antibody class switching measured using only sequences inheriting all germline mutations from parent. Top panels show the relative frequency of class switch events from the class indicated by the column to the class indicated by the row. Middle panels show the destination probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the column switches to the class indicated to the row. Bottom panels show the arrival probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the row arose via direct switch from the class indicated by the column. Sample (left) and biological replicate (right) are shown. (<bold>B</bold>) Comparison between the landscape of antibody class switching measured using only sequences inheriting all germline mutations from parent and the landscape measured using the full lineage reconstruction approach. The values that define the landscape (relative switch frequencies, destination probabilities, and arrival probabilities) are plotted against the values obtained using all parent-child sequence pairs. Squared Pearson correlation coefficient is shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.016">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.016</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.017</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Patterns of class switching measured using sequences supported by consensus reads are highly similar to those measured using the full lineage reconstruction approach.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Landscape of antibody class switching measured using only sequences supported by consensus reads formed from ≥3 sequencing reads. Top panels show the relative frequency of class switch events from the class indicated by the column to the class indicated by the row. Middle panels show the destination probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the column switches to the class indicated to the row. Bottom panels show the arrival probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the row arose via direct switch from the class indicated by the column. Sample (left) and biological replicate (right) are shown. (<bold>B</bold>) Comparison between the landscape of antibody class switching measured using only sequences supported by consensus reads and the landscape measured using the full lineage reconstruction approach. The values that define the landscape (relative switch frequencies, destination probabilities, and arrival probabilities) are plotted against the values obtained using all parent-child sequence pairs. Squared Pearson correlation coefficient is shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.017">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.017</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.018</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Landscape of class switching cannot be explained by random switching in proportion to the abundance of antibody classes.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Landscape of antibody class switching measured after shuffling parent-child pairs of sequences. Top panel shows the relative frequency of class switch events from the class indicated by the column to the class indicated by the row. Middle panel shows the destination probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the column switches to the class indicated to the row. Bottom panel shows the arrival probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the row arose via direct switch from the class indicated by the column. (<bold>B</bold>) Comparison of the landscapes of antibody class switching before and after shuffling parent-child pairs of sequences. The values that define the landscapes (relative switch frequencies, destination probabilities, and arrival probabilities) are plotted against each other. Squared Pearson correlation coefficient is shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.018">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.018</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp4-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s5" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.019</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 5.</label><caption><title>Landscape of class switching saturates with respect to sequencing depth.</title><p>Rarefaction analysis of class switching landscapes of five subjects.Sequencing reads were sampled to varying depth, and the class switching landscape was measured in each case, the values of the relative switch frequency are plotted. The relative switch frequency is obtained by dividing the number of switches for a given transition by the maximum number of switches observed for any transition. For each subject, 5 replicate subsamples were performed at each depth, and the values obtained in these replicates are indicated by points, while the line connects medians of the replicates.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.019">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.019</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp5-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s6" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.020</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 6.</label><caption><title>Rarefaction analysis indicates that switch intermediates are robustly detected.</title><p>Sequencing reads were subsampled to varying depth for the five subjects shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s5">Figure 2—figure supplement 5</xref> with five replicate subsamplings at each depth. Data from all five subjects was pooled and used to calculate the fraction of switches from A to C indicated by the title of each panel that were direct (A -&gt; C) and indirect (A -&gt; B -&gt; C). Median across replicates is indicated by the red line.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.020">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.020</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp6-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s7" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.021</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 7.</label><caption><title>Class switching landscape is not sensitive to the lineage clustering cutoff parameter.</title><p>Clustering to identify clonal lineages of antibodies was performed on all repertoires from D0 with varying values of the clustering cutoff parameter ranging from 0.80 to 0.95. The class switching landscape was then calculated. In this calculation, we included only lineages having ≤2500 sequences in every parameter setting to ensure computational tractability. The landscape in each case is plotted against the landscape measured when the cutoff is 0.95. Squared Pearson correlation is shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.021">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.021</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp7-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s8" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.022</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 8.</label><caption><title>Landscape of class switching in humans.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Class switch state transition diagram including the rare classes IgG4 and IgE. Classes are indicated as pies and possible switches are indicated as arrows. Radius of each pie indicates the relative abundance of the class. The width of each arrow indicates the relative frequency of the switch (also reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) Heatmaps showing the class switch landscape as an average across subjects. Top panel shows the relative frequency of class switch events from the class indicated by the column to the class indicated by the row. Middle panel shows the destination probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the column switches to the class indicated to the row. Bottom panel shows the arrival probability, which is the probability that a given sequence of class indicated by the row arose via direct switch from the class indicated by the column. Sample (left) and biological replicate (right) are shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.022">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.022</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp8-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s9" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.023</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 9.</label><caption><title>Comparisons of class switch landscapes across individuals.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Differences between class switch landscapes (measured by Jensen-Shannon distance). Distances were calculated between the vectors representing (<bold>A</bold>) relative switch frequency or (<bold>B</bold>) destination probability. Lane 1 compares the two biological replicates for each subject. Lanes 2 and 3 compare pairs of subjects (identical twins or unrelated individuals). Median is indicated by red line. (<bold>C</bold>) Comparison of class switching landscapes of identical twins and unrelated pairs of subjects. Destination probabilities of identical twin pairs (red) and all possible pairs of unrelated subjects (blue) are plotted against one another. Intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) for twins and unrelated pairs was calculated using bootstrap resampling of pairs of subjects (1000 replicates) and reported in the legend (5th to 95th percentile range). (<bold>D</bold>) Comparison of the relative switch frequency of all possible class switches across subjects. Each point indicates the relative frequency of the switch indicated on the x-axis for an individual subject. Median is indicated by red line. Relative frequency of all switches is similar across all subjects.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.023">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.023</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp9-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s10" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.024</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 10.</label><caption><title>Class switching landscapes of individual subjects.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Relative switch frequency, (<bold>B</bold>) destination probability, and (<bold>C</bold>) arrival probability are shown for each subject. Twins are shown on the same row and zygosity is indicated by row label.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.024">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.024</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp10-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s11" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.025</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 11.</label><caption><title>Measurement of rates of class switching.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Motifs analyzed to characterize the rate of CSR. (<bold>B</bold>) Distributions of mutations accumulated prior to class switching. Switches from IgM/IgD to activated classes (IgG, IgA, IgE) are plotted separately from switches between activated classes, as indicated by color. The p value of Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, two-sample comparing these two distributions is shown. (<bold>C</bold>) Cumulative probability of class switching as mutations accumulate. Origin and destination of class switch are indicated by color. (<bold>D</bold>) Rate constants of class switching along all switch paths where we observed &gt;250 direct switches. Exponential distributions were fitted to the distributions of the number of mutations accumulated prior to class switching (see examples in panel <bold>E</bold>) and the rate constant was extracted. (<bold>E</bold>) Examples of exponential distributions (modified to have an additional parameter for non-zero y-intercept [CDF(x) = 1 – exp(-ax) + b]) fitted to the empirical distributions of the number of mutations accumulated prior to class switching. Fit was performed using the curve_fit function in the scipy.optimize module in Python, which implements the Levenberg-Marquardt nonlinear least squares algorithm. Rate constants of the fitted exponential distributions are shown in panel <bold>D</bold>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.025">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.025</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig2-figsupp11-v1"/></fig></fig-group><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.026</object-id><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Number of parent-child pairs having each possible pair of classes. Data from all subjects and both biological replicates are included. Total number of parent-child pairs is 3,304,346. Number in parentheses indicates the relative frequency of each class switch.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.026">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.026</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="8">Parent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>Child</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgM/IgD</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgG3</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgG1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgA1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgG2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgG4</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgE</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgA2</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgM/IgD</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>1,495,250</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG3</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2,530(0.09)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>48,357</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>19,881(0.74)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>4,726(0.18)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>645,591</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgA1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>26,915(1.00)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>935(0.03)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>17,480(0.65)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>493,999</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>12,695(0.47)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>3,178(0.12)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>15,663(0.58)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>8,028(0.30)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>375,284</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG4</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>312(0.01)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>157(0.006)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>342(0.01)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>57(0.002)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>542(0.02)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>16,091</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgE</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>10(0.0004)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0(0)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>16(0.0006)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>5(0.0002)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>1(0.00004)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>3(0.0001)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>419</p> </td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgA2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>7,344(0.27)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>139(0.005)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>2,934(0.11)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>12,176(0.45)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>6,455(0.24)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>17(0.0006)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>0(0)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>86,814</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Variation in class switching landscape between individuals</title><p>Next, we examined how the landscape of class switching varies between individuals. The landscapes of individual subjects are broadly similar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s9">Figure 2—figure supplements 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s10">10</xref>), and the dominant usage of several major switch pathways is conserved across all subjects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s9">Figure 2—figure supplement 9D</xref>). This similarity is also apparent when measured by the Jensen-Shannon distance, which reveals that the magnitude of variation between subjects is similar to variation between biological replicates of the same subject (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s9">Figure 2—figure supplement 9A and B</xref>). We conclude that healthy young adults share a broadly conserved landscape of antibody class switching.</p><p>We also asked whether class switching landscapes were more similar among identical twins compared to unrelated individuals. We found that the class switching patterns of identical twins are no better correlated than pairs of unrelated individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s9">Figure 2—figure supplement 9A–C</xref>), suggesting that the regulation of CSR involves substantial environmental or stochastic influences, as has been found in many other parameters of the immune system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Brodin et al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Class switch recombination from naïve to activated classes is slower than between activated classes</title><p>Despite progress in dissecting the molecular mechanisms of CSR, many fundamental characteristics of class switching under physiological conditions remain unresolved. For example, the tempo of class switching within activated B cell lineages has not been measured. Motivated by this, we used somatic mutations as a molecular clock to measure the rate of CSR between naïve and activated classes within clonal lineages. We searched the clonal lineage trees for motifs consisting of multiple sequences sharing the same class that accumulated mutations prior to a class switch event (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s11">Figure 2—figure supplement 11A</xref>). We asked how many somatic mutations accumulate prior to CSR and whether different antibody classes tend to accumulate different numbers of mutations before class switching.</p><p>We found that naïve classes (IgM or IgD) accumulated significantly more mutations before undergoing CSR to activated classes (IgG, IgA, or IgE), in comparison with CSR between activated classes. Among IgM/IgD sequences, the average number of mutations accumulated in the variable region prior to CSR is 4.1 ± 6.7 (mean ± s.d.). In contrast, only 2.5 ± 4.3 mutations accumulate in sequences of activated classes prior to further CSR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s11">Figure 2—figure supplement 11B and C</xref>; p = 1.8 × 10<sup>–45</sup> and 1.3 × 10<sup>–12</sup> for Samples and Bio. Rep. respectively; Mann-Whitney U test, two-sided). We found that the distributions of mutations accumulated prior to CSR were well fit by an exponential distribution, suggesting that CSR is a memory-less process with respect to somatic mutation and allowing us to estimate rates of CSR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s11">Figure 2—figure supplement 11E</xref>). We found that the rate constants of class switching from IgM/IgD to activated classes were ~0.37 mutation<sup>-1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). By contrast, the rate constants of switching between activated classes were ~0.60 mutation<sup>-1</sup> (p &lt; 1.5 × 10<sup>–4</sup>; Mann-Whitney U test, two-sided). These patterns were robustly observed across biological replicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s11">Figure 2—figure supplement 11D</xref>). Because class switching can be initiated from mutated IgM memory cells for which we may have failed to detect naïve progenitors, our measurements of the number of mutations accumulated in IgM sequences prior to class switching are likely an underestimate, supporting an argument for differences in the rate of CSR between naïve and activated classes. Thus, our results suggest that activated B cells which have already undergone class switching tend to rapidly undergo further class switching, as measured by the clock of somatic hypermutation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Class switch fates are strongly correlated among closely related cells and lose coherence as somatic mutations accumulate</title><p>The isotype composition of the antibody repertoire is ultimately determined by class switch decisions made by individual B cells, which belong to clonal lineages. However, nothing is known about how class switch fates vary among cells within a clonal lineage. To address this, we traced the descent of individual B cells, using somatic mutations as both lineage markers and a molecular clock, and examined the class switch fates of clonally related cells. We asked whether closely related cells, as measured by the number of somatic mutations accumulated in their sequences since their divergence from a common progenitor, exhibit more concordant class switch fates than more distantly related cells, as well as unrelated cells (from distinct clonal lineages).</p><p>To find pairs of related cells, we searched the clonal lineage trees for motifs consisting of a pair of sequences that (1) shared a common progenitor, (2) were the same class, and (3) each had class-switched progeny (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). We further required that each sequence inherit all of the somatic mutations present in its ancestor, yielding ~40,000 pairs of sequences for this analysis. We binned these sequence pairs by their mutational distance from the common progenitor, revealing that the pairs spanned a broad spectrum of relatedness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>). For each level of relatedness (bin), we calculated the probability that both sequences in a pair switched to the same class. To quantify the strength of concordance, we used Yule’s Q, which measures the agreement between pairs of sequences. Yule’s Q ranges from -1 to 1, with 1 indicating that both sequences always switched to the same class (perfect agreement), -1 indicating that the two sequences always switched to different classes (perfect disagreement), and 0 indicating no correlation between the fates of sequences in a pair.</p><p>We discovered that closely related cells made highly concordant class switch decisions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). The most closely related cells, separated by ≤2 mutations from their common progenitor, had a very significant tendency to switch to the same class, in contrast to unrelated pairs of cells which were obtained by shuffling (p values ranging from 6 × 10<sup>–5</sup> to 1.1 × 10<sup>–186</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3</xref>). When we examined pairs of cells that were less closely related (as measured by mutations from their common progenitor), we found that the concordance in class switch fates dissipated as somatic mutations accumulated, becoming indistinguishable from unrelated cells after ~10 somatic mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4</xref>). These findings were corroborated by examining the probability distributions of class switch fate conditioned upon the fate of a closely related cell: closely related cells exhibit probability distributions that are strongly biased toward the same class switch fate, and the bias dissipates as somatic mutations accumulate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s5">Figure 3—figure supplement 5</xref>). Importantly, we found that mutational distances (i.e. branch lengths) are not associated with particular switching events (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s6">Figure 3—figure supplement 6</xref>), and that mutational distances among related sequences are not correlated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s7">Figure 3—figure supplement 7</xref>), indicating that correlations in switch fate are not due to differential sampling of lineages. These findings demonstrate that class switch decisions are coordinated within clonal lineages of B cells in living humans and that this coordination dissipates at large genealogical distances within a lineage.<fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.027</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Class switch fates of closely related sequences are correlated and lose coherence as somatic mutations accumulate.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Concordance between the class switch fates of closely related sequences having ≤2 substitutions from their common progenitor, as measured using Yule’s Q. Distinct switch paths are indicated on the x-axis. Bars show standard deviation of the concordance Q betweenpairs of unrelated sequences, which were obtained by shuffling (1000 replicates). (<bold>B</bold>) Concordance between the class switch fates of pairs of sequences plotted by their relatedness, as measured by number of mutations from their common progenitor. For comparison, red shading indicates the probability density of concordance between unrelated sequence pairs obtained by shuffling (1000 replicates). To account for variation due to sampling statistics, the number of pairs at each level of relatedness was preserved during shuffling.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.027">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.027</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.028</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Motif analyzed to characterize the class switch fates of clonally related cells.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.028">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.028</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig3-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.029</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Relatedness of the pairs of cells used to characterize the class switch fates of clonally related cells in vivo.</title><p>Distributions of relatedness between pairs of related sequences measured by the maximum number of mutations among the two sequences to their common progenitor (most recent common ancestor [MRCA]).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.029">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.029</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig3-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.030</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Estimation of significance of correlations between class switch fates of related sequences.</title><p>Plots show examples of distributions of Yule’s Q for unrelated sequence pairs obtained by shuffling with 1000 replicates, together with fitted Gaussian distribution and observed value of Yule’s Q for the most closely related cells (2 or fewer mutations from common progenitor) for comparison. We calculated the exact one-sided p value of the observed value of Yule’s Q as the probability of the Gaussian random variable taking a value greater than or equal to the observed value of Q.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.030">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.030</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig3-figsupp3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.031</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Concordance between the class switch fates of related sequences plotted against relatedness as measured by number of mutations from common progenitor for all common switch paths.</title><p>Column header indicates class of the related sequences. Title of each panel indicates the downstream switch destination. Observed data are shown in red. Gray lines indicate concordance between unrelated sequence pairs obtained by shuffling (1000 replicates) while preserving the number of pairs having each degree of relatedness to account for variation due to sampling statistics.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.031">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.031</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig3-figsupp4-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s5" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.032</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 5.</label><caption><title>Closely related B cells often switch to the same class.</title><p>Probability distributions of class switch fate conditioned upon the fate of closely related cell. These plots represent the probability distribution of class switch fate of 'Related cell 2', given the fate of 'Related cell 1'. Column header indicates class of the related sequences. X-axis label of each row indicates the class switch fate of 'Related cell 1'. Color indicates the relatedness of the cells, measured by the number of mutations from common progenitor. Number of sequence pairs contributing to each panel N is shown. Right panel shows original samples and left panel shows biological replicates.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.032">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.032</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig3-figsupp5-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s6" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.033</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 6.</label><caption><title>Branch lengths are not associated with particular switching events.</title><p>Fraction of switches from naïve classes (IgM/IgD) to each possible destination class is shown as a function of mutational distance (bins in increments of 2 mutations) from (<bold>A</bold>) common progenitor (most recent common ancestor [MRCA]) to parent cell, and (<bold>B</bold>) parent cell to switched progeny.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.033">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.033</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig3-figsupp6-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s7" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.034</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 7.</label><caption><title>Mutational distances among related cells, common progenitors, and switched progeny are not correlated.</title><p>Number of mutations from (<bold>A</bold>) common progenitor (most recent common ancestor [MRCA]) to cell 1 and cell 2, (<bold>B</bold>) cell 1 to switched progeny and cell 2 to switched progeny, and (<bold>C</bold>) common progenitor to cell and cell to switched progeny. The mutational distances compared in each panel are indicated by the colored edges in the motif on the right (x-axis, orange; y-axis, blue). Color indicates number of pairs of related sequences in each bin. Squared Pearson correlation values are shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.034">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.034</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig3-figsupp7-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Coordination of class switch fate within clonal lineages is an autonomous property of purified B cells</title><p>We reasoned that the coordination of class switch decisions among closely related cells could arise if CSR is directed to specific isotypes by cytokine signals originating from cognate cells in spatially localized niches, which sister cells at some point co-occupy and therefore are directed synchronously toward the same class switch fate. Alternatively, sister cells might share an imprinted state, which is transmitted from a common progenitor and directs CSR toward specific isotypes in a cell-autonomous fashion. To discriminate between these models and test whether cellular interactions are necessary to generate correlations between class switch fates of sibling cells, we measured the class switch behavior of purified primary human B cells stimulated with cytokines in culture. We purified CD19+ IgM+ B cells from whole blood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>) and cultured them in the presence of multimeric CD40 ligand (CD40L), IL-4, and IL-10 for 8 days, then prepared sequencing libraries of the IGH locus. The purified B cells were 99.6% CD19+ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref>), and sequencing of the IgM+ cells used to initiate the culture revealed that 97% of the sequences were IgM/IgD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). During culture, the cells proliferated and underwent class switching to IgG1, IgG2, IgG3, and IgA1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). After reconstructing the histories of clonal lineages, we identified ~1900 pairs of IgM/IgD sequences sharing a common progenitor that subsequently underwent class switching.<fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.035</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Class switch fates of closely related sequences are correlated in purified B cells induced to class switch in vitro.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Class composition of CD19+ IgM+ cells used to initiate cell culture as measured by sequencing of the IGH locus. (<bold>B</bold>) Class composition of cells after culture for 8 days in the presence of multimeric CD40L, IL-4 and IL-10 (mean of three replicates). (<bold>C</bold>) Concordance between class switch fates of closely related sequences having ≤2 mutations from their common progenitor measured using Yule’s Q. Distinct switch paths are indicated on the x-axis. Bars show standard deviation of the concordance Q for unrelated pairs of sequences, which were obtained by shuffling (1000 replicates). Results of three replicate experiments are indicated by color.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.035">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.035</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig4-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.036</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Purification of CD19+ IgM+ B cells for in vitro culture.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Fluorescence activated cell sorting (FACS) procedure for purifying CD19+ IgM+ B cells. Purified B cell populations obtained using RosetteSep were stained with CD19-PE, CD20-AF647, IgM-BV421, passed through a 40 um filter, and sorted on a Sony SH800 instrument (top). Fluorescence intensity cutoffs for CD19+ and IgM+ were set based on an unstained control (bottom). Analysis of CD20-AF647 fluorescence confirmed that 99.9% of CD19+ IgM+ cells were CD20+. Abbreviations: PE, phycoerythrin; AF647, AlexaFluor 647; BV421, Brilliant Violet 421. (<bold>B</bold>) Analysis of sorted CD19+ IgM+ populations immediately after sort to confirm purity.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.036">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.036</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig4-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.037</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Relatedness of the pairs of cells used to characterize the class switch fates of clonally related cells in vitro.</title><p>Distributions of relatedness between pairs of sister sequences, as measured by the maximum number of mutations among the two sequences to their common progenitor (most recent common ancestor [MRCA]).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.037">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.037</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-16578-fig4-figsupp2-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>In vitro, the concordance between the class switch fates of the most closely related cells was as evident as in vivo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). Closely related sequences separated from a common progenitor by ≤2 substitutions exhibited a highly significant tendency to switch to the same class, in comparison with unrelated sequences (p values ranging from 5 × 10<sup>–4</sup> to 5 × 10<sup>–28</sup>). Since sequences having more somatic mutations were exceedingly rare (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>), it was not possible to examine the dissipation of concordance as somatic mutations accumulated. Importantly, no pairs of sequences sharing a common progenitor that subsequently underwent class switching were detected in the IgM+ B cell populations that initiated the culture, confirming that imperfect IgM+ B cell purification cannot account for the class switches detected after culturing. These results demonstrate that coordination of class switch decisions in clonal lineages of B cells is not dependent upon the in vivo environment and interactions with cognate cells, but rather seems to be an autonomous property of purified B cells. This finding suggests that CSR is directed toward specific isotypes by an imprinted state, which is transmitted from a common progenitor to sister cells.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Deep sequencing of the immune repertoire offers unprecedented views into the human immune system. In this study, we set out to use antibody repertoire sequencing to investigate the nature of antibody class switching in healthy humans. The mechanisms of CSR and each individual's history of immune activation leave indelible imprints on the diversity of immunoglobulin sequences. We have exploited these signatures to characterize patterns of class switching in the natural setting in living humans and dissect the cellular processes that govern CSR.</p><p>Our findings provide a comprehensive map of the patterns of antibody class switching in humans. The data reveal that pathways of CSR are organized into two tiers: (1) naïve classes (IgM/IgD) switch predominantly to proximal classes such as IgG3, IgG1, or IgA1, and (2) proximal classes may subsequently switch to distal classes, such as IgG2, IgG4, or IgA2. IgG1 and IgA1 seem to be central intermediates linking naïve to distal classes. This pattern is evident from (1) the high probability of switching from naïve to proximal classes together with the low probability of switching directly from naïve to distal classes, and (2) observations of frequent sequential switches via IgG3, IgG1, and IgA1 intermediates. This hierarchy mirrors the linear geometry of the IGH constant region loci on chromosome 14, suggesting that chromosomal structure or topology influences CSR. Consistent with this, previous studies which showed that mouse B cells stimulated in vitro with CD40L and IL-4 switched to IgG1 with high frequency after three divisions, while switching to the downstream classes IgE and IgG2a increased after five or six divisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Hasbold et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hodgkin et al., 1996</xref>). A previous study on human populations reported increasing levels of point mutation in progressively further downstream IgG subclasses, supporting sequential class switching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Jackson et al., 2014b</xref>). This study also suggested the existence of a preferential switch pathway from IgG2 to IgA2 based on evidence of stronger antigen-driven selection in IgA2 than IgA1 sequences, which is consistent with our results. Our examination of clonal histories of B cell lineages with mixed isotypes provides more direct evidence for sequential class switching and the existence of dominant class switch pathways. While our lineage reconstruction approach circumvents the difficulties associated with ancestral inference and probabilistic models of class switching, one limitation is that measurements of switch rates can be affected by undersampling of ancestors, especially for switches between rare classes, such as IgE and IgG4. We have estimated this undersampling rate by using a Chapman estimator to gauge the total number of each isotype in circulation compared to the number we detected, and found results ranging from 0.1% to 5% depending on the subject, which does not affect any of the conclusions of this work.</p><p>Prior to this work a limited number of class transitions had been observed in human samples. Our data identifies ten transitions which to our knowledge have not been previously identified (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). In conjunction with other published results, it appears that, with the possible exception of IgE, any transition which is permitted to happen by the geometry of the immunoglobulin locus is observed in healthy human samples. This finding supports the view that the machinery underlying CSR is intrinsically stochastic, and that biological regulation enforces probabilistic preferences, rather than strict rules in switch behavior.<table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.038</object-id><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Summary of class switch recombination events that have been observed in human cells. Switches that have previously been observed are indicated as 'Known' and the literature references are provided. All of the previous studies demonstrated the existence of switch events by sequencing recombination junctions or switch circles. 'Novel' indicates switches which have not previously been reported that we observed in our dataset of ~35,000 pairs of sequences sharing identical VDJ sequences, but having different constant region genes. 'Not detected' indicates switches that we did not observe in this dataset of identical sequences.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.038">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.038</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="7">Source class</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>Destination class</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgM/IgD</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgG3</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgG1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgA1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgG2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgG4</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>IgE</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG3</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Fujieda et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Malisan et al., 1996</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Fujieda et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Malisan et al., 1996</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgA1</p> </td><td valign="top">Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Jabara et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Zan et al., 1998</xref>)</td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lin et al., 2014</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Zan et al., 1998</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Malisan et al., 1996</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG4</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Fujieda et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Jabara et al., 1993</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgE</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Jabara et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Xiong et al., 2012</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Not detected</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Xiong et al., 2012</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Not detected</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Jabara et al., 1993</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgA2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">He et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lin et al., 2014</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lin et al., 2014</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lin et al., 2014</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">He et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lin et al., 2014</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lin et al., 2014</xref>)</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Novel</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>Not detected</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>The broad contours of the class switching landscape appear to be conserved across individuals, but there is variation between individuals that likely reflects differences in the history of immune activation and environmental exposure. Importantly, identical twins did not exhibit identical class switching landscapes, indicating that class switching is driven largely by non-heritable factors, which likely include exposure to pathogens or other microbes. Previous studies of identical twins have suggested that genetic background controls features of the antibody repertoire, such as IGHV, IGHD, and IGHJ gene use, and CDR3 length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Wang et al., 2015</xref>). On the other hand, studies examining other components of the immune system have indicated that non-heritable factors dominantly influence most features of serological and cellular responses, including serum protein abundances and cell populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Brodin et al., 2015</xref>). Our findings suggest that variation between human in the class composition of the antibody repertoire is predominantly driven by the ability of the immune system to adapt to environmental stimuli, rather than genetic predisposition. Unique landscapes of antibody class switching in identical twins likely arise from the unpredictable stimulation of B cell clones and different exposure to many microbes over the course of a lifetime. Our measurement of the conserved class switching landscape of healthy, young adult humans provides a reference for comparison against individuals with altered immune states, such as autoimmunity or chronic infection.</p><p>Our work demonstrates how somatic mutations can be exploited as a molecular clock to reconstruct the genealogies of cells and characterize the dynamics of cell state. We have uncovered strong correlations between the class switch fates of closely related B cells which have undergone maturation in the natural context in living humans. These correlations appear to decay on a timescale of ~10 somatic mutations. Such correlations between closely related cells are also generated during in vitro culture of purified B cell populations in the presence of cytokines that induce class switching, demonstrating that the correlations are an autonomous property of purified B cells and that the in vivo environment is not necessary to create them. Although cytokine signals driving CSR in vivo likely originate from cognate T helper cells and dendritic cells in localized intercellular niches, our experiments show that correlations in class switch fate between sibling cells cannot simply be attributed to exposure to common signals due to co-occupancy of the same niche. This mode of regulation contrasts with stem cell maintenance and differentiation in the mammalian lung, which are regulated by signaling from parent/progenitor cells to daughter cells in localized niches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Pardo-Saganta et al., 2015</xref>). We note that the correlations that we observed in vitro were not quite as strong as those seen in vivo, suggesting that cellular interactions in the natural context might enhance sibling correlations in class switch fates. We note that in our culture experiments the starting populations were heterogeneous and included both naïve and memory B cells, leaving the lineage characteristics of class switching within these compartments to be examined in future work.</p><p>Our data suggest a model where CSR is directed toward specific classes by a transient epigenetic state, which is transmitted from parent cells to daughter cells and relaxes on a timescale of ~10 somatic mutations. Consistent with this, directed CSR is thought to be regulated via cytokine-activated transcription at specific IGHC loci, which targets the region for modification by activation-induced cytidine deaminase (AID). Germline transcription of IGHC genes is associated with histone modifications that increase DNA accessibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jeevan-Raj et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Wang et al., 2009</xref>), and germline IGHC transcripts can form RNA-DNA hybrids with genomic DNA, exposing ssDNA to AID attack (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Reaban and Griffin, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Reaban et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Yu et al., 2003</xref>). Using single-cell transcriptomics, we have found that single B cells stimulated to class switch in vitro often predominantly express germline transcripts from a single IGHC locus (F. Horns, unpublished data). We propose that inheritance during mitosis of germline transcripts and chromatin state in the IGHC locus, including perhaps histone modifications influencing DNA accessibility, is a mechanism that generates correlations in the class switch fates of sister cells. Importantly, epigenetic inheritance of active and repressed chromatin state during mitosis has been demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Cavalli and Paro, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Grewal and Klar, 1996</xref>). Our measurements suggest that the timescale on which the relative accessibility of IGHC loci persists is ~10 somatic mutations. Calibration of the mutational clock should allow recovery of information about epigenetic state and phenotypic dynamics in units of time and cellular generations. Together with recent studies of mammalian (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Spencer et al., 2009</xref>) and bacterial cells in culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Hormoz et al., 2015</xref>), our work suggests that phenotypic correlations between sister cells due to shared inheritance are widespread. We predict that such correlations often will be detected when genealogical relationships between individual cells can be resolved. We propose that inheritance of epigenetic state provides a mechanism for orchestrating cellular behavior without the need for signaling.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Twin cohort</title><p>All study participants gave informed consent and protocols were approved by the Stanford Institutional Review Board. Twenty-two human twins aged 18–28, including 11 males and 11 females, were recruited in 2010. All subjects were apparently healthy and showed no signs of disease. Twin zygosity was determined by short tandem repeat analysis with 18 loci. Monozygosity was assigned when all loci and the gender-determining marker were identical.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Sample collection, PBMC isolation, and RNA extraction</title><p>Blood was drawn from each subject by venipuncture. Peripheral-blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) were isolated using a Ficoll gradient and frozen in 10% (vol/vol) DMSO/40% (vol/vol) fetal bovine serum (FBS) following Stanford Human Immune Monitoring Center protocols. After cells were thawed, total RNA was extracted using the Qiagen AllPrep kit (Valencia, CA). Subjects were vaccinated with the 2010 seasonal trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine immediately after the sample was drawn. Biological replicates were drawn 28 days later. Biological replicates were indistinguishable from the original samples with respect to antibody class and V gene usage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s4">Figure 1—figure supplements 4B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s7">7</xref>), as expected given that the most pronounced immune response occurs 7 days after vaccination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Wrammert et al., 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Library preparation</title><p>Sequencing libraries were prepared using 500 ng of total RNA as input following the protocol described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Vollmers et al., 2013</xref>). Briefly, primer annealing to a pooled set of five isotype-specific IGH constant region primers that contain 8 random nts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl5">Table 5</xref>) was carried out at 72°C for 3 min then immediately placed on ice for 2 min. First-strand cDNA synthesis was performed using Superscript III reverse transcriptase (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA) according to manufacturer's instructions. Second-strand cDNA synthesis was done using Phusion HiFi DNA polymerase (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA) and a pool of six IGH variable region primers that contain 8 random nts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl6">Table 6</xref>) (98°C for 4 min, 52°C for 1 min, 72°C for 5 min). Double-stranded cDNA was purified twice using Ampure XP beads (Beckman Coulter, Indianapolis, IN) at a 1:1 ratio, then amplified using Platinum HiFi enzyme (Life Technologies) and primers containing Illumina adapters and dual indexes. PCR products were purified once using Ampure XP beads at a 1:1 ratio then pooled for multiplexed sequencing.<table-wrap id="tbl5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.039</object-id><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>IGH constant region primers.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.039">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.039</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Name</th><th>Primer (5’ to 3’)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgM</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>TGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNTGCCTCGCACAGGACTTC</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgD</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>TGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNTGCTTGATAACTGGGTACCA</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgE</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>TGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNCCTGGCCACGGGCTACTT</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgA</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>TGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNGTCCAGGGCTTCTTCCCC</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>IgG</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>TGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNCTGCCTGGTCAAGGACTACT</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.040</object-id><label>Table 6.</label><caption><p>IGH variable region primers.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.16578.040">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.16578.040</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Name</th><th>Primer (5’ to 3’)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>Primer1_1_70</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>ACACTCTTTCCCTACACGACGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNSCAGCTGGTGCAGTCTGG</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>Primer1/3/5_70</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>ACACTCTTTCCCTACACGACGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNGTGCAGCTGGTGGAGTCTG</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>Primer2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>ACACTCTTTCCCTACACGACGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNTCACCTTGAAGGAGTCTGG</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>Primer4_1</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>ACACTCTTTCCCTACACGACGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNTGCAGCTGCAGGAGTCG</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>Primer4_2</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>ACACTCTTTCCCTACACGACGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNGTGCAGCTACAGCAGTGG</p> </td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>Primer6</p> </td><td valign="top"><p>ACACTCTTTCCCTACACGACGCTCTTCCGATCTNNNNNNNNGTACAGCTGCAGCAGTCA</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Sequencing and data preprocessing</title><p>High-throughput sequencing was performed on the Illumina MiSeq platform (Illumina, San Diego, CA) with 300 bp paired end reads. Reads were passed through a pipeline to construct consensus sequences from reads containing the same 16 nt random barcode similar to (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Vollmers et al., 2013</xref>). Base quality scores in the consensus were calculated from the error probabilities associated with bases in the raw reads. Sequences were annotated with V and J germline gene usage and CDR3 length using IgBlast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Ye et al., 2013</xref>). Classes were determined using BLASTN against a custom database of IGH constant region fragments. We have deposited the sequencing reads in the Sequence Read Archive (accession number PRJNA324281). Preprocessed sequence data and custom analysis scripts are available for download (doi:10.5061/dryad.bv989).</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Lineage clustering</title><p>Sequences belonging to the same clonal B cell lineage were identified using clustering as follows. Sequences sharing the same V-J combination and CDR3 length were grouped. Within each group, clusters were found by performing single linkage clustering with a cutoff of 95% sequence identity across both the CDR3 and the rest of the variable region. Sequence identity was computed from ungapped pairwise alignments by counting mismatches. Stringent quality filtering was implemented by assuming mismatches at positions at which the base in either aligned sequence had Q ≤ 5.</p><p>To choose the optimal cutoff for identifying sequences in clonal lineages, we examined the distributions of pairwise sequence identity within groups of CDR3 sequences sharing the same V and J gene combination and CDR3 length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s5">Figure 1—figure supplement 5</xref>). By plotting the identity of each sequence to the most similar sequence in its group (its 'nearest neighbor'), we saw that sequences separate into two groups: sequences with a highly similar nearest neighbor (&gt;90% identity) and sequences that are substantially dissimilar to the nearest neighbor (40–80% identity). This pattern suggests that the first group consists of sequences that belong to a clonal lineage, while the second group consists of singleton sequences. Thus using a stringent cutoff of 95% sequence identity in the CDR3 ensures that the identified lineages contain sequences that are clonally related. In order to show that the results are not sensitive to the particular choice of a cutoff value we repeated subsequent analyses with cutoffs varying from 80% to 95% and obtained nearly identical results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s7">Figure 2—figure supplement 7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Rarefaction analysis</title><p>Rarefaction of preprocessed sequences, which represent molecules of IGH mRNA, was performed by selecting a fraction of sequences uniformly at random from the sequences prior to lineage clustering using a custom script written in Python.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Reconstructing clonal histories of lineages</title><p>The clonal history of each lineage was reconstructed using a custom algorithm. An ungapped multiple alignment of sequences in each lineage was performed by aligning the anchor sequences that mark the start and end of the CDR3. The concatenated sequences of the V and J germline genes were then added to this alignment by performing a profile-profile alignment using MUSCLE with options '-maxiters 2 –diags' which introduces a gap corresponding to the D gene and untemplated nucleotides. A pairwise distance matrix was constructed by counting the number of substitutions required to transform each aligned sequence into the others. This matrix defines a weighted graph of possible ancestor-child relationships. A constraint on ancestry based on antibody class was then applied by pruning edges that violate the geometry of the IGH constant region locus. The minimum evolution tree was identified by using Edmonds’ algorithm to find a minimum spanning tree on this directed graph (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Edmonds, 1967</xref>). The tree was rooted on the germline sequence.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Measuring class switching landscapes</title><p>Class switching events were identified by traversing the minimum evolution tree for each lineage and searching for ancestor-child pairs of sequences having different classes. The probabilities that define the class switching landscape were calculated as follows. Relative switch frequency is equal to the number of switches observed from A to B divided by the total number of switches. Destination probability, which describes the probability that a cell switching from the ancestral class will choose the downstream class as the destination, is equal to the number of class switches from class A to class B divided by the total number of switches exiting class A. Similarly, arrival probability, which describes the probability that a cell of a given downstream class originated from the ancestral class, is equal to the number of class switches from class A to class B by the total number of switches entering class B. To generate shuffled ancestor-child pairs, we performed sampling without replacement on the list of ancestor classes to assign an ancestor class to each child class.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Calculating twin correlations</title><p>To quantify correlations between twins, we developed a generalization of the intraclass correlation coefficient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Shrout and Fleiss, 1979</xref>) for multidimensional data. We treat each measurement as an n-dimensional vector, where n is the number of probabilities measured per twin. To calculate the between- and within-target variance, we computed the distance from the mean vector using the squared Euclidean norm. Intraclass correlation is then equal to (B – W)/(B + W), where B is the between-target variance and W is the within-target variance. To calculate intraclass correlation for twins, the twin pairs are treated as the within-target pairs. For unrelated individuals, all possible pairs of unrelated individuals are treated as the within-target pairs.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Analysis of rates of class switching</title><p>To quantify the amount of hypermutation between class switching events, we searched in the clonal lineage trees for motifs consisting of multiple parent-child pairs sharing the same class prior to a class switch event. We filtered for motifs in which each child sequence inherited all of the somatic mutations relative to the V and J germline genes that were present in its parent, yielding ~74,000 switches for this analysis. The number of mutations accumulated before CSR was calculated by summing the number of substitutions separating parent-child pairs prior to the class switching event. Fitting of an exponential distribution to the empirical distribution of the number of mutations prior to class switching was performed using Python and SciPy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Oliphant, 2007</xref>) in the IPython environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Perez and Granger, 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Analysis of correlations in class switch fates among related cells</title><p>To explore the inheritance of class switching fates, we searched in the trees for motifs in which two clonally related sequences sharing the same class (1) descended from a common progenitor of the same class and (2) subsequently switched to different classes. We further filtered for motifs where each descendant sequence inherited all of the somatic mutations relative to the V and J germline genes present in its ancestor. We binned these sequence pairs by relatedness measured by the number of substitutions separating the sequences from the common progenitor, using the maximum number among the two sequences. We then examined the downstream class to which each sequence switched. To quantify concordance, we calculated Yule's Q from the odds ratio describing whether both sequences switched to the same downstream class. Focusing on a single downstream class, let <italic>a</italic> be the number of cases where both sequence 1 and sequence 2 switched to this class, <italic>d</italic> be the number of cases where both sequence 1 and sequence 2 did not switch to this class, and <italic>b</italic> and <italic>c</italic> be the number of cases where sequence 1 switched to this class, but sequence 2 did not, and vice versa, respectively. Then the odds ratio OR is (ad)/(bc) and Yule’s Q is (OR – 1) / (OR + 1). We also examined the conditional probabilities describing the class switch fate of one sequence given the class switch fate of the other sequence.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Cell culture</title><p>We obtained whole blood drawn from volunteers at the Stanford Blood Center and prepared enriched B cell fractions using the RosetteSep kit (StemCell Technologies, Cambridge, MA) according to manufacturer’s instructions. We sorted CD19+ IgM+ cells and cultured them at 5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml for 5 days at 37 C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> in RPMI 1640 with L-glutamine (ThermoFisher) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 10 mM HEPES pH 7.4, 0.1 mM non-essential amino acid (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO), 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 100 µ/ml penicillin, 100 µg/ml streptomycin (ThermoFisher), 40 µg/ml apo-transferrin, 500 ng/µl multimeric CD40 ligand (Miltenyi Biotec, San Diego, CA), 200 ng/ml IL-4 (Sigma-Aldrich), and 200 ng/ml IL-10 (Sigma-Aldrich). We extracted RNA from the cells using the RNeasy Micro Kit (Qiagen) according to manufacturer’s instructions, but omitting the DNase digestion step. We then prepared sequencing libraries using 24.5 ng of total RNA as input as described above, except that PCR products were purified using Ampure XP beads at a 0.65:1 ratio instead of a 1:1 ratio before pooling for multiplexed sequencing. We processed the sequences, reconstructed the clonal lineage histories, and measured correlations between the class switch fates of related cells as described above.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank our study volunteers for their participation in this study. Thanks to SLVP vaccine study staff for conducting the clinical study: research nurses Sue Swope and Tony Trela; CRAs Ashima Goel, Sushil Batra, Isaac Chang, Kyrsten Spann, Raquel Fleischmann; and phlebotomist Michele Ugur. We also thank Lolita Penland for help with cell culture experiments; Christopher J Emig for discussions; and Norma Neff, Gary Mantalas and Ben Passarelli (Stanford Stem Cell Genome Center) for assistance with sequencing and computational infrastructure. This research was supported by the National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship (to FH) and NIH U19A1057229 (to MMD). This work was also supported in part by the Clinical and Translational Science Award UL1 RR025744 for the Stanford Center for Clinical and Translational Education and Research (Spectrum) from the National Center for Research Resources, National Institutes of Health.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf1"><p>The authors declare that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>FH, Designed the study, Performed cell culture experiments, Developed pipeline for sequence analysis, Analyzed data, Wrote the manuscript</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>CV, Prepared sequencing libraries from human samples</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>DC, Developed pipeline for sequence analysis</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>SFM, Coordinated subject recruitment and sample collection</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>GES, Coordinated subject recruitment and sample collection</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>CLD, Coordinated subject recruitment and sample collection</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>MMD, Designed the study</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>SRQ, Designed the study, Analyzed data, Wrote the manuscript</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Human subjects: All study participants gave informed consent and protocols were approved by the Stanford Institutional Review Board.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="s7" sec-type="datasets"><title>Major datasets</title><p>The following datasets were generated:</p><p><related-object content-type="generated-dataset" id="data-ro1" source-id="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.bv989" source-id-type="uri"><collab>Felix Horns</collab><x>,</x> <year>2016</year><x>,</x><source>Data from: Lineage Tracing of Human B Cells Reveals the In Vivo Landscape of Human Antibody Class Switching</source><x>,</x> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.bv989">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.bv989</ext-link><x>,</x> <comment>Available at Dryad Digital Repository under a CC0 Public Domain Dedication</comment></related-object></p><p><related-object content-type="generated-dataset" id="data-ro2" source-id="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA324281/" source-id-type="uri"><collab>Felix Horns</collab><x>,</x> <year>2016</year><x>,</x><source>Immunoglobulin heavy chain sequencing</source><x>,</x> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA324281/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA324281/</ext-link><x>,</x> <comment>Publicly available at NCBI BioProject (accession no: PRJNA324281)</comment></related-object></p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alt</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>DePinho</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reth</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yancopoulos</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1986">1986</year><article-title>Regulation of genome rearrangement events during lymphocyte differentiation</article-title><source>Immunological Reviews</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-065X.1986.tb01470.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuckerman</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>IgTree: creating Immunoglobulin variable region gene lineage trees</article-title><source>Journal of Immunological Methods</source><volume>338</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jim.2008.06.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Merker</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniar</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahaf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simen</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanczaruk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Egholm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miklos</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zehnder</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Measurement and clinical monitoring of human lymphocyte clonality by massively parallel VDJ pyrosequencing</article-title><source>Science Translational Medicine</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>12—</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3000540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brodin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jojic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Angel</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Furman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen-Orr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Butte</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maecker</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Variation in the human immune system is largely driven by non-heritable influences</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>160</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.12.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bubier</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sproule</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Foreman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Spolski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roopenian</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>A critical role for IL-21 receptor signaling in the pathogenesis of systemic lupus erythematosus in BXSB-Yaa mice</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>1518</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0807309106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Paro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>The Drosophila Fab-7 chromosomal element conveys epigenetic inheritance during mitosis and meiosis</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>93</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81181-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1967">1967</year><article-title>Optimum branchings</article-title><source>Journal of Research of the National Bureau of Standards Section B Mathematics and Mathematical Physics</source><volume>71B</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6028/jres.071B.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Radbruch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year><article-title>Immunoglobulin class switching: molecular and cellular analysis</article-title><source>Annual Review of Immunology</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.iy.08.040190.003441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujieda</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>IL-4 plus CD40 monoclonal antibody induces human B cells gamma subclass-specific isotype switch: switching to gamma 1, gamma 3, and gamma 4, but not gamma 2</article-title><source>Journal of Immunology</source><volume>155</volume><fpage>2318</fpage><lpage>2328</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Klar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Chromosomal inheritance of epigenetic states in fission yeast during mitosis and meiosis</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80080-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasbold</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kehry</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Cell division number regulates IgG1 and IgE switching of B cells following stimulation by CD40 ligand and IL-4</article-title><source>European Journal of Immunology</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>1040</fpage><lpage>1051</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1521-4141(199803)28:03&lt;1040::AID-IMMU1040&gt;3.0.CO;2-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Santini</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Polydorides</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Estrella</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chadburn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Villanacci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Plebani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rescigno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerutti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Intestinal bacteria trigger T cell-independent immunoglobulin A(2) class switching by inducing epithelial-cell secretion of the cytokine APRIL</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2007.04.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>B cell differentiation and isotype switching is related to division cycle number</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><volume>184</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.184.1.277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hormoz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Desprat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shraiman</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Inferring epigenetic dynamics from kin correlations</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>E2281</fpage><lpage>E2289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1504407112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humby</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bombardieri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Manzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Blades</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkham</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitzalis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Ectopic lymphoid structures support ongoing production of class-switched autoantibodies in rheumatoid synovium</article-title><source>PLoS Medicine</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>e1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0060001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwasato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Honjo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year><article-title>Circular DNA is excised by immunoglobulin class switch recombination</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(90)90248-D</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jabara</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vercelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Geha</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>Sequential switching from mu to epsilon via gamma 4 in human B cells stimulated with IL-4 and hydrocortisone</article-title><source>Journal of Immunology</source><volume>151</volume><fpage>4528</fpage><lpage>4533</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskin</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Glanville</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoh</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurley</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moody</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>García-Sastre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaparro-Riggers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajpal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simen</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanczaruk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Laserson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014a</year><article-title>Human responses to influenza vaccination show seroconversion signatures and convergent antibody rearrangements</article-title><source>Cell Host &amp; Microbe</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2014.05.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014b</year><article-title>Human immunoglobulin classes and subclasses show variability in VDJ gene mutation levels</article-title><source>Immunology and Cell Biology</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>729</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/icb.2014.44</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeevan-Raj</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cammas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Alt</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Losson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reina-San-Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Epigenetic tethering of AID to the donor switch region during immunoglobulin class switch recombination</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><volume>208</volume><fpage>1649</fpage><lpage>1660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20110118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Penland</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Quake</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Lineage structure of the human antibody repertoire in response to influenza vaccination</article-title><source>Science Translational Medicine</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>171ra19</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3004794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Penland</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Quake</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Determinism and stochasticity during maturation of the zebrafish antibody repertoire</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>5348</fpage><lpage>5353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1014277108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kindt</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldsby</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><source>Kuby Immunology</source><publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandtzaeg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan-Hammarström</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>IgA subclass switch recombination in human mucosal and systemic immune compartments</article-title><source>Mucosal Immunology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mi.2013.68</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Malisan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bouteiller</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Guret</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebecque</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Banchereau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Max</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Valdez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Within germinal centers, isotype switching of immunoglobulin genes occurs after the onset of somatic mutation</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1074-7613(00)80432-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Radbruch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Switch transcripts in immunoglobulin class switching</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>267</volume><fpage>1825</fpage><lpage>1828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.7892607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malisan</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Brière</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Harindranath</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Max</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Banchereau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Valdez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Interleukin-10 induces immunoglobulin G isotype switch recombination in human CD40-activated naive B lymphocytes</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><volume>183</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.183.3.937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mietzner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuiji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Velinzon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Stichweh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wardemann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussenzweig</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Autoreactive IgG memory antibodies in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus arise from nonreactive and polyreactive precursors</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>9727</fpage><lpage>9732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0803644105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minegishi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Hyper-IgE syndrome</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Immunology</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coi.2009.07.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliphant</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Python for scientific computing</article-title><source>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MCSE.2007.58</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parameswaran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskin</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Artiles</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zompi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Simen</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanczaruk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourmand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Balmaseda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Convergent antibody signatures in human dengue</article-title><source>Cell Host &amp; Microbe</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2013.05.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pardo-Saganta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tata</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>RDz</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gridley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajagopal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Parent stem cells can serve as niches for their daughter cells</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>523</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>IPython: a system for interactive scientific computing</article-title><source>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MCSE.2007.53</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Racanelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>De Re</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Caggiari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>De Zorzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Perosa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vacca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dammacco</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Antibody V(h) repertoire differences between resolving and chronically evolving hepatitis C virus infections</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e25606</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reaban</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year><article-title>Induction of RNA-stabilized DNA conformers by transcription of an immunoglobulin switch region</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>348</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/348342a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reaban</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebowitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Transcription induces the formation of a stable RNA.DNA hybrid in the immunoglobulin alpha switch region</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>269</volume><fpage>21850</fpage><lpage>21857</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwedler</surname><given-names>U. von</given-names></name><name><surname>Jck</surname><given-names>H-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wabl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year><article-title>Circular DNA is a product of the immunoglobulin class switch rearrangement</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>345</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/345452a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shrout</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleiss</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1979">1979</year><article-title>Intraclass correlations: uses in assessing rater reliability</article-title><source>Psychological Bulletin</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.86.2.420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Albeck</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorger</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Non-genetic origins of cell-to-cell variability in TRAIL-induced apoptosis</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>459</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stavnezer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Immunoglobulin class switching</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Immunology</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0952-7915(96)80058-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stavnezer-Nordgren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1986">1986</year><article-title>Specificity of immunoglobulin heavy chain switch correlates with activity of germline heavy chain genes prior to switching</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>IgG4-related disease</article-title><source>New England Journal of Medicine</source><volume>366</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1104650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusunoki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Katakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Essential role of Id2 in negative regulation of IgE class switching</article-title><source>Nature Immunology</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tangye</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Isotype switching by human B cells is division-associated and regulated by cytokines</article-title><source>Journal of Immunology</source><volume>169</volume><fpage>4298</fpage><lpage>4306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.169.8.4298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaidyanathan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Epigenetic codes programing class switch recombination</article-title><source>Frontiers in Immunology</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>405</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2015.00405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vollmers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sit</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Quake</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Genetic measurement of memory B-cell recall using antibody repertoire sequencing</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>13463</fpage><lpage>13468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1312146110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Saux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskin</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Looney</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Goronzy</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>B-cell repertoire responses to varicella-zoster vaccination in human identical twins</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1415875112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskin</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Laserson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Furman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Effects of aging, cytomegalovirus infection, and EBV infection on human B cell repertoires</article-title><source>Journal of Immunology</source><volume>192</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1301384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuerffel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khamlichi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenter</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>S region sequence, RNA polymerase II, and histone modifications create chromatin accessibility during class switch recombination</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><volume>206</volume><fpage>1817</fpage><lpage>1830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20081678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Quake</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>High-throughput sequencing of the zebrafish antibody repertoire</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>324</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1170020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wrammert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mays</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Garman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Air</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Capra</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Rapid cloning of high-affinity human monoclonal antibodies against influenza virus</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>453</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolpady</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wabl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Curotto de Lafaille</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafaille</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Sequential class switching is required for the generation of high affinity IgE antibodies</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><volume>209</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20111941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>IgBLAST: an immunoglobulin variable domain sequence analysis tool</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>W34</fpage><lpage>W40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Usuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishizaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year><article-title>Immunoglobulin switch circular DNA in the mouse infected with Nippostrongylus brasiliensis: evidence for successive class switching from mu to epsilon via gamma 1</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>7829</fpage><lpage>7833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.87.20.7829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chedin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieber</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>R-loops at immunoglobulin class switch regions in the chromosomes of stimulated B cells</article-title><source>Nature Immunology</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerutti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dramitinos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Casali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>CD40 engagement triggers switching to IgA1 and IgA2 in human B cells through induction of endogenous TGF-beta: evidence for TGF-beta but not IL-10-dependent direct S mu--&gt;S alpha and sequential S mu--&gt;S gamma, S gamma--&gt;S alpha DNA recombination</article-title><source>Journal of Immunology</source><volume>161</volume><fpage>5217</fpage><lpage>5225</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="article-commentary" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.045</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>Richard A</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff12"><institution>Max Planck Institute for Developmental Biology</institution>, <country>Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Lineage Tracing of Human B Cells Reveals the in vivo Landscape of Human Antibody Class Switching&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Arup Chakraborty as the Senior Editor. The reviewers have opted to remain anonymous.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>The manuscript uses sequencing reads of the variable region and parts of the surrounding constant region of immunoglobulin heavy chains to investigate the dynamics of class switch recombination (CSR) in humans. The data are used to infer the relative rates of all possible class switch events. The authors further demonstrate that class switch recombination is correlated within clonal B cell lineages and that this correlation decreases with increasing distance of the variable part of the sequence. All reviewers agreed that these are interesting results addressing an important question. However, we identified various points that require further discussion or additional analysis.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) It is not clear how errors were corrected using the molecular barcodes. You state that you obtained ~261k reads per sample which typically represented 170k distinct molecules (subsection “Antibody Repertoire Sequencing with Subclass Resolution”, first paragraph). This would suggest that most barcodes are represented only once and no consensus sequence of (&gt;=3 sequences) can be computed. Did you use singleton and doubleton barcodes as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref> suggests? If so, sequencing errors likely contribute to diversity in many of the clonal clusters (the inserts are quite long and the end of the 2nd read often has low sequencing quality, hence sequencing errors are a concern).</p><p>While it seems plausible that errors rarely produce sequences that have different classes, sequencing errors can produce additional sequences that are more similar to a sequence of a different class and hence inflate CSR rate estimates. This should be clarified and the analysis should be carefully controlled for the influence of sequencing errors. Ideally, only proper consensus variants should be used.</p><p>2) The authors have opted for a custom analysis pipeline using minimal spanning trees instead of phylogenetic reconstruction and probabilistic models of class switching. The analysis doesn't account for the possibility of unsampled ancestors and it is not clear how the assumption that all ancestors are sampled influences the inference of CSR events. The problem of unsampled ancestors is well known when reconstructing transmission histories of viruses (e.g. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003397">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003397</ext-link>). The authors performed a number of analysis to validate the CSR inference (presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>: restriction to identical VDJs, rarefaction analysis), but some concerns remain. A combination of a Z -&gt; X and a Z -&gt; Y transition with an unsampled Z will be misinterpreted as an X -&gt; Y transition, regardless of whether X and Y are separated by somatic mutations or not. For transitions with a small number of counts, a few such instances could contribute substantially. The rarefaction analysis is not informative for transitions with small rates and few counts.</p><p>The authors should either provide additional analyses that address these concerns, or state the limitations of their rate inference explicitly.</p><p>3) You claim that class switching landscapes of identical twins are not identical, but are they significantly more different than those inferred from biological replicates? If not, the section heading &quot;Identical Twins Do Not Share Identical Class Switching Landscapes&quot; is misleading.</p><p>4) The analysis of concordant class switch events on subtrees of two parents with a common ancestor in the same state which go on to produce progeny of different classes is elegant, but we would like to see an additional control: Is the distance between children to parents correlated with that of parents to the common progenitor? Such correlations could arise due to differential sampling of lineages. In this case, similarities in switching might be due to similar distances of parents to children. In other words: Are the length of branches associated with particular switching events? And if so, are branch length of sisters correlated? This can be readily checked.</p><p>We would also like you to clarify whether you can conclude that there is a cell specific state that favors specific CSR events, or whether the observed correlation between closely related cells can be explained by an overall variation of in the switching rate, which will mostly result in switches to the same state. An analysis of the conditional probabilities of switching, given the switch of the sister (as mentioned in the subsection “Analysis of Correlations in Class Switch Fates among Related Cells”) could address this. More detail on how Yule's Q is calculated should be given and its meaning briefly explained in the main text.</p><p>5) Analysis scripts, code, and data need to be made publicly available. Ideally, documented scripts (the authors used python, iPython notebooks might be an option) along with preprocessed data should be provided. In particular, in the light of possible improvements of the analysis, preprocessed data sets that facilitate analysis by others would be welcome. Raw data needs to be deposited in short read archives.</p><p>6) The caption of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B</xref> refers to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>, but <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref> doesn't contain similar matrices. The caption of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2A</xref> refers to pies and colored slices, but all pies are mono-chrome. <italic>eLife</italic> has no limit on the number of figures. We suggest reorganizing the supplementary figures into smaller more coherent units. The current multi-panel figures with very small print and long captions are not helpful.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.16578.046</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p><italic>Essential revisions:</italic></p><p><italic>1) It is not clear how errors were corrected using the molecular barcodes. You state that you obtained ~261k reads per sample which typically represented 170k distinct molecules (subsection “Antibody Repertoire Sequencing with Subclass Resolution”, first paragraph). This would suggest that most barcodes are represented only once and no consensus sequence of (&gt;=3 sequences) can be computed. Did you use singleton and doubleton barcodes as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref> suggests? If so, sequencing errors likely contribute to diversity in many of the clonal clusters (the inserts are quite long and the end of the 2nd read often has low sequencing quality, hence sequencing errors are a concern).</italic> </p><p><italic>While it seems plausible that errors rarely produce sequences that have different classes, sequencing errors can produce additional sequences that are more similar to a sequence of a different class and hence inflate CSR rate estimates. This should be clarified and the analysis should be carefully controlled for the influence of sequencing errors. Ideally, only proper consensus variants should be used.</italic></p><p>When the analysis is performed using only sequences supported by &gt;= 3 reads, for which a consensus-read approach could be used to correct PCR and sequencing errors, we found that the patterns of class switching measured are highly similar to those measured using all sequences, including singleton and doubleton barcodes (R^2 ranging from 0.86 to 0.98). This suggests that PCR and sequencing error have not substantially distorted our measurements. We have added a supplemental figure showing these results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3</xref>) and noted these results in the main text in the subsection “Measuring the Landscape of Antibody Class Switching”.</p><p><italic>2) The authors have opted for a custom analysis pipeline using minimal spanning trees instead of phylogenetic reconstruction and probabilistic models of class switching. The analysis doesn't account for the possibility of unsampled ancestors and it is not clear how the assumption that all ancestors are sampled influences the inference of CSR events. The problem of unsampled ancestors is well known when reconstructing transmission histories of viruses (e.g. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003397">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003397</ext-link>). The authors performed a number of analysis to validate the CSR inference (presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>: restriction to identical VDJs, rarefaction analysis), but some concerns remain. A combination of a Z -&gt; X and a Z -&gt; Y transition with an unsampled Z will be misinterpreted as an X -&gt; Y transition, regardless of whether X and Y are separated by somatic mutations or not. For transitions with a small number of counts, a few such instances could contribute substantially. The rarefaction analysis is not informative for transitions with small rates and few counts.</italic> </p><p><italic>The authors should either provide additional analyses that address these concerns, or state the limitations of their rate inference explicitly.</italic></p><p>We agree that properly accounting for unsampled ancestors is an important issue and we appreciate the opportunity to clarify this point. In the example raised, independent somatic mutations are likely to have accumulated along the Z -&gt;X and Z -&gt; Y branches. Therefore, one can exclude most cases where the X -&gt; Y transition is incorrectly inferred due to failure to sample Z by examining only sequences where all somatic mutations present in X are inherited by Y. We repeated our analysis of class switch landscapes using only pairs of sequences which satisfy this condition. We called somatic mutations relative to the germline V and J genes to ensure that the ancestral state is known with high confidence. We found that the patterns of class switching measured using only these sequences were highly similar to those measured using all sequence pairs from the full lineage tree approach (R^2 ranging from 0.96 to 1). This suggests that artifacts arising from imperfect sampling of ancestral sequences have not substantially distorted our measurements. We have added a supplemental figure showing these results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>) and noted these results in the main text in the subsection “Measuring the Landscape of Antibody Class Switching”.</p><p>Nevertheless, we acknowledge that undersampling of ancestors gives rise to limitations in our rate inference. We performed an additional analysis to estimate the extent of undersampling by estimating the number of each isotype in circulation compared to the number we detected. We found that 0.1 to 5% of each isotype in circulation was sampled, which does not affect our conclusions. We added an explicit discussion of this limitation in the main text in the Discussion.</p><p><italic>3) You claim that class switching landscapes of identical twins are not identical, but are they significantly more different than those inferred from biological replicates? If not, the section heading &quot;Identical Twins Do Not Share Identical Class Switching Landscapes&quot; is misleading.</italic></p><p>There is a trend toward larger differences between twins compared with biological replicates, but this was not statistically significant (P = 0.59 and P = 0.24 for relative switch frequency and destination probability respectively). Because the variation between twins is similar to the variation between biological replicates separated by 28 days, we agree with the reviewers that the claim that “identical twins do not share identical class switching landscapes” is misleading. Indeed, an individual’s class switching landscape is not identical with his or her own landscape measured 28 days later. Nevertheless, our data show that class switching patterns of identical twins are no better correlated than pairs of unrelated individuals. We have modified the language in the main text in the subsection “Variation in Class Switching Landscape between Individuals” to more clearly state this claim.</p><p><italic>4) The analysis of concordant class switch events on subtrees of two parents with a common ancestor in the same state which go on to produce progeny of different classes is elegant, but we would like to see an additional control: Is the distance between children to parents correlated with that of parents to the common progenitor? Such correlations could arise due to differential sampling of lineages. In this case, similarities in switching might be due to similar distances of parents to children. In other words: Are the length of branches associated with particular switching events? And if so, are branch length of sisters correlated? This can be readily checked.</italic> </p><p><italic>We would also like you to clarify whether you can conclude that there is a cell specific state that favors specific CSR events, or whether the observed correlation between closely related cells can be explained by an overall variation of in the switching rate, which will mostly result in switches to the same state. An analysis of the conditional probabilities of switching, given the switch of the sister (as mentioned in the subsection “Analysis of Correlations in Class Switch Fates among Related Cells”) could address this. More detail on how Yule's Q is calculated should be given and its meaning briefly explained in the main text.</italic></p><p>We agree with the reviewers that the possibility that correlations in class switch fate arise due to differential sampling of lineages should be carefully tested. As suggested, we have checked whether mutational distances (i.e. branch lengths) are associated with particular switching events, and found that they are not. We also checked whether mutational distances among related sequences are correlated, and found that they are not (R^2 ranging from 0 to 0.19). These results show that correlations in switch fate are not due to differential sampling of lineages. We have added supplemental figures showing these results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s6">Figure 3—figure supplement 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s7">Figure 3—figure supplement 7</xref>) and noted these findings in the main text in the section “Class Switch Fates are Strongly Correlated among Closely Related Cells and Lose Coherence as Somatic Mutations Accumulate”.</p><p>We believe that there is a cell state that favors specific CSR events. To show this more clearly, we have plotted the conditional probability of switch fates given the switch fate of sister, as suggested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s5">Figure 3—figure supplement 5</xref>). These plots show that the probability distribution of switch fate is strongly biased toward the class to which the sister switches, and the bias dissipates as somatic mutations accumulate. This change in the probability distribution is consistent with the existence of a cell state that favors a particular class switch outcome. On the other hand, we have found no evidence for an overall variation in switch rate that is correlated between clonally related cells, as indicated by the lack of correlations between branch lengths of related cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s7">Figure 3—figure supplement 7</xref>). We have added a supplemental figure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s5">Figure 3—figure supplement 5</xref>) and clarified this point in the main text in the section “Class Switch Fates are Strongly Correlated among Closely Related Cells and Lose Coherence as Somatic Mutations Accumulate”.</p><p>As suggested, we have expanded the explanation of Yule’s Q when it is first introduced to the reader in the main text. We have also included additional detail about how to calculate Yule’s Q in the Materials and methods section.</p><p><italic>5) Analysis scripts, code, and data need to be made publicly available. Ideally, documented scripts (the authors used python, iPython notebooks might be an option) along with preprocessed data should be provided. In particular, in the light of possible improvements of the analysis, preprocessed data sets that facilitate analysis by others would be welcome. Raw data needs to be deposited in short read archives.</italic></p><p>We have uploaded our preprocessed data consisting of annotated immunoglobulin heavy chain (IGHC) sequences and their clonal lineage histories to a web server where they can be downloaded freely. Several example scripts accompany these data and additional scripts are available upon request. We have also deposited the raw sequencing reads in the Sequence Read Archive. We have provided links to these resources in the Materials and methods section.</p><p><italic>6) The caption of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B</xref> refers to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>, but <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref> doesn't contain similar matrices. The caption of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2A</xref> refers to pies and colored slices, but all pies are mono-chrome. eLife has no limit on the number of figures. We suggest reorganizing the supplementary figures into smaller more coherent units. The current multi-panel figures with very small print and long captions are not helpful.</italic> </p><p>As suggested, we have reorganized all of the supplementary figures to be smaller, coherent units that will be clearer for readers. We have fixed the captions of both figures mentioned.</p></body></sub-article></article>