<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="article-commentary" dtd-version="1.1d3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">eLife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">04600</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.04600</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Insight</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology and Infectious Disease</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sub-display-channel"><subject>Viruses</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gene swapping in the dead zone</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-19827"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>Jillian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><x> is in the </x></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-13466"><name><surname>Dubilier</surname><given-names>Nicole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><x> is in the </x></contrib><aff id="aff1"><institution content-type="dept">Symbiosis Department</institution>, <institution>Max Planck Institute of Marine Microbiology</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Bremen</named-content></addr-line>, <country>Germany</country> <email>jmpeters@mpi-bremen.de</email></aff><aff id="aff2"><institution content-type="dept">Symbiosis Department</institution>, <institution>Max Planck Institute of Marine Microbiology</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Bremen</named-content></addr-line>, <country>Germany</country> <email>ndubilie@mpi-bremen.de</email></aff></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e04600</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014, Petersen and Dubilier</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Petersen and Dubilier</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-04600-v1.pdf"/><related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="ra1" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.03125"/><abstract><p>Viruses can swap DNA between bacteria that live in regions of the oceans with little or no oxygen.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Author keywords</title><kwd>SUP05</kwd><kwd>bacteriophages</kwd><kwd>virus</kwd><kwd>single cell genomic</kwd><kwd>oxygen minimum zone</kwd><kwd>viral dark matter</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Virus</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text><p><bold>Related research article</bold> Roux S, Hawley AK, Torres Beltran M, Scofield M, Schwientek P, Stepanauskas R, Woyke T, Hallam SJ, and Sullivan MB. 2014. Ecology and evolution of viruses infecting uncultivated SUP05 bacteria as revealed by single-cell- and meta-genomics. <italic>eLife</italic> <bold>3</bold>:e03125. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.03125">10.7554/eLife.03125</ext-link></p><p><bold>Image</bold> Schematic of two different viruses introducing new DNA into the genome of a marine bacterium</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="elife-04600-inf1-v1"/></p></boxed-text><p>The oceans are home to a staggering number of viruses, roughly 10<sup>30</sup>, making them the most abundant organisms on the planet. Most of these viruses infect bacteria, which are also found in huge numbers. Genetic surveys have revealed that the viruses and bacteria in the oceans are extremely diverse, yet the interactions between them can be highly specific. However, it is challenging to link marine bacteria with their viruses because most of them cannot be cultured on artificial media in the lab, which is the traditional method for studying virus–bacteria interactions.</p><p>Now, in <italic>eLife</italic>, a collaboration between researchers from the US and Canada—with Simon Roux of the University of Arizona as first author—has used a new technology called single-cell genome sequencing to link a group of highly abundant and widespread marine bacteria with two specific groups of viruses, without having to culture either the host bacteria or the virus in the lab (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Roux et al., 2014</xref>). The collaboration was led by Matthew Sullivan of Arizona and Steven Hallam of the University of British Columbia, and also included researchers at the Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences and the DOE Joint Genome Institute.</p><p>The bacteria, called SUP05, are marine bacteria that oxidize reduced sulfur compounds such as hydrogen sulfide to gain energy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Walsh et al., 2009</xref>). They are close relatives of the sulfur-oxidizing bacteria that live inside mussels and clams at marine hydrothermal vents and cold seeps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Lavik et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Petersen et al., 2012</xref>). The energy they obtain from oxidizing sulfur is used to fix carbon dioxide to make the organic carbon compounds the bacteria need to grow.</p><p>SUP05 bacteria are widespread in open water and are particularly abundant in regions of water that contain very little oxygen. These oxygen minimum zones (OMZs), also known as marine dead zones, form where oxygen respiration is rapid, and the physical processes that would replenish oxygen supplies (such as mixing and exposure to the atmosphere) are weak. It is estimated that between 1 and 7% of the oceans are OMZs. These large swathes of water are lethal to animals that require oxygen, but they are hot-spots for microbes that can live on sulfur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Wright et al., 2012</xref>). SUP05 bacteria can survive in oxygen-poor environments because they use dissolved nitrate instead of oxygen for respiration.</p><p>The microbes living in OMZs transform sulfur, nitrogen and carbon on such large scales that they can alter ocean chemistry, and contribute to climate change through the production of greenhouse gases. In turn, global warming is predicted to increase the extent and intensity of OMZs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Stramma et al., 2008</xref>). Therefore, understanding the factors that control the activities of microbes in OMZs is crucial for predicting their role in future climate change.</p><p>Roux et al. sampled the water of Saanich Inlet, a fjord on the Canadian Pacific coast where an OMZ forms every summer. Samples were taken at three different depths that spanned the transition from oxygenated surface waters to the deeper low-oxygen ‘core’ of the OMZ. From these samples, individual bacterial cells were sorted into tiny wells by a device called a flow cytometer. The DNA in each well (including DNA from the viruses infecting the bacterial cells) was then copied to produce enough DNA to individually sequence the genome of each cell.</p><p>Roux et al. found that 33% of all the single-cell genomes contained viral DNA, the very first estimate of infection rates in a natural bacterial population. This closely matches previous estimates of whole-community infection rates based on metagenome sequencing, where the DNA of all the microbes in a sample is sequenced altogether (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Suttle, 2007</xref>). Intriguingly, Roux et al. found that the percentage of infected SUP05 cells varied between samples taken at different depths, with the highest infection rates in the deepest part of the OMZ, where SUP05 cells are most abundant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>).<fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Interactions between viruses and bacteria in the Saanich Inlet marine ‘dead zone’.</title><p>In summer, viruses from the order <italic>Caudovirales</italic> (orange) and the family <italic>Microviridae</italic> (blue) become abundant at depths where the water contains very little oxygen (pale blue regions) because their hosts, SUP05 bacteria (black), are also abundant in these oxygen minimum zones. The viruses can shuttle bacterial genes between different host cells (<bold>A</bold>). This can lead to changes in the metabolism of the host bacteria if the new genes are expressed by the host cells (<bold>B</bold>). Co-infection of a host cell by two different viruses could lead to new combinations of genes in the bacterial genome (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-04600-fig1-v1.tif"/></fig></p><p>Understanding the specificity of viruses—that is, understanding which organisms they can infect—is essential for predicting their effects in nature, as shown by the recent outbreaks of Ebola and other viruses in humans. Unfortunately, very little is known about the specificity of most marine viruses. Roux et al. identified five new types of viruses from the order <italic>Caudovirales</italic> and the family <italic>Microviridae</italic> that infect SUP05 bacteria. Although it is not known whether these viruses can infect other bacterial species, the identification of one host species is a major step forward. The <italic>Microviridae</italic> were almost always found in cells infected by <italic>Caudovirales</italic>, which indicates that they may cooperate in some way.</p><p>Roux et al. then used the viral genomes to search through genomic databases for more information about their distribution in the environment, starting with the data they had collected from the waters of Saanich Inlet. Similar SUP05-infecting viruses were consistently found in the OMZ over the three-year sampling period. Roux et al. were also able to observe evolution in the viruses, with new genes that appeared in the genomes of some of the viruses in the second sampling year being found in virtually all of the viruses by the third year.</p><p>Next, they searched for the SUP05-infecting viruses in metagenomes—collections of all the genetic material found in environmental samples—from around the globe. The viruses that infect SUP05 in Saanich Inlet were rarely found in other ocean regions, even those adjacent to the Inlet, or in distant regions populated by similar SUP05 bacteria. This shows a surprisingly strict geographic restriction, despite regular seasonal mixing of Saanich Inlet with waters from the neighboring north eastern Pacific Ocean.</p><p>Viruses can alter the course of bacterial evolution by introducing new genes into the cells they infect. Bacterial DNA can be taken up by virus particles and shuttled to the next host bacterial cell, where it can be used to the new cell's advantage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). Well-known examples of virus-mediated gene shuttling are the transfer of key photosynthesis genes between marine cyanobacteria, and the exchange of cholera toxin genes between different <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Faruque et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Lindell et al., 2004</xref>). Genes for sulfur cycling were recently discovered in viruses associated with SUP05 from hydrothermal vents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anantharaman et al., 2014</xref>). Roux et al. also discovered genes for sulfur oxidation in the genomes of SUP05 viruses from Saanich Inlet. Thus, viruses might play a key role in altering core metabolism of SUP05, not only in the deep sea, but also in widespread OMZs. The sharing of bacterial genes by viruses may be a universal feature of natural microbial communities.</p><p>Bacteria are often referred to as the engines that drive nutrient cycles in the marine environment. They do this by catalyzing key processes such as CO<sub>2</sub> fixation, organic matter recycling, conversion of nitrogen, and removal of toxic hydrogen sulfide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Falkowski et al., 2008</xref>). To extend the analogy, viruses may be the mechanics who tinker with the efficiency of these engines by shuttling metabolic genes between bacterial host cells.</p></body><back><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf1"><label>Competing interests:</label><p>The authors declare that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anantharaman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Duhaime</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Breier</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Toner</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Sulfur oxidation genes in diverse deep-sea viruses</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>344</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1252229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falkowski</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenchel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Delong</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>The microbial engines that drive Earth's biogeochemical cycles</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>320</volume><fpage>1034</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1153213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faruque</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alim</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Induction of the lysogenic phage encoding cholera toxin in naturally occurring strains of toxigenic <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> O1 and O139</article-title><source>Infection and Immunity</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>3752</fpage><lpage>3757</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stührmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brüchert</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Plas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohrholz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mussmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Amann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lass</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuypers</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Detoxification of sulphidic African shelf waters by blooming chemolithotrophs</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>457</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolonen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohwer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chisholm</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Transfer of photosynthesis genes to and from <italic>Prochlorococcus</italic> viruses</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of USA</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>11013</fpage><lpage>11018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0401526101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wentrup</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Verna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Knittel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubilier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Origins and evolutionary flexibility of chemosynthetic symbionts from deep-sea animals</article-title><source>The Biological Bulletin</source><volume>223</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>137</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawley</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres Beltran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scofield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwientek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepanauskas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Woyke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Ecology and evolution of viruses infecting uncultivated SUP05 bacteria as revealed by single-cell- and meta-genomics</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>e03125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.03125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stramma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprintall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohrholz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Expanding oxygen-minimum zones in the tropical oceans</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>320</volume><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1153847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suttle</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Marine viruses—major players in the global ecosystem</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaikova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tringe</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tortell</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Metagenome of a versatile chemolithoautotroph from expanding oceanic dead zones</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>326</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1175309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Konwar</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Microbial ecology of expanding oxygen minimum zones</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2778</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>