<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.2"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">83364</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.83364</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reassessment of weak parent-of-origin expression bias shows it rarely exists outside of known imprinted regions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-292206"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>Carol A</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1887-1280</contrib-id><email>cae28@cam.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-292207"><name><surname>Watkinson</surname><given-names>William MD</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-292208"><name><surname>Telerman</surname><given-names>Stephanie B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-292209"><name><surname>Hulsmann</surname><given-names>Lisa C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-292210"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Russell S</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0598-3793</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-144925"><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>Anne C</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7608-5894</contrib-id><email>afsmith@gen.cam.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/013meh722</institution-id><institution>Department of Genetics, University of Cambridge</institution></institution-wrap><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Cambridge</named-content></addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bourc'his</surname><given-names>Deborah</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04t0gwh46</institution-id><institution>Institut Curie</institution></institution-wrap><country>France</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>Detlef</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0243gzr89</institution-id><institution>Max Planck Institute for Biology Tübingen</institution></institution-wrap><country>Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="publication"><day>14</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e83364</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2022-10-08"><day>08</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2023-03-08"><day>08</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a preprint at .</event-desc><date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2022-08-21"><day>21</day><month>08</month><year>2022</year></date><self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.08.21.504536"/></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2023, Edwards et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Edwards et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-83364-v2.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="figures-pdf" xlink:href="elife-83364-figures-v2.pdf"/><abstract><p>In mouse and human, genes subjected to genomic imprinting have been shown to function in development, behavior, and post-natal adaptations. Failure to correctly imprint genes in human is associated with developmental syndromes, adaptive, and metabolic disorders during life as well as numerous forms of cancer. In recent years researchers have turned to RNA-seq technologies applied to reciprocal hybrid strains of mice to identify novel imprinted genes, causing a threefold increase in genes reported as having a parental origin-specific expression bias. The functional relevance of parental origin-specific expression bias is not fully appreciated especially since many are reported with only minimal parental bias (e.g. 51:49). Here, we present an in-depth meta-analysis of previously generated RNA-seq data and show that the methods used to generate and analyze libraries greatly influence the calling of allele-specific expression. Validation experiments show that most novel genes called with parental-origin-specific allelic bias are artefactual, with the mouse strain contributing a larger effect on expression biases than parental origin. Of the weak novel genes that do validate, most are located at the periphery of known imprinted domains, suggesting they may be affected by local allele- and tissue-specific conformation. Together these findings highlight the need for robust tools, definitions, and validation of putative imprinted genes to provide meaningful information within imprinting databases and to understand the functional and mechanistic implications of the process.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>epigenetics</kwd><kwd>imprinting</kwd><kwd>gene expression</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Mouse</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000265</institution-id><institution>Medical Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MR/R009791/1</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>Anne C</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Genes with parent-of-origin specific expression are not as numerous as previously reported and validated parentally-biased expressed genes tend to be peripheral to known imprinted domains indicating shared regional control.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Genomic imprinting is a mammalian-specific epigenetic process causing some genes to be expressed in a parent-of-origin-specific manner, leading to the functional inequality of parental genomes. In the 35 years since imprinting was first discovered in mammals much has been learned about the mechanisms governing this process and the role epigenetic mechanisms as a whole play in genome function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Tucci et al., 2019</xref>.) To date, approximately 150 imprinted genes have been identified in mice and humans where they have been shown to have vital roles in development, behavior, and post-natal adaptations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Tucci et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Plasschaert and Bartolomei, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Cleaton et al., 2014</xref>). Failure to correctly imprint genes in human is associated with developmental syndromes, adaptive, and metabolic disorders during life as well as numerous forms of cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ishida and Moore, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Uribe-Lewis et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Canonical imprinting is established during gametogenesis when certain regions of the genome become differentially DNA methylated in the two germlines. Germline differentially methylated regions (gDMRs) associated with imprinted genes differ from others because they are protected from the global demethylation that occurs in the zygote; a process requiring the KRAB-zinc finger proteins Zfp57 and Zfp445 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Li et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Takahashi et al., 2019</xref>). Imprinted genes are frequently organized into clusters or pairs in the genome and a single gDMR acts as an imprinting control region (ICR) for the entire domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Edwards and Ferguson-Smith, 2007</xref>). Secondary or somatic DMRs are also associated with imprinted genes: these DMRs are established after fertilization, under the control of the ICR, and are generally not bound by Zfp57 and or Zfp445. More recently Inoue et al., identified a germline-derived histone 3 lysine 27 tri-methylation (H3K27me3) mediated mechanism that also can confer parental origin-specific expression. These ‘non-canonically’ imprinted genes show paternally biased expression in the preimplantation embryo which persists in extra-embryonic tissue but is lost in the embryo proper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Inoue et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Advances in RNA-sequencing technology and analysis pipelines have enabled the quantification of allele-specific expression and the identification of imprinted genes in reciprocal hybrids between distantly related strains of mice. Early studies using this method highlighted the challenges of analyzing data derived from reciprocal hybrids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Babak et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Wang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gregg et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Gregg et al., 2010a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Wang et al., 2011b</xref>). For example, in 2010 two related works reported approximately 1300 new imprinted genes in the brain, which would have increased the number of known imprinted genes in the mouse by an order of magnitude (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gregg et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Gregg et al., 2010a</xref>). These datasets were subsequently shown to include multiple false positives emphasizing the need for validation of putative imprinted genes via a complementary method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">DeVeale et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>More recent studies applied improved analytical tools, as well as additional controls, statistical filtering, and validation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Babak et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Crowley et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Andergassen et al., 2017</xref>). The tissues interrogated in these studies vary and each identifies a distinct set of genes with significant parental-origin-specific expression biases raising the possibility that the imprinting status of these new candidates might be cell or tissue-specific and hence overlooked to date. Particular attention has been paid to neurological tissues where a much higher proportion of putative imprinted genes were identified. Interestingly, most of the candidates have significant yet weak allelic biases including those with only 51–60% expression originating from the preferred allele. Here, applying the same analysis tools and validation approach to all datasets, we investigate genes with weak parental origin-specific bias further by focusing on four studies: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Babak et al., 2015</xref> (Dataset A), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref> (Dataset B), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref> (Dataset C), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Crowley et al., 2015</xref> (Dataset D). It is noteworthy that the different studies have employed different analysis pipelines.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Limited overlap between the sets of novel imprinting candidates from RNA-seq</title><p>The four studies used for our analysis generated whole transcriptomes from reciprocal hybrid mouse tissues to identify novel imprinted genes. Reciprocal mouse crosses take advantage of sequence-specific polymorphisms to distinguish parental-origin effects from those caused by the genetic background of different mouse strains. A summary comparing the methods used in all four studies is described in the methods section and summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1a</xref>. We first assessed the overlap between the studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A and B</xref>). For this, all genes identified were compiled and those with alternative names between studies were merged. This produced a list of 313 genes of which only 36 (11.5%) were identified with allelic biases in all four studies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1b</xref>). Genes were then divided into ‘Known’ (had previously been identified as imprinted or validated using a non-RNA-seq method - <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1b</xref>) or ‘Novel’ (first identified in these studies or previously un-validated RNA-seq experiments). By our classification, Dataset A identified 99 genes with ASE, of which 26 were novel and 73 were known. Dataset B identified 209 genes, 151 novel and 58 known. Dataset C identified 112 genes, 51 novel and 61 known, and Dataset D identified 95 genes, 57 novel and 38 known. When the overlap between studies was assessed, 30 out of 87 (35%) known genes were identified in all four studies compared with six out of 226 novel genes (2.7%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A and B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1c</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>limited overlap between novel genes identified in the four studies.</title><p>(<bold>A–B</bold>) Euler diagrams showing the overlap of (<bold>A</bold>) - known imprinted genes and (<bold>B</bold>) – novel biased genes between the four studies. (<bold>C</bold>) – overlaps between different classes of novel genes. Class-1 = novel singletons &gt;1 Mb from another gene identified in any of the studies. Class-2 = novel clusters where two or more novel genes are within 1 Mb of each other but over 1 Mb from a known imprinted gene. Class-3=novel genes are within 1 Mb of a known imprinted gene. (<bold>D</bold>) - proportion of known and novel genes by number of studies they were identified in. (<bold>E–F</bold>) Venn diagrams showing tissue-specific overlaps in <bold>E</bold> - known imprinted genes and <bold>F</bold> – novel biased genes.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><p>As imprinted genes tend to be clustered within the genome, novel genes were subdivided into three categories. Class-1 are novel singletons that are more than 1 Mb from another gene identified in any of the studies. Class-2 are novel clusters where two or more novel genes are within 1 Mb of each other but over 1 Mb from a known imprinted gene. Finally, Class-3 novel genes are within 1 Mb of a known imprinted gene. The degree of overlap of each of these classes of novel genes varies greatly with a much higher proportion of Class-3 genes overlapping. Indeed, the only six novel genes that came up in all four studies belong to Class-3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>) indicating that the boundaries of some imprinting clusters may not have been fully defined previously.</p><p>The vast majority (82.7%) of novel parental-origin-specific biased genes were unique to one study, whereas only 28.7% of known genes fell in the same category (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). The lack of overlap in novel genes suggests that the genes identified in these studies may be subjected to tissue-specific imprinting. Most known genes only identified in one study come from Dataset A. This is not surprising since more tissues were analyzed including four extra-embryonic tissues and 6 of the 14 unique known genes from this study have previously been shown to be specifically imprinted in the placenta or yolk sac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Wang et al., 2011b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Zwart et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Okae et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Paulsen et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Kuzmin et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Wang et al., 2011a</xref>). To investigate the effect of tissue specificity further, gene sets identified in different studies, but in the same tissue, were compared. Once again minimal overlap was observed between novel genes compared with known genes in the same tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E and F</xref>). Thus, despite the careful analytical measures that appear to have been taken in all four studies to reduce false positives, the minimal overlap between the sets of novel genes suggests that some of these may indeed be false positives.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Reanalysis of data from previous studies indicates differences between studies are due to experimental design and analysis</title><p>The lack of overlap between the four studies could be due to the different methods used, and we, therefore, decided to run the sequence data generated from three of the studies (which all used C57BL/6xCastEiJ reciprocal crosses) through the same analysis pipeline and see if the overlap was improved. We utilized the more recently established ISoLDE (Integrative Statistics of alleLe Dependent Expression) package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Reynès et al., 2020</xref>) that had not been employed in any of the four studies to call allele-specific expression (ASE). ISoLDE uses a nonparametric statistical method to infer ASE in RNA-seq data from reciprocal crosses. It was benchmarked by the authors on six RNA-seq datasets including Datasets B and C used in this study and has been used by others to study imprinted gene expression in the mammary gland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Xu et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>We chose the hypothalamus, cerebellum, liver, muscle, and whole adult brain from Dataset A, the arcuate nucleus (ARN), the dorsal raphe nucleus (DRN), liver and muscle from Dataset B, and P8 and P60 cerebellum from Dataset C. First, we assessed the overlap between our calls and the calls from the original studies. 204 genes were identified across the five different tissues from Dataset A (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1d</xref>). 66% of total known genes and 17% of Class-3 genes overlap using their approach and ISoLDE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). For these data, ISoLDE identified a high proportion of Class-1 +2 genes (65.2%). No overlap is observed in Class-1 +2 genes as none were identified in the original study. This high number of novel genes called by ISoLDE is most likely due to the absence of biological replicates in Dataset A as other datasets without biological replicates also have increased novel calls (data not shown).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Limited overlap between novel genes called by different analysis pipelines.</title><p>(<bold>A–C</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the overlap between allelic biased genes called by our pipeline with the ISoLDE package (gray circles) versus the original studies. <bold>A</bold> – Dataset A, <bold>B</bold> - Dataset B, <bold>C</bold> - Dataset C. Overlapping novel genes are listed to the right. Dataset A only genes called in the hypothalamus, cerebellum, liver, muscle, and whole adult brain were analyzed. (<bold>D–G</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the overlap between allelic biased genes called by our pipeline from sequence data generated from the same tissue by different studies: liver (<bold>D</bold>), muscle (<bold>E</bold>), hypothalamus (<bold>F</bold>) from Dataset A and Dataset B and cerebellum (<bold>G</bold>) from Dataset A and Dataset C. (<bold>H–I</bold>) Venn diagrams of three-way overlap between allelic biased genes called by our pipeline from sequence data from the liver (<bold>H</bold>) and muscle (<bold>I</bold>) generated by Dataset A, Dataset B, and Dataset E.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Expression levels of genes called as biased in at least one of the original studies.</title><p>Data generated from re-analysis of original RNA-seq datasets. To allow for comparison across the different datasets, expression levels are reported as mean TPM (transcripts per million) from all biological replicates. Source data is in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1f</xref>. Samples: Dataset A - whole adult brain, cerebellum (cb) hypothalamus (hypo) liver, muscle. Dataset B - arcuate nucleus (ARN), dorsal raphe nucleus (DRN), liver, and muscle. Dataset C - P8 and P60 cerebellum.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig2-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Overlapping underdetermined genes called between Dataset B (<bold>A</bold>) and Dataset C (<bold>B</bold>) and ISoLDE pipeline.</title><p>Number of ISoLDE called genes are in pale gray, and overlaps with original study are in dark gray. Overlapping genes are listed to the right. Genes in red were flagged by ISoLDE and genes in bold were validated by pyrosequencing.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig2-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>For Datasets B and C, this identified 86 and 63 total ASE genes, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1d</xref>). For Dataset B, 49 known genes overlap which is 73% of all genes identified using both methods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). This is consistent across all four tissues analyzed with between 50–71% of known imprinted genes overlapping in the tissues (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1e</xref>). Fewer novel genes show overlap between the two methods: 11% of Class-3 genes and 1% of Class-1 +2 overlap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1d</xref>). A similar pattern is observed in the Dataset C with 67% of known genes overlapping, 14% of Class-3, and 8% of Class-1 +2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). For both datasets, fewer novel genes were identified using the common pipeline than in the original studies indicating that the individual methods used to identify allele-specific genes in the four studies greatly influence the calling of novel imprinted genes. Only one Class-1 +2 gene was found in each study: <italic>Gm11410</italic> in Dataset B and <italic>BC034090</italic> in Dataset C. This is a much lower proportion of Class-1 +2 genes than was called in Dataset A (2.3% and 3.2% in datasets B and C, respectively vs. 65.2%) and is most likely due to the higher number of biological replicates sampled in Datasets B and C.</p><p>To gain further insight into how methodology affects calling, datasets derived from the same tissue from different studies, but analyzed using our pipeline, were compared. We were able to compare data for postnatal liver, skeletal muscle, and hypothalamus (ARN) between Datasets A and B and for cerebellum between the Datasets A and C. Nine out of 20 known imprinted genes identified in the two liver datasets overlapped (45% - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>), 20 of 29 in muscle (69% - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>), 37 of 53 in the hypothalamus (70% - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>), and 24 of 49 in the cerebellum (49% - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2G</xref>). Fewer overlaps were found for Class-3 genes: Two out of 5 genes overlapped between the muscle datasets (40% - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>), 14 of 36 in the hypothalamus (39% - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>), and 8 of 24 in the cerebellum (33% - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2G</xref>). Only one gene was identified in the liver datasets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). No overlapping Class-1 +2 genes were identified in any tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D–G</xref>).</p><p>RNA-seq technology involves PCR which can increase biases in lowly expressed genes through the random amplification of a small pool of molecules. To see if the lack of reproducibility was due to the weakly biased genes being poorly expressed in the original datasets, the expression levels for genes identified as biased in the original studies were compared (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1f</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>). Weakly expressed genes were not overrepresented in the Class-1 and 2 genes. Indeed, all four classes of genes have similar distributions of expression levels, suggesting weak expression is not the only factor affecting the lack of overlap between the two pipelines.</p><p>To see if a particular dataset caused the lack of overlap, we next incorporated data from another study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Andergassen et al., 2017</xref> – Dataset E) that investigated imprinting across multiple tissues and time points in CastEiJ and FVB reciprocal crosses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Andergassen et al., 2017</xref>). Liver and muscle data were run through our pipeline (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1d</xref>). The three-way comparison shows a high overlap between the known genes identified in all three datasets (36–57%), variable overlap in Class-3 genes (0–17%) and no overlap between Class-1 +2 called genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2H,I</xref>). Together, these data show that the methods used to generate libraries, the number of biological replicates included, and the methods used to call ASE all greatly influence the genes called.</p><p>We next investigated whether strain biases influenced novel gene calling and the impact of this on calling parental-origin-specific expression bias. The overlap between strain specific genes called by ISoLDE and novel genes called in Datasets B and C was compared. Twenty-five genes called as ASE in Dataset B are called as strain-specific by ISoLDE of which 20 are Class-1 +2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1g</xref>) compared with only one overlapping parent-of-origin called gene, suggesting they were miscalled as imprinted in the original study. Five overlapping strain-specific genes were called in the Dataset C: three of them in known imprinted regions and two known imprinted genes – highlighting that strain-specific expression can also act on imprinted genes and needs to be considered when calling allele-specific expression.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Weakly biased Class-3 genes are peripherally located and preferentially expressed from the chromosome carrying the germline methylation mark</title><p>One of the most surprising findings of the cited studies is that many novel imprinting candidates show only a weak bias in the expression of the parental alleles, in some cases only slightly different from an unbiased 50:50 expression ratio. Perez and colleagues grouped their genes according to the percentage expression from the preferred allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>) and we used and extended this grouping to the gene sets from the other studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1b</xref>). Overall, among the 311 known and novel candidate genes for which bias data was available, we observed a bimodal distribution with 169 genes in the 50–60% bias group and 95 genes in the 90–100% group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). This bimodal distribution had already been described by Perez and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>). Notably, two-thirds of known imprinted genes (77.3%) were in the 90–100% group while only 12.1% of novel candidates show this high expression bias. Most novel genes (73.1%) were found to have only weak biases with 50–60% expression coming from the preferred allele. 88.7% of Class-1 novel singletons and 83.9% of Class-2 genes in novel clusters fall within this weakly biased group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). Interestingly, Class-3 genes, close to known imprinted regions, also show a bimodal distribution: 53.7% fall in the 50–60% group and 23.2% in the 90–100% group but, only nine genes (9.5%) show a 70–90% expression bias. The presence of Class-3 genes displaying strong imprinted expression again indicates that the full extent of imprinted expression at some imprinted clusters has not been fully established.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Weakly biased Class-3 genes are preferentially expressed from the chromosome carrying the germline methylation mark.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Distribution of biased genes by maximum reported bias. Class-1 = novel singletons &gt;1 Mb from another gene identified in any of the studies. Class-2 = novel clusters where two or more novel genes within 1 Mb of each other but over 1 Mb from a known imprinted gene. Class-3 = novel genes are within 1 Mb of a known imprinted gene. (<bold>B</bold>) – Distribution of biased genes by preferential parental chromosome and maximum reported bias. Genes preferentially expressed from the maternal chromosome are shown in red, paternal chromosome in blue, and preferentially expressed from both chromosomes in a tissue-specific manner in gray. (<bold>C</bold>) - Distribution of known and Class-3 genes by the methylation status of the imprinting control region (ICR) on the preferentially expressed allele. Genes preferentially expressed from the Meth-ICR chromosome are shown in black, Un-ICR chromosome in pale-gray, and preferentially expressed from both chromosomes in a tissue-specific manner in dark-gray. (<bold>D</bold>) – Heap maps of DNA methylation (fetal and six week male frontal cortex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Shen et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Sloan et al., 2016</xref>) and Histone H3 lysine 27 trimethylation (E16 and P0 forebrain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Gorkin et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Shen et al., 2012</xref>) over the promoters of known and Class-3 novel genes. Promoters are defined as 500 bp upstream of the transcription factor binding site. Genes are sorted by maximum reported bias and methylation status of the ICR on the preferentially expressed allele. Source data for the figure can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1h</xref>.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig><p>Next, we compared the direction of the parental bias among our four classes of genes. Both Class-1 and 2 genes had a relatively even split between preferentially paternal or maternal expression in both weak and strongly bias genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). Interestingly, although the known imprinted genes consist of about equal proportions of maternally and paternally expressed genes (42 paternal, 33 maternal, 13 genes with both directions depending on tissue), paternally expressed genes tend to have higher expression biases (37 have 90–100% bias), while all eleven known genes with a low expression bias (50–70%) are maternally expressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). Novel genes in known clusters (Class-3) follow the same trend of parental bias and direction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>) with 70.3% of weakly biased genes preferentially expressed from the maternal chromosome and 64.5% of highly biased genes expressed from the paternally inherited chromosome. Most imprinted regions are controlled by maternal, allele-specific methylation at the ICR acting as a repressed promoter for maternally repressed imprinted alleles. As a consequence of this direct repression, these genes show very strong paternal expression bias whereas paternally repressed genes within these same regions tend to rely on more indirect repression mechanisms such as transcription of a long ncRNA and differential histone modifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fitzpatrick et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Pandey et al., 2008</xref>). To see if the direction of ICR methylation is causing the trend towards strong paternal and weak maternal biases, we categorized the genes in regions with known ICRs according to whether the preferentially expressed allele was on the chromosome with a methylated (Meth-ICR) or unmethylated ICR (Un-ICR) regardless of parental origin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). The direction of methylation does influence the bias as weakly biased genes tend to be preferentially expressed from the chromosome with the Meth-ICR (81% of Class-3 and 100% known &lt;70% biased) whereas strongly biased genes tend to be preferentially expressed from the chromosome with the Un-ICR (80% of Class-3 and 54% known &gt;70% biased -<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>).</p><p>To investigate this trend further, we assessed the DNA methylation and H3K27me3 at the promoter regions of all the Class-3 and known genes at canonically imprinted clusters using previously published embryonic and postnatal data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lister et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Gorkin et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Shen et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1h</xref>). Strongly biased known genes on the Un-ICR chromosome were associated with promoter methylation suggesting direct regulation by DNA methylation, whilst strongly biased known genes on the Meth-ICR chromosome tend to have unmethylated promoters but higher levels of H3K27me3 indicating repression of genes on the Un-ICR chromosome is controlled by differential histone modifications rather than differential promoter methylation. Interestingly, strongly biased Class-3 genes on the Un-ICR chromosome follow the same trend as the known genes and have methylated promoters indicating a shared mechanism, whereas strongly biased genes preferentially expressed from the Meth-ICR show low promoter methylation and H3K27me3 occupancy. Weakly biased genes tend to be associated with unmethylated promoters and low H3K27me3 regardless of which allele is preferentially expressed. This is unsurprising as the biases are so weak, however, the trend for low biased genes to be preferentially expressed from the Meth-ICR allele implies the genic environment is more repressive on the Un-ICR chromosome perhaps due to ectopic spreading of repressive marks in some cells.</p><p>Next, Class-3 genes were classified by whether they were flanked by previously known imprinted genes or were peripherally located within known imprinted clusters. Weakly biased novel genes are predominantly found at the periphery of annotated imprinted domains: 83% of peripheral Class-3 genes (60/72) have a bias below the 70:30 canonical imprinting threshold set by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Andergassen et al., 2017</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Conversely, highly biased Class-3 genes tend to be flanked by known imprinted genes: only 13% (3/23) of novel genes flanked by known imprinted genes have a ratio below 70:30 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Most of the 20 flanked, highly biased Class-3 genes belong to just two imprinted domains. Fourteen map between <italic>Ndn</italic> and <italic>Snrpn</italic> on chromosome 7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>) and five map downstream of <italic>Meg3</italic> on chromosome 12 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). In both cases, these highly biased genes follow the direction of imprinting of the long non-coding gene in the region that is repressed on the meth-ICR chromosome suggesting that these may be poorly annotated RNAs arising from known poly-cistronic imprinted transcripts.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Weakly biased Class-3 genes are located at the periphery of known imprinted domains.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) – Distribution of Class-3 biased genes in relation to known imprinted genes. Genes flanked by known imprinted genes are shown in turquoise and those peripheral to known imprinted genes are shown in green.(<bold>B</bold>) – Sunburst graph of a relationship between position in cluster, the extent of bias, and ICR methylation in Class-3 genes. Low bias = &lt;70% expression from preferential chromosome, high bias = &gt;70% expression from the preferential chromosome. Preferential expression from the methylated imprinting control region (ICR) chromosome is shown in black, preferential expression from the unmethylated ICR chromosome is shown in gray, and genes reported as being biased on both chromosomes depending on tissue or study are shown in red. (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) – Schematics of the <italic>Snrpn</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) and <italic>Dlk1</italic> (<bold>D</bold>) regions. Highly biased novel genes (80–100%) are located between known imprinted transcripts whereas low-biased genes (50–70%) are located at the periphery. Red boxes = known maternally expressed genes. Blue boxes = known paternally expressed genes. Pink boxes = novel maternally biased genes called by original studies. Turquoise boxes = novel paternally biased genes called by original studies. Blue arrow = cluster of imprinted MBII snoRNAs. Turquoise arrow <italic>Mir344</italic> cluster. (<bold>E</bold>) – Allele-specific expression analysis in peripheral genes in the <italic>Dlk1</italic> region in IG-DMR knockout mice. Female mice, heterozygous for IG-DMR knockout were crossed with male CastEiJ mice, and expression was assessed by pyrosequencing. Wildtype (n=5) and maternal heterozygote (n=6) expression biases were compared using an unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test ** p &lt;0.01 * p &lt; 0.5.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig><p>We next integrated the position and strength of bias with the ICR status on the chromosome preferentially expressing the gene and found over half of all Class-3 genes are weakly biased, at the edge of the known cluster and preferentially expressed from the chromosome that carries the methylated copy of the ICR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). This suggests that secondary repressive mechanisms acting at imprinted genes on the unmethylated chromosome are exerting a small effect on the expression levels of a gene at the periphery of the cluster. Perez et al., previously showed that the degree of bias is reduced as a function of distance from the most strong bias gene in the cluster indicating that the influence of ICRs diminishes over distance. To test whether the ICRs control these weak biases we used the <italic>Dlk1/Dio3</italic> region as a model since it has strongly biased Class-3 genes in the centre of the cluster and nine weakly biased genes were called at the periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). Utilizing a previously described mouse model with a deletion of its ICR (IG-DMR) that causes a maternal-to-paternal epigenotype switch when maternally inherited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Lin et al., 2003</xref>), we looked to see if the biased expression of peripheral genes was lost when the ICR was removed. Female mice heterozygous for the deletion were crossed with castaneus males to allow allele-specific expression to be determined by pyrosequencing. <italic>Dync1h1</italic> which is located on the distal side of the region and was reported to be paternally biased in two of the original studies shows fully biallelic expression in E15.5 brain from maternal heterozygotes and wildtype littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>). Conversely, two genes proximal to the defined cluster, <italic>Wars,</italic> and <italic>Wdr25</italic>, both show a weak paternal expression bias in wildtype brains that is significantly reduced in mice with the IG-DMR deletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>). This indicates that the weak biases seen at the edges of imprinted clusters are regulated by the ICRs and may be innocent bystanders of the different epigenetic environments established by the ICR on each chromosome.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Weakly biased genes close to known imprinted domains are more likely to experimentally validate than novel genes elsewhere in the genome</title><p>The lack of overlap between studies in the same tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D–I</xref>) implies a high number of false positives. To test if these parent-of-origin biases are real we performed quantitative RT-PCR and pyrosequencing validation on eight Class-1, 15 Class-2 genes (representing five novel clusters), and 20 Class-3 genes identified close to seven known imprinted domains. These genes included those that overlapped between the original studies, and those called as ASE or ‘Undetermined’ by ISoLDE that overlapped with an original study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A–C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1c and i</xref>). Six known imprinted genes were tested as controls: the robustly imprinted <italic>Dlk1</italic> and <italic>Peg3</italic>, the more moderately biased <italic>Mcts2</italic> and <italic>Herc3,</italic> and the extra-embryonic tissue-specific imprinted genes <italic>Gab1</italic> and <italic>Ampd3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Okae et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Schulz et al., 2006</xref>). Thirteen tissues were analyzed from three different timepoints e16.5, P7, and P60. Expression was called as biallelic if the mean of the paternal expression from both the C57BL/6 × CastEiJ and CastEiJ × C57BL/6 crosses was between 45 and 55% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Table showing the summary of all the allele-specific pyrosequencing performed to validate putative-biased genes.</title><p>Values show the mean expression (%) from the paternal allele of both reciprocal crosses to eliminate strain bias. Values above 55% are called as paternally biased (blue) and values below 45% are called as maternally biased (red). Assays with a strain bias of greater than 45:55 in more than one tissue are indicated in the 19<sup>th</sup> column. Genes that only validate in the placenta are called as Placental in the 20<sup>th</sup> column (Red = Maternal, Blue = Paternal).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2">Genes</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2">Chr.</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2">Dataset</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2">Direction previously reported</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2">Class</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">e16.5</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">e16.5</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">e16.5</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P7</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P7</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P7</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P7</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P7</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P60</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P60</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P60</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P60</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">P60</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2">Strain Bias</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2">Validation status</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">Plac.</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Liver</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Brain</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Cortex</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Hyp.</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Cb.</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Hipp.</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">B.S</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Cortex</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Hyp.</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Cb.</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Hipp.</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">B.S</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="5"><italic>Class-1 (Novel Singletons</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>L3mbtl1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ahi1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">10</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.5</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Platr20</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">11</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Calm1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">12</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">45.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">43.4</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Nhlrc1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">13</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B, C, D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">55.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">57.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">58.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">58.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">55.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">55.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">55.2</named-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Paternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Tnk1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">11</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Mlana</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">18</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Gm16299</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">19</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="5"><italic>Class-2 (Novel Clusters</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Stx6</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Gabra5</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.5</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Wnk4</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">11</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">45.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">44.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">44.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">45.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Maternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Vat1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">11</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">43.9</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Placental</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rdm1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">11</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Gaa</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">11</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.8</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Pcdhb10</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">18</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Pcdhb12</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">18</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">40.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">41.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">41.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">39.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">41.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">42.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">42.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">42.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">43.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">44.9</named-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Maternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Pcdhb20</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">18</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Prdx5</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">19</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rtn3</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">19</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">44.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Placental</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Pla2g16</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">19</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">40.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Placental</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Mr1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>BC034090</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Tmem106a</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">11</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="5"><italic>Class-3 (Close to known imprinted genes</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Adam23</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A,B,C,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">59.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">57.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">58.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">55.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">58.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Paternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Mcts2</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A,B,C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">K</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">77.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">82.9</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">64.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">71.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">80.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">73.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">77.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">80.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">85.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">78.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">70.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">87.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">84.2</named-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Paternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Cox4i2</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">69.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">60.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">55.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">55.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.9</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Paternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Bcl2l1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A,B,C,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">61.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">60.9</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">61.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">58.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">59.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">58.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">59.9</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">61.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">57.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">59.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">59.0</named-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">P</named-content><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">a</named-content><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">ternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Tpx2</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">55.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">64.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">62.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">61.1</named-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Paternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Herc3</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">6</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A,B,C,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">K</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">45.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">43.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">45.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">40.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">40.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">32.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">44.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">29.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">39.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">42.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">24.4</named-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Maternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Fam13a</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">6</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.4</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">n/a</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Zfp78</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">both</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Smim17</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">38.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><bold>48.8</bold></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">35.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><bold>50.9</bold></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">44.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">44.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><bold>45.2</bold></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">43.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><bold>52.1</bold></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><bold>50.8</bold></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><bold>49.3</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Maternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Peg3</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A,B,C,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">K</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">96.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">99.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">99.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">92.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">92.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">94.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">94.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">95.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">97.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">98.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">98.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">97.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">97.7</named-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Paternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Zfp954</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Zfp773</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Zfp772</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Low expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Clcn4-2</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">44.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Placental</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ifitm10</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">41.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">45.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">43.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">43.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.0</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Maternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ctsd</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.5</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Evl</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">12</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.6</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Slc25a29</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">12</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">18.9</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">45.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">56.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Placental</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Wars</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">12</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">45.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">55.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">56.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">53.2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Paternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Wdr25</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">12</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">59.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">-</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Paternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dlk1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">12</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A,B,C,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">K</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">95.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">87.9</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">93.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">92.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">92.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">94.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">90.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">95.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">89.5</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">95.6</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">93.2</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">86.9</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">95.2</named-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Paternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ppp2r5c</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">12</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">54.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">45.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dync1h1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">12</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B,C</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.8</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">Biallelic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ago2</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">15</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A,B,C,D</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">30.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">24.1</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">25.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">28.8</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">28.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">19.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">25.9</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">28.7</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">38.0</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">33.3</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">24.6</named-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Maternal</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ampd3</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">7</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">B</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">mat</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">K</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">23.4</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">46.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.5</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>✓</bold></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a3">Placental</named-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Gab1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">8</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">pat</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">K</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">74.9</named-content></td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">52.7</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">51.0</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">47.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">49.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">48.8</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">50.2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom"><named-content content-type="author-callout-style-a1">Placental</named-content></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s2-4-1"><title>Class-1</title><p>Of the eight novel singletons (Class-1) tested, four were biallelically expressed in all tissues and indeed three were expressed at very low levels. One gene, <italic>Nhlrc1</italic>, showed a consistent paternal bias across all postnatal brain tissues (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). It is noteworthy that this was the only Class-1 gene that was called in three of the original studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1c</xref>). <italic>Nhlrc1</italic> lies 1.3 kb downstream from a known germline DMR and a Zfp57 binding site suggesting a plausible mechanism for biased gene expression at the region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Proudhon et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Strogantsev et al., 2015</xref>). To see if this DMR persists postnatally, bisulfite pyrosequencing was performed on DNA from the P7 cerebellum and liver. In the cerebellum, the DMR is partially retained: the maternal allele is hypermethylated compared with the paternal allele in both BxC and CxB crosses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). However, in the liver where <italic>Nhlrc1</italic> shows no parental bias (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A</xref>), both alleles are hypermethylated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>), indicating <italic>Nhlrc1</italic> expression is parentally biased only in tissues where the DMR is retained. This suggests a mechanism whereby a gDMR can influence tissue-specific imprinting postnatally.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Experimentally validated Class-1 and Class-2 genes.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) – <italic>Nhlrc1</italic> (Class-1) is paternally biased in all postnatal neuronal tissues tested. (<bold>B-C</bold>) Bisulfite sequencing analysis in P7 tissues.(<bold>B</bold>) – Cerebellum, (<bold>C</bold>)- Liver. Each line represents a different clone of bisulfite sequencing derived from two BxC animals and two CxB animals. Numbers of identical clones sequenced are indicated to the right. Black = methylated CpG and Gray = unmethylated CpG, white = CpG absent from clone. Percentage of methylated CpGs from all clones is indicated underneath.(<bold>D</bold>) – <italic>Pcdhb12</italic> (Class-2) is maternally biased in all postnatal tissues tested. (<bold>E</bold>) – Three Class-2 genes show a maternal bias in e16.5 placenta: <italic>Vat1</italic>, <italic>Pla2g16,</italic> and <italic>Rtn3</italic>. These biases are weaker than seen in <italic>Ampd3</italic> which is imprinted in the placenta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Schulz et al., 2006</xref>). Allele-specific expression graphs (<bold>A, D and E</bold>) show mean expression (%) from the paternal allele (deep blue) and maternal allele (red) in C57BL/6 × CastEiJ (BC) and four CastEiJ × C57BL/6 (CB) crosses. Castaneus allele is denoted by a spotted pattern. Standard error of the mean is shown n=3 or 4. Data are normalized to gDNA.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Coro1c pseudogene is almost exclusively expressed from the castaneus allele.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) <italic>Nhlrc1</italic> expression bias in P6 cerebellum and liver which were also used for bisulfite sequencing analysis. (<bold>B</bold>) Allelic balance of expression of <italic>Coro1c</italic> pseudogene that overlaps the <italic>Nhlrc1</italic> DMR. Graph shows mean expression (%) from the paternal allele (blue) and maternal allele (red). C57BL/6 × CastEiJ (BC) and CastEiJ × C57BL/6 (CB) crosses. Castaneus allele is denoted by a spotted pattern. Standard error of the mean is shown, n=2 for <italic>Nhlrc1</italic> and 3 for <italic>Coro1c</italic> pseudogene.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig5-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Allelic bias in <italic>Wnk4</italic> novel cluster.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Weak bias in <italic>Wnk4</italic> gene. (<bold>B</bold>) location of genes in the novel cluster, (<bold>C</bold>) location of gDMRs, and antisense transcript. Graph shows mean expression (%) from the paternal allele (blue) and maternal allele (red) C57BL/6 × CastEiJ (BC) and four CastEiJ × C57BL/6 (CB) crosses. Castaneus allele is denoted by a spotted pattern. Standard error of the mean is shown, n=3 or 4. Data are normalized to gDNA.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig5-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Expression levels of genes tested by allele-specific pyrosequencing.</title><p>Data are extracted from <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1f</xref>. Genes that were only validated in the placenta were counted as unvalidated and the two known placental-specific imprinted genes are not included in the figure. Expression levels were reported as the mean transcripts per million (TPM) across all biological replicates. Samples: Dataset A - whole adult brain, cerebellum (cb) hypothalamus (hypo) liver, muscle. Dataset B - arcuate nucleus (ARN), dorsal raphe nucleus (DRN), liver, and muscle. Dataset C - P8 and P60 cerebellum. The original study the genes were reported as biased is noted on the y-axis – A=Dataset A, B=Dataset B, C=Dataset C, and D=Dataset D.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig5-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-4-2"><title>Class-2</title><p>Four of the 15 Class-2 genes tested fell below the expression threshold (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). Of the other 11, six were biallelic in all tissues tested, two showed biased expression in the postnatal brain (<italic>Pcdhb12</italic> and <italic>Wnk4</italic>) and three had a weak maternal bias in the placenta (<italic>Vat1, Rtn3,</italic> and <italic>Pla2g16</italic>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). <italic>Pcdhb12</italic> shows preferential expression from the maternal allele in all postnatal tissues which is consistent with the Datasets B and C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>). This gene encodes protocadherin beta-12 and is in a cluster of protocadherin genes on chromosome 18 including <italic>Pcdhb10</italic> and <italic>Pcdhb20</italic> which were also called as biased in the original studies. Both of these genes were also tested: <italic>Pcdhb10</italic> was only expressed at very low levels and <italic>Pcdhb20</italic> showed biallelic expression (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>The other Class-2 gene which validated in the postnatal brain is <italic>Wnk4</italic>. This gene forms a novel cluster with <italic>Vat1</italic>, <italic>Tmem106a,</italic> and <italic>Rdm1</italic> on chromosome 11 that spans approximately 375 kb. Both validating tissues exhibit a weak bias. Indeed, <italic>Wnk4</italic> has a much stronger strain bias in both tissues in C57BL/6xCastEiJ hybrids which may be confounding the data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2</xref>). Further analysis of this gene in other reciprocal hybrid strains is necessary to confirm the nature of its bias. One of the other genes in the <italic>Wnk4</italic> novel cluster, <italic>Vat1</italic>, was one of three Class-2 genes that validated with maternal expression bias in the placenta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>). The other two genes <italic>Rtn3</italic> and <italic>Pla2g16</italic> form a novel cluster with <italic>Prdx5</italic> (which is biallelic in all tissues tested) on Chromosome 19. All three genes with the maternal placental bias were originally called as being biased in neural tissue where no evidence for biased expression was found.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4-3"><title>Class-3</title><p>The 20 peripheral Class-3 genes assessed by allele-specific cDNA pyrosequencing had all been called as biased in brain tissues in the original studies and had maximum biases below 70%, except for <italic>Ago2</italic> which has a maximal maternal bias of 79.3%. In contrast with the putative-biased genes identified elsewhere in the genome, we found those peripheral to known imprinted clusters were more likely to validate. Nine of the 20 tested genes were validated in somatic tissues (<italic>Adam23, Cox4i2, Bcl2l2, Tpx2, Smim17, Ifitm10, Wars, Wdr25,</italic> and <italic>Ago2</italic> - <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). Of these <italic>Bcl2l1</italic> and <italic>Ago2</italic> showed a bias in all neural tissues tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplements 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">2</xref>). <italic>Bcl2l1</italic>, along with <italic>Cox4i2</italic> and <italic>Tpx2</italic> is located close to the known imprinted gene <italic>Mcts2</italic>. All three genes showed a paternal bias in at least five neural tissues. Interestingly, <italic>Tpx2</italic> was validated in all P60 tissues but not in the E16.5 or P7 material (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>) suggesting the bias strengthens over time postnatally.</p><p>Of the six genes tested that are located close to the <italic>Peg3</italic> cluster, four could not be tested due to low expression. In contrast, <italic>Smim17</italic> (<italic>Gm16532</italic>) is preferentially expressed from the maternal allele in five neural tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3</xref>). <italic>Smim17</italic> bias is strongest in the P7 hypothalamus (64.7%) but is reduced to 56.7% by P60. A maternal bias is also detected in the P7 hippocampus and brain stem but is lost by P60, together indicating the <italic>Smim17</italic> bias reduces over time (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Six genes were tested that are located at the periphery of the <italic>Dlk1</italic>/<italic>Dio3</italic> cluster on Chromosome 12. <italic>Wdr25</italic> was biallelically expressed in all tissues except the P60 hypothalamus where 59.7% of expression is from the paternal allele (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). Unlike <italic>Wdr25</italic>, <italic>Wars</italic> expression was consistently higher from the paternally inherited allele in all somatic tissues however, the bias was only above the 55% cut-off in two tissues: e16.5 brain (55.1%) and P7 hypothalamus (56.2%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). The most peripheral genes tested on both the proximal (<italic>Evl</italic>) and distal (<italic>Ppp2r5c</italic> and <italic>Dync1h1</italic>) side of the cluster were called as paternally biased in the original studies but biallelic in all tissues we assessed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A and F</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). <italic>Slc25a29</italic> was called as paternally biased in ARN and DRN in Dataset B, but we found it to be biallelic in all neural tissues. Taken together our data suggest the weak biases observed at the periphery of known imprinted domains are tissue- and stage-specific.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Allele-specific expression analysis of the <italic>Dlk1</italic> domain.</title><p><italic>(<bold>A–F</bold>) Allelic bias in Evl</italic> (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>Slc25a29</italic> (<bold>B</bold>), <italic>Wars</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>Wdr24</italic> (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>Dlk1</italic> (<bold>E</bold>), and <italic>Dync1h1</italic> (<bold>F</bold>) Graphs show mean expression (%) from the paternal allele (blue) and maternal allele (red) C57BL/6 × CastEiJ (BC) and four CastEiJ × C57BL/6 (CB) crosses. Castaneus allele is denoted by a spotted pattern. Standard error of the mean is shown, n=3 or 4. Tissues with a mean bias greater than 45:55 are indicated by arrow heads. Amplification bias was assessed in genomic DNA and the data are corrected. (<bold>G</bold>) – Imprinting of Slc25a29 in e15.5 placenta is not under the control of the IG-DMR. WT (BC) = maternal allele is wildtype for the IG-DMR paternal allele is CastEiJ (n=5). Mat_Het = maternal allele has IG-DMR deletion and the paternal allele is CastEiJ (n=6). WT (CB)=paternal allele is wildtype for the IG-DMR maternal allele is CastEiJ (n=5). Pat_Het = Paternal allele has IG-DMR deletion and the maternal allele is CastEiJ (n=7). (<bold>H</bold>) Schematic of the validated expression data in the <italic>Dlk1</italic> region. Red boxes = known maternally expressed genes. Blue boxes = known paternally expressed genes. Pink boxes = novel validated maternally biased genes. Turquoise boxes = novel validated paternally biased genes. Gray boxes = biallelically expressed genes.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig6-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Allelic bias in the <italic>Mcts2</italic> region.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) <italic>Mcts2</italic> imprinted region. (<bold>B–E</bold>) Allelic bias (%) in <italic>Mcts2</italic> (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>Cox4i2</italic> (<bold>B</bold>), <italic>Bcl2l1</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) , and <italic>Tpx2</italic> (<bold>D</bold>). Graphs show mean expression (%) from the paternal allele (blue) and maternal allele (red) C57BL/6 × CastEiJ (BC) and four CastEiJ × C57BL/6 (CB) crosses. Castaneus allele is denoted by a spotted pattern. Standard error of the mean is shown, n=3 or 4. Data are normalized to gDNA.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig6-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Allelic bias (%) in <italic>Adam23</italic> (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>Ifitm10</italic> (<bold>B</bold>), and <italic>Ago2</italic> (<bold>C</bold>).</title><p>Graphs show mean expression (%) from the paternal allele (blue) and maternal allele (red) C57BL/6 × CastEiJ (BC) and four CastEiJ × C57BL/6 (CB) crosses. Castaneus allele is denoted by a spotted pattern. Standard error of the mean is shown, n=3 or 4. <italic>Adam23</italic> and <italic>Iftim10</italic> data are normalized for an amplification bias in gDNA. Data are normalized to gDNA.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig6-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Allelic bias in <italic>Peg3</italic> region.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) <italic>Peg3</italic> imprinted region. (<bold>B–D</bold>) Allelic bias (%) in <italic>Smim17</italic> (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>Peg3</italic> (<bold>B</bold>), and <italic>Clcn4</italic> (<bold>C</bold>). Graphs show mean expression (%) from the paternal allele (blue) and maternal allele (red) C57BL/6 x CastEiJ (BC) and four CastEiJ × C57BL/6 (CB) crosses. Castaneus allele is denoted by a spotted pattern. Standard error of the mean is shown, n=3 or 4. <italic>Clcn4</italic> data are normalized for an amplification bias in gDNA. Data are normalized to gDNA.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig6-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Interestingly<italic>, Slc25a29</italic> showed a very strong maternal bias in the placenta (81.1% - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>). To determine if this biased expression is regulated by the <italic>Dlk1</italic>/<italic>Dio3</italic> imprinting control region, we again made use of the IG-DMR knockout mouse model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Lin et al., 2003</xref>), Male and female mice heterozygous for the IG-DMR deletion were crossed with CastEiJ mice and placentas were collected at E15.5. Allele-specific pyrosequencing revealed maternal and paternal heterozygotes to both the same degree of maternal bias as wildtype litter mates indicating that <italic>Slc25a29</italic> imprinting in the placenta is not under the control of the IG-DMR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6G</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In order to discuss weak parent-of-origin expression bias, it is first necessary to define canonical imprinting. Historically, imprinted expression was defined as monoallelic but as the sensitivity of methods quantifying ASE has improved it has become apparent that many imprinted genes show low-level expression from the repressed allele. Within a single canonically imprinted cluster, the extent of bias can vary greatly between genes. For example, in the <italic>Dlk1/Dio3</italic> region &gt;98% of <italic>Meg3</italic>/<italic>Gtl2</italic> expression arises from the maternal allele, and 84–99% of <italic>Dlk1</italic> expression arises from the paternal chromosome, but for <italic>Dio3</italic>, 80% of expression is from the paternal allele in the embryo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Tsai et al., 2002</xref>). However, <italic>Dio3</italic> is still considered to be an imprinted gene as this bias is established by the ICR for this region and when the ICR is deleted from the maternal chromosome imprinting is lost from the entire region and <italic>Dio3</italic> shows 50:50 expression from both alleles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Lin et al., 2003</xref>).</p><p>We, therefore, propose to define ‘canonical imprinting’ as genes that are expressed predominantly (&gt;70%) from one allele in a parent-of-origin specific manner in at least one tissue. We have taken a 70% cut-off as this was used previously by others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Andergassen et al., 2017</xref>). Canonical imprinted genes are also under the control of a differentially methylated ICR that is established during gametogenesis with expression returning to biallelic levels or completely lost on perturbation of the ICR. Genes with a weak bias at the periphery of known imprinted domains that lose the expression bias on the loss of the ICR we term ‘weak canonical imprinting’. The term ‘non-canonical imprinting’ is often used to refer to those genes for which imprinting is established in the germline via regions of differential of H3K27me3 (DMKs) leading to tissue-specific imprinting in the extra-embryonic compartment, such as <italic>Sfmbt2, Smoc1, and Gab1 (</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Inoue et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Okae et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Hanna et al., 2019</xref>). Finally, genes with a weak bias of less than 70% in tissues and with no known mechanism for the establishment of the bias we call ‘parental-origin-specific biased genes’.</p><p>Although many parental-origin-specific biased genes were identified in the brain in the original studies, only two of the Class-1 or 2 genes tested here were validated in more than two tissues (<italic>Nhlrc1</italic> and <italic>Pcdhb12</italic>). Our analysis also revealed a little overlap of novel weakly biased genes between the four datasets detailed above, even when compared between the same tissues. This lack of reproducibility could be due to several factors. Firstly, expression levels can influence ASE calling: the lack of read depth in lowly expressed genes may erroneously lead to genes being called as biased, because a small difference in read numbers produces a larger bias in weakly expressed transcripts. Of the 23 Class-1 or 2 genes tested by pyrosequencing, seven could not be confirmed due to low expression levels. However, re-analysis of the RNA-seq data from three of the original studies shows weakly expressed genes are not overrepresented in the novel biased genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>). Furthermore, when the expression levels are extracted for each of the genes tested by pyrosequencing, we see no correlation between expression levels and validation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s3">Figure 5—figure supplement 3</xref>). Expression levels are consistent between studies, especially in the same tissue, indicating the lack of reproducibility between studies is not due to differing expression. Second, the number of biological replicates can greatly influence the number of biased genes called. We found that analysis of datasets with only one or two replicates (Datasets A and E) leads to a higher number of false positive novel biased genes being called compared with datasets with &gt;6 replicates (Datasets B and C). Third, the influence of genetic background on gene expression needs to be considered. We found a greater overlap between the original studies with genes called as strain biased by ISoLDE than those called with a parental bias. Moreover, 22 of the genes we experimentally tested had a strain bias in two or more tissues compared with 16 genes with parental origin bias in one or more tissues. Finally, the method for calling ASE greatly affects the results: minimal overlap was observed between the same data analyzed by two different methods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A–C</xref>). It is noteworthy that the two Class-1 or 2 genes that experimentally validated in most tissues were both called by two or more of the original studies suggesting a more accurate picture of ASE may be achieved by combining two calling methods. Taken together, these observations highlight the need for careful planning before embarking on projects to call parental-bias, stringent filtering for low expression and strain effects, and validation via an independent method to confirm findings.</p><p>Most of the unique novel genes identified in the original studies are in regions where imprinting has not previously been identified. Although only 6 of the 23 we tested validated experimentally (three in the placenta) there may be others that display a true parent-of-origin bias. None of the Class-1 and 2 genes that were validated show a bias greater than 60:40. Such weak biases can be explained in different ways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>). First, a weak bias is seen in each cell in the population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). Second, bias may be due to true imprinting in a subset of cells within the population which could be random, clonal, or cell type-specific (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B and C</xref>). If this is due to canonical imprinting, we would expect to see a DMR. Indeed, at the <italic>Nhlrc1</italic> locus, we found that a previously reported Zfp57-bound, germline DMR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Proudhon et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Strogantsev et al., 2015</xref>) is partially retained in postnatal neural tissues indicating that its expression bias could be regulated by canonical imprinting mechanisms. We assessed the genomic intervals with other validated novel genes for germline DMRs (gDMRs) or Zfp57 binding using previously published data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Strogantsev et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kobayashi et al., 2012</xref>). No gDMRs or Zfp57 binding sites were reported in the <italic>Pcdhb</italic> cluster. In the novel cluster between <italic>Prdx5</italic> and <italic>Pla2g16</italic> there are three oocyte-methylated gDMRs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kobayashi et al., 2012</xref>). However, none of them overlap with the biased genes or a Zfp57-bound region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Strogantsev et al., 2015</xref>). Interestingly, there are two oocyte-methylated gDMRs in the interval between <italic>Wnk4</italic> and <italic>Rdm1</italic>, both of which overlap with <italic>Wnk4</italic>: one over the promoter and one over exons 5 and 6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kobayashi et al., 2012</xref>). As <italic>Wnk4</italic> is maternally biased it is hard to reconcile with methylation at the maternal promoter since most maternally methylated promoters lead to repression of the maternal allele. However, the second DMR overlaps with a lncRNA (<italic>Gm11615</italic>): further investigation is needed to establish if this transcript is reciprocally biased and offers a possible mechanism for the observed <italic>Wnk4</italic> bias. Finally, bias could be due to a skew towards activating one allele in random monoallelic expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7D</xref>). The 22 <italic>Pcdhb</italic> isoforms exhibit allelic exclusion and are mono-allelically expressed in a stochastic and combinatorial fashion in individual neurons so each cell expresses two genes from the maternally inherited chromosome and two from the paternal copy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Hirayama and Yagi, 2017</xref>). However, <italic>Pcdhb12</italic> showed a maternal bias in all postnatal tissues tested. This may reflect interindividual random bias: but, of the 60 tissue samples tested, 54 showed a maternal bias in <italic>Pcdhb12</italic> and only six showed a paternal bias, indicating there are more neurons expressing the maternally inherited copy of the gene than randomly expected. This suggests that the <italic>Pcdhb12</italic> bias does not reflect a maternal bias in each cell but rather a population bias within the brain of individuals: single cell analysis of neurons is needed to confirm this hypothesis.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Possible mechanisms behind parent-of-origin expression biases in tissues.</title><p>(<bold>A-D</bold>) Scenarios causing biased expression in heterogenous cell populations: bias occurs in every cell in the tissue (<bold>A</bold>), random imprinting in the subset of cells (<bold>B</bold>), cell-type specific imprinting (<bold>C</bold>) or random monoallelic expression that is skewed towards one allele (<bold>D</bold>). (<bold>E-H</bold>) Possible Mechanisms behind parent-of-origin biases at the periphery of imprinted domains.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-83364-fig7-v2.tif"/></fig><p>Most novel genes called in more than one study reside in or close to known imprinted regions. These genes were also more likely to validate (11 out of 20) but again, it is not known on a population level if these biases occur in every cell or are the result of complete imprinting is a subset of cells. We find that parental bias is stronger for known and novel genes within imprinted clusters than those at the periphery of the cluster. At the periphery, biased genes show temporal and tissue-specific changes: <italic>Tpx2</italic> only validates in P60 samples whereas <italic>Smim17</italic>’s bias decreases at this later stage showing biases are dynamic. We have found that weak Class-3 genes are more likely to be repressed on the chromosome with the unmethylated ICR where repression of known imprinted genes relies on repressive histone marks. Perez et al. previously showed that biases decrease towards the edge of imprinted clusters. Together, these observations suggest the influence of ICRs diminishes with distance and that differences in the local environment on each chromosome may play a role in biased gene expression. One possibility is that differential 3D architecture between the two chromosomes is contributing to the bias. It has long been known that the <italic>Igf2</italic>/<italic>H19</italic> cluster shows different conformation on each parental chromosome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Murrell et al., 2004</xref>) and a more recent single-cell 3D analysis found eight known imprinted regions have parental-origin-specific TADs in the postnatal cortex and hippocampus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Tan et al., 2021</xref>). TADs are flanked by convergent CTCF sites and were originally believed to be stable domains that demarcate regions of shared regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Dixon et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Rao et al., 2014</xref>). However, recent findings show CTCF binding is dynamic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hansen et al., 2017</xref>) and the boundaries of TADs can vary between cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Nagano et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Szabo et al., 2020</xref>). It is also known that the expression of an imprinted ncRNA from one chromosome can recruit a polycomb repressive complex to repress other genes <italic>in cis (</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Terranova et al., 2008</xref>). It is, therefore, possible that in imprinted regions, parental chromosome-specific conformations are affecting the expression of peripheral genes either by preventing the spread of repressive marks to the periphery or by reducing the enhancer/silencer interactions on the weaker allele (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7E–H</xref>). Such mechanisms could bring about weak bias in all cells or complete imprinting in a subset and are likely locus dependent; higher resolution analysis at the end of clusters and in single cells is needed to address this.</p><p>We have shown that the number of novel imprinted genes in the genome has been over-estimated by RNA-seq. However, some weakly biased genes do exist. We confirmed the weakly biased imprinting of the novel singleton <italic>Nhlrc1</italic> and many Class-3 genes. What is the functional relevance of such weak biases? As strain bias has a greater effect on expression than parent-of-origin bias then imprinting per se, may not be functionally relevant, especially if the bias is occurring within each cell. If on the other hand, the bias is due to canonical imprinting in a subset of cells, then it may be important. One known weak canonically imprinted gene is <italic>Th (</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Schulz et al., 2006</xref>), which was picked up by two of the studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Crowley et al., 2015</xref>) and shows 50–60% maternal expression bias. Importantly, this gene was found to be monoallelic in a subset of cells and be associated with a behavioral phenotype depending on maternal or paternal inheritance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>). It is, therefore, possible that other weakly biased genes are robustly imprinted in certain cell types and where their monoallelic expression is functionally important. Indeed, the <italic>Bcl2l1</italic> is a weak paternally biased gene in the <italic>H13/Mcts2</italic> imprinted domain, deletion of which leads to loss of certain neuron types and reduction in brain mass upon paternal but not maternal transmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>). In conclusion, genomic imprinting is not as widespread in the genome as recent studies have claimed. However, at the periphery of known imprinted clusters, weak parent-of-origin specific bias appears to be conferred on some genes. Whether all these weakly bias genes are functionally relevant or if some are simply innocent bystanders of local allele- and tissue-specific environments remains to be established.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Comparison of methods used in the four studies chosen for analysis</title><p>For the best comparison, we ignored all non-mouse data, as well as imprinting data from the mouse X chromosome, which was only analyzed in one of the studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>) as well as any non-imprinting work performed. Crowley et al., used CastEiJ, PWK/PhJ, and WSB/EiJ mice in reciprocal crosses of all combinations whereas the other three studies all used C57BL/6 x CastEiJ reciprocal mouse crosses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Babak et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Crowley et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>). As RNA-seq starting material, Perez and colleagues used mouse cerebellum at postnatal day (P)8 and P60 (Dataset C) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>). Bonthuis et al., used mouse liver and skeletal muscle, as well as two highly specific brain regions, the arcuate nucleus (ARN) of the hypothalamus and the dorsal raphe nucleus (DRN) of the midbrain, at 8–10 weeks of age (Dataset B) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>). Crowley and colleagues used the whole brain at P23 for their imprinting analysis (Dataset D) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Crowley et al., 2015</xref>). The Babak et al., study generated an imprinting atlas from 23 tissues from between 35- and 45 days’ post-partum (including whole brain and six brain regions) and three fetal tissues, in addition to reanalyzing data from five previous studies (Dataset A) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Babak et al., 2015</xref>). Details of the four different studies can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1a</xref>.</p><p>Although all studies used the same methods for RNA-seq (Illumina Tru-Seq RNA Kit v2), each group used a different number of replicates. The Crowley and Perez studies used six males and six females for each reciprocal cross in each tissue. Whereas Bonthuis and colleagues used eight or nine replicate females for each cross and tissue. Babak et al., pooled tissues dissected from two males for some tissues so only one library was generated for each reciprocal cross in most cases. All four studies used the Illumina HiSeq 2000 sequencing platform. The Bonthuis and Perez studies generated 59 bp single-end data and Babak et al., and Crowley et al., generated 90 bp and 100 bp paired-end data, respectively.</p><p>Three of the studies (Babak, Crowley, and Perez) used previously annotated SNPs whilst Bonthuis et al., performed RNA-seq on C57BL/6 and Castaneus parents, allowing them to identify 400,820 SNPs high confidence SNPs between the two strains. All four studies also used different statistical analyses to call allele-specific expression. Babak et al. quantified ASE for each gene by counting uniquely mapped read pairs within the gene (including introns) that overlapped at least one SNP and allowed the parent of origin to be determined. They then estimated ASE from the cumulative binomial distribution with the random expectation set to 50% (equal expression from both alleles). The log10 of the least significant p-value between the two reciprocally crossed tissue is taken as the imprinting score with the paternal bias set as negative and maternal expression as positive. The Bonthuis study tallied the C57BL/6 and Castaneus reads for all SNPs across each informative gene adjusting for reads that contained more than one SNP. They then used generalized linear modeling with false discovery rate (FDR) estimation centered upon a permutation-based approach. To reduce the variance in the data related to sample and strain effects they contrasted the full model: (allele counts ~sample + strain +parent) with the reduced model (allele counts ~sample + strain). For each dataset, they used a p-value that yielded an FDR of 1%. Crowley et al., called ASE when a paired-end read overlapped at least one SNP or indel that was heterozygous between the paternal and maternal strains. They then used the method detailed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Zou et al., 2014</xref> to jointly model the total number of reads (TReC) and the number of allele-specific reads (ASE) of each gene, which, they claim, significantly boosts power for detecting strain and particularly parent-of-origin effects. Finally, the Perez study used an in-house pipeline, the Bayesian regression allelic imbalance model (BRAIM), which accounts for all sources of variability in the experimental design i.e., cross, sex, and age.</p><p>A critical analysis of using RNA-seq to infer imprinted expression highlighted the need for validation via an independent method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">DeVeale et al., 2012</xref>). However, only three of the studies included such validation. One of the studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>) conducted a full quantitative validation by pyrosequencing of all novel genes. They found nine false positives, which are not included in our meta-analysis. Bonthuis and colleagues validated only a subset of 18 novel genes by pyrosequencing, of which 8 failed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>). Since this approach was not very systematic, testing only 12% of all novel genes, we included the original RNA-seq results including the false positives in our meta-analysis. Babak and colleagues validated most of the novel genes by pyrosequencing but in only one of all respective positive tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Babak et al., 2015</xref>). They only made RNA-seq data available for novel genes that either passed validation (13 genes) or could not be tested (12 genes), so we could not include other results. The final numbers of ASE autosomal genes reported for each study were as follows: Babak et al<italic>., -</italic> 125 (Dataset A), Bonthuis et al., - 210 (Dataset B), Perez et al., - 115 (Dataset C), and Crowley et al., – 95 (Dataset D) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Babak et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Crowley et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Meta-analysis of previous data</title><p>Co-ordinates from the Datasets A and B were converted to mm10 using the LiftOver function at UCSC (Kent et al.). Any overlapping genes with different names were individually assessed and merged if found to represent the same transcript. Overlaps between studies were then assessed.</p><p>The maximum bias from each gene was assigned into 1 of 5 bins (50-60, 60-70, 70-80, 80-90, 90-100). For Dataset C these were taken straight from elife-07860-supp1-v2.xlsx (Table G). For the Dataset A, read counts for the reciprocal crosses were taken from the original source data. The bias for each gene in every tissue was calculated by:<disp-formula id="equ1"> <mml:math id="m1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>or<disp-formula id="equ2"><mml:math id="m2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>For Dataset B, the maternal bias for each gene in every tissue was calculated as:<disp-formula id="equ3"><mml:math id="m3"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>For Dataset D, the maximum bias was calculated by taking the mean paternal and maternal bias from each reciprocal cross to eliminate strain biases.</p><p>For promoter analysis, the 500 bp upstream of the transcriptional start site was taken for each Class-3 and known imprinted gene. Methylation levels for fetal and male six week frontal cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lister et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Song et al., 2013</xref>) and Histone H3 lysine 27 trimethylation (E16 and P0 forebrain) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Gorkin et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Shen et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Sloan et al., 2016</xref>) were extracted using UCSC Table Browser (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Karolchik et al., 2004</xref>). The mean level across the 500 bp interval was calculated then the heatmap was produced using ggplot2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Wickham, 2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Allele-specific expression analysis</title><p>Raw sequencing read FASTQ files were downloaded from EMBL-EBI European Nucleotide Archive for each of the RNA-seq datasets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Babak et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Crowley et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Andergassen et al., 2017</xref>). Low-quality bases and adapters were removed with trim_galore (v0.4.1) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/">Babraham Bioinformatics - Trim Galore!</ext-link>). SNPSplit (v0.3.4) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Krueger and Andrews, 2016</xref>) was used to separate reads by the parent of origin, which first required the preparation of allele-specific reference genomes for C57BL6/CAST_Eij and CAST_Eij/FVB (based on C57BL6) with the following commands SNPsplit_genome_preparation <monospace>--vcf_file</monospace> mgp.v5.merged.snps_all.dbSNP142.vcf.gz <monospace>--reference_genome</monospace> GRCm38_fasta/ <monospace>--strain CAST_EiJ</monospace> and SNPsplit_genome_preparation <monospace>--vcf_file</monospace> mgp.v5.merged.snps_all.dbSNP142.vcf.gz <monospace>--reference_genome</monospace> GRCm38_fasta/ <monospace>--strain</monospace> CAST_EiJ <monospace>--strain2</monospace> FVB_NJ <monospace>--dual_hybrid</monospace>. VCF files for strain-specific SNPs were obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/data/mouse-genomes-project">http://www.sanger.ac.uk/data/mouse-genomes-project</ext-link>.</p><p>The Clusterflow pipeline tool was used to enable running multiple jobs in parallel across multiple processors on an HPC, however, all scripts are also compatible with running on a single processor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Ewels et al., 2016</xref>). Trimmed reads were aligned to either the C57BL6/CAST_Eij or CAST_Eij/FVB reference genomes using HiSat2 (v2.1.0) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kim et al., 2019</xref>), run via the hisat2 ClusterFlow module. Aligned reads were then name sorted to be compatible with SNPSplit, and run via the samtools (v1.9) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Li et al., 2009</xref>) Clusterflow module. Aligned files were run through SNPSplit to produce separated parent-specific alignment files using the SNP files produced by the genome preparation: all_SNPs_CAST_EiJ_GRCm38.txt.gz or all_FVB_NJ_SNPs_CAST_EiJ_reference.based_on_GRCm38.txt.gz. A custom Clusterflow module was created for SNPsplit [SNPSplit.cfmod]. Gene counts from each parent-specific alignment BAM file produced by SNPSplit were calculated using featureCounts (v1.5.0-p2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Liao et al., 2014</xref>) via Clusterflow. A custom Rscript DESeq2_featureCounts_2_CountsTables.R is used to make a single counts table, including normalized reads, from the individual featureCount files. All scripts to reproduce the analysis are freely available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/darogan/ASE_Meta_Analysis">https://github.com/darogan/ASE_Meta_Analysis</ext-link> (copy archived at <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Edwards et al., 2023</xref>) For gene expression comparisons, the sum of the raw read counts per gene for both genomes was calculated. These values were converted to TPM (transcripts per million) then the mean value across biological replicates was calculated.</p><p>The counts tables were then manipulated into the configuration needed for the ISoLDE R package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Reynès et al., 2020</xref>). ISoLDE was used to test both allele-specific parental and strain biases. The default resampling method was used with nboot = 3000 for datasets with more than two replicates. For datasets with two replicates or fewer the threshold method was used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Reynès et al., 2020</xref>). Overlaps were then identified between the different datasets.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Mice</title><p>All animal procedures were subject to local institutional ethical approval and performed under a UK Government Home Office license (project license number: PC213320E). Reciprocal crosses of the mouse lines C57BL/6 J and castaneus (CAST/EiJ) were generated. For loss of IG-DMR studies, mutant mice were maintained on a C57BL6/J background by crossing males heterozygous for the deletion with wild-type females. For expression analysis, female or male heterozygotes were mated to castaneus (CAST/EiJ) mice to generate IG-DMR deletion heterozygotic conceptuses and wildtype littermates.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Tissue collection</title><p>Samples were harvested from three to four mice from each cross at three developmental stages: e16.5 (16.5 days after conception), P7 (7 days after birth), and P60 (60 days after birth). At e16.5, the whole brain, liver, and placenta were harvested. At P7 and P60, the brain stem, cerebellum, cortex, hippocampus, and hypothalamus were harvested. Samples were snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at –80 degrees. For loss of IG-DMR studies samples were collected at E15.5, n=6 maternal heterozygotes and five wildtype littermates.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>qRT–PCR</title><p>DNA and RNA were extracted from samples using AllPrep DNA/RNA Mini kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. 5 μg RNA was treated with DNaseI (Thermo Scientific) as per the manufacturer’s instructions. 1 μg RNA was reverse transcribed with Revert Aid RT (Thermo Scientific). Assays were designed using PyroMark Assay Design SW 2.0 (Qiagen) and provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1j</xref>. The annealing temperature for each primer set was optimized by gradient PCR. The qPCR reactions were run on a LightCycler 480 (Roche) with Brilliant III Ultra-Fast SYBR Green qPCR Master Mix and the following conditions: 95 °C for 5 min followed by 45 cycles of 95 °C - 10 s, specific annealing temperature - 10 s, 72 °C - 10 s. All reactions were run in duplicate, and the relative expression of each gene was calculated using the ΔCt method and normalized to the housekeeping gene <italic>Tbp</italic>. Genes with expression lower than 0.05 times that of the housekeeping gene <italic>Tbp</italic> after qRT-PCR were not analyzed further as weak expression leads to inconsistent results between technical replicates in pyrosequencing.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Allelic expression analysis</title><p>Parental allelic expression quantification was performed by pyrosequencing. Streptavidin Sepharose High-Performance beads (GE healthcare) dissolved in binding buffer (10 mM Tris-HCL pH7.6, 2 M NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 0.1% Tween-20) were shaken with the qPCR product at 1400 rpm for 20 min. The biotinylated strand was purified using a PyroMark Q96 Vacuum Workstation (QIAGEN) then sequencing primers annealed in annealing buffer (20 mM Tris-acetate pH7.6, 2 M magnesium acetate) at 85 °C for 3 min. Sequencing was performed on a PyroMark Q96 MD pyrosequencer (Qiagen) using PyroMark Gold Q96 Reagents (Qiagen). The mean expression bias from three or four biological replicates of tissue was then calculated. Genomic DNA was also assessed to identify any amplification bias from the primers and all assays were corrected for this bias.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Clonal methylation analysis</title><p>DNA (0.5–1 µg) was bisulfite treated using the two-step protocol of the Imprint DNA Modification Kit (Sigma). converted DNA was amplified using primers Fwd 5’ <named-content content-type="sequence">TTGATGGAGTAAAAGGAATTGTTTTAGG</named-content> and Rev 5’ <named-content content-type="sequence">CCAATTCAAAAATTTAAAAAAAACAAAACC</named-content> with HotStarTaq DNA Polymerase (QIAGEN). The PCR conditions were: (1) 95 °C – 5 min; (2) 94 °C – 30 s, 55 °C – 30 s, 72 °C – 55 s, 40 cycles; (3) 72 °C – 5 min. PCR Products were run on a 1.5% agarose gel, bands were then cut out and DNA was extracted using MinElute Gel Extraction Kit (QIAGEN). Purified DNA was ligated into the pGEM-T Easy Vector and transformed into Stellar Competent Cells (Cat# 636766). Selected colonies were Sanger sequenced by GENEWIZ. At least 20 clones were tested for each tissue and genotype from two biological replicates. Clones were assessed using BISMA - Bisulfite sequencing DNA Methylation Analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Rohde et al., 2010</xref>).</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information" id="s5"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing – original draft, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Writing – review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Formal analysis</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Conceptualization, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing – review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>All animal procedures were subject to local institutional ethical approval and performed under a UK Government Home Office license (project license number: PC213320E).</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Data generated in this study.</title><p>(a) Study information for Dataset A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Babak et al., 2008</xref>), Dataset B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bonthuis et al., 2015</xref>), Dataset C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Perez et al., 2015</xref>), Dataset D (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Crowley et al., 2015</xref>) and Dataset E (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Andergassen et al., 2017</xref>). (b) All genes called in original studies. (c) Overlapping Novel genes called in original studies. (d) All genes called in this study using ISoLDE. (e) Number of genes called in individual tissues in the original study and this study. (f) Expression levels of genes in RNA-seq data used for ISoLDE and called as biased in original study - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>. (g) Strain biased genes called in Dataset B and Dataset C in this study. (h) CpG Methylation and H3K27me3 over promoter regions of imprinted and Class-3 genes - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>. (i) Overlapping genes called in this study and the original one. This list includes genes generated in the undetermined list by the ISoLDE pipeline. (j) List of primers used in the study.</p></caption><media xlink:href="elife-83364-supp1-v2.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="mdar"><label>MDAR checklist</label><media xlink:href="elife-83364-mdarchecklist1-v2.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s7"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files. Allele specific pyrosequencing data and clonal bisulfite sequencing data generated in this study is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.17863/CAM.90155">https://doi.org/10.17863/CAM.90155</ext-link>.</p><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><element-citation publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy" id="dataset1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkinson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Telerman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulsmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><data-title>Research data supporting &quot;Reassessment of weak parent-of-origin expression bias shows it rarely exists outside of known imprinted regions&quot;</data-title><source>Apollo</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17863/CAM.90155</pub-id></element-citation></p><p>The following previously published datasets were used:</p><p><element-citation publication-type="data" specific-use="references" id="dataset2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>DeVeale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kukurba</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Kooy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jb</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><data-title>Genetic conflict reflected in tissue-specific maps of genomic imprinting in human and mouse</data-title><source>NCBI Sequence Read Archive</source><pub-id pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/?term=SRP020526">SRP020526</pub-id></element-citation></p><p><element-citation publication-type="data" specific-use="references" id="dataset3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonthuis</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stacher Hörndli</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><data-title>Noncanonical Genomic Imprinting Effects in Offspring</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE70484">GSE70484</pub-id></element-citation></p><p><element-citation publication-type="data" specific-use="references" id="dataset4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhabotynsky</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakatci</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Calaway</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Aylor</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Buus</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Calaway</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Didion</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gooch</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Quackenbush</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrick</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonneman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xenakis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdar</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenarcic</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Threadgill</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarantino</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo-Manuel de Villena</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cp</surname><given-names>Fu</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><data-title>Analyses of allele-specific gene expression in highly divergent mouse crosses identifies pervasive allelic imbalance</data-title><source>NCBI Sequence Read Archive</source><pub-id pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/?term=SRP056236">SRP056236</pub-id></element-citation></p><p><element-citation publication-type="data" specific-use="references" id="dataset5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Needleman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho-Shing</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zirlinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dulac</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><data-title>Quantitative and functional interrogation of parent-of-origin allelic expression biases in the brain</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE67556">GSE67556</pub-id></element-citation></p><p><element-citation publication-type="data" specific-use="references" id="dataset6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andergassen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dotter</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bammer</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Muckenhuber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulinski</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Theussl</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Penninger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauler</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><data-title>Mapping the mouse Allelome reveals tissue-specific regulation of allelic expression</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE75957">GSE75957</pub-id></element-citation></p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andergassen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dotter</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bammer</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Muckenhuber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulinski</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Theussl</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Penninger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauler</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Mapping the mouse Allelome reveals tissue-specific regulation of allelic expression</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e25125</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.25125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28806168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Deveale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Armour</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Kooy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Global survey of genomic imprinting by transcriptome sequencing</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1735</fpage><lpage>1741</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2008.09.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19026546</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>DeVeale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kukurba</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Kooy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Genetic conflict reflected in tissue-specific maps of genomic imprinting in human and mouse</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>544</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25848752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonthuis</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stacher Hörndli</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Noncanonical genomic imprinting effects in offspring</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2015.07.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26235621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleaton</surname><given-names>MAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Phenotypic outcomes of imprinted gene models in mice: elucidation of pre- and postnatal functions of imprinted genes</article-title><source>Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-genom-091212-153441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24898037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhabotynsky</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakatci</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Calaway</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Aylor</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Buus</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Calaway</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Didion</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gooch</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Quackenbush</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrick</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonneman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xenakis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdar</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenarcic</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>C-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Threadgill</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarantino</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo-Manuel de Villena</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Analyses of allele-specific gene expression in highly divergent mouse crosses identifies pervasive allelic imbalance</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25730764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeVeale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Kooy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Babak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Critical evaluation of imprinted gene expression by RNA-seq: a new perspective</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e1002600</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22479196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Topological domains in mammalian genomes identified by analysis of chromatin interactions</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>485</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22495300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Mechanisms regulating imprinted genes in clusters</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Cell Biology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2007.04.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17467259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkinson</surname><given-names>WMD</given-names></name><name><surname>Telerman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulsmann</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><data-title>ASE meta analysis paper</data-title><version designator="swh:1:rev:fd696964037bd176a2a1b26fa5252c027a245639">swh:1:rev:fd696964037bd176a2a1b26fa5252c027a245639</version><source>Software Heritage</source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/swh:1:dir:5dc32bc14c726797ffe317b54bb0fe5fb8c1775b;origin=https://github.com/darogan/ASE_Meta_Analysis;visit=swh:1:snp:8399645c7aef644039a6acdeb9f63f5d682c32d1;anchor=swh:1:rev:fd696964037bd176a2a1b26fa5252c027a245639">https://archive.softwareheritage.org/swh:1:dir:5dc32bc14c726797ffe317b54bb0fe5fb8c1775b;origin=https://github.com/darogan/ASE_Meta_Analysis;visit=swh:1:snp:8399645c7aef644039a6acdeb9f63f5d682c32d1;anchor=swh:1:rev:fd696964037bd176a2a1b26fa5252c027a245639</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewels</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Käller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Cluster flow: a user-friendly bioinformatics workflow tool</article-title><source>F1000Research</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>2824</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.10335.2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28299179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Soloway</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Regional loss of imprinting and growth deficiency in mice with a targeted deletion of kvdmr1</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12410230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="preprint"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorkin</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name><name><surname>Barozzi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wildberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Strattan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Afzal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Plajzer-Frick</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickle</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garvin</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>QT</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannion</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda-Yuzawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Preissl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trout</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickel</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennacchio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Systematic Mapping of Chromatin State Landscapes during Mouse Development</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/166652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Haig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dulac</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010a</year><article-title>Sex-specific parent-of-origin allelic expression in the mouse brain</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>329</volume><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1190831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20616234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissbourd</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroth</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Haig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dulac</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010b</year><article-title>High-resolution analysis of parent-of-origin allelic expression in the mouse brain</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>329</volume><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1190830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20616232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pérez-Palacios</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gahurova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Biggins</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Colomé-Tatché</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourc’his</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelsey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Endogenous retroviral insertions drive non-canonical imprinting in extra-embryonic tissues</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>225</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-019-1833-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31665063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pustova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattoglio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Darzacq</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>CTCF and cohesin regulate chromatin loop stability with distinct dynamics</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e25776</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.25776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28467304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Regulation of clustered protocadherin genes in individual neurons</article-title><source>Seminars in Cell &amp; Developmental Biology</source><volume>69</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2017.05.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28591566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Maternal h3k27me3 controls DNA methylation-independent imprinting</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>547</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature23262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28723896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The role of imprinted genes in humans</article-title><source>Molecular Aspects of Medicine</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>826</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mam.2012.06.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22771538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karolchik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Furey</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskin</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugnet</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>The UCSC table browser data retrieval tool</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>D493</fpage><lpage>D496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paggi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Graph-based genome alignment and genotyping with HISAT2 and HISAT-genotype</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>907</fpage><lpage>915</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-019-0201-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31375807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yayoi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotomaru</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Contribution of intragenic DNA methylation in mouse gametic DNA methylomes to establish oocyte-specific heritable marks</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e1002440</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22242016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>SNPsplit: allele-specific splitting of alignments between genomes with known SNP genotypes</article-title><source>F1000Research</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>1479</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.9037.2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27429743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>MRW</given-names></name><name><surname>Latham</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Varmuza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>The PcG gene sfmbt2 is paternally expressed in extraembryonic tissues</article-title><source>Gene Expression Patterns</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.modgep.2007.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Youngson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Leder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>A maternal-zygotic effect gene, Zfp57, maintains both maternal and paternal imprints</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2008.08.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18854139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Homer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Abecasis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><collab>1000 Genome Project Data Processing Subgroup</collab></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>The sequence alignment/map format and samtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>FeatureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Youngson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Reik</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavaille</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Asymmetric regulation of imprinting on the maternal and paternal chromosomes at the DLK1-GTL2 imprinted cluster on mouse chromosome 12</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12937418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukamel</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nery</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Urich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Puddifoot</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwork</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonti-Filippini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Esteller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Haghighi</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Global epigenomic reconfiguration during mammalian brain development</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>341</volume><elocation-id>1237905</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1237905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23828890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murrell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heeson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reik</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Interaction between differentially methylated regions partitions the imprinted genes IGF2 and H19 into parent-specific chromatin loops</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15273689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubling</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenfelder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Laue</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Single-Cell hi-C reveals cell-to-cell variability in chromosome structure</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>502</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24067610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okae</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Funayama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaegashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Arima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Re-Investigation and RNA sequencing-based identification of genes with placenta-specific imprinted expression</article-title><source>Human Molecular Genetics</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddr488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Enroth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Redrup</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Komorowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancini-Dinardo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanduri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Kcnq1Ot1 antisense noncoding RNA mediates lineage-specific transcriptional silencing through chromatin-level regulation</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.08.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18951091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Maarri</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Engemann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Strödicke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Franck</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reik</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Sequence conservation and variability of imprinting in the Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome gene cluster in human and mouse</article-title><source>Human Molecular Genetics</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>1829</fpage><lpage>1841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/9.12.1829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10915772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Needleman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho-Shing</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zirlinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dulac</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Quantitative and functional interrogation of parent-of-origin allelic expression biases in the brain</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e07860</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.07860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26140685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plasschaert</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartolomei</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Genomic imprinting in development, growth, behavior and stem cells</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>141</volume><fpage>1805</fpage><lpage>1813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.101428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24757003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Proudhon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffié</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajjan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iranzo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbajosa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Saadeh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Oakey</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakyan</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourc’his</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Protection against de novo methylation is instrumental in maintaining parent-of-origin methylation inherited from the gametes</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2012.07.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22902559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>SSP</given-names></name><name><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamenova</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bochkov</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanborn</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Machol</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Omer</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Aiden</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A 3D map of the human genome at kilobase resolution reveals principles of chromatin looping</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>159</volume><fpage>1665</fpage><lpage>1680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.11.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25497547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynès</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kister</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouschet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Varrault</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rialle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Journot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>ISoLDE: a data-driven statistical method for the inference of allelic imbalance in datasets with reciprocal crosses</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31350542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeltsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>BISMA -- fast and accurate bisulfite sequencing data analysis of individual clones from unique and repetitive sequences</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-11-230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20459626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Menheniott</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodfine</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Oakey</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Chromosome-Wide identification of novel imprinted genes using microarrays and uniparental disomies</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>34</volume><elocation-id>e88</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16855283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>McCleary</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Edsall</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobanenkov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>A map of the cis-regulatory sequences in the mouse genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>488</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22763441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Malladi</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Strattan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitz</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabdank</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreszer</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Podduturi</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Encode data at the encode portal</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>D726</fpage><lpage>D732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26527727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Decato</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garvin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>A reference methylome database and analysis pipeline to facilitate integrative and comparative epigenomics</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e81148</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24324667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strogantsev</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamazawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman-Roberts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Allele-Specific binding of Zfp57 in the epigenetic regulation of imprinted and non-imprinted monoallelic expression</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>112</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0672-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26025256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Donjon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerković</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheutin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonev</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nora</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruneau</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bantignies</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Regulation of single-cell genome organization into tads and chromatin nanodomains</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>1151</fpage><lpage>1157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-020-00716-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33077913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Coluccio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorball</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Planet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Offner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Turelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Imbeault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Trono</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>ZNF445 is a primary regulator of genomic imprinting</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.320069.118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30602440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Deisseroth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Changes in genome architecture and transcriptional dynamics progress independently of sensory experience during post-natal brain development</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>184</volume><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.12.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33484631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terranova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>van Lohuizen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orkin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>AHFM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Polycomb group proteins EZH2 and RNF2 direct genomic contraction and imprinted repression in early mouse embryos</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2008.08.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18848501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Genomic imprinting contributes to thyroid hormone metabolism in the mouse embryo</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0960-9822(02)00951-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12176332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tucci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Isles</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelsey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><collab>Erice Imprinting Group</collab></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Genomic imprinting and physiological processes in mammals</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>176</volume><fpage>952</fpage><lpage>965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.01.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30794780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uribe-Lewis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodfine</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stojic</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Murrell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of genomic imprinting and clinical implications for cancer</article-title><source>Expert Reviews in Molecular Medicine</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1462399410001717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21262060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xu</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mardis</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Soloway</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Transcriptome-Wide identification of novel imprinted genes in neonatal mouse brain</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e3839</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19052635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Seaby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrana</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Miri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastromonaco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Caniggia</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Varmuza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011a</year><article-title>Recent acquisition of imprinting at the rodent sfmbt2 locus correlates with insertion of a large block of mirnas</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>204</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-12-204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21510876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Soloway</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011b</year><article-title>A survey for novel imprinted genes in the mouse placenta by mrna-seq</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>189</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.111.130088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21705755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><source>Ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</source><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-24277-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Landscape of genomic imprinting and its functions in the mouse mammary gland</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>857</fpage><lpage>869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jmcb/mjaa020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32369566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhabotynsky</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo-Manuel de Villena</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A novel statistical approach for jointly analyzing RNA-seq data from F1 reciprocal crosses and inbred lines</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>197</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.113.160119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24561482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleutels</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wutz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schinkel</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Bidirectional action of the IGF2R imprint control element on upstream and downstream imprinted genes</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>2361</fpage><lpage>2366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.206201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11562346</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="sa0"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.83364.sa0</article-id><title-group><article-title>Editor's evaluation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bourc'his</surname><given-names>Deborah</given-names></name><role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04t0gwh46</institution-id><institution>Institut Curie</institution></institution-wrap><country>France</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><related-object id="sa0ro1" object-id-type="id" object-id="10.1101/2022.08.21.504536" link-type="continued-by" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2022.08.21.504536"/></front-stub><body><p>This manuscript presents a useful meta-analysis of genes with parent-specific expression from mouse-published RNA-seq datasets, focusing on genes with weak allelic bias. A combination of systematic bioinformatic analysis and experimental validation convincingly shows that the number of parentally biased genes has been overestimated and the few novel ones lie at the periphery of known imprinted loci. The work will be of interest to genomicists with an interest in imprinting and its mechanisms.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.83364.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bourc'his</surname><given-names>Deborah</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04t0gwh46</institution-id><institution>Institut Curie</institution></institution-wrap><country>France</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text id="sa2-box1"><p>Our editorial process produces two outputs: (i) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2022.08.21.504536">public reviews</ext-link> designed to be posted alongside <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.21.504536v1">the preprint</ext-link> for the benefit of readers; (ii) feedback on the manuscript for the authors, including requests for revisions, shown below. We also include an acceptance summary that explains what the editors found interesting or important about the work.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Weak parent-of-origin expression bias: is this imprinting?&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by 3 peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Detlef Weigel as the Senior Editor. The reviewers have opted to remain anonymous.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed their reviews with one another, and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>The three reviewers overall appreciated the work, and the clarification it provides about the genome-wide occurrence of genomic imprinting. In addition, please provide a point-to-point answer to the reviewers.</p><p>1) Improve Figure 3 D.</p><p>2) Address the question as to why allelic ratios in the pyrosequencing analyses were not systematically normalized by amplification biases of gDNA.</p><p>3) Provide expression level comparison between true imprinted genes (confirmed ones) and the ones that were falsely called with (weak) parental bias.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>Pcdhb12 – &quot;This is not imprinting per se as does not reflect a bias in single cells but rather a population bias within the brain of individuals.&quot; This sentence should either have a reference to previous work about random monoallelic expression (if it is convincingly shown there) or it should be softened, since the data of this study doesn't allow making conclusions about population bias.</p><p>gDNA amplification bias in the pyrosequencing data – as indicated above, I don't understand (a) why this is not corrected for all loci. Even if the bias is very small, this would feel like the right thing to do, (b) if/when it's corrected, showing the 50-50 ratio in plots is meaningless and I'd suggest omitting it, or showing the original bias.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #3 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>It appears that thresholding is used in calling allelic bias: &quot;Expression was called as biallelic if the mean of the paternal expression from both the C57BL/6 x CastEiJ and CastEiJ x C57BL/6 crosses was between 45 and 55%&quot;. At the same time they provide the explanation of an important statistical flaw of such approaches: &quot;expression levels can influence ASE calling: the lack of read depth in lowly expressed genes may erroneously lead to genes being called as biased, because a small difference in read numbers produces larger bias in weakly expressed transcripts&quot;. An additional source of FP is overdispersion (i.e. additional variation present compared to statistical model), which might introduce significant changes in width of confidence intervals.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.83364.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>1) Improve Figure 3 D.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree this is difficult to read. We have removed the names from the figure and improved the resolution of writing on axes and key. We have also provided a supplemental table with the corresponding gene names and methylation/H3K27 levels from which the figure was generated.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) Address the question as to why allelic ratios in the pyrosequencing analyses were not systematically normalized by amplification biases of gDNA.</p></disp-quote><p>The PCR amplification bias has now been corrected for in every assay, and the corrected gDNA data now has been removed from each figure.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) Provide expression level comparison between true imprinted genes (confirmed ones) and the ones that were falsely called with (weak) parental bias.</p></disp-quote><p>We have now taken the RNAseq data that was processed through the ISoLDE pipeline and extracted the transcripts per million (TPM) expression levels for each of the genes called in the original studies. We find no over representation of lowly expressed genes in the novel biased genes compared with known imprinted genes. This is now provided in Figure 2 —figure supplement 1. We also looked specifically at the expression levels of the genes tested by pyrosequencing in these datasets and saw no relationship between validation and expression levels. Expression levels are consistent between studies, especially in the same tissue, indicating the lack of reproducibility between studies is not due to differing expression. This has now been presented in the manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>Pcdhb12 – &quot;This is not imprinting per se as does not reflect a bias in single cells but rather a population bias within the brain of individuals.&quot; This sentence should either have a reference to previous work about random monoallelic expression (if it is convincingly shown there) or it should be softened, since the data of this study doesn't allow making conclusions about population bias.</p></disp-quote><p>This sentence has now been rewritten “This suggests that the <italic>Pcdhb12</italic> bias does not reflect a maternal bias in each cell but rather a population bias within the brain of individuals: single cell analysis of neurons is needed to confirm this hypothesis.”</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>gDNA amplification bias in the pyrosequencing data – as indicated above, I don't understand (a) why this is not corrected for all loci. Even if the bias is very small, this would feel like the right thing to do, (b) if/when it's corrected, showing the 50-50 ratio in plots is meaningless and I'd suggest omitting it, or showing the original bias.</p></disp-quote><p>Thank you for this perspective. In response to the reviewer, the PCR amplification bias has now been corrected for all assays and the corrected gDNA data removed from each figure.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #3 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>It appears that thresholding is used in calling allelic bias: &quot;Expression was called as biallelic if the mean of the paternal expression from both the C57BL/6 x CastEiJ and CastEiJ x C57BL/6 crosses was between 45 and 55%&quot;. At the same time they provide the explanation of an important statistical flaw of such approaches: &quot;expression levels can influence ASE calling: the lack of read depth in lowly expressed genes may erroneously lead to genes being called as biased, because a small difference in read numbers produces larger bias in weakly expressed transcripts&quot;. An additional source of FP is overdispersion (i.e. additional variation present compared to statistical model), which might introduce significant changes in width of confidence intervals.</p></disp-quote><p>We used the threshold approach only to call bias in pyrosequencing data. This allows for the error in the pyrosequencing methodology which could lead to biallelic genes being called as biased. As stated in the methods we omitted genes that had low relative expression compared with TBP (&lt;0.05) as we found that this led to large variation between technical replicates in the pyrosequencing.</p></body></sub-article></article>