<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">34711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Structural Biology and Molecular Biophysics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>An NMDAR positive and negative allosteric modulator series share a binding site and are interconverted by methyl groups</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-103907"><name><surname>Perszyk</surname><given-names>Riley</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8283-7709</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-104277"><name><surname>Katzman</surname><given-names>Brooke M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-104278"><name><surname>Kusumoto</surname><given-names>Hirofumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-104279"><name><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>Steven A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-109210"><name><surname>Epplin</surname><given-names>Matthew P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-104280"><name><surname>Tahirovic</surname><given-names>Yesim A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-104281"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Rhonda L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-104282"><name><surname>Menaldino</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-104283"><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>Pieter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con9"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-104284"><name><surname>Liotta</surname><given-names>Dennis C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con10"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-44037"><name><surname>Traynelis</surname><given-names>Stephen F</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3750-9615</contrib-id><email>strayne@emory.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con11"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf6"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Pharmacology</institution><institution>Emory University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Atlanta</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Chemistry</institution><institution>Emory University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Atlanta</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Pharmacology</institution><institution>Emory University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Atlanta</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor" id="author-5115"><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>Kenton J</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff id="aff4"><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>24</day><month>05</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e34711</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2017-12-29"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-03-28"><day>28</day><month>03</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018, Perszyk et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Perszyk et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-34711-v1.pdf"/><related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="ra1" related-article-type="commentary" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.37413"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.001</object-id><p>N-methyl-<sc>d</sc>-aspartate receptors (NMDARs) are an important receptor in the brain and have been implicated in multiple neurological disorders. Many non-selective NMDAR-targeting drugs are poorly tolerated, leading to efforts to target NMDAR subtypes to improve the therapeutic index. We describe here a series of negative allosteric NMDAR modulators with submaximal inhibition at saturating concentrations. Modest changes to the chemical structure interconvert negative and positive modulation. All modulators share the ability to enhance agonist potency and are use-dependent, requiring the binding of both agonists before modulators act with high potency. Data suggest that these modulators, including both enantiomers, bind to the same site on the receptor and share structural determinants of action. Due to the modulator properties, submaximal negative modulators in this series may spare NMDAR at the synapse, while augmenting the response of NMDAR in extrasynaptic spaces. These modulators could serve as useful tools to probe the role of extrasynaptic NMDARs.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>The neurons in the brain form networks that can change in response to experience, causing new connections to form between certain neurons and breaking the connections between others. This remodeling process underlies learning and memory. However, in certain neurological disorders, such as schizophrenia and epilepsy, these networks are disrupted and no longer work correctly.</p><p>A receptor protein called the NMDA receptor plays an important role in reshaping the networks of neurons. Chemicals called neurotransmitters that are released by one neuron bind to and activate NMDA receptors on a neighbouring neuron to communicate with it. This activation encourages new connections to form between neurons.</p><p>Drugs that alter the activity of the NMDA receptor could potentially act as treatments for neurological conditions that disrupt how the networks of neurons work. However, few have been approved for use in patients because most of the potential drug compounds investigated so far produce severe side effects.</p><p>Perszyk et al. have now identified a new group of compounds that can potentially alter the activity of NMDA receptors without fully blocking the response, potentially eliminating the unwanted side effects. The compounds were tested on frog egg cells and human embryonic kidney cells that had been engineered to produce NMDA receptors. Small changes to the chemical structure of these compounds could switch their effect from increasing to decreasing the activity of the receptor. The compounds only interact with active receptors that have a neurotransmitter bound to them, and compete with each other to bind to the receptors.</p><p>Perszyk et al. also found that some compounds behaved differently depending on how active the NMDA receptor was. These compounds could potentially be used to sense the activity in a network of neurons, which opens up new options for treating neurological conditions that affect the networks.</p><p>Further experiments are now required to see how these compounds affect the activity of NMDA receptors in neurons and living animals. The range of effects produced by the compounds studied by Perszyk et al. suggests that other related compounds may have different effects on receptor activity. Future work could investigate the properties of these compounds to see if they could treat a different set of neurological disorders.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>NMDAR</kwd><kwd>Allosteric modulator</kwd><kwd>Pharmacology</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>None</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000065</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NS036654,NS065371</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Traynelis</surname><given-names>Stephen F</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000057</institution-id><institution>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>GM008602</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Perszyk</surname><given-names>Riley</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>A series of novel compounds selective for N-methyl-D-aspartate-type glutamate receptor includes positive and negative allosteric modulators that act at the same site, show use-dependence, increase agonist potency, and have differential activity based on the agonist concentration.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>N-methyl-<sc>d</sc>-aspartate receptors (NMDARs) are a subtype of ionotropic glutamate receptors that are broadly expressed in the brain and are important for normal development, neuronal plasticity and memory formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Traynelis et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Paoletti et al., 2013</xref>). NMDARs contribute a slow, Ca<sup>2+</sup> permeable component to fast excitatory neurotransmission that is voltage dependent by virtue of its sensitivity to pore block by extracellular Mg<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Traynelis et al., 2010</xref>). The typical NMDAR is comprised of 2 GluN1 and 2 GluN2 subunits, creating the potential for diversity given that there are eight splice variants of GluN1 and 4 independent genes encoding GluN2 subunits (A-D) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Traynelis et al., 2010</xref>). The regulation and functional properties of the NMDAR are controlled by the subunits incorporated into the receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Monyer et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Vicini et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Vance et al., 2012</xref>). NMDARs are expressed at most excitatory synapses, and are also found in peri- and extrasynaptic locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Sans et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Steigerwald et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Groc et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Traynelis et al., 2010</xref>). Although NMDARs have been studied extensively, there are still important questions about the different roles that NMDARs may play given differences in subunit composition and synaptic localization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Hardingham and Bading, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Gladding and Raymond, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Paoletti et al., 2013</xref>). Pharmacological approaches can be useful for probing these questions, but tool compounds to differentiate these NMDAR subtypes have been limited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Ogden and Traynelis, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Monaghan et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Santangelo et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Strong et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Zhu and Paoletti, 2015</xref>). Whereas NMDAR receptors have been implicated in many neurological diseases, there remains a dearth of clinically-approved drugs that target NMDARs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Kalia et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Traynelis et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Paoletti et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Strong et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Multiple endogenous and exogenous modulatory sites in the NMDAR recently have been described. In addition, nearly complete NMDAR structures obtained using crystallographic approaches are now available (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Karakas and Furukawa, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lee et al., 2014</xref>), and these data, together with recent cryo-EM structures in the receptor super family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Twomey and Sobolevsky, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Twomey et al., 2017a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Twomey et al., 2017b</xref>), illustrate the overall topography of the NMDAR and suggest a mechanism for some allosteric modulators, such as GluN2B-selective ifenprodil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Tajima et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Zhu et al., 2016</xref>). However, a complete understanding of how other modulatory sites operate and can be exploited has been elusive. Advances in the understanding of specific roles of particular NMDAR subunits have led to renewed interest in targeted therapeutic intervention, and recent work has yielded a growing tool box of novel ligands that act on NMDARs with diverse sites and mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Ogden and Traynelis, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Monaghan et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Hackos and Hanson, 2017</xref>). To date, there are positive and negative modulators that bind to the amino-terminal domain (ATD), agonist binding domain (ABD), or transmembrane domain (TMD). Each new class of compounds discovered enriches our understanding of the function of NMDAR and how these receptors can be modulated. The information gained from these modulators has the potential to provide insight into both NMDAR function and therapeutic strategies to treat complex neurological diseases.</p><p>This study describes a series of compounds that includes both positive allosteric modulators (PAMs) as well as negative allosteric modulators (NAMs) of NMDAR function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Katzman et al., 2015</xref>). A set of aliphatic substitutions off an ester linkage to the scaffold interconverts these compounds between positive and negative allosteric modulators. Remarkably, the difference between the positive and negative modulation to the same chemical scaffold was influenced by the addition or removal of individual methyl groups. These modulators appear to bind to a shared site to bring about opposing actions, and share mechanistic features, such as agonist dependence and enhancement of agonist potency. The spectrum of properties in this series of modulators could serve as useful tool compounds for probing the role of NMDARs in circuits in both healthy brain and in neuropathological situations.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Identification of a new class of positive allosteric modulators of NMDAR function</title><p>We have previously described the structure-activity relationship (SAR) of a series of negative allosteric pan-NMDAR modulators that contained an amidothiophene core, the most potent possessing a tetrahydrobenzothiophene, with different alkyl and aryl substitutions connected via an ester linkage at the 3-position (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Katzman et al., 2015</xref>). These compounds inhibited the response to saturating concentration of co-agonists at NMDARs expressed in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocyte experiments, typified by <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (compound 4 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Katzman et al., 2015</xref>). We describe here a new set of closely related analogues that can either potentiate or inhibit responses depending on subtle changes in structure and agonist concentration. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>, <bold>EU1794-4</bold> contained an ethyl ester similar to <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and lacked a methyl substituent on the tetrahydrobenzothiophene core. <bold>EU1794-4</bold> potently inhibited GluN1/GluN2D with a substantial residual current remaining at saturating concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B,C</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). Interestingly, ester substitutions that had a larger calculated functional group volume than the ethyl ester in <bold>EU1794-4</bold> potentiated NMDAR responses to saturating concentrations of glutamate and glycine. For example, the isopropyl ester (<bold>EU1794-5</bold>) potentiated GluN1/GluN2D responses to nearly 200% of control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A–C</xref>). Restoration of the methyl to the tetrahydrobenzothiophene core restored negative allosteric modulation (<bold>EU1794-19</bold>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B,C</xref>). Thus, the direction of modulation (positive or negative) could be determined by the size of the alkyl ester and substitution to the tetrahydrobenzothiophene core.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.003</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>The <bold>EU1794</bold> series of NMDAR NAMs can be converted to PAMs with subtle structural modifications.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative concentration-response experiments for a negative (<bold>EU1794-2</bold>, above) and positive (<bold>EU1794-5</bold>, below) allosteric modulator using two-electrode voltage-clamp recordings of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs activated by saturating concentrations of agonist. 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine application is represented by the grey bar and increasing concentrations of modulator are shown by grey scale boxes (0.3, 1, 3, 10, 30 µM for <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and 1, 3, 10, 30, 100 µM for <bold>EU1794-5</bold>). (<bold>B</bold>) Chemical structures of the NAMs <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, <bold>EU1794-4, EU1794-19</bold> and PAM <bold>EU1794-5</bold> are given, which show all permutations of two methyl substitutions. This series illustrates how subtle changes in chemical structure interconvert modulator activity. (<bold>C</bold>) The concentration-response curves for the compounds shown in (<bold>B</bold>) acting on GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs activated by maximally effective concentrations of co-agonists and fitted by the Hill equation. (<bold>D</bold>) Chemical structures of <bold>EU1794</bold> PAMs. (<bold>E</bold>) Concentration-response curves for <bold>EU1794</bold> PAMs on the responses of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs to maximally effective concentrations of co-agonists. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref> for fitted EC<sub>50</sub> values at all diheteromeric NMDARs. Data represent 4–18 oocytes recorded in at least two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig1-v1"/></fig><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.004</object-id><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>The effect of alkyl ester and tetrahydrobenzothiophene ring substitutions on the potency and efficacy of <bold>EU1794</bold> analogues.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="4"><inline-graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-inf1-v1"/></th><th colspan="4">EC<sub>50</sub> (µM) [conf. int.]* <break/>Maximal Degree of Modulation (% of control)<sup>†</sup></th></tr><tr><th>Compound</th><th>R<sub>1</sub></th><th>R1 volume (Å<sup>3</sup>)</th><th>R<sub>2</sub></th><th>GluN2A</th><th>GluN2B</th><th>GluN2C</th><th>GluN2D</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>EU1794-4</bold></td><td>Et</td><td>45.15</td><td>H</td><td>2.2 [1.8, 2.8] <break/>32 ± 3%</td><td>2.6 [1.4, 4.8] <break/>67 ± 4%</td><td>0.42 [0.28, 0.61] <break/>52 ± 2%</td><td>0.36 [0.29, 0.45] <break/>51 ± 3%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>EU1794-2</bold></td><td>Et</td><td>45.15</td><td>Me</td><td>0.60 [0.44, 0.82] <break/>6 ± 2%</td><td>1.2 [0.8, 1.9] <break/>10 ± 3%</td><td>0.26 [0.21, 0.31] <break/>14 ± 1%</td><td>0.20 [0.17, 0.25] <break/>14 ± 1%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>EU1794-5</bold></td><td>iPr</td><td>62.16</td><td>H</td><td>18 [9.0, 36] <break/>36 ± 5%</td><td>2.5 [1.4, 4.4] <break/>71 ± 4%</td><td>4.0 [3.5, 4.6] <break/>140 ± 3%</td><td>9.3 [8.1, 11] <break/>169 ± 7%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>EU1794-19</bold></td><td>iPr</td><td>62.16</td><td>Me</td><td>1.1 [0.5, 2.3] <break/>19 ± 6%</td><td>1.1 [0.9, 1.3] <break/>43 ± 2%</td><td>0.74 [0.57, 0.96] <break/>32 ± 3%</td><td>0.43 [0.32, 0.59] <break/>46 ± 2%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>EU1794-27</bold></td><td>tBu</td><td>79.23</td><td>H</td><td>7.4 [5.3, 10] <break/>52 ± 7%</td><td>1.4 [1.2, 1.7] <break/>130 ± 3%</td><td>2.8 [2.5, 3.2] <break/>230 ± 10%</td><td>2.4 [1.8, 3.3] <break/>250 ± 8%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>EU1794-25</bold></td><td>Bn</td><td>98.87</td><td>H</td><td>-</td><td>1.0 [0.9, 1.2] <break/>220 ± 13%</td><td>0.77 [0.56, 1.0] <break/>180 ± 12%</td><td>1.0 [0.95, 1.1] <break/>250 ± 19%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>EU1794-29</bold></td><td>n-Bu</td><td>79.12</td><td>H</td><td>3.7 [1.7, 8.0] <break/>59 ± 5%</td><td>1.4 [1.1, 1.8] <break/>140 ± 3%</td><td>3.8 [2.6, 5.7] <break/>130 ± 7%</td><td>5.7 [5.1, 6.4] <break/>166 ± 8%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*EC<sub>50</sub> values for potentiation of responses to saturating glutamate and glycine (100 μM, 30 μM) were obtained by least-squares fitting of data from individual experiments by the Hill equation. EC<sub>50</sub> values are given as the mean with the 95% confidence interval determined from log(EC<sub>50</sub>).</p><p><sup>†</sup>The maximal degree of modulation is given as mean ±SEM. For all compounds, data are from 4 to 18 oocytes recorded in at least two independent experiments. Data were not fit (shown as -) if the response recorded at 30 µM of test compound did not differ by more than 15% from control.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The size of the ester-linked substituent controlled the extent and potency of positive modulation. The <italic>t</italic>-butyl ester <bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiated GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs with greater efficacy and higher potency, increasing responses to maximally effective glutamate and glycine to 250% of control with an EC<sub>50</sub> value of 2.4 µM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D,E</xref>). The benzyl ester (<bold>EU1794-25</bold>) also strongly potentiated responses with a potency similar to <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D,E</xref>). However, <bold>EU1794-29</bold>, which had a longer substitution, <italic>n</italic>-butyl, reduced both the maximal potentiation and potency, suggesting an optimal substituent size and shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D,E</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Allosteric modulation of agonist potency by NAMs and PAMs</title><p>The tetrahydrobenzothiophene-containing NAMs reported here inhibit all diheteromeric NMDARs without substantial subunit selectivity, similar to those that we previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Katzman et al., 2015</xref>). By contrast, the novel PAMs described here show distinct GluN2 dependence (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>). All PAMs are active at GluN1/GluN2C and GluN1/GluN2D, but do not enhance the response of GluN1/GluN2A to maximally effective concentrations of agonist, in some cases resulted in inhibition of these responses. Most PAMs were also capable of potentiating GluN1/GluN2B (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). As seen with other series of NMDAR PAMs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Malayev et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Horak et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Horak et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hackos et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Wang et al., 2017</xref>), allosteric modulation can be dependent on agonist concentrations. Thus, we assessed the ability of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> to modulate NMDAR responses activated by sub-saturating co-agonist concentrations, clearly exemplified by modulation of GluN1/GluN2C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2">Table 2</xref>). In these conditions, <bold>EU1794-27</bold> positively modulated all NMDAR subtypes and enhanced previously potentiated subtypes to a greater extent than in saturating agonist (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A and C</xref>). We hypothesized that this agonist-dependence was due to <bold>EU1794-27</bold> altering the agonist potency. Therefore, we determined the glutamate and glycine EC<sub>50</sub> values in the absence and presence of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A,B</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). <bold>EU1794-27</bold> produced modest but significant decreases (higher potency) in the EC<sub>50</sub> values for both glutamate and glycine at all NMDARs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). Given this effect by the PAMs in this series, we subsequently considered whether the NAMs in the series shared this mechanism. We selected <bold>EU1794-4</bold> for use in evaluating actions on agonist potency since it retains a large steady-state current even for receptors that have bound <bold>EU1794-4</bold> (saturated inhibition is between 40–70% of control, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). We co-applied <bold>EU1794-4</bold> during responses stimulated by sub-saturating concentrations of agonist (glutamate and glycine concentrations that resulted approximately in a EC<sub>20</sub> response), which resulted in positive modulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E,F</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2">Table 2</xref>). Furthermore, the negative modulator <bold>EU1794-4</bold> enhanced the glutamate and glycine potencies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C,D</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4">Table 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). Interestingly, positive modulation elicited by 10 µM <bold>EU1794-4</bold> is dependent on the sub-saturating agonist concentrations used (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5">Table 5</xref>). <bold>EU1794-4</bold> inhibited GluN1/GluN2C responses to saturating concentrations of agonist to 54% of control, and positively modulated equivalent EC<sub>30</sub> responses (equal effective concentrations of glutamate and glycine concentrations that when applied resulted in a 30% of a maximal response) to 140% of control, and positively modulated average equivalent EC<sub>3</sub> responses by 660% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5">Table 5</xref>). We did not observe augmentation of sub-saturating agonist responses by <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, most likely due to its greater extent of inhibition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>). However, the degree of inhibition produced by <bold>EU1794-2</bold> was reduced on sub-saturating responses at GluN1/GluN2C from 16% to 45% of control (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5">Table 5</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.005</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Modulation of both <bold>EU1794</bold> PAMs and NAMs is dependent on agonist concentration.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The concentration-response relationship for <bold>EU1794-27</bold> at diheteromeric NMDARs activated by 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine (data for GluN1/GluN2D shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref> is included here for clarity). GluN1/GluN2C and GluN1/GluN2D (which are superimposed) are potentiated to a greater extent than GluN1/GluN2B; there appears to be slight inhibition of GluN1/GluN2A. (<bold>B</bold>) A representative concentration-response recording of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> at GluN1/GluN2B activated by sub-saturating concentrations of agonist. The initial response was activated using saturating 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine (black box) followed by 1/0.3 µM glutamate/glycine (grey box, roughly resulting in an activity state that was 20% of the maximal response) administered in the absence and presence of increasing concentrations of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (0.3, 1, 3, 10, 30 µM). (<bold>C</bold>) Concentration-response relationship for <bold>EU1794-27</bold> at diheteromeric NMDARs activated by sub-saturating concentration of agonist (glutamate/glycine concentrations used for GluN1/GluN2A were 2/0.6 µM, GluN1/GluN2B and GluN1/GluN2C were 1/0.3 µM, and GluN1/GluN2D were 0.6/0.2 µM). Note potentiation of all subunits. (<bold>D–F</bold>) Similar experiments as in A-C, but using the NAM <bold>EU1794-4</bold> at saturating (<bold>D</bold>) or sub-saturating (<bold>E,F</bold>) concentrations of agonist (glutamate/glycine concentrations used for GluN1/GluN2A, GluN1/GluN2B and GluN1/GluN2C were 1/0.3 µM, and GluN1/GluN2D were 0.3/0.09 µM); data for GluN1/GluN2D presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref> are included here for comparison. Note the inhibition by the NAM at saturating agonist concentration (<bold>D</bold>) compared to potentiation in submaximal concentrations of agonist in (<bold>E,F</bold>). Data represent 4–13 oocytes recorded in two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.006</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><bold>EU1794-2</bold> actions possess modest agonist concentration-dependence.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Concentration-response relationship for <bold>EU1794-2</bold> at each diheteromeric NMDAR activated by saturating concentration of agonist (100/30 µM glutamate/glycine; data for GluN1/GluN2D are reproduced from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) A representative recording of the response to <bold>EU1794-2</bold> at GluN1/GluN2C NMDARs activated by sub-saturating concentrations of agonist. The initial response was activated using saturating concentrations (100/30 µM glutamate/glycine, black box) of agonist followed by sub-saturating concentrations of agonist (0.6/0.2 µM glutamate/glycine, grey box) co-applied with increasing concentrations of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (0, 0.3, 1, 3, 10, 30 µM). (<bold>C</bold>) Concentration-response relationship for <bold>EU1794-2</bold> at each diheteromeric NMDAR activated by sub-saturating concentration of agonist (as noted in B). Saturating data are from 4 to 18 oocytes from at least two independent experiments and sub-saturating data are from six oocytes.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig2-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.007</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title><bold>EU1794</bold> PAMs and NAMs enhance glutamate and glycine potency.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative glutamate (left) and glycine (right) concentration-response curves of oocytes expressing GluN1/GluN2C with and without <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (10 µM, grey box). The glutamate concentration-response curve (0.1, 0.3, 1, 3, 10, 30 µM) was generated with 30 µM glycine and the glycine concentration-response curve (0.03, 0.1, 0.3, 1, 3, 10 µM) was recorded in 100 µM glutamate. (<bold>B</bold>) Mean concentration-response data for glutamate (left) and glycine (right) at GluN1/GluN2C (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref> for other subunits). Each curve was normalized to the maximal response in the absence of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> to illustrate the actions of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> on agonist EC<sub>50</sub>. (<bold>C,D</bold>) A similar set of experiments as in (<bold>A,B</bold>), but with <bold>EU1794-4</bold> are shown (10 µM, grey box). Note the variation of the order of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> application in experimental traces, which was selected randomly. The glutamate concentration-response curve (glutamate concentration are 0.03, 0.1, 0.3, 1, 3, and 100 µM and glycine concentrations are 10 and 30 µM) and the glycine concentration-response curve (glycine concentrations are 0.01, 0.03, 0.1, 0.3, 1, 30 µM, and glutamate concentration are 30 and 100 µM). Each curve was normalized to the maximal response from each oocyte in the absence of <bold>EU1794-4</bold>. Data are from 4 to 12 paired oocytes recordings from at least two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.008</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>The effects of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> and <bold>EU1794-4</bold> on agonist potency for all diheteromeric NMDARs.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Mean concentration response data for glutamate (<italic>top</italic>) and glycine (<italic>bottom</italic>) at each diheteromeric NMDAR with and without 10 µM of the PAM <bold>EU1794-27</bold>. Each curve was normalized to the maximal response (either in the absence or presence of <bold>EU1794-27</bold>) to better illustrate the shift in agonist EC<sub>50</sub>. (<bold>B</bold>) A similar set of plots as in (<bold>A</bold>) but with 10 µM of the NAM <bold>EU1794-4</bold>. Each set of curves was normalized to the maximal response from each cell in the absence of <bold>EU1794-4</bold>. Data are from 4 to 12 paired oocytes recordings from at least two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig3-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group><table-wrap id="table2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.009</object-id><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Effect of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> at sub-saturated NMDAR responses.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="4">EC<sub>50</sub> (µM) [conf. int.]* <break/>Maximal Degree of Modulation (% of control)<sup>†</sup></th></tr><tr><th/><th>GluN2A</th><th>GluN2B</th><th>GluN2C</th><th>GluN2D</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>EU1794-4</bold></td><td>3.9 [0.78, 20] <break/>500 ± 32%</td><td>4.3 [1.3, 14] <break/>210 ± 6.8%</td><td>15 [6.5, 35] <break/>220 ± 20%</td><td>14 [6.5, 29] <break/>540 ± 190%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>EU1794-27</bold></td><td>8.1 [5.7, 12] <break/>340 ± 32%</td><td>6.3 [5.0, 8.0] <break/>400 ± 50%</td><td>5.0 [3.7, 6.6] <break/>680 ± 50%</td><td>8.3 [5.3, 13] <break/>580 ± 86%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*EC<sub>50</sub> values of modulator action on responses to sub-saturating glutamate/glycine concentrations were obtained by least-squares fitting of data from individual experiments by the Hill equation. For <bold>EU1794-4</bold> modulation of GluN1/GluN2A, GluN1/GluN2B and GluN1/GluN2C, glutamate/glycine concentrations were 1/0.3 µM; for GluN1/GluN2D glutamate/glycine were 0.3/0.09 µM. For <bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiation, glutamate/glycine concentrations were 2/0.6 µM (GluN1/GluN2A), 1/0.3 µM (GluN1/GluN2B, GluN1/GluN2C), and 0.6/0.2 µM (GluN1/GluN2D). EC<sub>50</sub> for potentiation values are given as the mean with the 95% confidence interval determined from log(EC<sub>50</sub>).</p><p><sup>†</sup>The extent of modulation is given as a percent of the control response in the absence of test compound. The maximal degree of modulation is given as mean ±SEM. For all compounds, data are from 4 to 13 oocytes recorded in two independent experiments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.010</object-id><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>EU1794-27 effects on glutamate and glycine EC<sub>50</sub> values.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="6">EC<sub>50</sub> (µM) [conf. int.]*</th></tr><tr><th/><th>Control Glutamate</th><th>EU1794-27 <break/>Glutamate</th><th valign="top">Fold <break/>Difference</th><th>Control <break/>Glycine</th><th>EU1794-27 <break/>Glycine</th><th valign="top">Fold <break/>Difference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>GluN2A</bold></td><td>2.9 <break/>[2.2, 4.0]</td><td>1.1 <break/>[0.88, 2.1]</td><td>2.3<sup>†</sup></td><td>0.57 <break/>[0.34, 0.96]</td><td>0.38 <break/>[0.23, 0.64]</td><td>1.6</td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2B</bold></td><td>1.2 <break/>[1.1, 1.3]</td><td>0.65 <break/>[0.49, 0.85]</td><td>2.0<sup>†</sup></td><td>0.28 <break/>[0.22, 0.36]</td><td>0.14 <break/>[0.08, 0.24]</td><td>2.9<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2C</bold></td><td>0.67 <break/>[0.61, 0.73]</td><td>0.22 <break/>[0.16, 0.31]</td><td>3.3<sup>†</sup></td><td>0.23 <break/>[0.13, 0.40]</td><td>0.10 <break/>[0.07, 0.15]</td><td>2.4</td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2D</bold></td><td>0.21 <break/>[0.17,0.27]</td><td>0.054 <break/>[0.028, 0.11]</td><td>5.3<sup>†</sup></td><td>0.086 <break/>[0.077, 0.095]</td><td>0.020 <break/>[0.013, 0.029]</td><td>4.9<sup>†</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Glutamate EC<sub>50</sub> values (in the presence of 30 µM glycine) and glycine EC<sub>50</sub> values (in the presence of 100 µM glutamate) were obtained by least-squares fitting of data from independent oocyte recordings by the Hill equation. EC<sub>50</sub> values are given as the mean with the 95% confidence interval determined from log(EC<sub>50</sub>). Data in the absence and presence of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> were obtained from the same oocyte. Data are from 5 to 12 paired oocytes recordings from at least two independent experiments.</p><p><sup>†</sup>indicates paired measurements with non-overlapping confidence intervals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.011</object-id><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>EU1794-4 effects on glutamate and glycine EC<sub>50</sub> values.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="6">EC<sub>50</sub> (µM) [conf. int.]*</th></tr><tr><th/><th>Control <break/>Glutamate</th><th>EU1794-4 <break/>Glutamate</th><th valign="top">Fold <break/>Difference</th><th>Control <break/>Glycine</th><th>EU1794-4 <break/>Glycine</th><th valign="top">Fold <break/>Difference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>GluN2A</bold></td><td>3.6 <break/>[3.3, 4.0]</td><td>1.5 <break/>[1.2, 2.1]</td><td>2.4<sup>†</sup></td><td>0.89 <break/>[0.72, 1.1]</td><td>0.35 <break/>[0.17, 0.70]</td><td>2.8<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2B</bold></td><td>1.5 <break/>[1.2, 2.0]</td><td>0.8 <break/>[0.48, 1.3]</td><td>2.0<sup>†</sup></td><td>0.46 <break/>[0.37, 0.56]</td><td>0.14 <break/>[0.12, 0.17]</td><td>3.3<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2C</bold></td><td>0.84 <break/>[0.57, 1.2]</td><td>0.29 <break/>[0.15, 0.55]</td><td>3.2<sup>†</sup></td><td>0.31 <break/>[0.15, 0.62]</td><td>0.08 <break/>[0.024, 0.25]</td><td>4.6<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2D</bold></td><td>0.63 <break/>[0.41, 0.95]</td><td>0.17 <break/>[0.065, 0.43]</td><td>3.9<sup>†</sup></td><td>0.15 <break/>[0.089, 0.24]</td><td>0.016 <break/>[0.007, 0.038]</td><td>8.9<sup>†</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Glutamate EC<sub>50</sub> values (in the presence of 10 μM glycine) and glycine EC<sub>50</sub> values (in the presence of 30 μM glutamate) were obtained by least-squares fitting of data by the Hill equation. EC<sub>50</sub> values are given as the mean with the 95% confidence interval determined from log(EC<sub>50</sub>). Data in the absence and presence of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> were obtained from the same oocyte. Data are from 4 to 8 paired oocytes recordings from two independent experiments.</p><p><sup>†</sup>indicates paired measurements with non-overlapping confidence intervals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.012</object-id><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>Comparison of <bold>EU1794-27</bold>, <bold>EU1794-4</bold>, and <bold>EU1794-2</bold> effects at GluN1/GluN2C NMDAR responses to sub-saturating agonist.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>GluN2C</th><th>Glu/Gly <break/>(µM)</th><th>Relative agonist Response* <break/>(% of maximal response)</th><th>Modulation by 10 µM<sup>†</sup> <break/>(% of control)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>EU1794-27</bold></td><td>100/30 <break/>1/0.3</td><td>- <break/>20 ± 1.6</td><td>190 ± 10% <break/>480 ± 31%<sup>‡</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>EU1794-4</bold></td><td>100/30 <break/>1/0.3 <break/>0.3/0.09</td><td>- <break/>27.7 ± 3.3 <break/>2.8 ± 0.7</td><td>54 ± 1.6% <break/>140 ± 12%<sup>‡</sup> <break/>660 ± 110%<sup>‡</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>EU1794-2</bold></td><td>100/30 <break/>0.6/0.2</td><td>- <break/>21.5 ± 6.8</td><td>16 ± 1.0% <break/>43 ± 2.1%<sup>‡</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The data presented are mean ±SEM.</p><p>*Reported average responses to sub-saturating agonist were normalized to a 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine response.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>†</sup>The degree modulation is reported as a percent of the control response to sub-saturating agonist. Some of these data points correspond to those used to calculated EC<sub>50</sub> values for each modulator in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2">Table 2</xref> or <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>. Data are mean ±SEM.</p><p><sup>‡</sup>p&lt;0.05 as compared to 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine response, determined by an unpaired t-test, n = 4–10 cells.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>PAMs and NAMs display both glutamate and glycine dependence</title><p>We studied NMDARs expressed in HEK293 cells to investigate the time course of modulator action. Concentration-dependent association of <bold>EU1794-2, EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> and concentration-independent disassociation were evaluated by co-applying modulator with glutamate and glycine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A,B</xref>). These modulators were tested on GluN1/GluN2A and GluN1/GluN2D to see whether there were differences in modulation given the distinct properties of these NMDAR subtypes. We analyzed the concentration-dependence of the exponential time course describing the onset of action during co-application with saturating concentrations of glutamate plus glycine to determine modulator association and dissociation rates. From these we calculated the kinetically-determined affinity constant (K<sub>d</sub>), which we found to be similar to the EC<sub>50</sub> values determined from concentration-response experiments. <bold>EU1794-2</bold> K<sub>d</sub> was 1.1 µM at GluN1/GluN2D (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A,B</xref>). Complex actions of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> were observed, with two temporally-distinct phases of modulation evident for the association of these modulators (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Both compounds produced a rapid inhibition followed by a slowly developing potentiating phase for <bold>EU1794-27</bold>. The rapid association rate determined during the rapid inhibition produced by <bold>EU1794-4</bold> was approximately three times faster than <bold>EU1794-2</bold>; similarly, the dissociation rate was also faster for <bold>EU1794-4</bold> than <bold>EU1794-2</bold>. Quantitative analysis of the slower phases was challenging due to its lower signal-to-noise ratio. Likewise, the rapid inhibitory phase was also difficult to measure for <bold>EU1794-27</bold> because its rapid time course was convolved with the potentiation time course. Additionally, the depotentiation time course is preceded by a transient enhancement of the current response, followed by a relaxation to the pre-modulation level. The time course for potentiation and depotentiation were best fit with an exponential function summed with an additional linear component after the rapid phase subsided. K<sub>d</sub> determined from the association and dissociation rates of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> was 4.2 µM and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> was 4.3 µM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). All modulatory effects were independent of voltage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>). The steady state modulator responses from HEK293 cells approximately match the concentration-response relationship determined from TEVC recordings from <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, <italic>inset graphs</italic>). The time-course of modulator binding of <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, <bold>EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> was also determined for GluN1/GluN2A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C,D</xref>). Higher K<sub>d</sub> values (lower potency) were determined for each molecule at GluN1/GluN2A as compared to GluN1/GluN2D that parallel EC<sub>50</sub> values determined using <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes. Similar to oocyte data, robust inhibition was produced by <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, modest inhibition was produced by <bold>EU1794-4</bold>, and transient inhibition and recovery was observed by the application of <bold>EU1794-27</bold>. Interestingly, the extent of steady-state modulation for this series appeared to be dependent on the level of desensitization of the receptors at the time of modulator application. When classifying the cells as either having high or low levels of desensitization (using 35% steady-state/peak response as a cut-off), the extent of modulation by 10 µM was significantly different for <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (p=0.02, unpaired t-test, N = 4,2, respectively). The low desensitized group (40% average desensitization) was modulated by 107%, whereas the high desensitized group (10% average desensitization) was modulated to 247% of control by 10 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1F</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.013</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>The association and dissociation time course of <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, <bold>EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> differ at GluN1/GluN2A and GluN1/GluN2D.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative whole-cell current recordings of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs exemplifying the modulation time course of <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, <bold>EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (1, 3, 10 µM). Responses were evoked by 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine and were normalized for display. Insets show the steady state modulation extent from the HEK cell experiments fit by the Hill equation (Hill slope fixed to 1). (<bold>B</bold>) Analysis of the time course for the onset of PAM and NAM action as a function of concentrations for <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<italic>left</italic>), <bold>EU1794-4</bold> (<italic>left</italic>) and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<italic>right</italic>) used to determine the association rate <italic>k<sub>ON</sub></italic> (black circles) and dissociation rate <italic>k<sub>OFF</sub></italic> (grey squares), from which we can calculate <italic>K<sub>d</sub></italic> for each modulator. Data are from at least 3 cells for each concentration of modulator. For <bold>EU1794-27</bold> the association and dissociation rate linear component was also found to be concentration dependent (<italic>m<sub>on</sub></italic> = −0.98 pA/(ms*µM), <italic>m<sub>off</sub></italic> = 0.62 pA/(ms*µM)). (<bold>C,D</bold>) Similar set of panels as A,B but examining <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, <bold>EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> modulation of GluN1/GluN2A. In example recordings, all modulator concentrations are 10 µM. Data are from at least 3 cells for each concentration of modulator. For <bold>EU1794-27</bold> time-course was fitted with the sum of an exponential and linear function, and both the time constant and slope were concentration dependent (<italic>m<sub>on</sub></italic> = −0.33 pA/(s*µM), <italic>m<sub>off</sub></italic> = 0.16 pA/(s*µM)).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig4-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.014</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>The actions of <bold>EU1794</bold> modulators are voltage-independent and are influenced by the desensitization level.</title><p>(<bold>A–C</bold>) A representative current response of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<bold>A</bold>, the ratio of the % modulation by <bold>EU1794-2</bold> at +40 mV and −60 mV was 1.1 ± 0.27, n = 3), <bold>EU1794-4</bold> (<bold>B</bold>, the ratio of modulation at +40 mV and −60 mV was 0.88 ± 0.06, n = 6) and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<bold>C</bold>, the ratio of modulation at +40 mV and −60 mV was 0.99 ± 0.15, n = 3) modulation with the Vm held at +40 mV and −60 mV; all responses shown were using 10 µM of test compound. (<bold>D–F</bold>) Representative whole-cell current recordings exemplifying the modulation time course of 10 µM <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<bold>D</bold>), <bold>EU1794-4</bold> (<bold>E</bold>), and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<bold>F</bold>) on GluN1/GluN2A NMDAR responses with a high degree of desensitization. Responses were evoked by 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine and were normalized for display. <bold>EU1794-2</bold> modulated low desensitized steady state responses to 13% (drug/control) and high desensitized steady state responses to 32% of control (n = 3, 1). <bold>EU1794-4</bold> modulated low desensitized steady state responses to 47% and high desensitized steady state responses to 79% of control (n = 2, 1). <bold>EU1794-27</bold> modulated low desensitized steady state responses to 107 ± 16% and high desensitized steady state responses to 247 ± 31% of control (n = 2, 4; p=0.028 unpaired t-test).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig4-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group><p>Given that other NMDAR modulators have displayed agonist-dependence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Petrovic et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Acker et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Hansen and Traynelis, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Borovska et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Vyklicky et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Wang et al., 2017</xref>), we performed rapid solution exchange experiments to examine if these modulators had different affinities at agonist-bound and <italic>apo</italic> receptors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A,B</xref>). The instantaneous current response to a rapid step into glutamate plus glycine (from glycine alone) gives an estimate of whether a modulator was pre-bound to receptors with only glycine (but not glutamate) bound. The immediate NMDAR activation after a rapid switch to a solution containing glutamate and glycine should occur faster than modulator binding. We chose to test for agonist-dependence using GluN1/GluN2D since they lack desensitization, which would complicate interpretation of this modulator property. We found that the peak current was similar when cells were preincubated in glycine with or without 3 µM <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, suggesting that <bold>EU1794-2</bold> does not bind appreciably to the receptor in the absence of glutamate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A,C</xref>). After the rapid step into glutamate where glycine and modulator were pre-exposed, we observed a relaxation to a new response level that was similar in amplitude to that observed with steady state co-application of glutamate plus glycine and modulator (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A,C</xref>). Interestingly, we also observed a similar effect for the converse experiment, in which we pre-applied glutamate with or without <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, followed by a rapid step into glutamate plus glycine and <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B,C</xref>). We interpret these data to suggest that <bold>EU1794-2</bold> associates with the receptor with higher affinity after glutamate and glycine binding.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.015</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>The <bold>EU1794</bold> series has agonist-dependence that alters the response time-course.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative whole-cell recordings of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs exemplifying the <bold>EU1794-2</bold> dependence on glutamate binding. The cell was exposed continuously to 30 µM glycine with/without 3 µM <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, and then was rapidly stepped into a solution additionally containing 100 µM glutamate. The <italic>right panel</italic> shows an expanded view of the rise of the receptor response and the rapid time course of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> action. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative whole-cell current recordings of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs exemplifying the <bold>EU1794-2</bold> dependence on glycine binding. The cell was exposed continuously to 100 µM glutamate with/without 3 µM <bold>EU1794-2</bold>, and then was rapidly stepped into a solution additionally containing 30 µM glycine. The <italic>right panel</italic> shows an expanded view of the rise of the receptor response and the rapid time course of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> action. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of the modulation of the immediate peak response and steady state data (shown as a percentage <bold>EU1794-2</bold>/control for each phase) from agonist-dependence experiments for <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (3 µM, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A,B</xref> and S4B). * signifies p&lt;0.05 as determined by a Bonferroni's multiple comparison test where only <bold>EU1794-2</bold> <italic>vs</italic> control was compared for both peak and steady state conditions after a significant repeat measures ANOVA (F(3,3) = 7.66 for pre-applied glycine and F(3,7) = 12.4 for pre-applied glutamate). (<bold>D</bold>) Representative whole-cell current recordings of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs exemplifying the <bold>EU1794-27</bold> dependence on glutamate binding. The cell was exposed continuously to 30 µM glycine with/without 3 µM <bold>EU1794-27,</bold> and the solution was rapidly changed to one additionally containing 100 µM glutamate. The <italic>right panel</italic> is an expanded view of the activation kinetics of the responses and the onset of modulation. (<bold>E</bold>) Quantification of the modulation of the immediate peak and steady state response (shown as a percentage <bold>EU1794-27</bold>/control for each phase) from agonist-dependence experiments for <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (3 µM, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref> and S4A). * signifies p&lt;0.05 from the <italic>post hoc</italic> Bonferroni's multiple comparison test (F(3,3) = 17.8 for pre-applied glycine and F(3,2) = 13.5 for pre-applied glutamate).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig5-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.016</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><bold>EU1794</bold> modulators are dependent on co-agonist binding.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative whole-cell current recordings of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs exemplifying the <bold>EU1794-27</bold> modulation in the presence of contaminant levels of glycine. The <italic>left panel</italic> shows the response to glutamate in the absence of 3 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> but with a low, unknown level of glycine. Note the initial response to just glutamate, which fades with time to a small constitutive current. When 3 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> is applied in the presence of only glutamate, there is a slowly rising response as <bold>EU1794-27</bold> binds and increases glycine potency, allowing the receptor to re-equilibrate with the contaminant level of glycine. The cell was then rapidly stepped to a solution containing 30 µM glycine (in addition to the previous ligands). The <italic>right panel</italic> shows an expanded view (grey box in the <italic>left panel</italic>) of the rise of the receptor activation and the rapid kinetics of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> action once the receptor is fully activated. Note the difference in modulation time course prior to full activation and during full activation. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative whole-cell current recordings of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs exemplifying <bold>EU1794-2</bold> modulation that is similar to the trace shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative whole-cell current recordings of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs exemplifying the <bold>EU1794-27</bold> modulation dependence on the closed GluN1 ABD. The left current response shows the steady state response to 3 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold>. The right current response is shown for the same cell to 100 µM glutamate plus 100 µM 7-CKA either with or without 3 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> followed by a rapid change to a solution lacking 7-CKA and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> with 30 µM glycine. Similar results were observed in 3 cells. (<bold>D</bold>) Representative whole-cell current recordings of GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs exemplifying the <bold>EU1794-27</bold> modulation dependence on the closed GluN2 ABD. The <italic>left trace</italic> shows the exposure of GluN1/GluN2D to 100 µM glutamate, 100 µM APV, and either with or without 3 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> followed by a rapid change to a solution lacking APV and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> but containing 30 µM glycine. The <italic>right trace</italic> generated from the same cell shows the response if both solutions contained <bold>EU1794-27</bold>. Similar results were observed in 2 cells.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig5-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group><p>We repeated these use-dependent experiments with <bold>EU1794-27</bold>, which yielded a similar result, although a slightly different experimental design was required for consistent responses. The pre-application of glycine with <bold>EU1794-27</bold> produced a similar level of immediate activation following glutamate application (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D,E</xref>). This was then followed by the complex actions observed when <bold>EU1794-27</bold> was applied to steady-state responses of NMDARs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>, <italic>right panel</italic>). Using the same protocol to pre-apply glutamate became problematic for some cells due the degree to which <bold>EU1794-27</bold> enhances agonist potency, a feature exemplified by the prolongation of deactivation. This action of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> was able to render nanomolar contaminate levels of glycine (when present) more active, which necessitated a different experimental design (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1A</xref>). When <bold>EU1794-2</bold> was used in this experimental paradigm, inhibition of the contaminate level of activity was observed upon modulator application (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Nevertheless, we still observed a similar result with pre-application of glycine and <bold>EU1794-27</bold>, with the instantaneous response reaching the control level, followed by a slow relaxation to a new potentiated level that reflected the time course for association of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> after binding of both glutamate and glycine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>). This result illustrates a requirement for glycine to be bound to the receptor for high-affinity binding of <bold>EU1794-27</bold>. To circumvent any ambiguity associated with glycine contamination, we utilized another experimental design described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Vyklicky et al. (2015)</xref>. Glutamate was pre-applied with 7-CKA (100 µM) to antagonize the glycine site, blocking any occupancy by contaminant glycine. The receptor was activated by switching to a solution that lacked 7-CKA and contained glycine plus glutamate (with or without modulator, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1C</xref>). To test the ability of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> to bind to the receptor with the GluN1 ABD bound to antagonist, <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (3 µM) was added to the solution containing 7-CKA. Upon the switch from the 7-CKA/<bold>EU1794-27</bold> solution containing glutamate to a solution just containing glutamate and glycine, no detectable change in the response rise time or peak amplitude was observed. If <bold>EU1794-27</bold> bound during the 7-CKA phase prior to agonist binding, we would have expected an increased instantaneous peak current upon switching to glutamate plus glycine given that the dissociation of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> is slower than 7-CKA (compare the steady state response and the 7-CKA response in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1C</xref>). Additionally, comparable experiments were performed with 100 µM APV with similar results, as APV stabilizes the GluN2 agonist binding domain (ABD) open-cleft conformation, and thereby prevents the pre-binding of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1D</xref>). When <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (3 µM) was included in all solutions, potentiation was observed but APV unbinding was a required prior to modulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1D</xref>). Together these data suggest that the <bold>EU1794</bold> series is capable of high affinity binding only when glutamate and glycine are bound to the receptor.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Evaluation of interactions with known modulatory sites</title><p>To identify the molecular determinants of action for the <bold>EU1794</bold> series, we evaluated the ability of GluN2 ATD deletion, GluN1 ATD splice variants, and co-application of known modulators to alter the effects of the <bold>EU1794</bold> modulators. The ATD harbors the binding site for the GluN2B-selective negative allosteric modulator ifenprodil. Deletion of the ATD from GluN2A, GluN2B, or GluN2C had no effect on the actions of the PAM <bold>EU1794-27</bold>; deletion of the ATD from GluN2D reduced but did not eliminate potentiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1A</xref>). Similarly, inclusion of 21 residues in the ATD encoded by alternatively spliced GluN1 exon5 only slightly altered the extent of potentiation of <bold>EU1794-27</bold>, but was without effect on EC<sub>50</sub> for potentiation of GluN2B- and GluN2D-containing NMDARs activated by saturating agonist (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1B</xref>). We previously described a similar result for the negative allosteric modulator <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Katzman et al., 2015</xref>). These data are consistent with minimal involvement of the GluN1 or GluN2 ATD in the actions of <bold>EU1794</bold> modulators.</p><p>We next screened for interaction with known modulators to focus our search for the molecular determinants of <bold>EU1794</bold> series modulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Mullasseril et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Acker et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Hansen and Traynelis, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Hansen et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Khatri et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Ogden et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hackos et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Tajima et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Yi et al., 2016</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2A</xref>). In these experiments, a known positive or negative modulator was co-applied with either <bold>EU1794-2</bold> or <bold>EU1794-27</bold>, with each pair always containing one PAM and one NAM. If there is no interaction between paired modulators, their combined activity should be predicted by multiplying the extent of their independent actions. Co-application of the modulator pairs ifenprodil/<bold>EU1794-27</bold>, <bold>EU1794-2</bold>/CIQ and <bold>EU1794-2</bold>/PYD-106 produced levels of modulation that largely could be predicted from their independent actions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2B</xref>, <italic>top row</italic>). Modest differences from predictions were observed with modulators that bind to the ABD interface, TCN-201/<bold>EU1794-27</bold>, <bold>EU1794-2</bold>/GNE-6901 and <bold>EU1794-2</bold>/GNE-0723 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2B</xref>, <italic>bottom left</italic>). Co-application of the GluN2C/GluN2D-selective negative allosteric modulators QNZ46 and DQP-1105 paired with <bold>EU1794-27</bold> resulted in the greatest divergences from predictions, raising the possibility that these modulators have partially overlapping binding sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2B</xref>, <italic>bottom right</italic>) or similar downstream mechanisms.</p><p>We also examined the ability of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> to modulate NMDARs harboring mutations within the structural determinants for other known allosteric modulators. Mutations in GluN1 (I519A, R755A) and GluN2A (L780A, G786A) that block TCN-201 inhibition were evaluated for effects on <bold>EU1794</bold> series of modulators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Hansen et al., 2012</xref>). NMDARs that contained GluN1/GluN2A(L780A), GluN1/GluN2A(G786A), GluN1(R755A)/GluN2D, GluN1(I519A)/GluN2D were equally sensitive as wild type receptors to inhibition by <bold>EU1794-2</bold> or potentiation by <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3A</xref>). GluN1/GluN2A(E530A), GluN1/GluN2A(V783W), GluN1(Y535W)/GluN2A, GluN1(Y535V)/GluN2D and GluN1(Y535W)/GluN2D, which reduce the actions of GNE-6901 and GNE-0723 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hackos et al., 2016</xref>), produced no significant effects on inhibition by <bold>EU1794-2</bold> or potentiation by <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3B</xref>). Inhibition by EU1794-2 of GluN1/GluN2C(K470G) and GluN1/GluN2C(S472T), which block PYD-106 potentiation of GluN1/GluN2C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Khatri et al., 2014</xref>), was similar to wild type NMDARs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3C</xref>). Interestingly, inhibition by <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and potentiation by <bold>EU1794-27</bold> was not significantly changed by GluN1/GluN2D(Q701Y) and GluN1/GluN2D(L705F), mutations that appear to confer subunit selectivity for GluN2C/D over GluN2A/B for QNZ-46 and DQP-1105 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3D</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Acker et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Hansen and Traynelis, 2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Mutagenesis suggests shared structural determinants of action for PAMs and NAMs</title><p>The result obtained with the QNZ-46/DQP-1105 interaction test suggested that the two residues we evaluated for QNZ-46 and DQP-1105 insufficiently probed the structural determinants of action for these compounds. We therefore examined a GluA2 AMPA receptor structure bound to CP-465,022, which shares a core scaffold with QNZ modulators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Yelshanskaya et al., 2016</xref>). Residues identified as being important for CP-465,022 binding in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Yelshanskaya et al., 2016</xref> were aligned to the GluN1 and GluN2D subunits to map this modulatory site onto the NMDAR subunits, in addition to critical residues for GNE-9278 in this same region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). This broader range of residues were located on the pre-M1, M3, and pre-M4 regions of both GluN1 and GluN2D, which have previously been suggested to cooperate to control gating (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Ogden and Traynelis, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Alsaloum et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Chen et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Ogden et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Yelshanskaya et al., 2017</xref>). These residues were suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Yelshanskaya et al., 2016</xref> to constitute a binding site in homomeric GluA2 AMPARs. However, mapping the homologous residues onto NMDAR structures yields two pockets given the multimeric subunit architecture, one of which consists of the residues of GluN1 and the other of residues of GluN2. Certain residues of M3, depending on their position on the helix, could point towards either pocket, rendering the two pockets to be lined by a mixture of GluN1 and GluN2 residues. 15 GluN1 and 15 GluN2D residues in these two regions that probed these pockets were identified and mutated to allow a test of the contribution of each residue to <bold>EU1794-2</bold> inhibition and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiation. Inhibition by <bold>EU1794-2</bold> was significantly altered by substitutions at six residues in GluN1 and 2 GluN2D residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>), which were found on pre-M1 and M3 regions of both GluN1 and GluN2D. Potentiation by <bold>EU1794-27</bold> was more labile, being altered in mutations at 9 GluN1 residues and 6 GluN2D residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>). Residues that perturbed the actions of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> were spread across all regions tested except for the GluN2D pre-M1. Modulation was observed to be altered in three different ways by the mutations studied here: activity could be reduced, increased, or inverted.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.017</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Distinct and overlapping pattern of residues contribute to the actions of <bold>EU1794</bold> modulators with opposing effects.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Ribbon representation (<italic>left</italic>) of a GluN1/GluN2D model based on published crystal structures of GluN1/GluN2B and GluA2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Karakas and Furukawa, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lee et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Yelshanskaya et al., 2016</xref>). The GluN1 subunits are grey and the GluN2D are purple; surface shell indicate residues of interest in GluN1 and GluN2D, including residues that are homologous to those identified in recent studies investigating transmembrane domain interacting modulators of NMDAR and AMPAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Yelshanskaya et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). These GluN1 and GluN2D residues were changed to alanine (or tyrosine in two cases, as previously reported) and tested for effects on the NMDAR sensitivity to <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold>. Top down (<italic>right top</italic>) and side (<italic>right bottom</italic>) view of the model TMD and linker segments highlight two potential pockets with GluN1 and GluN2 M3 helices in the background. One pocket is primarily associated with GluN1 and the other GluN2. (<bold>B</bold>) The responses (mean ±99% CI) in <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (5 µM, <italic>left</italic>) and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (10 µM, <italic>right</italic>) are shown as a % of the mutant receptor response to 100 µM glutamate and 30 µM glycine in the absence of the test compound. The wild type mean response is shown by the dashed line, surrounding dotted lines, which indicate the 99% confidence interval. Residues with non-overlapping confidence intervals with the wild type are colored with magenta indicating apparent loss of activity, yellow indicating augmented activity, and green indicating robust inverted modulation. Data for the mutations shown represent 4–18 oocytes from at least two independent experiments and the wild type response shown represent 83 oocytes for <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and 76 oocytes for <bold>EU1794-27,</bold> recorded each experimental day to ensure consistency. We were not able to test all mutant receptors due to low expression for some (NT, not tested). (<bold>C</bold>) The residues (shown by the space-filling shell) identified in (<bold>B</bold>) that altered the effects of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<italic>left</italic>) and/or <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<italic>right</italic>) were mapped onto the model with colors as described in (<bold>B</bold>). Views are the same as (<bold>A</bold>), with the all residues probed shown as grey transparent shell representation.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig6-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.018</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><bold>EU1794</bold> series effects are not altered by ATD perturbations.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) 10 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiates GluN2-ΔATD NMDARs (n = 4–12). (<bold>B</bold>) Concentration-response curves for <bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiation of GluN2B and GluN2D with GluN1-1a and GluN1-1b (with and without exon5, respectively, n = 6–10). * signifies p&lt;0.05 as determined by an unpaired t-test.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig6-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig6s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.019</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Compound competition screen of the <bold>EU1794</bold> series with NMDAR modulators highlights potential interactions with the ABD and the TMD.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Overlaid surface and ribbon representations of the GluN1/GluN2D model (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>) highlighting proposed ligand binding sites for ifenprodil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Karakas et al., 2011</xref>), PYD-106 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Khatri et al., 2014</xref>), CIQ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Ogden and Traynelis, 2013</xref>), GNE-6901 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hackos et al., 2016</xref>), TCN-201 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Yi et al., 2016</xref>), DQP-1105 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Acker et al., 2011</xref>), and QNZ-46 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Hansen and Traynelis, 2011</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) Single concentration competition experiments are summarized for ifenprodil (0.3 µM, on GluN1/GluN2B, n = 10), CIQ (20 µM, GluN1/GluN2D, n = 15), PYD-106 (100 µM, GluN1/GluN2C, n = 14), TCN-201 (1 µM, 1 µM glycine, GluN1/GluN2A, n = 11), GNE-6901 (30 µM, GluN1/GluN2A, n = 6), GNE-0723 (30 µM, GluN1/GluN2A, n = 6), DQP-1105 (10 µM, GluN1/GluN2D, n = 10), and QNZ-46 (5 µM, GluN1/GluN2D, n = 8) co-administered with maximally effective glutamate and glycine plus either <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (3 µM) or <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (20 µM). The individual average effects of the pairs of modulators along with the co-applied effect are plotted, and the predicted mean net effect of the modulators is displayed as a dashed line (SEM, dotted lines). * signifies p&lt;0.05 as determined by a paired t-test comparing co-applied modulators and predicted net effect of modulator actions. All pairs were tested during two independent experiments sessions. The predicted net effect was calculated by Effect<sub>Predicted-Net</sub> = (Response<sub>DRUG,A</sub> / Response<sub>CONTROL,A</sub>) * (Response<sub>DRUG,B</sub> / Response<sub>CONTROL,B</sub>) and displayed as %.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig6-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig6s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.020</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Residues in known modulator binding sites do not perturb actions of the <bold>EU1794</bold> series.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Inhibition by 5 µM <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<italic>left</italic> and <italic>middle</italic>) and potentiation by 10 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<italic>right</italic>) on NMDARs possessing mutations known to alter the activity of TCN-201 as compared to wild type GluN1/GluN2A (<italic>left</italic>) and GluN1/GluN2D (<italic>middle</italic> and <italic>right</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Hansen et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Yi et al., 2016</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) Inhibition by 5 µM <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<italic>left</italic> and <italic>middle</italic>) and potentiation by 10 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<italic>right</italic>) on NMDARs possessing mutations that alter the activity of GNE-6901 and GNE-0723 as compared to wild type GluN1/GluN2A (<italic>left</italic>) and GluN1/GluN2D (<italic>middle</italic> and <italic>right</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hackos et al., 2016</xref>). (<bold>C</bold>) Inhibition by 5 µM <bold>EU1794-2</bold> on NMDARs possessing mutations that alter the activity of PYD-106 as compared to wild type GluN1/GluN2C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Khatri et al., 2014</xref>). (<bold>D</bold>) Inhibition by 5 µM <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<italic>left</italic>) and potentiation by 10 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<italic>right</italic>) on NMDARs possessing mutations that alter the activity of DQP-1105 and QNZ-46 as compared to wild type GluN1/GluN2D (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Acker et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Hansen and Traynelis, 2011</xref>). Wild type GluN1/GluN2D data are same as in (<bold>A</bold>). Data represent recordings from 3 to 9 oocytes. * denotes significance as determined by a one-way ANOVA with Dunnett’s multiple comparison test (compared to control).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig6-figsupp3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig6s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.021</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Mutated residues that impact <bold>EU1794</bold> actions have lower open probability.</title><p>(<bold>A–B</bold>) Calculated open probability (Po) of mutations at residues that were important determinants of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> action was measured by MTSEA modification of either GluN2-A651C (A7C, (<bold>A</bold>) or GluN1-A652C (A7C, (<bold>B</bold>). MTSEA (0.2 mM) effect on steady state responses to saturating concentration of glutamate and glycine was determined after 3 min of application, and a correction factor was used to account for changes in channel conductance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Yuan et al., 2005</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig6-figsupp4-v1"/></fig></fig-group><p>The distributions of residues that altered modulation by <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> shows clear overlap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). Inhibition by <bold>EU1794-2</bold> was altered primarily by mutations in GluN1, whereas potentiation by <bold>EU1794-27</bold> was perturbed by residues both in GluN1 and in the M3 helix of GluN2D. Interestingly, the mutations that invert activity of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> were distinct, but in some cases were in close proximity. For example, <bold>EU1794-2</bold> was inverted by GluN1-F654A, whereas mutation of the adjacent residue GluN1-L655A/Y inverted the modulatory action of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). <bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiation was also converted to inhibition by four mutations at residues residing on the 3 areas of GluN1 that were investigated (pre-M1, M1, M3) and also on the M3 GluN2D helix, which were in close proximity to each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). <bold>EU1794-27</bold> actions on GluN1-L655A/Y and GluN2D-M678Y, which are homologous residues immediately downstream of the SYTANLAAF motif, resulted in opposite effects (GluN1-L655A/Y converts <bold>EU1794-27</bold> to an inhibitor and GluN2D-M678Y increases the potentiation of <bold>EU1794-27</bold>). We interpret these results to suggest that the activity of both PAMs and NAMs of the <bold>EU1794</bold> series is dependent on multiple residues in the GluN1 subunit, some of which are overlapping. Furthermore, potentiation by <bold>EU1794-27</bold> is dependent on a wider range of GluN1 and GluN2 residues. One possible way to account for this would be if both modulators bound near the GluN1 pre-M1 helix, with potentiator actions dependent on the nearby GluN2 M3 residues associated with the GluN1 pocket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A,C</xref>).</p><p>To assess whether mutated residues impacted <bold>EU1794</bold> series modulation through altering receptor open probability, we estimated mutant open probability using MTSEA modification of an introduced cysteine residue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Jones et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Yuan et al., 2005</xref>). The open probability of GluN2D-containing receptors is very low and may not allow for precise determination of the effects of mutations, thus we used GluN2B-containing receptors for comparison. GluN1 mutations were expressed with a GluN2B A7C construct (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s4">Figure 6—figure supplement 4</xref> legend) and GluN2 mutations were expressed with a GluN1 A7C construct. Several residues were assayed that resulted in reversed, enhanced, or blocked modulator activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s4">Figure 6—figure supplement 4A</xref>). GluN1-P557A, which blocked activity of both <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold>, had an increased open probability as compared to wild type. GluN1-F654A, which converted <bold>EU1794-2</bold> into a potentiator and enhanced <bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiation, had a similar open probability as compared to wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s4">Figure 6—figure supplement 4A</xref>). Interestingly, mutation of the homologous GluN2 residue (GluN2-F653A), which reduced <bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiation, also lowered open probability as compared to wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s4">Figure 6—figure supplement 4B</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s4">Figure 6—figure supplement 4</xref> shows that GluN1-L665A and GluN1-N803A, which both converted <bold>EU1794-27</bold> into an inhibitor, had significantly lower open probabilities as compared to wild type NMDARs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s4">Figure 6—figure supplement 4A</xref>). These data suggest that altered <bold>EU1794</bold> modulator action by mutated residues is not directly dependent on alterations in open probability.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>PAMs and NAMs exert their opposing effects via a shared binding site on NMDARs</title><p>Given the similarity in chemical structure between positive and negative modulators in this series, we hypothesized that they might have overlapping binding sites. In order to conduct a detailed functional analysis of competition between allosteric modulators, we first used modeling to examine a receptor’s functional response to co-application of positive and negative modulators acting at the same or different sites. We evaluated two models of modulator binding built into a scheme first proposed by (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lester and Jahr, 1992</xref>). Model 1 describes receptors with a single binding site that can accommodate either PAM or NAM, but not both. Model 2 describes a receptor to which both modulators can bind at the same time in different sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>). We evaluated hypothetical responses from these models (see Materials and methods, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1A–C</xref>). Responses to maximally effective concentrations of agonist were simulated at various concentrations of the positive and negative modulators. When the modulators compete for the same binding site, they act similarly to stated theory about competitive antagonists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Arunlakshana and Schild, 1959</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Christopoulos and Kenakin, 2002</xref>), with the PAM causing a rightward shift of the NAM IC<sub>50</sub> and generating a linear relationship in dose ratio analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1D,E</xref>, <italic>Model 1</italic>). By contrast, there is no apparent EC<sub>50</sub> shift when the two modulators are capable of binding simultaneously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1D,E</xref>, <italic>Model 2</italic>). Additional simulations showed the reciprocal effect of NAM on PAM EC<sub>50</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1F,G</xref>). We subsequently performed competition experiments to test the hypothesis that this series of PAMs and NAMs compete for a mutually exclusive modulatory pocket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7D</xref>). We observed that fixed concentrations of the PAM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> caused parallel shifts in the concentration-response curve of the NAM <bold>EU1794-2</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7E</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6">Table 6</xref>). A similar phenomenon was shown for the reverse, as fixed concentrations of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> caused parallel shifts in the <bold>EU1794-27</bold> concentration-response curves (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table6">Table 6</xref>). These results closely match <italic>Model 1</italic>, where PAMs and NAMs bind in a mutually exclusive fashion. This suggests that the opposing modulators in the <bold>EU1794</bold> series share overlapping binding sites instead of the coincidence that the subtle chemical differences confer unique binding sites.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.022</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title><bold>EU1794</bold> PAMs and NAMs act in a competitive manner that matches receptor models with mutually exclusive modulator binding.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Cartoon models show two potential modulator binding schemes. Model 1 possesses mutually exclusive modulator binding whereas Model 2 can bind either or both modulators. Ligands are denoted by [N] (NAM) and [P] (PAM). (<bold>B,C</bold>) Dose-ratio plots are shown for simulated concentration-response curves of the NAM in various concentration of the PAM for <italic>Model 1</italic> (<bold>B</bold>) and <italic>Model 2</italic> (<bold>C</bold>). IC<sub>50</sub>’ is the observed NAM IC<sub>50</sub> in the presence of a fixed concentration PAM. (<bold>D</bold>) A representative TEVC recording (fixed 3 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> and 0.3, 1, 3, 10, 30 µM <bold>EU1794-2</bold>) is shown for GluN1/GluN2D NMDARs (top). (<bold>E</bold>) The mean steady state responses in (<bold>D</bold>) were fitted with the Hill equation. Concentration-response data in the absence of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> are included for comparison from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>. (<bold>F</bold>) Dose-ratio analysis of experimental data illustrates the shift in the IC<sub>50</sub> of the NAM as a function of PAM concentration. Data are from at least six oocytes evaluated from two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig7-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.023</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><bold>EU1794</bold> PAMs and NAMs act in a competitive manner that suggests mutually exclusive modulator binding.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Cartoon and Markov models of potential modulator binding schemes. <italic>Model 1</italic> possesses mutually exclusive modulator binding whereas <italic>Model 2</italic> can bind either or both modulators. Ligand-dependent transitions are denoted by [A] (agonist), [N] (NAM), [P] (PAM). (<bold>B</bold>) Simulated concentration-response curves of hypothetical modulator actions on an agonist-saturated response of <italic>Model 1</italic> and <italic>2</italic> (NAM EC<sub>50</sub>0.89 µM, PAM EC<sub>50</sub>0.85 µM). (<bold>C</bold>) Simulation of co-administered hypothetical modulators for <italic>Model 1</italic> (left) and <italic>Model 2</italic> (right) to an agonist-saturated response. Responses to NAM concentrations (0.03, 0.1, 0.3, 1, 3, 10, 30, 100 µM) were simulated in the presence of fixed concentrations of PAM (0, 0.3, 1, 3, 10, 30 µM). (<bold>D</bold>) Simulated concentration-response data fit with the Hill equation for <italic>Model 1</italic> (left) and <italic>Model 2</italic> (right). (<bold>F</bold>) Simulated responses for co-application of multiple modulators using <italic>Model 1</italic> and <italic>Model 2</italic> (<italic>left</italic> and <italic>right</italic>, respectively). The current response to saturating agonist concentration was simulated in the presence of eight PAM concentration responses (0.03, 0.1, 0.3, 1, 3, 10, 30, 100 µM) and fixed concentrations of NAM (0, 0.3, 1, 3, 10, 30 µM). (<bold>G</bold>) The steady-state responses from each condition was plotted as a function of concentration and fit with the Hill equation. Rates used are (concentration dependent rates in µM s<sup>−1</sup>) b<sup>+</sup>=10.4 [A]*s<sup>−1</sup>, b<sup>-</sup>=73 s<sup>−1</sup>, k<sup>+</sup>=501.6 s<sup>−1</sup>, k<sup>-</sup>=790 s<sup>−1</sup>, n<sup>+</sup>=0.786 [N]*s<sup>−1</sup>, n<sup>-</sup>=0.393 s<sup>−1</sup>, p<sup>+</sup>=0.786 [P]*s<sup>−1</sup>, p<sup>-</sup>=0.786 s<sup>−1</sup>, k<sub>n</sub><sup>+</sup>=25.08 s<sup>−1</sup>, k<sub>n</sub><sup>-</sup>=790 s<sup>−1</sup>, k<sub>p</sub><sup>+</sup>=1003.2 s<sup>−1</sup>, k<sub>p</sub><sup>-</sup>=790 s<sup>−1</sup>, k<sub>pn</sub><sup>+</sup>=50.16 s<sup>−1</sup>, k<sub>pn</sub><sup>-</sup>=790 s<sup>−1</sup>.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig7-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group><table-wrap id="table6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.024</object-id><label>Table 6.</label><caption><title>The response to co-application of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> suggest a common binding site.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="4">EU1794-2 IC<sub>50</sub> (µM) [conf. int.]*</th><th colspan="3">EU1794-27 EC<sub>50</sub> (µM) [conf. int.]*</th></tr><tr><th/><th>+EU1794-27 <break/>0 µM</th><th>+EU1794-27 <break/>3 µM</th><th>+EU1794-27 <break/>10 µM</th><th>+EU1794-27 <break/>20 µM</th><th>+EU1794-2 <break/>0 µM</th><th>+EU1794-2 <break/>1 µM</th><th>+EU1794-2 <break/>3 µM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>GluN2A</bold></td><td>0.60<sup>†</sup> <break/>[0.44, 0.82]</td><td>2.5<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[1.9, 3.1]</td><td>3.6<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[2.4, 4.8]</td><td>8.0<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[1.3, 15]</td><td>-<sup>§</sup></td><td>-<sup>§</sup></td><td>-<sup>§</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2B</bold></td><td>1.2<sup>†</sup> <break/>[0.8, 1.9]</td><td>NR</td><td>3.5<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[2.1, 4.9]</td><td>12 <break/>[~, 26]</td><td>1.4<sup>†</sup> <break/>[1.2, 1.7]</td><td>6.0<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[4.6, 7.4]</td><td>8.4 <break/>[~, 18]</td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2C</bold></td><td>0.21<sup>†</sup> <break/>[0.18, 0.25]</td><td>1.2<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[0.91, 1.4]</td><td>2.4<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[1.8, 3.0]</td><td>6.0<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[4.1, 7.8]</td><td>2.8<sup>†</sup> <break/>[2.5, 3.2]</td><td>7.3<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[5.9, 8.8]</td><td>7.3 <break/>[2.1, 11.74]</td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2D</bold></td><td>0.20<sup>†</sup> <break/>[0.17, 0.25]</td><td>1.4<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[1.2, 1.6]</td><td>2.7<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[2.3, 3.2]</td><td>7.3<sup>‡*</sup> <break/>[4.6, 9.9]</td><td>2.4<sup>†</sup> <break/>[1.8, 3.3]</td><td>7.5<sup>‡</sup> <break/>[5.6, 9.3]</td><td>7.8 <break/>[1.1, 14]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>A five point concentration response curve was obtained for modulator effects on responses to maximally effective concentrations of glutamate and glycine (100/30 µM) for <bold>EU1794-2</bold> co-administered with increasing concentrations of <bold>EU1794-27</bold>, and for <bold>EU1794-27</bold> in increasing concentrations of <bold>EU1794-2</bold>.</p><p>*IC<sub>50</sub> and EC<sub>50</sub> values were obtained by least-squares fitting of data by the Hill equation. IC<sub>50</sub> and EC<sub>50</sub> values are given as the mean with the 95% confidence interval determined from log(IC<sub>50</sub>) or log(EC<sub>50</sub>). Data are from at least six oocytes evaluated from two independent experiments for the <bold>EU1794-2</bold> IC<sub>50</sub> determinations and from at least three oocytes evaluated from one experiment for the <bold>EU1794-27</bold> EC<sub>50</sub> determinations.</p></fn><fn><p>NR, Given the low potency for modulators at GluN2B, the <bold>EU1794-2</bold> concentration-response curve with 3 µM <bold>EU1794-27</bold> determination was not recorded.</p><p><sup>†</sup> Data from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref> is included here for clarity.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>‡</sup>indicates non-overlapping 95% confidence interval with the <bold>EU1794-2</bold> IC<sub>50</sub> without <bold>EU1794-27</bold> or <bold>EU1794-27</bold> EC<sub>50</sub> without <bold>EU1794-2</bold>.</p><p><sup>§</sup><bold>EU1794-27</bold> does not potentiate GluN2A responses to maximally effective concentrations of glutamate and glycine.</p></fn><fn><p>~indicates that the confidence interval reached the theoretical limit (EC<sub>50</sub> = 0).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> were separated to determine whether the racemic activity reflected the actions of only one enantiomer (see Supplemental methods). (-)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiated NMDAR responses similarly to the racemic mixture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table7">Table 7</xref>). By contrast, (+)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold> exhibited only weak potentiation of GluN1/GluN2C and GluN1/GluN2D, which may be due to the purity achieved via chiral separation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table7">Table 7</xref>). We previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Katzman et al., 2015</xref>) that purified enantiomers were likely to racemize in aqueous solutions, which should proceed by a first-order reaction dependent on multiple factors such as ionic strength, pH, buffer, etc. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Smith et al., 1978</xref>). Thus, to quantitatively determine if racemization would impact our experiments using the enantiomers, we performed a functional assessment of this property in our standard experimental solution. We observed racemization of the enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> with a half-life of 197 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table7">Table 7</xref>). Both enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> inhibited NMDAR responses, but with different potencies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary File 2</xref>). A similar rate of racemization was observed for the enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> (half-life of 196 min, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1D</xref>). All enantiomer studies, other than the racemization time-course, were performed rapidly to minimize any racemization, being completed in less than 80 min after making the aqueous solution of modulator. Similar to results in oocytes, when the enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> were applied to steady-state GluN1/GluN2D responses in HEK cells, (-)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold> potentiated responses whereas (+)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold> had a slight inhibitory effect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A</xref>). In additional, 10 µM of both enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> had similar inhibitory actions on GluN1/GluN2D responses to maximally effective concentrations of glutamate and glycine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8B</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig8" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.025</object-id><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>The enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> have different action.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative modulation of GluN1/GluN2D responses by the enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (both 10 µM, 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine). Similar results were observed in at least 3 cells to fresh modulator solution made less than one hour before experiment conclusion. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative modulation of GluN1/GluN2D responses by the enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> (both 10 µM, 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine). Similar results were observed in at least 3 cells to fresh modulator solution made less than one hour before experiment conclusion. (<bold>C</bold>) Single concentration competition experiments illustrating an interaction between both enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> (+and -) and the positive modulating enantiomer of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (-) at GluN1/GluN2D. The individual average effects of the pairs of modulators along with the co-applied effect are plotted, and the predicted mean net effect of the modulators is displayed as a dashed line (SEM, dotted lines, n = 10 from two independent experiments). * signifies p&lt;0.05 as determined by a paired t-test comparing co-applied modulators and predicted net effect of modulator actions.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig8-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig8s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.026</object-id><label>Figure 8—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>The concentration response and stability of the enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> and <bold>EU1794-4</bold>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The concentration-response relationships illustrate the selective action of the enantiomer (-)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold>. Responses were activated with 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine and modulated with 0.3, 1, 3, 10, and 30 µM of each enantiomer. (<bold>B</bold>) The time course is shown for <bold>EU1794-27</bold> enantiomer racemization in working solutions. Individual paired differences in the % modulation of the enantiomers are plotted versus time. As previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Katzman et al., 2015</xref>), this series appears prone to racemization in aqueous solution, which may account for differences in activity due to the time the enantiomers spend in the working solution. The difference in the extent of modulation of the enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> was reduced slowly over time, producing modest racemization over the time frame of enantiomer experiments. (<bold>C</bold>) The concentration-response relationships illustrate the selective action of one enantiomer of <bold>EU1794-4</bold>. Responses were activated with 100/30 µM glutamate/glycine and modulated with 0.1, 0.3, 1, 3, 10, and 30 µM of each enantiomer. Data are from 4 to 7 oocytes from at least two independent experiments. (<bold>D</bold>) The time course of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> enantiomer racemization in working solutions is shown; all data are from one racemization experiment (1–2 recordings at each time point). The difference in the extent of modulation of the enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> was reduced slowly over time.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig8-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group><table-wrap id="table7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.027</object-id><label>Table 7.</label><caption><title>Enantiomeric preference of <bold>EU1794-27</bold>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="4">EC<sub>50</sub> (µM) [conf. int.]* <break/>Maximal Modulation Extent (% of control)</th></tr><tr><th>Compound</th><th>EU1794-27</th><th>(-)-EU1794-27</th><th>(+)-EU1794-27</th><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>GluN2A</bold></td><td>7.4 [5.3, 10]<sup>†</sup> <break/>52 ± 7%</td><td>5.6 [2.7, 12] <break/>67 ± 5%</td><td>-</td><td>‡</td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2B</bold></td><td>1.4 [1.2, 1.7]<sup>†</sup> <break/>130 ± 3%</td><td>2.8 [2.0, 3.8] <break/>170 ± 10%</td><td>-</td><td>‡</td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2C</bold></td><td>2.8 [2.5, 3.2]<sup>†</sup> <break/>230 ± 10%</td><td>5.1 [4.1, 6.4] <break/>260 ± 24%</td><td>7.1 [3.6, 14] <break/>160 ± 6.2%</td><td>‡</td></tr><tr><td><bold>GluN2D</bold></td><td>2.4 [1.8, 3.3]<sup>†</sup> <break/>250 ± 8%</td><td>8.2 [6.7, 9.9] <break/>340 ± 21%</td><td>7.4 [3.7, 15] <break/>130 ± 4.7%</td><td>‡</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*EC<sub>50</sub> values were obtained by least-squares fitting of data from individual experiments by the Hill equation. EC<sub>50</sub> values are given as the mean with the 95% confidence interval determined from log(EC<sub>50</sub>); the maximal degree of modulation is given as mean ±SEM. Data are from 4 to 7 oocytes from at least two independent experiments. Data were not fitted (shown as -) if the response recorded at 30 µM of test compound did not differ by more than 15% from control.</p><p><sup>†</sup>Data from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref> is included here for clarity.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>‡</sup>indicates significant unpaired t-test between the percent modulation between 30 µM (-)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold> and (+)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To assess whether both enantiomers bound to similar or distinct sites on the NMDAR, we performed single concentration competition experiments. Co-application of each enantiomer of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> with the (-)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold> resulted in a degree of modulation that was significantly different than that predicted for independent sites of action at both GluN1/GluN2A and GluN1/GluN2D (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8C</xref>). Interestingly, the competition by <bold>EU1794-4</bold> was not dependent on the direction of modulation by (-)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold>, which had a potentiating action at GluN1/GluN2D (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8C</xref>, <italic>top panels</italic>) and an inhibitory effect at GluN1/GluN2A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8C</xref>, <italic>bottom panels</italic>). Although there remain potential caveats, the evidence suggests that the co-application of (-)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold> with either enantiomer of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> displays mutual exclusivity in modulator binding.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study highlights how subtle chemical variations in a series of NMDAR allosteric modulators can result in fundamentally different actions on NMDAR responses to maximally effective concentrations of agonists. This series of small molecule allosteric modulators show a spectrum of effects ranging from strong negative modulation to robust positive modulation. In addition, there are features that are shared across this series, including agonist-dependence and the ability to enhance agonist potency. Thorough analysis of the actions of this series illustrates a potential way forward in designing new analogues to achieve a wide range of activities. Additionally, the novel features found in this class of modulators suggest potential new strategies for targeting distinct populations of NMDARs, such as extrasynaptic receptors that typically are not activated by high concentrations of glutamate or distinct patterns of stimulation.</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>The site and mechanism of action for the EU1794 series</title><p>In the evaluation of the kinetic properties of modulator action, we observed complex actions of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold>, which could arise from multiple binding sites, enantiomers of these compounds, or could reflect distinct modulator-dependent mechanistic actions from occupancy of a single binding site. The modulation by <bold>EU1794-4</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> is voltage independent, eliminating potential channel block within the ion channel pore by potential cationic species as a confounding site that contributes to the observed effects. Given that there is high homology between GluN1 and GluN2, especially in the ABD and the TMD, a reasonable hypothesis is that multiple binding sites exist for <bold>EU1794</bold> series modulators in homologous regions on GluN1 and GluN2 subunits. However, the mutagenesis data argue against this idea, given that the residues at which mutations perturbed the actions of <bold>EU1794-2</bold> and <bold>EU1794-27</bold> overlapped and clustered around the pre-M1, M3, and M4 of the GluN1 subunit. Whereas there were a few residues of the GluN2 M3 helix that influenced <bold>EU1794-27</bold> modulation, the structural NMDAR models suggest that these residues face the GluN1 M3 helix, and thus could interact with the pocket adjacent to the GluN1 pre-M1 helix. Additionally, it’s likely the M3 helixes of both GluN1 and GluN2, which are in close contact, act in concert with one another to control rapid pore opening or closing. If these residues identified by mutagenesis controlled conformational changes downstream of the <bold>EU1794</bold> binding site(s), it would limit potential binding site candidates to the interface between the GluN1 and the GluN2 ABDs, which would then have only two identical binding sites in diheteromeric NMDARs. Therefore there would be less potential for non-identical binding sites that contribute to the mixed actions that are observed for <bold>EU1794-27</bold> and <bold>EU1794-4</bold>. For these reasons, the idea that the positive and negative allosteric actions reflect modulator specific mechanisms from occupancy of a single site seems the most plausible interpretation.</p><p>Evaluation of the effects of enantiomers provides further insight into the binding site of the <bold>EU1794</bold> series. <bold>EU1794-27</bold> exhibits strong stereoselectivity, with the (-) enantiomer showing a typical potentiation time course and the (+) enantiomer producing inhibition. The enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> are both capable of producing inhibition but with the (-) enantiomer being more potent (3–10 fold) than the (+) enantiomer. Additionally, both enantiomers of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> appear to compete with <bold>EU1794-27</bold> for access to the binding site, suggesting that enantiomers may interact differently with the same binding site. An alternative explanation for lack of additivity of the effects of the two compounds could be that there are shared residues downstream of the PAM and NAM binding sites that mediate their effects; additional studies are required to evaluate this hypothesis. However, the idea that the enantiomers of the <bold>EU1794</bold> series act at the same site suggests their complex actions on NMDARs expressed in HEK is a mixture of receptors bound to one or the other enantiomer of racemic <bold>EU1794-27</bold> and <bold>EU1794-4</bold>. The available enantiomeric data further support the idea that positive and negative modulators within the <bold>EU1794</bold> series share a single or overlapping binding site.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>EU1794 series links positive and negative allosteric modulators that act at the TMD</title><p>An increasing number of NMDAR and AMPAR modulators have been identified with structural determinants of action that reside in transmembrane linker regions and extracellular portions of the transmembrane domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Mullasseril et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Acker et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Hansen and Traynelis, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Ogden and Traynelis, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Yelshanskaya et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Swanger et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). Other cell surface receptor families have bi-directional modulator pockets, including multiple GPCRs as well as the benzodiazepine binding site in GABA-A receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Barnard et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Rudolph and Knoflach, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Wootten et al., 2013</xref>). Among all ionotropic glutamate receptor modulators interacting with this region of the receptor, there are positive (CIQ, GNE-9278) and negative (DQP-1105, QNZ-46, CP-465,022, GYKI 52466) modulators with diverse scaffolds. However, the <bold>EU1794</bold> compounds represent the first bidirectional NMDAR modulator series with structural determinants of activity within this region, low micromolar potency and with clear rules to control modulation. The similarity in structure of positive and negative modulators illustrates how subtle differences in the ligand can interconvert functional actions between inhibition and potentiation. It is unclear precisely how the different sized ester alkyl chain substitutions of these analogs bring about opposing actions, further investigation of the structure activity relationship may elucidate these details. The ability to potentiate NMDAR seems to be unique to (-)-<bold>EU1794-27,</bold> which may have a specific interaction with the receptor achieved only by its stereoselective active pose in the binding pocket. Work with this series may lead to an understanding of the mechanistic link between the PAMs and NAMs that interact in this portion of the receptor.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Differential actions on synaptic and extrasynaptic receptors by submaximal EU1794 analogues</title><p>The <bold>EU1794</bold> series has a property of agonist-dependence, requiring both glutamate and glycine to be bound before the modulator binding site adopts a high potency orientation for members of the series. Relatedly, use-dependence is a property of open channel blockers (e.g. memantine, MK-801, ketamine, etc.) that inhibit the receptor through interactions within the ion permeation path, and thus rely on pore opening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Traynelis et al., 2010</xref>). Given that the <bold>EU1794</bold> series are allosteric modulators are not voltage-dependent, the mechanism of their agonist-dependence is unclear. Previously, the NAMs QNZ-46, DQP-1105, and NAB-14 have been reported to show varying degrees of glutamate- but not glycine-dependence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Acker et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Hansen and Traynelis, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Swanger et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, neurosteroid derivatives with NAM activity have also been shown to have glutamate- and glycine-dependence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Vyklicky et al., 2015</xref>), and the PAM GNE-9278 was reported to be glutamate-dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). Thus, the <bold>EU1794</bold> series is the first series of positive and negative modulators that has been shown to possess the property of being both glutamate- and glycine-dependent. Our working hypothesis is that the <bold>EU1794</bold> series of modulators requires conformational changes in both GluN1 and GluN2 subunits that reflect pre-gating or gating transitions, after which its affinity for its binding site is increased. However, we cannot rule out at this time the possibility that the pore must open to increase modulator binding. Resolving the specific mechanism of the <bold>EU1794</bold> may lead to a more complete understanding of the activation transitions NMDAR.</p><p>We believe that <bold>EU1794-4</bold> highlights a novel sub-class of NMDAR modulators that have the capability to selectively act at extrasynaptic NMDARs based on the combinations of its properties. Extrasynaptic NMDAR are hypothesized to respond to glutamate spillover or glial release of glutamate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Rusakov and Kullmann, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Haydon and Carmignoto, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Sahlender et al., 2014</xref>). The potential ability to preferentially act at these non-synaptic sites arises from three mechanistic features of the allosteric mechanism: (1) the submaximal inhibitory effects at saturating concentrations of modulator and agonist, (2) the agonist-dependent and slow association rate, which might limit activity at synaptic receptors, and (3) the ability to enhance NMDAR responses to low agonist concentrations. A similar property has been described for the GluN2B-selective agent ifenprodil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kew et al., 1996</xref>), although the extent to which <bold>EU1794-4</bold> can enhance the response to low concentrations of agonist is amplified by the large degree of residual current at saturating levels of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> (30–60%) compared to ifenprodil (~10%). There are numerous studies that suggest the importance of extrasynaptic NMDARs in normal biology but study of them requires complex experimental paradigms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Harris and Pettit, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Paoletti et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Papouin and Oliet, 2014</xref>). Alternatively, the agonist-dependence of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> may alter this capability in instances of repeated stimulation. In either case, <bold>EU1794-4</bold> is a unique compound that may act as a tool that could be used to probe the contribution of distinct types of NMDARs or their activity in circuit function. Further work is required to fully understand the utility of this modulator as a probe for extrasynaptic NMDARs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Reagent type (species) <break/>or resource</th><th>Designation</th><th>Source or reference</th><th>Identifiers</th><th>Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>gene (<italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>)</td><td>GluN1-1a</td><td>U11418</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>gene (<italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>)</td><td>GluN1-1b</td><td>U08263</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>gene (<italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>)</td><td>GluN2A</td><td>D13211</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>gene (<italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>)</td><td>GluN2B</td><td>U11419</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>gene (<italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>)</td><td>GluN2C</td><td>M91563</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>gene (<italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>)</td><td>GluN2D</td><td>L31611</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>cell line (<italic>Xenopus laevis</italic>)</td><td>stage VI oocytes</td><td>Ecocyte Biosciences <break/>(Austin, TX); <break/>Xenopus 1 (Dexter, MI)</td><td>NA; #10004</td><td/></tr><tr><td>cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>)</td><td>HEK293</td><td>ATCC (Manassas, VA)</td><td>CRL-1573</td><td/></tr><tr><td>commercial assay or kit</td><td>QuikChange kit</td><td>Agilent Technologies <break/>(Santa Clara, CA)</td><td>200524</td><td/></tr><tr><td>commercial assay or kit</td><td>mMessage <break/>mMachine <break/>SP6 or t7</td><td>Ambion/ThermoFisher <break/>Scientific (Waltham, MA)</td><td>AM1340 or AM1344</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>EU1794-4</td><td>PMID: 26525866</td><td>SMILES: CCOC(=O)C1 = C(NC(=O) <break/>CC2SC(=N)NC2 = O)SC2 = C1CCCC2</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>EU1794-2</td><td>PMID: 26525866</td><td>SMILES: CCOC(=O)C1 = C(NC(=O) <break/>CC2SC(=N)NC2 = O)SC2 = C1CCC(C)C2</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>EU1794-5</td><td>this paper</td><td>SMILES: CC(C)OC(=O)C1 = C(NC(=O) <break/>CC2SC(=N)NC2 = O)SC2 = C1CCCC2</td><td>See sumplemental <break/>information</td></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>EU1794-19</td><td>this paper</td><td>SMILES: CC(C)OC(=O)C1 = C <break/>(NC(=O)CC2SC(=N)NC2 = O) <break/>SC2 = C1CCC(C)C2</td><td>See sumplemental <break/>information</td></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>EU1794-25</td><td>this paper</td><td>SMILES: CC1CCC2 = C(C1)SC(NC(=O) <break/>CC1SC(=N)NC1 = O)=C2C(=O) <break/>OC1 = CC = CC=C1</td><td>See sumplemental <break/>information</td></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>EU1794-27</td><td>this paper</td><td>SMILES: CC(C)(C)OC(=O)C1 = C <break/>(NC(=O)CC2SC(=N)NC2 = O) <break/>SC2 = C1CCCC2</td><td>See sumplemental <break/>information</td></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>EU1794-29</td><td>this paper</td><td>SMILES: CCCCOC(=O)C1 = C(NC(=O) <break/>CC2SC(=N)NC2 = O)SC2 = C1CCC(C)C2</td><td>See sumplemental <break/>information</td></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>βCD</td><td>Acros Organics or <break/>ChemCenter</td><td>2-(hydroxypropyl)-β-cyclodextrin <break/>(CAS# 128446-35-5)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>APV</td><td>Tocris (Minneapolis, MN)</td><td>(2)-amino-5-phosphonovaleric acid <break/>(CAS# 76326-31-3)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>7-CKA</td><td>Tocris (Minneapolis, MN)</td><td>7-chlorokynurenic acid (CAS# 18000-24-3)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>MTSEA</td><td>TRC Canada (Toronto, ON)</td><td>Methanethiosulfonate ethylammonium <break/>(CAS# 16599-33-0)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>CIQ</td><td>Tocris (Minneapolis, MN)</td><td>CAS# 486427-17-2</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>Ifenprodil</td><td>Tocris (Minneapolis, MN)</td><td>CAS# 23210-56-2</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>PYD-106</td><td>PMID: 25205677</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>TCN-201</td><td>Tocris (Minneapolis, MN)</td><td>CAS# 852918-02-6</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>GNE-6901</td><td>PMID: 26875626; Genentech <break/>(San Francisco, CA)</td><td/><td>generously provided by <break/>Jesse Hanson and <break/>Genentech</td></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>GNE-0723</td><td>PMID: 26919761; Genentech <break/>(San Francisco, CA)</td><td/><td>generously provided by <break/>Jesse Hanson and <break/>Genentech</td></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>DQP-1105</td><td>Tocris (Minneapolis, MN)</td><td>CAS# 380560-89-4</td><td/></tr><tr><td>chemical compound, drug</td><td>QNZ-46</td><td>Tocris (Minneapolis, MN)</td><td>CAS# 1237744-13-6</td><td/></tr><tr><td>software, algorithm</td><td>Perszyk2018_ <break/>sim_Markov_ <break/>Modulator <break/>Competition</td><td>this paper</td><td/><td>Matlab code, see <break/>sumplemental <break/>information</td></tr><tr><td>software, algorithm</td><td>Axopatch and <break/>Clampfit</td><td>Molecular Devices <break/>(San Jose, CA)</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>software, algorithm</td><td>Easy Oocyte</td><td>Custom written Software <break/> (Emory University, Atlanta, GA)</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>software, algorithm</td><td>Prism</td><td>GraphPad (La Jolla, CA)</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>software, algorithm</td><td>Matlab</td><td>Mathworks (Natick, MA)</td><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Molecular Biology</title><p>cDNAs for rat wild type NMDAR subunits GluN1-1a (GenBank U11418, U08261; hereafter GluN1 or GluN1a), GluN1-1b (U08263, hereafter GluN1b), GluN2A (D13211), GluN2B (U11419), GluN2C (M91563), and GluN2D (L31611, modified as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Monyer et al., 1994</xref>) were provided by Drs. S. Heinemann (Salk Institute), S. Nakanishi (Kyoto University), and P. Seeburg (University of Heidelberg). Site-directed mutagenesis was conducted using the QuikChange kit (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA) following the recommended protocol. DNA sequencing was used to verify all mutations. The amino acid numbering system started with the initiating methionine as residue number one. For expression in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocytes, cDNA constructs were linearized by restriction enzymes, and subsequently used to synthesize in vitro cRNAs following the manufacturer’s protocol (mMessage mMachine, Ambion, ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, MA).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Two-electrode voltage-clamp recordings</title><p><italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> stage VI oocytes (Ecocyte Biosciences, Austin, TX) were injected as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hansen et al., 2013</xref>) 2–7 days prior to recording with cRNA encoding the NMDAR subunits and stored at 15°C in media containing (in mM) 88 NaCl, 2.4 NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 1 KCl, 0.33 Ca(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>, 0.41 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.82 MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 5 Tris-HCl; pH was adjusted to 7.4 with NaOH and the solution supplemented with 1 U/mL penicillin, 0.1 mg/mL gentamicin sulfate, and 1 μg/mL streptomycin. Two-electrode voltage-clamp recordings were performed at room temperature (21–23°C) using different internal solutions for voltage and current electrodes (0.3 M and 3.0 M KCl, respectively). All extracellular solutions were made from a solution containing (in mM) 90 NaCl, 1 KCl, 10 HEPES, 0.5 BaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.01 EDTA (pH 7.4 with NaOH). Experiments were performed using an eight port Modular Valve Positioner (Hamilton Company, Reno, NV) and controlled by custom software (Easy Oocyte, Emory University, Atlanta, GA)to exchange solutions. Oocyte currents were recorded at a holding potential of −40 mV using a two-electrode voltage-clamp amplifier (OC-725B or OC-725C, Warner Instruments, Hamden, CT). For some recordings, 1 mM 2-(hydroxypropyl)-β-cyclodextrin was added to wash solutions to ensure modulators did not adhere to the tubing, valves, or recording chamber. In MTSEA experiments, fresh MTSEA solutions (0.2 mM) were prepared and utilized in less than 30 min to limit compound degradation.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Whole cell patch-clamp recordings</title><p>HEK293 cells (CRL-1573, ATCC, Manassas, VA) were maintained in a tissue culture room solely reserved for their culturing and transfected using a CaPO<sub>4</sub> protocol to express the diheteromeric NMDARs as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hansen et al., 2013</xref>). Cell lines were obtained directly from the supplier, were expanded, frozen and kept in liquid nitrogen in a dewar. Mycoplasma testing was not performed. cDNA ratios for transfection were 1:1:1 (GluN2D) or 1:1:5 (GluN2A) for GluN1:GluN2:GFP. Cells were maintained in 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 37°C for 12–36 hr post-transfection. Prior to and during recording, cells were bathed in a solution containing (in mM) 150 NaCl, 10 HEPES, 3 KCl, 0.5 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.01 EDTA (pH 7.4). Cells were patched with borosilicate glass micropipettes (3–4 MΩ) that were filled with internal recording solution that contained (in mM) 95 CsGluconate, 5 CsCl, 40 HEPES, 8 NaCl, 5 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 BAPTA, 0.6 EGTA, 2 Na<sub>2</sub>ATP, and 0.3 NaGTP (pH 7.35). The whole cell recording conformation was achieved, and the cell lifted into the flow of solution from a two barreled theta glass or a triple barrel square glass perfusion system to perform rapid solution exchange experiments. The theta/triple barreled glass was translated using a piezoelectric manipulator to exchange the solution around the cell. Calibration of the perfusion manifold was performed each day to ensure the 10–90% rise time of the solution exchange (switching between 0/100% and 50/50% H<sub>2</sub>O/external solution) around an open tip was less than 1.5 ms for a theta tube and 4 ms for a transition into an outside lane and 2 ms for a transition between lanes for a triple barreled manifold. For some recordings, 1 mM 2-(hydroxypropyl)-β-cyclodextrin was added to wash solutions to ensure modulators did not adhere to the tubing, valves, or recording chamber.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Concentration-response curves for both positive and negative modulators were fitted by the Hill equation:<disp-formula id="equ1"><mml:math id="m1"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>I</italic> is the measured response of receptor activation, <italic>Extent</italic> is the maximal predicted modulation of the glutamate/glycine response, [<italic>M</italic>] is the concentration of the modulator being used, <italic>h</italic> is the Hill slope, and <italic>EC<sub>50</sub></italic> is the half-maximal effective concentration of the modulator. Modulator concentration response data were plotted as a percentage of unmodulated response and displayed fitted curves were obtained by fitting all data simultaneously.</p><p>Glutamate and glycine concentration-response curves were fit with the Hill equation as follows:<disp-formula id="equ2"><mml:math id="m2"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>I</italic> is the measured response of receptor activation, [<italic>A</italic>] is the concentration of the agonist, <italic>h</italic> is the Hill slope, and <italic>EC<sub>50</sub></italic> is the half-maximally effective concentration of the agonist. Agonist concentration-response data, unless otherwise stated, were plotted as a percentage of maximal response and displayed fitted curves were obtained by fitting all data simultaneously with the appropriate Hill equation.</p><p>The time course for the onset and offset of positive and negative modulation was fitted using a single exponential function:<disp-formula id="equ3"><mml:math id="m3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∆</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>t</italic> is time, <italic>I<sub>t</sub></italic> is the difference in current at a given time point as compared to the response at <italic>t</italic> = 0, <italic>A</italic> is the amplitude of the exponential, <italic>τ</italic> is the time constant for the exponential and <italic>c</italic> is a constant. Additionally, some of the complex modulator time-courses were fitted with the sum of a single exponential equation and a linear component<disp-formula id="equ4"><mml:math id="m4"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∆</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>m</italic> is the slope.</p><p>Measurements are given as mean ± SEM unless otherwise indicated. The number of replicate experiments used was chosen to ensure a power level of at least 0.80 when α = 0.05 and when detecting appropriate effect sizes. EC<sub>50</sub> and IC<sub>50</sub> values and confidence intervals reported were calculated by averaging the log(EC<sub>50</sub>) or log(IC<sub>50</sub>) value, determining confidence intervals for mean log(EC<sub>50</sub>) or log(IC<sub>50</sub>), and converting back to units of molarity. Statistical significance evaluations (α set to 0.05) were performed using a one-way ANOVA with Dunnett’s multiple comparison test, a paired t–test, or other appropriate tests as described.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Modelling receptor function</title><p>Matlab (Mathworks, Natick, MA) scripts were written based on previously described approaches to modelling channel function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Colquhoun and Hawkes, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Colquhoun and Hawkes, 1995</xref>). Briefly, a Q matrix was constructed for a model that accounts for macroscopic responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lester and Jahr, 1992</xref>). The glutamate association and dissociation rates were from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Erreger et al., 2005</xref>), and unidirectional rate constants for gating and modulator binding were chosen to allow the model to be used for modulator competition. The differential equations derived by the Q matrix were solved using an ordinary differential equation solver (ode23s, Matlab) and occupancy of each state was determined at equilibrium given the concentrations of the theoretical ligands.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Supplemental methods</title><sec id="s4-6-1"><title>Synthetic chemistry experimental details</title><p>All reagents were obtained from commercial suppliers and used without further purification unless specified otherwise, and were &gt; 90% pure as determined by the manufacturer. Reaction progress was monitored by thin layer chromatography (TLC) on pre-coated glass plates (silica gel 60 F254, 0.25 mm) or liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC-MS) using an analytical column (ZORBAX Eclipse XDB-C18, 4.6 x 50 mm, 3.5 µm, Agilent). When noted, flash chromatography was performed on a Teledyne (Lincoln, NE) ISCO Combiflash Companion with prepackaged Teledyne Redisep or Silicycle disposable normal phase silica columns. Proton and carbon NMR spectra were recorded on an INOVA-400 (400 MHz), VNMRS 400 (400 MHz), INOVA-600 (600 MHz), or Unity-600 (600 MHz). All chemical shifts are reported in parts per million and referenced to the residual solvent peak. Mass spectra were performed by the Emory University Mass Spectroscopy Center on either a VG 70-S Nier Johnson or JEOL instrument. The IR spectra were acquired with a Nicolet Avatar 370 DTGS. Final compound purity was established either through high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) under the conditions listed or by elemental analysis performed by Atlanta Microlab Inc. where C, H, N agreed with proposed structures within ±0.4% of theoretical values unless indicated otherwise.</p><sec id="s4-6-1-1"><title>Separation of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> enantiomers</title><p>Semi-preparative separation of <bold>EU1794-4</bold> enantiomers from racemic <bold>EU1794-4</bold> (0.020 g) was accomplished using a ChiralPak OD-RH (21 mm × 250 mm, 5 μm) with the following conditions: 10.4 mL/min flow rate, 10 mL injection volume (2 mg/1 mL), 30% ACN/70% water with 0.1% formic acid over 120 min to afford (−)-<bold>EU1794-4</bold>, t<sub>R</sub> 62 min; (+)-<bold>EU1794-4</bold>, t<sub>R</sub> 65 min. The enantiomeric excess (ee) was determined using a ChiralPak OD-RH column (4.6 mm × 150 mm, 5 μm) with the following conditions: 1 mL/min flow rate, 5 μL injection volume, 30% ACN/70% water with 0.1% formic acid. (−)-<bold>EU1794-4</bold>: t<sub>R</sub> 29 min; 88% ee; [α]D<sup>20</sup> = −185 (c 1.0, dry CHCl<sub>3</sub>). (+)-<bold>EU1794-4</bold>: t<sub>R</sub> 34 min, 73% ee; [α]D<sup>20</sup> = +191 (c 1.0, dry CHCl<sub>3</sub>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-6-1-2"><title>Separation of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> enantiomers</title><p>Semi-preparative separation of <bold>EU1794-27</bold> enantiomers from racemic <bold>EU1794-27</bold> (0.020 g) was accomplished using a ChiralPak OD-RH (21 mm × 250 mm, 5 μm) with the following conditions: 10.4 mL/min flow rate, 10 mL injection volume (2 mg/1 mL), 60% ACN/40% water with 0.1% formic acid over 120 min to afford (−)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold>, t<sub>R</sub> 55 min; (+)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold>, t<sub>R</sub> 59 min. The enantiomeric excess (ee) was determined using a ChiralPak OD-RH column (4.6 mm × 150 mm, 5 μm) with the following conditions: 1 mL/min flow rate, 5 μL injection volume, 40% ACN/60% water with 0.1% formic acid. (−)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold>: t<sub>R</sub> 13 min; 88% ee; [α]D<sup>20</sup> = −172 (c 1.0, dry CHCl<sub>3</sub>). (+)-<bold>EU1794-27</bold>: t<sub>R</sub> 15 min, 46% ee; [α]D<sup>20</sup> = +178 (c 1.0, dry CHCl<sub>3</sub>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-6-1-3"><title>General Procedure A: Preparation of aminothiophene compounds in alcohol solvent</title><p>To a solution of aldehyde/ketone (1.0 eq.) in alcohol (0.2-0.4 M, corresponding to the ester moiety for each reaction, see below) was added cyanoacetate (1.1 eq.), elemental sulfur (1.1 eq.), and morpholine (1.4 eq.). The reaction mixture was heated to 50 °C in an oil bath. When TLC or LC-MS indicated complete conversion (12-24 h.), the reaction mixture was concentrated in vacuo. The resulting residue was taken up in EtOAc and washed with water (2x) and brine (2x). The organic layer was dried over MgSO<sub>4</sub> and filtered. The solvent was removed <italic>in vacuo</italic>. The resulting product was subjected to flash column chromatography.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6-1-4"><title>General Procedure B: Preparation of aminothiophene compounds in DMF</title><p>To a solution of aldehyde/ketone (1.0 eq.) in DMF (1.0 M) was added cyanoacetate (1.1 eq.), elemental sulfur (1.1 eq.), and morpholine (1.4 eq.). The reaction mixture stirred at room temperature for 24 hours and then concentrated <italic>in vacuo</italic>. The resulting residue was taken up in EtOAc and washed with water (3x) and brine (3x). The organic layer was dried over MgSO<sub>4</sub> and filtered. The solvent was removed <italic>in vacuo</italic>. The resulting product was subjected to flash column chromatography.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6-1-5"><title>General Procedure C: Preparation of (<italic>Z</italic>)-4-oxo-4-(thiophen-2-ylamino)but-2-enoic acid compounds</title><p>A solution of the aminothiophene (1.0 eq.) in anhydrous ether was added dropwise to a solution of maleic anhydride (1.0 eq.) in anhydrous ether for a total concentration of 0.1-0.2 M. Reaction was allowed to stir at room temperature or refluxed until complete consumption of starting material was observed by TLC or LC-MS (16 h.-6 days). The resulting precipitate was filtered, washed with ether, and carried on without further purification.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6-1-6"><title>General Procedure D: Preparation of 2-(2-imino-4-oxothiazolidin-5-yl)-<italic>N</italic>-(thiophen-2-yl)acetamide compounds from (<italic>Z</italic>)-4-oxo-4-(thiophen-2-ylamino)but-2-enoic acid using EDCI</title><p>To a solution of carboxylic acid (1 eq.) in dry DMF (0.15 M) was added HOBt (1.1 eq.) and EDCI (1.5 eq.). The reaction mixture was stirred at room temperature for 1 hour or until all materials were in solution. To the solution was added thiourea (1.1 eq.). The reaction mixture was allowed to stir at room temperature for an additional hour and then heated to 60 °C for 24 hours. The reaction mixture was poured into EtOAc and washed with water (2x) and brine (2x). The organic extracts were combined, dried over anhydrous MgSO<sub>4</sub> and concentrated in vacuo. Crude material was dissolved in hot methanol or ethanol and then slowly cooled to room temperature. The resulting precipitate was filtered and washed with cold solvent.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6-1-7"><title>General Procedure E: Preparation of aryl maleimide compounds</title><p>A mixture of carboxylic acid (1.0 eq.), acetic anhydride (3.3-7.0 eq.), and sodium acetate (0.2 eq.) was heated to 75 °C in an oil bath. After consumption of starting material, reaction mixture was cooled to room temperature where it stirred for 12-18 hours. The reaction was diluted with water and extracted with DCM (3x). The organic extracts were dried over MgSO<sub>4</sub>, filtered, and concentrated. The resulting product was subjected to flash column chromatography.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6-1-8"><title>General Procedure F: Preparation of 2-(2-imino-4-oxothiazolidin-5-yl)-<italic>N</italic>-(thiophen-2-yl)acetamide compounds from aryl maleimides</title><p>A mixture of maleimide (1.0 eq.) and thiourea (1.0 eq.) in absolute EtOH (0.1 M) stirred at room temperature for 24-48 hours. Reaction mixture was filtered, and solid material was washed with EtOH and DCM.</p><fig id="C1" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.028</object-id><label>Chemical structure 1.</label><caption><title>ethyl 2-amino-6-methyl-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>11b</bold>).</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig9-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>11b</bold> was prepared according to procedure A using 4-methylcyclohexanone (1.6 mL, 13.4 mmol) and ethyl 2-cyanoacetate (1.6 mL, 14.7 mmol) in absolute ethanol (0.2-0.4 M). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 120 g silica gel column, 0-10% EtOAc-Hexanes over 25 minutes) to afford the title compound as a white crystalline solid (3.14 g, 98%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 5.92 (br s, 2H), 4.26 (q, J = 7.0 Hz, 2H), 2.85-2.90 (m, 1H), 2.53-2.63 (m, 2H), 2.11-2.17 (m, 1H), 1.81-1.88 (m, 2H), 1.29-1.37 (m, 4H), 1.05 (d, J = 6.4 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 166.3, 162.0, 132.3, 117.4, 105.8, 59.5, 32.8, 31.3, 29.7, 26.9, 21.7, 14.7; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>18</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>S 240.10528, found 240.10521.</p><fig id="C2" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.029</object-id><label>Chemical structure 2.</label><caption><title>ethyl 2-amino-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[b]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>11c</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig10-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>11c</bold> was prepared according to procedure A using cyclohexanone (5.3 mL, 50.9 mmol) and ethyl 2-cyanoacetate (6.0 mL, 56.0 mmol) in absolute ethanol (0.2-0.4 M). The crude material was recrystallized from absolute ethanol to afford the title compound as light yellow crystals (10.0 g, 87%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 5.96 (br s, 2H), 4.26 (q, J = 7.1 Hz, 2H), 2.73-2.69 (m, 2H), 2.52- 2.48 (m, 2H), 1.81-1.71 (m, 4H), 1.34 (t, J = 7.2 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 166.3, 161.9, 132.6, 117.8, 105.9, 59.5, 27.1, 24.7, 23.4, 23.0, 14.7; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>11</sub>H<sub>16</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>S 226.08963, found 226.08966; IR (solid ATR): 3400, 3294, 2982, 2939, 2895, 1644, 1593, 1488, 1271 cm<sup>-1</sup>.</p><fig id="C3" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.030</object-id><label>Chemical structure 3.</label><caption><title>isopropyl 2-amino-6-methyl-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>11f</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig11-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>11f</bold> was prepared according to procedure A using 4-methylcyclohexanone (2.2 mL, 17.8 mmol) and isopropyl 2-cyanoacetate (2.5 mL, 19.6 mmol) in isopropanol (0.2-0.4 M). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 80 g silica gel column, 0-20% EtOAc-Hexanes over 25 minutes) to afford the title compound as an off-white solid (4.42 g, 98%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 5.96 (br s, 2H), 5.16 (septet, J = 6.3 Hz, 1H), 2.84-2.91 (m, 1H), 2.52-2.65 (m, 2H), 2.10-2.18 (m, 1H), 1.80-1.90 (m, 2H), 1.25-1.35 (m, 1H), 1.32 (d, J = 6.4 Hz, 3H), 1.31 (d, J = 6.4 Hz, 3H), 1.04 (d, J = 6.7 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 165.9, 161.9, 132.3, 117.4, 106.1, 66.8, 32.9, 31.3, 29.6, 27.0, 22.4, 21.7; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>13</sub>H<sub>20</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>S 254.12093, found 254.12052.</p><fig id="C4" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.031</object-id><label>Chemical structure 4.</label><caption><title>isopropyl 2-amino-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>11h</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig12-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>11h</bold> was prepared according to procedure A using cyclohexanone (2.1 mL, 20.4 mmol) and isopropyl 2-cyanoacetate (2.8 mL, 22.4 mmol) in isopropanol (0.2-0.4 M). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 120 g silica gel column, 0-10% EtOAc-Hexanes over 25 minutes) to afford the title compound as a white solid (4.12 g, 84%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 6.12 (br s, 2H), 5.16 (septet, J = 6.2 Hz, 1H), 2.69-2.71 (m, 2H), 2.46-2.48 (m, 2H), 1.72-1.77 (m, 4H), 1.31 (d, J = 6.2 Hz, 6H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 165.7, 162.0, 132.3, 117.4, 105.6, 66.6, 27.0, 24.5, 23.2, 22.9, 22.1; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>18</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>S 240.10528, found 240.10549; Elem. Anal. calc’d for C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>17</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>S, C, 60.22; H, 7.16; N, 5.85, found C, 60.49; H, 7.26; N, 5.79.</p><fig id="C5" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.032</object-id><label>Chemical structure 5.</label><caption><title>tert-butyl 2-amino-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>11k</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig13-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>11k</bold> was prepared according to procedure A using cyclohexanone (1.6 mL, 15.3 mmol) and tert-butyl 2-cyanoacetate (2.4 mL, 16.8 mmol) in absolute ethanol (40.0 mL). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 80 g silica gel, 0-20% EtOAc-Hexanes over 25 minutes) to afford the title compound as a yellow oil (2.45 g, 63%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 5.83 (br s, 2H), 2.67-2.64 (m, 2H), 2.49-2.46 (m, 2H), 1.76-1.69 (m, 4H), 1.52 (s, 9H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 165.8, 161.2, 132.7, 117.7, 107.4, 80.2, 28.8, 27.4, 24.8, 23.5, 23.1; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>13</sub>H<sub>20</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>S 254.12093, found 254.12087; IR (solid ATR): 3434, 3324, 2932, 1732, 1660, 1576, 1484, 1141 cm<sup>−1</sup>.</p><fig id="C6" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.033</object-id><label>Chemical structure 6.</label><caption><title>butyl 2-amino-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[b]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>11l</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig14-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>11l</bold> was prepared according to procedure B using cyclohexanone (1.2 mL, 11.6 mmol) and butyl 2-cyanoacetate (1.8 mL, 12.8 mmol). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 80 g silica gel, 0-10% EtOAc-Hexanes over 20 minutes) to afford the title compound as a yellow oil (2.35 g, 80%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 5.96 (br s, 2H), 4.21 (t, J = 6.6 Hz, 2H), 2.72-2.69 (m, 2H), 2.52-2.49 (m, 2H), 1.82-1.66 (m, 6H), 1.45 (sextet, J = 7.4 Hz, 2H), 0.96 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 166.5, 161.9, 132.6, 117.8, 106.0, 63.5, 31.1, 27.2, 24.7, 23.4, 23.1, 19.6, 114.0; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>13</sub>H<sub>20</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>S 254.12093, found 254.12061; IR (solid ATR): 3433, 3325, 2932, 2857, 1664, 1576, 1485, 1265 cm<sup>-1</sup>.</p><fig id="C7" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.034</object-id><label>Chemical structure 7.</label><caption><title>benzyl 2-amino-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>11m</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig15-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>11m</bold> was prepared according to procedure B using cyclohexanone (0.7 mL, 6.5 mmol) and benzyl 2-cyanoacetate (1.1 mL, 7.1 mmol). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 40 g silica gel, 0-20% EtOAc-Hexanes over 15 minutes) to afford the title compound as a yellow tinted oil (1.38 g, 74%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 7.43-7.33 (m, 5H), 6.00 (br s, 2H), 5.29 (s, 2H), 2.74-2.71 (m, 2H), 2.52-2.49 (m, 2H), 1.81-1.68 (m, 4H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 166.0, 162.4, 136.9, 132.5, 128.7, 128.1, 128.1, 117.8, 105.5, 65.4, 27.2, 24.7, 23.4, 23.0; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>18</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>S 288.10528, found 288.10519; IR (solid ATR): 3442, 3325, 2980, 2934, 1659, 1575, 1483, 1261 cm<sup>-1</sup>.</p><fig id="C8" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.035</object-id><label>Chemical structure 8.</label><caption><title>(<italic>Z</italic>)-4-((3-(ethoxycarbonyl)-6-methyl-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophen-2-yl)amino)-4-oxobut-2-enoic acid (<bold>13b</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig16-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>13b</bold> was prepared according to procedure C using compound <bold>11b</bold> (2.6 g, 10.7 mmol). The crude yellow solid (3.54 g, 98%) was carried on without further purification. <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 12.22 (s, 1H), 6.51 (d, J = 12.8 Hz, 1H), 6.45 (d, J = 12.8 Hz, 1H), 4.38 (q, J = 7.0 Hz, 2H), 2.95-2.99 (m, 1H), 2.78 (dd, J = 4.9, 15.9 Hz, 1H), 2.66-2.75 (m, 1H), 2.29-2.35 (m, 1H), 1.89-1.93 (m, 2H), 1.42 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 4H), 1.09 (d, J = 6.7 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 166.9, 164.3, 162.1, 144.4, 137.8, 132.1, 130.8, 130.0, 115.0, 61.6, 32.8, 31.0, 29.3, 26.3, 21.5, 14.4; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>20</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>S, 338.10567, found 338.10550.</p><fig id="C9" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.036</object-id><label>Chemical structure 9.</label><caption><title>(<italic>Z</italic>)-4-((3-(ethoxycarbonyl)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophen-2-yl)amino)-4-oxobut-2-enoic acid (<bold>13c</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig17-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>13c</bold> was prepared according to procedure C using compound <bold>11c</bold> (3.0 g, 13.3 mmol). The crude yellow solid (4.02 g, 93%) was carried on without further purification. <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 12.18 (br s, 1H), 6.49 (d, J = 12.8 Hz, 1H), 6.45 (d, J = 12.8 Hz, 1H,), 4.36 (q, J = 7.1 Hz, 2H), 2.78 (app. t, J = 5.2 Hz, 2H), 2.69 (app. t, J = 4.9 Hz, 2H), 1.78-1.83 (m, 4H), 1.40 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 166.8, 164.3, 162.0, 144.2, 137.7, 132.3, 131.0, 130.0, 115.1, 61.5, 26.4, 24.7, 22.9, 22.7, 14.4; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>18</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>S 324.09002, found 324.08965.</p><fig id="C10" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.037</object-id><label>Chemical structure 10.</label><caption><title>(<italic>Z</italic>)-4-((3-(isopropoxycarbonyl)-6-methyl-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophen-2-yl)amino)-4-oxobut-2-enoic acid (<bold>13f</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig18-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>13f</bold> was prepared according to procedure C using compound <bold>11f</bold> (2.0 g, 7.9 mmol). The crude yellow solid (2.69 g, 97%) was carried on without further purification. <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 12.25 (br s, 1H), 6.49 (d, J = 12.8 Hz, 1H), 6.45 (d, J = 12.8 Hz, 1H), 5.22 (septet, J = 6.2 Hz, 1H), 2.93-2.97 (m, 1H), 2.64-2.79 (m, 2H), 2.26-2.33 (m, 1H), 1.84-1.92 (m, 2H), 1.29-1.43 (m, 7H), 1.08 (d, J = 6.1 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 166.4, 164.3, 162.0, 144.2, 137.8, 132.0, 130.7, 130.1, 115.3, 69.5, 32.7, 31.0, 29.3, 26.3, 22.1, 21.5; HRMS (ESI) [M–H]<sup>-</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>22</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>S 350.10677, found 350.10666.</p><fig id="C11" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.038</object-id><label>Chemical structure 11.</label><caption><title>(<italic>Z</italic>)-4-((3-(isopropoxycarbonyl)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophen-2-yl)amino)-4-oxobut-2-enoic acid (<bold>13h</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig19-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>13h</bold> was prepared according to procedure C using compound <bold>11h</bold> (1.5 g, 6.3 mmol). The crude yellow solid (2.01 g, 95%) was carried on without further purification. <sup>1</sup>H NMR [600 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 12.27 (br s, 1H), 6.50 (d, J = 12.8 Hz, 1H), 6.46 (d, J = 12.8 Hz, 1H), 5.23 (septet, J = 6.3 Hz, 1H), 2.79-2.80 (m, 2H), 2.69-2.70 (m, 2H), 1.81-1.82 (m, 4H), 1.39 (d, J = 6.0 Hz, 6H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [150 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 166.5, 164.3, 162.1, 144.1, 137.8, 132.4, 131.1, 130.1, 115.5, 69.5, 26.6, 24.7, 22.9, 22.8, 22.2; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>20</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>S 338.10567, found 338.10578.</p><fig id="C12" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.039</object-id><label>Chemical structure 12.</label><caption><title>(<italic>Z</italic>)-4-((3-(tert-butoxycarbonyl)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophen-2-yl)amino)-4-oxobut-2-enoic acid (<bold>13k</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig20-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>13k</bold> was prepared according to procedure C using compound <bold>11k</bold> (2.4 g, 9.6 mmol). The crude yellow solid (2.88 g, 86%) was carried on without further purification. HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>22</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>S 352.12132, found 352.12107.</p><fig id="C13" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.040</object-id><label>Chemical structure 13.</label><caption><title>ethyl 2-(2,5-dioxo-2,5-dihydro-1<italic>H</italic>-pyrrol-1-yl)-6-methyl-4,5,6,7- tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>18b</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig21-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>18b</bold> was prepared according to procedure E using compound <bold>13b</bold> (1.0 g, 3.0 mmol). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 24 g silica gel, 0-18% EtOAc-Hexanes over 15 minutes) to afford the title compound as a yellow oil that solidified upon standing (0.769 g, 81%). HRMS (APCI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub><sup>16</sup></sub>H<sub>18</sub>NO<sub>4</sub>S 320.09511, found 320.09520.</p><fig id="C14" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.041</object-id><label>Chemical structure 14.</label><caption><title>isopropyl 2-(2,5-dioxo-2,5-dihydro-1<italic>H</italic>-pyrrol-1-yl)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>18h</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig22-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>18h</bold> was prepared according to procedure E using compound <bold>13h</bold> (0.8 g, 2.4 mmol). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 24 g silica gel, 0-25% EtOAc-Hexanes over 20 minutes) to afford the title compound as a golden brown oil (0.712 g, 94%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 6.91 (s, 2H), 5.09 (septet, J = 5.3 Hz, 1H), 2.84 (app. t, J = 5.8 Hz, 2H), 2.75 (app. t, J = 5.5 Hz, 2H), 1.80-1.86 (m, 4H), 1.20 (d, J = 6.1Hz, 6H); HRMS (APCI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>18</sub>NO<sub>4</sub>S 320.09511, found 320.09527.</p><fig id="C15" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.042</object-id><label>Chemical structure 15.</label><caption><title>tert-butyl 2-(2,5-dioxo-2,5-dihydro-1<italic>H</italic>-pyrrol-1-yl)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>18k</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig23-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>18k</bold> was prepared according to procedure E using compound <bold>13k</bold> (2.0 g, 5.7 mmol). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 40 g silica gel, 0-18% EtOAc-Hexanes over 15 minutes) to afford the title compound as a light yellow solid (1.44 g, 76%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 6.90 (s, 2H), 2.83-2.79 (m, 2H), 2.75-2.72 (m, 2H), 1.86-1.76 (m, 4H), 1.44 (s, 9H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 169.1 (2C), 161.4, 136.6, 135.7, 135.1 (2C), 131.6, 130.4, 81.6, 28.4 (3C), 26.6, 25.4, 22.9, 22.6; HRMS (APCI) [M–O<italic>t</italic>-Bu]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>13</sub>H<sub>10</sub>NO<sub>3</sub>S 260.03759, found 260.03737; IR (solid ATR): 2918, 1709, 1565, 1410, 1393, 1367, 1136, 691 cm<sup>−1</sup>.</p><fig id="C16" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.043</object-id><label>Chemical structure 16.</label><caption><title>butyl 2-(2,5-dioxo-2,5-dihydro-1<italic>H</italic>-pyrrol-1-yl)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3- carboxylate (<bold>18l</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig24-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>18l</bold> was prepared according to procedure E using compound <bold>13l</bold> (1.2 g, 3.4 mmol). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 40 g silica gel, 0-18% EtOAc-Hexanes over 15 minutes) to afford the title compound as a light yellow solid (1.04 g, 91%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 6.91 (s, 2H), 4.13 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 6.7 Hz, 2H), 2.84 (app. t, <italic>J</italic> = 5.8 Hz, 2H), 2.75 (app. t, <italic>J</italic> = 5.8 Hz, 2H), 1.87-1.78 (m, 4H), 1.57 (p, <italic>J</italic> = 7.2 Hz, 2H), 1.34 (sextet, <italic>J</italic> = 7.5 Hz, 2H), 0.91 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 7.5 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 169.2 (2C), 162.21, 136.8, 135.9, 135.1 (2C), 133.0, 128.7, 64.7, 30.8, 26.6, 25.4, 22.8, 22.6, 19.3, 13.9; 62 HRMS (APCI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>20</sub>NO<sub>4</sub>S 334.11076, found 334.11128; IR (solid ATR): 3097, 2944, 1710, 1414, 1364, 1175, 836, 693 cm<sup>−1</sup>.</p><fig id="C17" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.044</object-id><label>Chemical structure 17.</label><caption><title>benzyl 2-(2,5-dioxo-2,5-dihydro-1<italic>H</italic>-pyrrol-1-yl)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3- carboxylate (<bold>18m</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig25-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>18m</bold> was prepared according to procedure E using compound <bold>13m</bold> (0.4 g, 1.0 mmol). The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 24 g silica gel, 0-25% EtOAc-Hexanes over 15 minutes) to afford the title compound as a light yellow solid (0.299 g, 78%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 7.40-7.21 (m, 5H), 6.44 (s, 2H), 5.07 (s, 2H), 2.91-2.78 (m, 2H), 2.75-2.64 (m, 2H), 1.88-1.71 (m, 4H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>] δ 169.2 (2C), 161.6, 137.0, 136.3, 135.4, 134.2 (2C), 133.3, 129.4 (2C), 128.8 (2C), 128.7, 128.3, 67.0, 26.4, 25.4, 22.8, 22.5; HRMS (APCI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>20</sub>H<sub>18</sub>NO<sub>4</sub>S 368.09511, found 368.09512; IR (solid ATR): 2942, 2850, 1763, 1672, 1638, 1537, 1176, 1137, 691 cm<sup>−1</sup>.</p><fig id="C18" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.045</object-id><label>Chemical structure 18.</label><caption><title>(<italic>Z</italic>)-4-((3-((benzyloxy)carbonyl)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophen-2-yl)amino)-4-oxobut-2-enoic acid (<bold>13m</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig26-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>13m</bold> was prepared according to procedure C using compound <bold>11m</bold> (0.6 g, 2.1 mmol). The crude yellow solid (0.573 g, 70%) was carried on without further purification. HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>20</sub>H<sub>20</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>S 386.10567, found 386.10587.</p><fig id="C19" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.046</object-id><label>Chemical structure 19.</label><caption><title>ethyl 2-(2-(2-imino-4-oxothiazolidin-5-yl)acetamido)-6-methyl-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>EU1794-2</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig27-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>EU1794-2</bold> was prepared according to procedure D using compound <bold>13b</bold> (0.3 g, 0.7 mmol). The crude material was precipitated from hot ethanol to afford the title compound (inseparable mixture of diastereomers) as a light yellow solid (0.0779 g, 27%). Compound <bold>EU1794-2</bold> was also prepared according to procedure F using compound <bold>18b</bold> (0.4 g, 1.3 mmol). The precipitate was rinsed with DCM to afford the title compound (inseparable mixture of diastereomers) as an off-white solid (0.406 g, 82%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] δ 10.98 (s, 1H), 9.03 (s, 1H), 8.80 (s, 1H), 4.42 (dd, J = 3.7, 10.4 Hz, 1H), 4.27 (q, J = 6.9 Hz, 2H), 2.99 (dd, J = 10.4, 15.3 Hz, 1H), 2.83-2.88 (m, 1H), 2.59-2.70 (m, 2H), 2.16-2.22 (m, 1H), 1.80 (m, 2H), 1.30 (t, J = 7.0 Hz, 4H), 1.01 (d, J = 6.7 Hz, 4H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] (<sup>13</sup>C resonance obstructed by solvent peak) δ 188.5, 182.0, 167.8, 164.7, 145.4, 130.2, 125.9, 111.7, 60.4, 51.4, 31.7, 30.5, 28.7, 25.6, 21.2, 14.1; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>13</sub>H<sub>16</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub>, 342.05768, found 342.05759; IR (solid ATR): 3224, 2927, 1673, 1562, 1534, 1496, 1460, 1435, 1376, 1284, 1257, 1231, 1166, 1142, 1081, 1027, 960, 843, 775, 741, 698, 636 cm<sup>-1</sup>; m.p. = 190-204 °C (dec.); Elem. Anal. calc’d for C<sub>13</sub>H<sub>15</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub>, C, 45.73; H, 4.43; N, 12.31, found C, 45.88; H, 4.46; N, 11.93.</p><fig id="C20" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.047</object-id><label>Chemical structure 20.</label><caption><title>ethyl 2-(2-(2-imino-4-oxothiazolidin-5-yl)acetamido)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>EU1794-4</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig28-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>EU1794-4</bold> was prepared according to procedure D using compound <bold>13c</bold> (0.4 g, 1.2 mmol). The crude material was precipitated from hot ethanol to afford the title compound as a light yellow solid (0.281 g, 60%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] δ 11.00 (s, 1H), 9.06 (s, 1H), 8.82 (s, 1H), 4.43 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 3.9, 10.2 Hz, 1H), 4.28 (q, <italic>J</italic> = 7.0 Hz, 2H), 3.36-3.42 (m, 1H), 3.01 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 10.2, 16.8, 1H), 2.69 (s, 2H), 2.59 (s, 2H), 1.72 (s, 4H), 1.31 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 7.0 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] (<sup>13</sup>C resonance obstructed by solvent peak) δ 188.5, 182.0, 167.8, 164.7, 145.3, 130.5, 126.3, 111.8, 60.3, 51.4, 25.8, 23.7, 22.5, 22.3, 14.1; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>20</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub>, 382.08952, found 382.08902; IR (solid ATR): 3661, 3269, 3195, 2933, 1655, 1563, 1527, 1439, 1408, 1366, 1326, 1231, 1134, 1032, 996, 969, 784, 703, 629 cm<sup>−1</sup>; m.p. = 163 °C (dec.); Elem. Anal. calc’d for C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>19</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2,</sub> C, 50.38; H, 5.02; N, 11.02, found C, 49.31; H, 5.00; N, 10.73 (Value did not fall within ± 0.4).</p><fig id="C21" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.048</object-id><label>Chemical structure 21.</label><caption><title>isopropyl 2-(2-(2-imino-4-oxothiazolidin-5-yl)acetamido)-6-methyl-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>EU1794-19</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig29-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>EU1794-19</bold> was prepared according to procedure D using compound <bold>13f</bold> (0.7 g, 2.0 mmol). The crude material was precipitated from hot ethanol to afford the title compound as a white solid (0.134 g, 16%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] δ 11.00 (s, 1H), 9.04 (s, 1H), 8.81 (s, 1H), 4.43 (dd, J = 3.8, 10.2 Hz, 1H), 4.29 (q, J = 7.1 Hz, 2H), 3.39 (dd, J = 3.8, 16.9 Hz, 1H), 3.00 (dd, J = 10.4, 16.8 Hz, 1H), 2.71 (app. t, J = 5.9 Hz, 2H), 2.38 (app. s, 2H), 1.48 (app. t, J = 6.3 Hz, 2H), 1.32 (t, J = 7.0 Hz, 3H), 0.95 (s, 6H).; <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] δ 188.5, 181.9, 167.7, 164.7, 145.5, 129.1, 125.6, 111.5, 60.4, 51.4, 39.2, 37.1, 35.0, 29.7, 27.4, 27.3, 23.5, 14.0; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>24</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub> 410.12028, found 410.12066; IR (solid ATR): 3205, 2923, 1655, 1561, 1531, 1492, 1386, 1293, 1233, 1148, 1106, 1074, 1011, 979, 960, 912, 835, 783, 761, 736, 698, 645 cm<sup>-1</sup>; m.p. = 229 °C (dec.); HPLC purity: &gt;95% t<sub>R</sub> = 1.300 min. (85% MeOH/Water with 0.1% formic acid, isocratic, 1.0 mL/min.); t<sub>R</sub> = 0.995 min. (75% MeCN/Water with 0.1% formic acid, isocratic, 1.0 mL/min.).</p><fig id="C22" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.049</object-id><label>Chemical structure 22.</label><caption><title>isopropyl 2-(2-(2-imino-4-oxothiazolidin-5-yl)acetamido)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>EU1794-5</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig30-v1"/></fig><p>To a solution of <bold>13h</bold> (0.2 g, 0.6 mmol) dissolved in dry DMF (5.0 mL) was added HATU (0.2 g, 0.6 mmol). The reaction mixture was allowed to stir at room temperature for 10 minutes. To the stirring mixture was added thiourea (0.1 g, 1.5 mmol) and DIPEA (0.5 mL, 3.0 mmol). The reaction was allowed to stir an additional 30 minutes before heating to 60 °C for 72 hours. The solvent was removed <italic>in vacuo</italic>. The crude material was purified by flash column chromatography (ISCO, 12 g silica gel column, 3-11% MeOH-DCM over 15 minutes). The resulting fractions were found to contain impurities. Material was re-purified by flash column chromatography (12 g silica gel column, 0-8% MeOH-DCM over 15 minutes) to afford the title compound as a light brown solid (0.0551 g, 23%). Compound <bold>EU1794-5</bold> was also prepared according to procedure F using <bold>18h</bold> (0.2 g, 0.7 mmol). The precipitate was rinsed with DCM to afford the title compound as a white solid (0.119 g, 42%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] δ 11.04 (s, 1H), 9.04 (s, 1H), 8.81 (s, 1H), 5.10 (septet, J = 6.3 Hz, 1H), 4.42 (dd, J = 3.9, 10.2 Hz, 1H), 3.40 (d, J = 3.5 Hz, 1H), 3.00 (dd, J = 10.2 16.8, 1H), 2.69 (br s, 2H), 2.58 (br s, 2H), 1.71 (br s, 4H), 1.31 (d, J = 6.3 Hz, 6H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] (<sup>13</sup>C resonance obstructed by solvent peak) δ 188.5, 181.9, 167.7, 164.4, 145.4, 130.4, 126.3, 112.0, 68.0, 51.4, 25.9, 23.7, 22.5, 22.3, 21.7 (2C); HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>22</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub> 396.10463, found 396.10409; m.p. = 152-154 °C; HPLC purity: &gt;95% t<sub>R</sub> = 2.082 min. (75-95% MeOH/Water with 0.1% formic acid, gradient over 3 minutes, 1.0 mL/min.); t<sub>R</sub> = 0.698 min. (85% MeCN/Water with 0.1% formic acid, isocratic, 1.0 mL/min.).</p><fig id="C23" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.050</object-id><label>Chemical structure 23.</label><caption><title>tert-butyl 2-(2-(2-imino-4-oxothiazolidin-5-yl)acetamido)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>EU1794-27</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig31-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>EU1794-27</bold> was prepared according to procedure F using compound <bold>18k</bold> (0.5 g, 1.5 mmol). The precipitate was rinsed with EtOH and EtOAc to afford the title compound as a light yellow solid (0.403 g, 66%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] δ 11.03 (s, 1H), 9.03 (s, 1H), 8.80 (s, 1H), 4.43 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 4.0, 10.2 Hz, 1H), 3.38 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 3.7, 16.8 Hz, 1H), 3.00 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 10.4, 16.8 Hz, 1H), 2.68 (app. br s, 2H), 2.58 (app. br s, 2H), 1.70 (app. br s, 4H), 1.54 (s, 9H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] (<sup>13</sup>C resonance obstructed by solvent peak) δ 188.5, 182.0, 167.7, 164.3, 145.2, 130.5, 126.1, 112.8, 81.5, 51.4, 28.0 (3C), 26.1, 23.8, 22.5, 22.4; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>24</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub> 410.12027, found 410.12011; IR (solid ATR): 3372, 2919, 1705, 1565, 1524, 1367, 1240, 1138 cm<sup>−1</sup>; HPLC purity: &gt;95% <italic>t</italic><sub>R</sub> = 0.765 min. (95% MeOH/Water with 0.1% formic acid, isocratic, 1.0 mL/min.).</p><fig id="C24" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.051</object-id><label>Chemical structure 24.</label><caption><title>butyl 2-(2-(2-imino-4-oxothiazolidin-5-yl)acetamido)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>EU1794-29</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig32-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>EU1794-29</bold> was prepared according to procedure F using compound <bold>18l</bold> (0.5 g, 1.5 mmol). The precipitate was rinsed with EtOH to afford the title compound as a light yellow solid (0.325 g, 53%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] δ 11.38 (s, 1H), 10.05 (br s, 1H), 7.53 (s, 1H), 4.55 (dd, J = 3.2, 11.1 Hz, 1H), 4.24 (t, J = 6.6 Hz, 2H), 3.54 (dd, J = 3.1, 16.8 Hz, 1H), 2.96 (dd, J = 11.3, 16.8 Hz, 1H), 2.72 (app. br s, 2H), 2.57 (app. br s, 2H), 1.76 (app. br s, 4H), 1.70 (p, J = 7.2 Hz, 2H), 1.44 (sextet, J = 7.4 Hz, 2H), 0.96 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 3H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] δ 189.1, 184.3, 167.0, 166.7, 146.9, 131.0, 127.2, 112.2, 64.7, 52.0, 40.2, 30.9, 26.5, 24.5, 23.1, 23.0, 19.6, 13.9; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>24</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub> 410.12027, found 410.11979; IR (solid ATR): 3307, 2939, 1650, 1567, 1521, 1414, 1245, 1115 cm<sup>-1</sup>; HPLC purity: &gt;95% t<sub>R</sub> = 1.479 min. (85% MeOH/Water with 0.1% formic acid, isocratic, 1.0 mL/min.).</p><fig id="C25" position="anchor"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.052</object-id><label>Chemical structure 25.</label><caption><title>benzyl 2-(2-(2-imino-4-oxothiazolidin-5-yl)acetamido)-4,5,6,7-tetrahydrobenzo[<italic>b</italic>]thiophene-3-carboxylate (<bold>EU1794-25</bold>)</title></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-34711-fig33-v1"/></fig><p>Compound <bold>EU1794-25</bold> was prepared according to procedure F using compound <bold>18m</bold> (0.3 g, 0.7 mmol). The precipitate was rinsed with DCM to afford the title compound as an off-white solid (0.124 g, 41%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR [400 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] δ 10.98 (s, 1H), 9.04 (s, 1H), 8.80 (s, 1H), 7.49-7.29 (m, 5H), 5.33 (s, 2H), 4.42 (dd, J = 3.8, 10.2 Hz, 1H), 3.37 (dd, J = 4.0, 16.8 Hz, 1H), 2.96 (dd, 1H, J = 10.2, 16.9 Hz, 1H), 2.72-2.64 (m, 2H), 2.62-2.54 (m, 2H), 1.77-1.61 (m, 4H); <sup>13</sup>C NMR [100 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>] (13C resonance obstructed by solvent peak) δ 188.5, 181.97, 167.9, 164.4, 145.7, 136.1, 130.5, 128.6 (2C), 128.2, 128.1 (2C), 126.4, 111.6, 65.9, 51.4, 25.9, 23.7, 22.5, 22.3; HRMS (ESI) [M+H]<sup>+</sup>, calc’d for C<sub>21</sub>H<sub>22</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub> 444.10463, found 444.10497; IR (solid ATR): 2936, 1649, 1564, 1517, 1237, 1191, 1020 cm<sup>-1</sup>; HPLC purity: &gt;95% t<sub>R</sub> = 2.470 min. (75-95% MeOH/Water with 0.1% formic acid, gradient over 3 minutes, 1.0 mL/min.).</p></sec></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Phuong Le, Jing Zhang, and Anel Tankovic for excellent technical assistance. GNE-6901 and GNE-0723 were generously provided by Jesse Hanson and Genentech. This work was supported by the NINDS (NS036654, NS065371, SFT) and NIGMS (T32-GM008602). We also thank the Emory Chemical Biology Discovery Center for their assistance.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf2"><p>BMK is an inventor of Emory-owned IP.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf3"><p>MPE is an inventor of Emory-owned IP.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf4"><p>DM is an inventor of Emory-owned IP.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf5"><p>DCL is a member of the Board of Directors at NeurOp Inc. and is an inventor of Emory-owned IP.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf6"><p>SFT is a co-founder of NeurOp Inc., a paid consultant for Janssen, a PI on a research grant from Janssen to Emory University, a member of the Scientific Advisory Board for Sage Therapeutics, and is an inventor of Emory-owned IP.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Software, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Data curation, Software, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Resources, Investigation, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con9"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con10"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con11"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.053</object-id><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Saturating and sub-saturating actions of EU1794-2.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-supp1-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.054</object-id><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>Enantiomeric actions of EU1794-4.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-supp2-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.055</object-id><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-34711-transrepform-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acker</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vance</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname> <given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullasseril</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Liotta</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Mechanism for noncompetitive inhibition by novel GluN2C/D N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor subunit-selective modulators</article-title><source>Molecular Pharmacology</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>795</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.111.073239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21807990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alsaloum</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazi</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollmuth</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>A molecular determinant of subtype-specific desensitization in ionotropic glutamate receptors</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>2617</fpage><lpage>2622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2667-15.2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26937003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arunlakshana</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schild</surname> <given-names>HO</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1959">1959</year><article-title>Some quantitative uses of drug antagonists</article-title><source>British Journal of Pharmacology and Chemotherapy</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-5381.1959.tb00928.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13651579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnard</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Skolnick</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohler</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieghart</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Biggio</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Braestrup</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bateson</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Langer</surname> <given-names>SZ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>International Union of Pharmacology. XV. Subtypes of gamma-aminobutyric acidA receptors: classification on the basis of subunit structure and receptor function</article-title><source>Pharmacological Reviews</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9647870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borovska</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyklicky</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Stastna</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapras</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Slavikova</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Horak</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chodounska</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyklicky</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Access of inhibitory neurosteroids to the NMDA receptor</article-title><source>British Journal of Pharmacology</source><volume>166</volume><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>1083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-5381.2011.01816.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22188257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shieh</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanger</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tankovic</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Au</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McGuire</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tagliati</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Madan-Khetarpal</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierson</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>GRIN1 mutation associated with intellectual disability alters NMDA receptor trafficking and function</article-title><source>Journal of Human Genetics</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jhg.2017.19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28228639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christopoulos</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenakin</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>G protein-coupled receptor allosterism and complexing</article-title><source>Pharmacological Reviews</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/pr.54.2.323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12037145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colquhoun</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkes</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1977">1977</year><article-title>Relaxation and fluctuations of membrane currents that flow through drug-operated channels</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><volume>199</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.1977.0137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colquhoun</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkes</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><chapter-title>A Q-matrix cookbook: How to write only one program to calculate the single-channel and macroscopic predictions for any kinetic mechanism</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sakmann</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Neher</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Single-Channel Recording</source><publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erreger</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Geballe</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dravid</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyllie</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Mechanism of partial agonism at NMDA receptors for a conformationally restricted glutamate analog</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>7858</fpage><lpage>7866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1613-05.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16120788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gladding</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Mechanisms underlying NMDA receptor synaptic/extrasynaptic distribution and function</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Neuroscience</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2011.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21600287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groc</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Heine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cousins</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephenson</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lounis</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cognet</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Choquet</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>NMDA receptor surface mobility depends on NR2A-2B subunits</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>18769</fpage><lpage>18774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0605238103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17124177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hackos</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupardus</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grand</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallweber</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Volgraf</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellers</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Paoletti</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Positive allosteric modulators of GluN2A-containing NMDARs with distinct modes of action and impacts on circuit function</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2016.01.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26875626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hackos</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Diverse modes of NMDA receptor positive allosteric modulation: Mechanisms and consequences</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2016.07.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27484578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Structural and mechanistic determinants of a novel site for noncompetitive inhibition of GluN2D-containing NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>3650</fpage><lpage>3661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5565-10.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21389220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Subunit-selective allosteric inhibition of glycine binding to NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>6197</fpage><lpage>6208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5757-11.2012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22553026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tajima</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Risgaard</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Perszyk</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jørgensen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vance</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Clausen</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Structural determinants of agonist efficacy at the glutamate binding site of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors</article-title><source>Molecular Pharmacology</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.113.085803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23625947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardingham</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bading</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Synaptic versus extrasynaptic NMDA receptor signalling: implications for neurodegenerative disorders</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20842175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettit</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Recruiting extrasynaptic NMDA receptors augments synaptic signaling</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.01169.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18057106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haydon</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmignoto</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Astrocyte control of synaptic transmission and neurovascular coupling</article-title><source>Physiological Reviews</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>1009</fpage><lpage>1031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00049.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16816144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horak</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlcek</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovic</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chodounska</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyklicky</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Molecular mechanism of pregnenolone sulfate action at NR1/NR2B receptors</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>10318</fpage><lpage>10325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2099-04.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15548645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horak</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlcek</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chodounska</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyklicky</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Subtype-dependence of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor modulation by pregnenolone sulfate</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><volume>137</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2005.08.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16257494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>VanDongen</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>VanDongen</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>The NMDA receptor M3 segment is a conserved transduction element coupling ligand binding to channel opening</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>2044</fpage><lpage>2053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.22-06-02044.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11896144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalia</surname> <given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalia</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Salter</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>NMDA receptors in clinical neurology: excitatory times ahead</article-title><source>The Lancet Neurology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>742</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(08)70165-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karakas</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Simorowski</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Subunit arrangement and phenylethanolamine binding in GluN1/GluN2B NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>475</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21677647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karakas</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Crystal structure of a heterotetrameric NMDA receptor ion channel</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>344</volume><fpage>992</fpage><lpage>997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1251915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24876489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katzman</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perszyk</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahirovic</surname> <given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotimehin</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liotta</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A novel class of negative allosteric modulators of NMDA receptor function</article-title><source>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>5583</fpage><lpage>5588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmcl.2015.10.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26525866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kew</surname> <given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Trube</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>A novel mechanism of activity-dependent NMDA receptor antagonism describes the effect of ifenprodil in rat cultured cortical neurones</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>497 (Pt 3)</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.1996.sp021807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9003561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khatri</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname> <given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanger</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Karakas</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Liotta</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Structural determinants and mechanism of action of a GluN2C-selective NMDA receptor positive allosteric modulator</article-title><source>Molecular Pharmacology</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.114.094516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25205677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goehring</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouaux</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>NMDA receptor structures reveal subunit arrangement and pore architecture</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>511</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25008524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lester</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahr</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>NMDA channel behavior depends on agonist affinity</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.12-02-00635.1992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1346806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malayev</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Farb</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Inhibition of the NMDA response by pregnenolone sulphate reveals subtype selective modulation of NMDA receptors by sulphated steroids</article-title><source>British Journal of Pharmacology</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjp.0704543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11861317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monaghan</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Irvine</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jane</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Pharmacological modulation of NMDA receptor activity and the advent of negative and positive allosteric modulators</article-title><source>Neurochemistry International</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2012.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22269804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monyer</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnashev</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurie</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakmann</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeburg</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Developmental and regional expression in the rat brain and functional properties of four NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0896-6273(94)90210-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7512349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullasseril</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vance</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurtkaya</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Santangelo</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vellano</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liotta</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>A subunit-selective potentiator of NR2C- and NR2D-containing NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms1085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20981015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>New advances in NMDA receptor pharmacology</article-title><source>Trends in Pharmacological Sciences</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>726</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tips.2011.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21996280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Contribution of the M1 transmembrane helix and pre-M1 region to positive allosteric modulation and gating of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors</article-title><source>Molecular Pharmacology</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.113.085209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23455314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatri</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Heldt</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Potentiation of GluN2C/D NMDA receptor subtypes in the amygdala facilitates the retention of fear and extinction learning in mice</article-title><source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2013.241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24008353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanger</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>McDaniel</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname> <given-names>LZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tankovic</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusumoto</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosobucki</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulien</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Pecha</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovski</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Aizenman</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Molecular mechanism of disease-associated mutations in the Pre-M1 helix of NMDA receptors and potential rescue pharmacology</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e1006536</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28095420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paoletti</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellone</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>NMDA receptor subunit diversity: impact on receptor properties, synaptic plasticity and disease</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn3504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23686171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papouin</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliet</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Organization, control and function of extrasynaptic NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><volume>369</volume><elocation-id>20130601</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2013.0601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25225095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrovic</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedlacek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Horak</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chodounska</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyklický</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>20-oxo-5beta-pregnan-3alpha-yl sulfate is a use-dependent NMDA receptor inhibitor</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>8439</fpage><lpage>8450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1407-05.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16162926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudolph</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoflach</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Beyond classical benzodiazepines: novel therapeutic potential of GABAA receptor subtypes</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Drug Discovery</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd3502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21799515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rusakov</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kullmann</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Extrasynaptic glutamate diffusion in the hippocampus: ultrastructural constraints, uptake, and receptor activation</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>3158</fpage><lpage>3170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.18-09-03158.1998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9547224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahlender</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Savtchouk</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Volterra</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>What do we know about gliotransmitter release from astrocytes?</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><volume>369</volume><elocation-id>20130592</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2013.0592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25225086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sans</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Petralia</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Blahos</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hell</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenthold</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>A developmental change in NMDA receptor-associated proteins at hippocampal synapses</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>1260</fpage><lpage>1271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.20-03-01260.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10648730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santangelo</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Acker</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Katzman</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Strong</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liotta</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Novel NMDA receptor modulators: an update</article-title><source>Expert Opinion on Therapeutic Patents</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1337</fpage><lpage>1352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/13543776.2012.728587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23009122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wonnacott</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1978">1978</year><article-title>Factors affecting the rate of racemization of amino acids and their significance to geochronology</article-title><source>The Journal of Organic Chemistry</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jo00395a001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steigerwald</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname> <given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenker</surname> <given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeburg</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Köhr</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>C-Terminal truncation of NR2A subunits impairs synaptic but not extrasynaptic localization of NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>4573</fpage><lpage>4581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.20-12-04573.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10844027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strong</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Prosser</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liotta</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>NMDA receptor modulators: an updated patent review (2013-2014)</article-title><source>Expert Opinion on Therapeutic Patents</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/13543776.2014.972938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25351527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swanger</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vance</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Acker</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>DiRaddo</surname> <given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bundgaard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosley</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Summer</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Menaldino</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liotta</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>A novel negative allosteric modulator selective for GluN2C/2D-containing NMDA receptors inhibits synaptic transmission in hippocampal interneurons</article-title><source>ACS Chemical Neuroscience</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acschemneuro.7b00329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29043770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tajima</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Karakas</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Simorowski</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz-Avalos</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigorieff</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Activation of NMDA receptors and the mechanism of inhibition by ifenprodil</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>534</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature17679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollmuth</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>McBain</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Menniti</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vance</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dingledine</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Glutamate receptor ion channels: structure, regulation, and function</article-title><source>Pharmacological Reviews</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/pr.109.002451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20716669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Twomey</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yelshanskaya</surname> <given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Grassucci</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobolevsky</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017a</year><article-title>Channel opening and gating mechanism in AMPA-subtype glutamate receptors</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>549</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature23479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28737760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Twomey</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yelshanskaya</surname> <given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Grassucci</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobolevsky</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017b</year><article-title>Structural bases of desensitization in AMPA receptor-auxiliary subunit complexes</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>94</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2017.04.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28472657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Twomey</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobolevsky</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Structural mechanisms of gating in ionotropic glutamate receptors</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.biochem.7b00891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29037031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vance</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>GluN1 splice variant control of GluN1/GluN2D NMDA receptors</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>590</volume><fpage>3857</fpage><lpage>3875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2012.234062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22641781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vicini</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Grayson</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Functional and pharmacological differences between recombinant N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.1998.79.2.555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9463421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vyklicky</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Krausova</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerny</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Balik</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zapotocky</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Novotny</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichnerova</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smejkalova</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaniakova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Korinek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovic</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kacer</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Horak</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chodounska</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyklicky</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Block of NMDA receptor channels by endogenous neurosteroids: implications for the agonist induced conformational states of the channel vestibule</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>10935</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep10935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26086919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellers</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupardus</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallweber</surname> <given-names>HJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Volgraf</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackos</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>A novel NMDA receptor positive allosteric modulator that acts via the transmembrane domain</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2017.04.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28457974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wootten</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Christopoulos</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sexton</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Emerging paradigms in GPCR allostery: implications for drug discovery</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Drug Discovery</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd4052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23903222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yelshanskaya</surname> <given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampson</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Narangoda</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurnikova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobolevsky</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Structural bases of noncompetitive inhibition of AMPA-subtype ionotropic glutamate receptors by antiepileptic drugs</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>1305</fpage><lpage>1315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2016.08.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27618672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yelshanskaya</surname> <given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesbahi-Vasey</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurnikova</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobolevsky</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Role of the ion channel extracellular collar in AMPA receptor gating</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>1050</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-01146-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28432359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mou</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorsett</surname> <given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Volkmann</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Menniti</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprang</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Structural basis for negative allosteric modulation of GluN2A-containing NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>1316</fpage><lpage>1329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2016.08.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27618671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Erreger</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dravid</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Conserved structural and functional control of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor gating by transmembrane domain M3</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>280</volume><fpage>29708</fpage><lpage>29716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M414215200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15970596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Paoletti</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Allosteric modulators of NMDA receptors: multiple sites and mechanisms</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Pharmacology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coph.2014.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25462287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshioka</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Goehring</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mchaourab</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouaux</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Mechanism of NMDA receptor inhibition and activation</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>165</volume><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.03.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27062927</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.057</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>Kenton J</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff id="aff5"><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;An NMDAR positive and negative allosteric modulator series share a binding site and are interconverted by methyl groups&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by Kenton Swartz as the Reviewing Editor and Richard Aldrich as the Senior Editor. The following individuals involved in review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Alexander Sobolevsky (Reviewer #1).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission. As you can see below, all three reviewers are enthusiastic about your manuscript and recommend publication in <italic>eLife</italic> once you have had the chance to address their relatively minor points; most of these can be addressed with careful editing of the manuscript. The one request for additional data concerns the open probability of a mutant that influences the activity of your allosteric ligands, which would be nice to include, but we leave this to your discretion and would accept inclusion of a discussion of this issue.</p><p>Reviewer #1:</p><p>NMDA receptors (NMDARs) are prominent elements of excitatory neurotransmission, important for learning and memory and implicated in a plethora of neurological disorders. Despite the enormous role in pathophysiology, attempts to design drugs targeting NMDARs had limited success, mainly due to a variety of accompanying side effects. Perszyk et al., describe a novel class of positive and negative allosteric modulators (PAMs and NAMs) and decipher the mechanism of their action, which suggests possibility of using this class of small molecules for future medicinal purposes. The uniqueness of the mechanism is that the small molecules of the same EU1794 scaffold, depending on decoration of the ester linkage to the scaffold by aliphatic substitutions and the NR2 subunit subtype, through binding to the same site at the ion channel extracellular collar can produce inhibition or potentiation of NMDAR-mediated currents that require receptor activation but can further be tuned by concentrations of agonist glutamate and co-agonist glycine. The new PAMs and NAMs therefore represent the first series of high potency bidirectional NMDAR modulators that have a potential to preserve NMDAR-mediated synaptic transmission, but to modulate extrasynaptic NMDARs in disease-specific ways. The study includes an impressive amount of data and the same time plenty of very elegant experiments. The experimental results are of high quality and interpretations are just.</p><p>Reviewer #2:</p><p>NMDA receptors play a central role in brain physiology and function as well as in numerous neurological disorders such as epilepsy, Alzheimer's disease, and schizophrenia to name just a small sample. The development of pharmacological tools to target NMDA receptors in the clinic as well as to understand their normal physiological function is critical. Given the wide spread distribution it is often challenging to target specific subclasses of NMDA receptor. In the present manuscript the authors address a new or modified class of pharmacological agents targeting NMDA receptors, the EU1794 series. Surprisingly certain members of this series can be interconverted from negative allosteric modulators (NAMs) to positive allosteric modulators (PAMs), or vice versa, by small changes in their chemistry. The authors do an outstanding job of characterizing these compounds and their properties that would be important to their potential use as experimental tools. The authors show that the activity of the compounds is dependent on agonist concentrations. Notable here is that some of the agents have no or only small modulatory effects at saturating concentrations but have very robust effects at sub-saturating concentrations. The authors characterize the time course of action showing that the compounds require glutamate and glycine binding before the compounds can have their modulatory effect. They identify potential sites of action for both negative and positive modulators and propose that they share overlapping sites.</p><p>The manuscript is well laid out and written-well. The conclusions are consistent with the presented data.</p><p>My only major comment is why do subtle changes in the structure of the EU1794 compounds lead to variations in modulation, either negative or positive allosteric modulation? Although the authors do a nice job of characterizing the effect of the compounds, it would be nice to have some sense of why the variation. Although the new compounds and the interconversion is interesting, it is not clear either structurally or mechanistically why they are interconverted.</p><p>Reviewer #3:</p><p>The manuscript by Perszyk et al., describes the work that involves discovery of positive and negative allosteric modulators (PAM and NAM) on NMDA receptors and characterization of the functional effects elicited by the compound binding. The compounds presented in this paper are novel in terms of compound-design and functional effects. The importance of PAM and NAM compounds for NMDA receptors in the field of neuropharmacology has been well illustrated for many years owing to their therapeutic potentials. The effort started a while ago with ifenprodil that binds an amino terminal domain (NTD) of NMDA receptors in a subtype-specific manner. In recent years, more efforts in developing a series of such compounds along with a completely new series of PAMs and NAMs have been undertaken in the field, thus, the importance of compound development for NMDA receptors is undisputable. The authors synthesized and purified enantiomers of the EU compounds and conducted thorough experiments to prove (at least at the level of pharmacology) that the binding sites for the PAM and NAM overlap by Schild-like analysis and demonstrated that a subtle difference in chemical structures can convert PAM to NAM and vice versa. They also demonstrated the binding site to be located at the tip of the transmembrane domain by extensive mutagenesis and domain truncations experiments. The overall quality of the work is high and it represents novel findings in a variety of ways (discovery of novel compounds, characterization). This manuscript contains useful information from chemistry perspective as well. Overall the work well qualifies to be published in <italic>eLife</italic>.</p><p>Results in Figure 6, especially the point mutations that reversed the effect of NAM is robust and interesting. I wonder if the authors can say more about the potential mechanism for PAM-NAM conversion. Related to this, it would be good to have a rough estimation of what the mutations do to the ion channel activity for the ones that inversed the activity. For example, what does 1a F654 do in terms of P open (rough estimation) and agonist potency since they both affect PAM/NAM activity as authors implied.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.34711.058</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #2:</p><p>[…] The manuscript is well laid out and written-well. The conclusions are consistent with the presented data.</p><p>My only major comment is why do subtle changes in the structure of the EU1794 compounds lead to variations in modulation, either negative or positive allosteric modulation? Although the authors do a nice job of characterizing the effect of the compounds, it would be nice to have some sense of why the variation. Although the new compounds and the interconversion is interesting, it is not clear either structurally or mechanistically why they are interconverted.</p></disp-quote><p>We are extremely interested in this question and are working with Hiro Furukawa to obtain structural information that would speak to the structural determinants of positive and negative allosteric modulation. This project has a long time-line, beyond the current study, as we are just now initiating co-crystallization screens.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #3:</p><p>[.] Results in Figure 6, especially the point mutations that reversed the effect of NAM is robust and interesting. I wonder if the authors can say more about the potential mechanism for PAM-NAM conversion. Related to this, it would be good to have a rough estimation of what the mutations do to the ion channel activity for the ones that inversed the activity. For example, what does 1a F654 do in terms of P open (rough estimation) and agonist potency since they both affect PAM/NAM activity as authors implied.</p></disp-quote><p>We are very interested in the mechanism of interconversion, and only have speculative hypotheses at present. We believe we need structural information to address this idea and have initiated a collaboration with a crystallographer to obtain data describing the site of action. We also have a computational program to dock ligands into space near the pre-M1 region. Neither project has progressed to a point where there is publication-ready data. However, to begin to explore ideas around this interconversion of modulator direction, we have added new data to the manuscript describing the effect of various mutations on the open probability. These data show various alterations in open probability for homologous mutations that interconvert the effect of the modulator, however no direct correlation is observed between the alteration in open probability and the alteration of modulator actions. We also continue to synthesize new derivatives, which could yield additional clues about nature of this interconversion.</p></body></sub-article></article>