<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.2" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">68336</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.68336</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Eukaryotic initiation factor EIF-3.G augments mRNA translation efficiency to regulate neuronal activity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-230351"><name><surname>Blazie</surname><given-names>Stephen M</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6701-6275</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-69622"><name><surname>Takayanagi-Kiya</surname><given-names>Seika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-230352"><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>Katherine A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-6322"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Yishi</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9371-9860</contrib-id><email>yijin@ucsd.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><institution>Section of Neurobiology, Division of Biological Sciences, University of California San Diego</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">La Jolla</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>Anne E</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Duke University School of Medicine</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>Piali</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>Brandeis University</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>29</day><month>07</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e68336</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2021-03-11"><day>11</day><month>03</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2021-07-28"><day>28</day><month>07</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a preprint at bioRxiv.</event-desc><date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2021-03-16"><day>16</day><month>03</month><year>2021</year></date><self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.03.15.435499"/></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021, Blazie et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Blazie et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-68336-v2.pdf"/><abstract><p>The translation initiation complex eIF3 imparts specialized functions to regulate protein expression. However, understanding of eIF3 activities in neurons remains limited despite widespread dysregulation of eIF3 subunits in neurological disorders. Here, we report a selective role of the <italic>C. elegans</italic> RNA-binding subunit EIF-3.G in shaping the neuronal protein landscape. We identify a missense mutation in the conserved Zinc-Finger (ZF) of EIF-3.G that acts in a gain-of-function manner to dampen neuronal hyperexcitation. Using neuron-type-specific seCLIP, we systematically mapped EIF-3.G-mRNA interactions and identified EIF-3.G occupancy on GC-rich 5′UTRs of a select set of mRNAs enriched in activity-dependent functions. We demonstrate that the ZF mutation in EIF-3.G alters translation in a 5′UTR-dependent manner. Our study reveals an in vivo mechanism for eIF3 in governing neuronal protein levels to control neuronal activity states and offers insights into how eIF3 dysregulation contributes to neurological disorders.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>neuronal excitation</kwd><kwd>5' utr</kwd><kwd>translation regulation</kwd><kwd>seizure</kwd><kwd>acetylcholine receptor</kwd><kwd>ncs-2</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd><italic>C. elegans</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NS R37 035546</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Yishi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100007911</institution-id><institution>University of California, San Diego</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NS007220</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Blazie</surname><given-names>Stephen M</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>The eIF3 translation initiation complex exerts specific regulation on neuronal protein levels by targeting mRNAs with GC-rich 5' UTR.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Protein synthesis is principally regulated by variations in the translation initiation mechanism, whereby multiple eukaryotic initiation factors (eIF1 through 6) engage elongation-competent ribosomes with the mRNA open reading frame (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Sonenberg and Hinnebusch, 2009</xref>). eIF3 is the largest translation initiation complex, composed of 13 subunits in metazoans, with versatile functions throughout the general translation initiation pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Valášek et al., 2017</xref>). Extensive biochemical and structural studies have shown that eIF3 promotes translation initiation by orchestrating effective interactions between the ribosome, target mRNA, and other eIFs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Smith et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cate, 2017</xref>). Mutations and misexpression of various subunits of eIF3 are associated with human diseases, such as cancers and neurological disorders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gomes-Duarte et al., 2018</xref>), raising the importance to advance mechanistic understanding of eIF3’s function in vivo.</p><p>Recent work has begun to reveal that different eIF3 subunits can selectively regulate translation in a manner depending on cell type, mRNA targets, and post-translational modification. Interaction of eIF3 RNA-binding subunits with specific 5′UTR stem-loop structures of mRNAs can trigger a translational switch for cell proliferation in human 293 T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2015</xref>), and can also act as a translational repressor, such as the case for human Ferritin mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Pulos-Holmes et al., 2019</xref>). Under cellular stress, such as heat shock, the eIF3 complex circumvents cap-dependent protein translation initiation and recruits ribosomes directly to m6A marks within the 5′UTR of mRNAs encoding stress response proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Meyer et al., 2015</xref>). Other specialized translation mechanisms appear to involve activities of particular eIF3 subunits that were previously hidden from view. For example, human eIF3d possesses a cryptic mRNA cap-binding function that is activated by phosphorylation and stimulates pre-initiation complex assembly on specific transcripts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lamper et al., 2020</xref>), while eIF3e specifically regulates metabolic mRNA translation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Shah et al., 2016</xref>). These findings hint that many other eIF3-guided mechanisms of cell-specific translational control await discovery.</p><p>In the nervous system, emerging evidence suggests that eIF3 subunits may have critical functions. Knockdown of multiple eIF3 subunits impairs expression of dendrite pruning factors in developing sensory neurons of <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Rode et al., 2018</xref>). In mouse brain, eIF3h directly interacts with collybistin, a conserved neuronal Rho-GEF protein underlying X-linked intellectual disability with epilepsy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Sertie et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Machado et al., 2016</xref>). In humans, altered expression of the eIF3 complex in the substantia nigra and frontal cortex correlates with Parkinson’s Disease progression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Garcia-Esparcia et al., 2015</xref>). Downregulation of mRNAs encoding eIF3 subunits is observed in a subset of motor neurons in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Cox et al., 2010</xref>). Furthermore, a single-nucleotide polymorphism located in the intron of human eIF3g elevates its mRNA levels and is associated with narcolepsy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Holm et al., 2015</xref>). While these data suggest that eIF3 function in neurons is crucial, mechanistic understanding will require experimental models enabling in vivo investigation of how eIF3 affects protein translation with neuron-type specificity.</p><p>Protein translation in <italic>C. elegans</italic> employs all conserved translation initiation factors. We have investigated the mechanisms of protein translation in response to neuronal overexcitation using a gain-of-function (<italic>gf</italic>) ion channel that arises from a missense mutation in the pore-lining domain of the acetylcholine receptor subunit ACR-2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jospin et al., 2009</xref>). The cholinergic motor neurons (ACh-MNs) in the ventral cord of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) mutants experience constitutive excitatory inputs, which gradually diminish pre-synaptic strength and cause animals to display spontaneous seizure-like convulsions and uncoordinated locomotion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jospin et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Zhou et al., 2017</xref>). <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) induces activity-dependent transcriptome changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref>). However, it is unclear how protein translation conducts the activity-dependent proteome changes that sustain function of these neurons.</p><p>Here, we demonstrate that <italic>C. elegans</italic> EIF-3.G/eIF3g regulates the translation efficiency of select mRNAs in ACh-MNs. We characterized a mutation (C130Y) in the zinc-finger of EIF-3.G that suppresses behavioral deficits of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) without disrupting general protein translation. By systematic profiling of EIF-3.G and mRNA interactions in ACh-MNs, we identified preferential binding of EIF-3.G to long and GC-rich 5'UTRs of mRNAs, many of which encode modulators of ACh-MN activity. We further provided in vivo evidence that EIF-3.G regulates the expression of two of its mRNA targets dependent on their 5′UTRs. Our findings illustrate the selectivity of EIF-3.G in augmenting mRNA translation to mediate neuronal activity changes.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>A missense mutation in EIF-3.G ameliorates convulsion behaviors caused by cholinergic hyperexcitation</title><p>We previously characterized numerous mutations that suppress convulsion and locomotion behaviors of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">McCulloch et al., 2017</xref>). One such suppressor mutation, <italic>ju807</italic>, was found to contain a single nucleotide alteration in <italic>eif-3.G,</italic> encoding subunit G of the EIF-3 complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>; see Materials and methods). <italic>C. elegans</italic> EIF-3.G is composed of 262 amino acids, sharing overall 35% or 32% sequence identity with human eIF3g and <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> TIF35 orthologs, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>). Both biochemical and structural data show that eIF3g/TIF35 proteins bind eIF3i/TIF34 through a domain in the N-terminus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Valášek et al., 2017</xref>). eIF3g/EIF-3.G also has a predicted CCHC zinc finger followed by an RNA recognition motif (RRM) at the C-terminus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>). The <italic>ju807</italic> mutation changes the second cysteine of the CCHC motif (Cys130, corresponding to Cys160 in human eIF3g) to tyrosine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Hereafter, we designate <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) as <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(C130Y) suppresses <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) convulsion behavior in the cholinergic motor neurons.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Illustration of the genomic locus of <italic>eif-3.G: Peif-3.G</italic> denotes the promoter, blue boxes are exons for coding sequences and gray for 3′UTR. Arrowhead indicates guanine to adenine change in <italic>ju807;</italic> and short line below represents a 19 bp deletion in <italic>ju1327</italic>, designated <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>), that would shift the reading frame at aa109, resulting in a premature stop (asterisk) after addition of 84aa of no known homology. (<bold>B</bold>) Illustration of EIF-3.G: shaded blue represents EIF-3.I binding region, ZF for Zinc Finger, RRM for RNA Recognition Motif. Below is a multi-species alignment of the zinc finger domain with bold residues as the CCHC motif and gray for conserved residues. <italic>ju807</italic> causes a C130Y substitution (black arrow). C127Y (red arrow, <italic>ju1840</italic>) was generated with CRISPR editing. <italic>C. elegans</italic> (<italic>C. e.</italic>; NP_001263666.1), <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (<italic>S. c.</italic>; NP_010717.1), <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> (<italic>D. m.</italic>; NP_570011.1), <italic>X. laevis</italic> (<italic>X. l.;</italic> NP_001087888.1), and <italic>H. sapiens</italic> (<italic>H.s.</italic>; AAC78728.1). (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of convulsion frequencies of animals of indicated genotypes, with the strains (left to right) as: N2, MT6241, CZ21759, CZ28495, CZ21759, CZ22977. Ex[<italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>)] transgenes (<italic>juEx7015</italic>/<italic>juEx7016</italic>) expressed full-length genomic DNA cloned from <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>). (<bold>D</bold>) Illustration of <italic>eif-3.G</italic> expression constructs: top shows the transgene expressing genomic <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+ for wild type and <italic>C130Y</italic> for <italic>ju807</italic>) with the endogenous <italic>eif-3.G</italic> promoter and 3′UTR, and coding exons in blue; bottom shows cell-type expression of <italic>eif-3.G</italic> cDNA driven by tissue-specific promoters (<italic>Pmyo-3</italic>- body muscle, <italic>Punc-25</italic>- GABAergic motor neurons, <italic>Punc-17β</italic> - cholinergic motor neurons). (<bold>E</bold>) Quantification of convulsion frequencies shows that convulsion behavior of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) double mutants is rescued by transgenes that overexpress <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+) genomic DNA or an <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+) cDNA in the ACh-MNs, but not in the GABAergic motor neurons or body muscle. Strains (left to right)- N2, CZ21759, CZ23125/ CZ23126, CZ22980/ CZ22981, CZ23791/ CZ23880, CZ22982/ CZ22983, CZ27881/ CZ27882. (<bold>F</bold>) Quantification of convulsion frequencies in animals of the indicated genotypes (left to right)- N2, CZ22917, MT6241, CZ21759, CZ28495, CZ21759, CZ21759, CZ23310, CZ26828. Data in (<bold>D-F</bold>) are shown as mean ± SEM and sample size is indicated within or above each bar. Statistics: (***) p&lt;0.001, (ns) not significant by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni’s post hoc test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata1"><label>Figure 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of convulsions per 60 s in strains of the indicated genotypes.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata2"><label>Figure 1—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of convulsions per 60 s in the indicated strains.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata3"><label>Figure 1—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of convulsions per 60 s in strains. Strain name or genotype is indicated in top row.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-data3-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>EIF-3.G is highly conserved and expressed ubiquitously.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Clustal-W sequence alignment of <italic>C. elegans</italic> EIF-3.G (NP_001263666.1) with the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (TIF-35; 32% identity; NP_010717.1) and human (eIF3g, 35% identity; AAC78728.1) orthologs. Residues identical to <italic>C. elegans</italic> EIF-3.G are shaded gray. The EIF-3.I binding region, zinc finger, RRM and RNP motifs are indicated below the corresponding sequences. The frame-shift caused by the <italic>ju1327</italic> deletion adds 85aa’s starting from the position marked by the purple arrow. The C130Y mutation (red asterisk), R-F-F residues changed to alanine in our RFF/AAA transgene construct (red boxes), and location of the Q191* mutation used to generate EIF-3.G(∆RRM) (blue arrow head) are shown. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative maximum intensity z-stack confocal images of L4 stage animals expressing GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) or GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) under the <italic>Peif-3.G</italic> promoter. GFP is visualized throughout <italic>C. elegans</italic> tissues and excluded from the gonads due to germline transgene silencing. The bright punctae in the animal midbody are autofluorescent gut granules. Scale bar = 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Motor neuron development is normal in <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) animals.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative confocal z-stack projection images of axonal commissures projecting from motor neurons of wild type or <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) single mutant L4 animals (head to the right). The quantification of axon commissure numbers in strains is shown on the right. (<bold>B</bold>) Single plane confocal images of L4 animals (head to the left) expressing GFP::SNB-1, which appear as puncta along the ventral nerve cord. Puncta quantification, shown at right, was performed in a 30 µm region anterior of the vulva (red box) in each animal. For (<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>), the number of animals used in quantification data is indicated in each bar and error bars represent ± SEM. Scales bar = 10 µm.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s2sdata1"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of axonal commissures in strains of the indicated genotypes.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-figsupp2-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s2sdata2"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of synaptic puncta in strains of the indicated genotypes.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-figsupp2-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>EIF-3.G(C130Y) modulation of convulsion behavior does not involve reduced EIF-3 complex dosage or ACR-2 expression.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Quantification of convulsion frequencies in animals of the indicated genotypes; the corresponding strains (left to right) are: MT6241, CZ27434, CZ27435, CZ21759, CZ27433, CZ27436. Error bars are ± SEM and n = 15 per sample. (ns) not significant by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni’s post-hoc test. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative images of L4 animals expressing ACR-2(WT)::GFP in the ventral nerve chord region anterior to the vulva. Quantification of fluorescence in animals (n = 8) is shown on the right. Scale bar = 10 µm. (ns) not significant by two-tailed t-test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s3sdata1"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of convulsions per 60 s in strains of the indicated genotypes.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-figsupp3-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s3sdata2"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3B</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of relative fluorescence intensity in the indicated strains.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-figsupp3-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig1-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Compared to <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) single mutants, <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals exhibited nearly wild-type movement and strongly attenuated convulsion behavior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>; <xref ref-type="video" rid="video1">Videos 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="video" rid="video3">3</xref>). <italic>acr-2(gf)</italic> animals carrying heterozygous e<italic>if-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>/<italic>+</italic>) showed partial suppression of convulsions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). Overexpression of wild type <italic>eif-3.G</italic> full-length genomic DNA in <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) double mutants restored convulsions to levels similar to <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>/+); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D–E</xref>; Materials and methods). Overexpression of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) full-length genomic DNA in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) single mutants also partially suppressed convulsions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C–D</xref>). In wild-type animals, overexpression of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+) or <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) caused no observable effects on locomotion. These data show that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) acts in a semi-dominant manner to ameliorate convulsion and uncoordinated locomotion behaviors of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>). To further test that altering the EIF-3.G zinc finger motif accounts for the observed suppression of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>), we edited the first cysteine of the CCHC motif (Cys127) to tyrosine using CRISPR-Cas9, and found that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C127Y</italic>) suppressed <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) convulsions to levels identical to <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B–C</xref>). This data provides support for the importance of the EIF-3.G zinc finger in regulation of ACh-MN activity. Hereafter, we focused our analysis on <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>).</p><media id="video1" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-68336-video1.mp4"><label>Video 1.</label><caption><title>N2 [Wild type] <italic>C. elegans</italic> movement on solid nematode growth media.</title></caption></media><media id="video2" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-68336-video2.mp4"><label>Video 2.</label><caption><title>MT6241 [<italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>)] <italic>C. elegans</italic> movement on solid nematode growth media.</title></caption></media><media id="video3" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-68336-video3.mp4"><label>Video 3.</label><caption><title>CZ21759 [<italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>)] <italic>C. elegans</italic> movement on solid nematode growth media.</title></caption></media><p>We next determined in which cell types <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) functions using cell-specific expression analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>; also see Materials and methods). <italic>acr-2(gf)</italic> phenotypes arise from a hyperactive ACR-2-containing ion channel expressed in the ventral cord cholinergic motor neurons (ACh-MNs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jospin et al., 2009</xref>). We found that overexpressing <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+) cDNA in ACh-MNs (<italic>Punc-17β</italic>) restored convulsions of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals to a similar degree as those expressing full-length <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+) under the endogenous promoter (<italic>Peif-3.G</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>). In contrast, overexpression of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+) cDNA in either ventral cord GABAergic neurons (GABA-MNs, <italic>Punc-25</italic>) or body muscle (<italic>Pmyo-3</italic>) in <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals caused no detectable effects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>). Co-expression of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+) in both ACh-MNs and GABA-MNs showed similar effects on <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals to that from expressing <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>+</italic>) in ACh-MNs alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>). Thus, <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) functions in ACh-MN to modulate <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) behaviors.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>EIF-3.G(C130Y) selectively affects translation in ACh-MNs</title><p><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) single mutants exhibit normal development, locomotion, and other behaviors (such as male mating and egg-laying) indistinguishably from wild-type animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video4">Video 4</xref>). Axon morphology and synapse number of ACh-MNs were also normal in <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A–B</xref>). To dissect how the C130Y mutation affects EIF-3.G function, we next generated a genetic null mutation (<italic>ju1327</italic>) using CRISPR editing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>; designated <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>), see Materials and methods). Homozygous <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>) animals arrested development at L1 stage, consistent with EIF-3 complex members being required for <italic>C. elegans</italic> development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Kamath et al., 2003</xref>). <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>/+); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals were indistinguishable from <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) single mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref>). We additionally tested null mutations in EIF-3.E and EIF-3.H, two essential subunits of EIF-3 complex, and found that <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals carrying heterozygous null mutations in either <italic>eif-3</italic> subunit gene showed convulsions similar to <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>/+); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A</xref>). Moreover, hemizygous <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>/<italic>0</italic>) animals are healthy at all stages and suppress behaviors of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) to levels comparable to <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref>). Reducing one copy of <italic>eif-3.H</italic>(<italic>+</italic>) or <italic>eif-3.E</italic>(<italic>+</italic>) in <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals also did not modify the suppression effect of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A</xref>). These observations suggest that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) retains sufficient function of wild-type <italic>eif-3.G</italic>, and likely affects a regulatory activity that is not dependent on EIF-3 subunit dosage.</p><media id="video4" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-68336-video4.mp4"><label>Video 4.</label><caption><title>CZ22197 [<italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>)] <italic>C. elegans</italic> movement on solid nematode growth media.</title></caption></media><p>We considered that EIF-3.G(C130Y) could alter EIF-3.G protein levels in ACh-MNs. To test this, we generated single-copy chromosomal integrated transgenes expressing EIF-3.G(WT) or EIF-3.G(C130Y) tagged with GFP at the N-terminus under the control of the endogenous <italic>eif-3.G</italic> promoter (Materials and methods and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Fluorescence from both GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) and GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) was observed in all somatic cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>). In ACh-MNs, both proteins showed cytoplasmic localization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). The GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) transgene rescued <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>) to adults (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>) and also restored convulsion behavior in the <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). In contrast, the GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) transgene reduced convulsion behavior in the <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) background. Furthermore, we introduced the GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) transgene into the <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) background and observed that this transgene rescued the arrested larvae to adults and nearly abolished convulsion behavior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). This analysis shows that GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) and GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) retain function and lends further support that <italic>eif-3.g</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) is responsible for the suppression of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>). Quantification of GFP levels in the ACh-MNs showed equivalent intensity and localization of GFP::EIF-3.G (WT and C130Y) between wild type and <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), indicating that EIF-3.G(C130Y) does not increase EIF-3.G protein stability.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) involves a selective function of EIF-3.G on translational control.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Quantification of convulsion frequency in animals expressing GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) or GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) under <italic>Peif-3.G</italic> in the indicated genetic backgrounds; and the strains (left to right) are: MT6241, CZ24729, CZ24652, CZ28497, CZ21759, CZ28107. Error bars represent ± SEM with n = 15 per sample. (***) P&lt; 0.001, (ns) not significant, by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni’s post-hoc test. (<bold>B</bold>) EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) show comparable expression in ACh-MNs. Left are representative single-plane confocal images of EIF-3.G(WT)::GFP or EIF-3.G(C130Y)::GFP driven by the <italic>Peif-3.G</italic> promoter as single-copy transgenes in L4 animals (head to the left). Red circles mark the soma of VA10, VB11, and DB7 ACh-MN, based on co-expressing a <italic>Pacr-2-mcherry</italic> marker. Scale bar = 4 µm. Right: Mean GFP fluorescence intensities (AU) in ACh-MN soma in animals of the indicated genotypes (n = 8). Each data point represents the mean intensity from VA10, VB11, and DB7 neurons in the same animal and normalized to the mean GFP::EIF-3.G intensity in a wildtype background. Error bars represent ± SEM; (ns) not significant by one-way ANOVA with Sidak’s multiple comparisons test. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative polysome profile traces from total mRNA-protein extracts of wild type and <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) single mutant animals. Vertical lines (marked by *) within traces indicate the boundaries of fraction collection. (<bold>D</bold>) Polysome::monosome (P/M) ratios calculated based on the area under the respective curves for polysomal and monosome (80S) fractions using two replicates of polysome profiles from total extracts of indicated genotypes. (ns) not significant by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni’s post-hoc test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata1"><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of convulsions per 60 s in the indicated strains.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig2-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata2"><label>Figure 2—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of relative fluorescence intensity in the indicated strains.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig2-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata3"><label>Figure 2—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of polysome to monosome ratios in wildtype(N2) and strains of the indicated genotypes.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig2-data3-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig><p>We further assessed whether <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) alters global translation by performing polysome profile analysis using whole <italic>C. elegans</italic> lysates of L4 stage animals. Both the distribution and ratio of monosomes and polysomes were similar among wild type, <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>), <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) and <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C–D</xref>), indicating that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) possesses normal function in the majority of tissues. It is possible that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) suppresses <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) by simply reducing ACR-2 translation. We tested this by examining a functional GFP-tagged ACR-2 single-copy insertion transgene (<italic>oxSi39</italic>). We observed both the levels of ACR-2::GFP fluorescence and post-synaptic localization in ACh-MNs were comparable between wild type and <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3B</xref>). These data support the conclusion that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) preferentially affects EIF-3’s function in ACh-MNs.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>The activity of EIF-3.G(C130Y) requires its RRM</title><p>The RRM located at the C-terminus of eIF3g has been shown to bind RNA in a non-specific manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hanachi et al., 1999</xref>). To address the role of the RRM in EIF-3.G’s function, we generated a transgene expressing EIF-3.G(∆RRM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Expressing EIF-3.G(∆RRM) under the endogenous promoter <italic>Peif-3.G</italic> in a wild-type background did not alter development or locomotion, and also did not rescue <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>) developmental arrest, supporting the essentiality of the EIF-3.G RRM. We then generated a transgene expressing EIF-3.G(C130Y) lacking the RRM domain (C130Y ∆RRM) in neurons of the <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). In contrast to full-length <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>), <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y ∆RRM</italic>) did not alter convulsion behavior of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>), indicating that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) function requires its RRM.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) requires the RNA-binding domain (RRM) to suppress <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) behaviors.</title><p>Top illustration of the EIF-3.G protein showing the EIF-3.I binding region (blue), zinc finger (ZF), RRM (dark grey), Q191* mutation in the EIF-3.G(∆RRM) transgene, RNP motifs (purple), and the RFF residues (bold dark blue) changed to alanine in the <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>RFF/AAA</italic>) construct. Below is an illustration of <italic>C. elegans</italic> EIF-3.I pointing to the position of E252R within the fourth WD40 domain. Bottom graph is quantification of convulsion frequency in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals expressing <italic>eif-3.G</italic> and <italic>eif-3.I</italic> variants in the nervous system (<italic>Prgef-1</italic>). The strains (left to right) are: MT6241, CZ23203/ CZ23204, CZ28152/ CZ28153, CZ23304/ CZ23305, CZ28152/ CZ28153, CZ28057/ CZ28058, CZ28064/ CZ28065. Bars represent mean convulsion frequency ± SEM and sample sizes are indicated within or above bars. (***) p&lt; 0.001, (ns) not significant, by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni’s post-hoc test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata1"><label>Figure 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of convulsions per 60 s in the indicated strains.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig3-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig><p>Studies on <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> TIF35/EIF3.G have shown that its RRM promotes scanning of the translation pre-initiation complex through structured 5′UTRs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cuchalová et al., 2010</xref>). Specifically, alanine substitution of three residues in the two ribonucleoprotein (RNP) motifs (K194 in RNP2 and L235 and F237 in RNP1) in TIF35 reduced translation of mRNA reporters carrying 5′UTRs with hairpin structures, without altering the biochemical RNA-binding activity of EIF-3.G/TIF35. Equivalent amino acid residues in <italic>C. elegans</italic> EIF-3.G correspond to R185, F225, F227, which are conserved in human (R242, F282, F284) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>). To determine whether these residues affect EIF-3.G’s function, we expressed <italic>C. elegans eif-3.G</italic> cDNA with the corresponding amino acids mutated to alanine, designated <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>RFF/AAA</italic>), in <italic>acr-2(gf)</italic> animals. We detected partial suppression of convulsion behavior in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p>It was also reported that a missense mutation (Q258R) in yeast EIF-3.I/TIF34, located in the sixth WD40 repeat, reduced the rate of pre-initiation complex scanning through 5′UTRs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cuchalová et al., 2010</xref>). To test if <italic>C. elegans eif-3.I</italic> shares similar activities, we made a mutant EIF-3.I(E252R), equivalent to yeast TIF34 (Q258R) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). In <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals, overexpressing <italic>eif-3.I</italic>(<italic>E252R</italic>), but not wild-type <italic>eif-3.I</italic>(<italic>+</italic>), caused suppression of convulsions to a similar degree as that by the <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>RFF/AAA</italic>) transgene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). These analyses suggest that attenuation of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>)-induced neuronal overexcitation may involve regulation of protein translation through modification of 5′UTR scanning rates during translation initiation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Both EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) associate with mRNA 5′UTRs in the cholinergic motor neurons</title><p>EIF-3.G may interact with specific mRNAs in the nervous system to regulate cholinergic activity. Therefore, we next searched for mRNAs that are associated with EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) in the ACh-MNs using single-end enhanced crosslinking and immunoprecipitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Van Nostrand et al., 2017</xref>). We generated single-copy transgenes expressing 3xFLAG-tagged EIF-3.G(WT), EIF-3.G(C130Y), or EIF-3.G(∆RRM) in the ACh-MNs of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals, with EIF-3.G(∆RRM) serving to detect indirect crosslinking events. We confirmed that the truncated EIF-3.G(∆RRM) transgene was expressed, but at reduced levels compared to the EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) transgenes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>). Following cross-linking and immunoprecipitation using anti-FLAG antibodies, we obtained a comparable amount of immunoprecipitated GFP::EIF-3.G proteins and obtained more reads from seCLIP on animals expressing each GFP::EIF-3.G transgene than on control animals lacking any transgene (IgG(-); see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp4">Supplementary file 4</xref>). There was a strong correlation between read clusters detected among sets of two biological replicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref>). We defined EIF-3.G-RNA crosslink sites as clusters of at least 20 high-quality reads with at least 1.5 fold change enrichment over the input control (see Materials and methods and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp5">Supplementary file 5</xref>). We further defined specific footprints of EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) by subtracting clusters detected with EIF-3.G(∆RRM) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp6">Supplementary file 6</xref>, also see Materials and methods). The EIF-3.G-specific footprints were primarily located within or near the 5′UTRs of protein-coding genes (5′UTR proximal) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A–B</xref>). In total, we detected 231 5′UTR proximal footprints of EIF-3.G(WT) or EIF-3.G(C130Y), which mapped to 225 different genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). The number of reads comprising EIF-3.G(WT) or EIF-3.G(C130Y) footprints was similar (e.g. <italic>egl-30</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>) for most of these genes. While some footprints were differentially detected between EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y), this was almost invariably due to small differences in seCLIP signal intensity (read cluster size) between samples close to the 20 reads threshold (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>), and we therefore did not further pursue its significance.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Both EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) associate with mRNA 5′UTRs in the cholinergic motor neurons.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Pie charts displaying the proportion of EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) footprints located within each gene feature. (<bold>B</bold>) seCLIP read density track of EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) footprints on the 5′UTR of <italic>egl-30</italic>, compared to the EIF-3.G(∆RRM) control. (<bold>C</bold>) Scatter plot comparing the signal intensity, in reads per million (RPM), of all 231 5′UTR proximal footprints detected in EIF-3.G(WT) or EIF-3.G(C130Y). (<bold>D</bold>) Plots show the cumulative coverage of all 5′UTR proximal (top) or 3′UTR (bottom) footprints of EIF-3.G(WT) or EIF-3.G(C130Y) relative to the start codon (top) or stop codon (bottom) position. Coverage is presented as reads per million (RPM). (<bold>E–F</bold>) Box plots comparing length and GC-content of all 5′UTR sequences of EIF-3.G target mRNAs with annotations (n = 179) to all 5′UTRs in the <italic>acr-2(gf</italic>) cholinergic neuronal transcriptome (n = 4573). Boxes are 5–95 percentile with outliers aligned in red. Statistics: (***) p&lt; 0.001, (**) p&lt; 0.01 by two-tailed Mann-Whitney test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata1"><label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>.</title><p>Number of read clusters representing footprints of EIF-3.G(WT) or EIF-3.G(C130Y) mapping to 5′UTR proximal or 3′UTR regions.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata2"><label>Figure 4—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>.</title><p>seCLIP reads for EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) 5’UTR proximal footprints represented as log<sub>2</sub>(reads per million).</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata3"><label>Figure 4—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>.</title><p>Cumulative EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) footprint coverage per base distance from the start codon (5’UTR proximal footprints) or stop codon (3’UTR footprints) represented as reads per million.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-data3-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata4"><label>Figure 4—source data 4.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>.</title><p>Length of 5’UTRs in mRNAs expressed in the ACh-MN transcriptome and EIF-3.G targets.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-data4-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata5"><label>Figure 4—source data 5.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F</xref>.</title><p>Percent GC of 5’UTRs in mRNAs expressed in the ACh-MN transcriptome and EIF-3.G targets.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-data5-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>EIF-3.G transgenes are expressed and produce similar results from replicate seCLIP experiments.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Western blotting from strains expressing each indicated 3xFLAG-tagged EIF-3.G transgene in the ACh-MNs under the Punc-17<italic>β</italic> promoter. Quantification of expression intensity relative to the actin control is shown to the right. Statistics: (*) P&lt; 0.05, (ns) not significant, one-way Anova with Bonferroni’s post hoc test. (<bold>B</bold>) Scatter plots comparing the cumulative RPM (reads per million mapped reads) mapped in genes detected between seCLIP replicates. Each dot represents a unique gene and RPM values are the total reads for all clusters mapped within the respective gene. p-Values are derived from a two-tailed Pearson’s correlation (r<sup>2</sup>). The number of genes per dataset (n) and linear fit (red line) are shown.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s1sdata1"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of band intensities from western blots using the indicated antibodies in each strain.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-figsupp1-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s1sdata2"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref>.</title><p>Number of EIF-3.G(WT), EIF-3.G(C130Y), or EIF-3.G(∆RRM) seCLIP reads mapping to each indicated gene.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-figsupp1-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>EIF-3.G associates with long and GC-rich 5′UTRs.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Pie charts show the proportion of trans-splicing (ts) among genes with 5′UTR proximal EIF-3.G footprints according to Allen et al. Unannotated genes were absent from the Allen et al. dataset. (<bold>B</bold>) Box plots compare the lengths of non-trans-spliced (blue) or trans-spliced (red) 5′UTR sequences of EIF-3.G target mRNAs (non-trans-spliced n = 57, trans-spliced n = 133) to all 5′UTRs in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> transcriptome (WS271; non-trans-spliced n = 5,970, trans-spliced n = 6,674). Boxes are 10–90 percentile with outliers in red. (<bold>C</bold>) Heat map shows 5′UTR %GC along the first 150 nts from the start codon in 10 nt bins of EIF-3.G target genes. Only genes with a 5′UTR of at least 150 nts (n = 49) are shown. Genes are ordered by one-minus Pearson hierarchical clustering. Asterisks point to example 5′UTRs with relative GC-rich sequence near the start codon (red) or closer to the distal 5′ end (blue). (<bold>D</bold>) and (<bold>E</bold>) Box plots comparing (<bold>D</bold>) length or (<bold>E</bold>) GC-content of 5′UTR sequences of HEK293 eIF3g target mRNAs (n = 255; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2016</xref>) versus all human transcriptome 5′UTRs (hg38; n = 19,914). Boxes are 5–95 percentile with outliers in red. For (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold>, and <bold>E</bold>) Statistics: (***) p&lt; 0.001, (**) p&lt; 0.01, (ns) not significant, two-tailed Mann-Whitney test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s2sdata1"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2A</xref>.</title><p>Number of EIF-3.G target genes exhibiting trans-splicing.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-figsupp2-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s2sdata2"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2B</xref>.</title><p>Length of 5’UTRs among trans-spliced or non-trans-spliced mRNAs expressed in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> transcriptome or EIF-3.G target mRNAs.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-figsupp2-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s2sdata3"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2C</xref>.</title><p>Percent GC in 10nt bins up to 150nt from the start codon for each indicated gene.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-figsupp2-data3-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s2sdata4"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2—source data 4.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2D</xref>.</title><p>Length of 5’UTRs among mRNAs expressed in the human(hg38) transcriptome or human eIF3 target mRNAs.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-figsupp2-data4-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s2sdata5"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2—source data 5.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2E</xref>.</title><p>Percent GC in 5’UTRs among mRNAs expressed in the human(hg38) transcriptome or human eIF3 target mRNAs.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-figsupp2-data5-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig4-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>In line with a recent report that the human eIF3 complex remains attached to 80S ribosomes in early elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Wagner et al., 2020</xref>), we observed the bulk of read clusters comprising EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) footprints mapping between (-)150 to (+)200 nucleotides of the start codon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). In contrast, the majority of signals comprising 3’UTR footprints of EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) were dispersed along the first 200 nucleotides downstream of the stop codon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). Overall, the footprint map shows that both EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) predominantly bind to similar locations within or near the 5′UTRs of 225 genes in the ACh-MNs, hereafter named EIF-3.G targets. Taken together with our finding that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) requires its RRM to suppress <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>), the seCLIP analysis suggests that the C130Y mutation does not dramatically alter the ability of EIF-3.G to associate with these mRNAs in the ACh-MNs.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>EIF-3.G preferentially interacts with long and GC-rich 5′UTR sequences</title><p>5′UTR sequences are widely involved in gene-specific regulation of translation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Pelletier and Sonenberg, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Leppek et al., 2018</xref>). We next assessed whether the selective role of EIF-3.G in protein translation might correlate with specific sequence features in the mRNA targets expressed in ACh-MNs by examining the length and GC-content of their 5′UTRs. In <italic>C. elegans</italic>, about 70% of mRNAs are known to undergo trans-splicing, and 5′UTRs of mRNAs with trans-splice leaders are usually short, with a median length of 29nt. We compared the EIF-3.G target gene list with a database containing a compilation of <italic>C. elegans</italic> trans-splice events from ENCODE analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Allen et al., 2011</xref>). We found that 133 of the 225 (59%) EIF-3.G targets are annotated to undergo trans-splicing, which is comparable to that of transcriptome-wide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Allen et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2A</xref>), suggesting that trans-splicing events may not contribute to EIF-3.G’s selectivity on mRNA targets. Interestingly, we found that the trans-spliced 5′UTRs of these 133 transcripts are significantly longer (median length = 43nt), compared with all trans-spliced 5′UTRs in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> transcriptome (median length = 29nt; n = 6,674) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2B</xref>). To assess the GC content for EIF-3.G mRNA targets, we then applied a threshold to the cholinergic neuronal transcriptome of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref>) defining a 5′UTR as at least 10 nucleotides upstream of ATG, and also selected the longest 5′UTR isoform per gene to avoid redundant analysis of target genes (see Materials and methods). Using this criterion, we identified a 5′UTR for 4573 different genes in the cholinergic transcriptome and for 179 of the 232 EIF-3.G targets in the ACh-MNs. The median 5′UTR among the 179 EIF-3.G target mRNAs was significantly longer (93 nt) and GC-enriched (42%), compared to the cholinergic transcriptome median (69 nt and 39% GC; n = 10,962; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E–F</xref>). We further analyzed the distribution of GC sequences in 5′UTRs, and observed non-random positioning such that some genes were relatively GC-rich near the start codon (e.g. <italic>zip-2</italic> and <italic>sec-61</italic>) and others had enrichment closer to the distal 5' end (e.g. <italic>pdf-1</italic> and <italic>kin-10</italic>), suggesting that discrete sequence elements in EIF-3.G associated transcripts may regulate translation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2C</xref>).</p><p>The incidence of long and GC-enriched 5′UTRs among EIF-3.G associated transcripts led us to speculate a major function of EIF-3.G, in addition to its necessity in general translation initiation, is in the selective regulation of translation. To extend our findings beyond <italic>C. elegans</italic>, we asked if the preferential association of EIF-3.G with these complex 5′UTRs could be conserved in mammals. We analyzed the published eIF3g PAR-CLIP sequencing data from HEK293 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2015</xref>) by comparing the 5′UTR lengths of human eIF3g target genes to all genes with 5′UTRs annotated in the hg38 genome. We found that human transcripts associated with eIF3g contained significantly longer and GC-enriched 5′UTRs than average (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2D–E</xref>). This analysis lends support for a conserved, specialized role of eIF3g in the translation of transcripts harboring complex 5′UTRs.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>EIF-3.G target mRNAs encode proteins that exhibit activity-dependent expression</title><p>To address whether EIF-3.G target mRNAs may preferentially affect specific biological processes, we performed Gene Ontology and KEGG pathway analysis. Significant GO term (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Ashburner et al., 2000</xref>) enrichment was identified in neuropeptide signaling genes (GO:0050793; 15 genes), which are known to affect <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Stawicki et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref>), and in stress response genes (GO: 0006950; 28 genes), which could modulate neuronal homeostasis or function under circuit activity changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). We also found many EIF-3.G target genes involved in protein translation and protein metabolism processes (GO:0019538; 29 genes; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). Additional enrichment was associated with metabolic components, kinase signaling, and calcium and synaptic signaling pathways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). Calcium and synaptic signaling genes included the CAMKII <italic>unc-43</italic>, and the G-proteins <italic>egl-30</italic> and <italic>goa-1,</italic> which are all known to regulate ACh-MN synaptic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Miller et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Richmond, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Treinin and Jin, 2020</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Gene network analyses of EIF-3.G target mRNAs show enrichment in activity-dependent expression.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Cytoscape network of EIF-3.G target genes with enriched GO terms (neuropeptide signaling, response to stress, and protein translation and protein metabolism) or KEGG pathways (calcium and synaptic signaling, metabolic components, MAPK-signaling, and mRNA surveillance). Enrichment p-values are derived from statistical analysis of our EIF-3.G targets (n = 225) in the PANTHER database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Mi et al., 2019</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) EIF-3.G target genes exhibiting significant transcript level changes in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) versus wild-type animals as determined from transcriptome sequencing of cholinergic neurons by McCulloch et al. PT and PM refers to protein translation and protein metabolism. Differential expression was assessed using DeSeq2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Love et al., 2014</xref>) with significance thresholds of (*) p&lt;0.05 and (**) p&lt;0.01.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata1"><label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>.</title><p>Foldchange in transcript expression in the cholinergic neuronal transcriptome of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) and wild-type animals.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig5-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig><p>To determine if expression of EIF-3.G target mRNAs is regulated in an activity-dependent manner, we next incorporated differential transcript expression data between wild type and <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) from a cholinergic neuron transcriptome dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref>). We found that 83% of EIF-3.G target mRNAs in the ACh-MNs are present in the cholinergic neuron transcriptome. Among the 45 genes exhibiting significant expression changes dependent on <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>), nearly all neuropeptide signaling transcripts (12 of 15) as well as three stress response genes were upregulated in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). Genes encoding metabolic components were variably upregulated (e.g. Glycine decarboxylate/<italic>gldc-1</italic>, aconitase/<italic>aco-1</italic>) and downregulated (e.g. glycogen phosphorylase/<italic>pygl-1</italic>, aldehyde dehydrogenase/<italic>alh-9</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). These data support the idea that wild type EIF-3.G imparts translational control to activity-dependent expression changes and that EIF-3.G(C130Y) may exert specific regulation to alter their protein expression in ACh-MNs of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>EIF-3.G modulates translation of HLH-30 and NCS-2 in hyperactive ACh-MNs</title><p>To experimentally validate that EIF-3.G regulates protein expression from its target mRNAs in the ACh-MNs, we next surveyed a number of candidate genes, chosen mainly based on the availability of transgenic reporters that contain endogenous 5′UTRs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). We identified two genes (<italic>hlh-30</italic> and <italic>ncs-2</italic>) whose expression in ACh-MNs of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals shows dependency on EIF-3.G. <italic>hlh-30</italic> produces multiple mRNA isoforms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>), which encode the <italic>C. elegans</italic> ortholog of the TFEB stress response transcription factor with broad neuroprotective roles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Decressac et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Polito et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lin et al., 2018</xref>). We observed strong seCLIP signals corresponding to EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) footprints in the 5′UTR of long isoform d, but not in isoform a (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>). The <italic>hlh-30d</italic> mRNA isoform has a 5′UTR of 190nt with 43% GC. Using computational RNA structure prediction (RNAfold), we found that the long <italic>hlh-30d</italic> 5′UTR forms strong stem-loop structures (∆G = −40.78 kcal/mol) that could affect HLH-30 translation. We examined expression of an HLH-30::EGFP fosmid reporter <italic>wgIs433</italic>, which encompasses the entire <italic>hlh-30</italic> genomic region with <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements for all mRNA isoforms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sarov et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). HLH-30::GFP was observed throughout the nervous system and primarily localized to cytoplasm in all genetic backgrounds tested. We observed significantly enhanced HLH-30::GFP signals in the ACh-MNs of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals, compared to those in wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). While <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) did not alter HLH-30::GFP, it reduced fluorescence intensity in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) to wild type levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). As <italic>hlh-30</italic> transcripts were detected at similar levels in ACh-MNs of wild type and <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref>), the enhanced HLH-30::GFP signal in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) likely reflects elevated translation upon neuronal activity changes, which is augmented by EIF-3.G. To strengthen this idea, we introduced an <italic>unc-13</italic> null allele, which blocks presynaptic release (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Richmond et al., 1999</xref>) to the above analyzed compound genetic mutants. We found that <italic>unc-13</italic>(<italic>0</italic>) abolished the enhanced HLH-30::GFP expression caused by <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). Additionally, we tested a transgenic HLH-30a::GFP reporter expressing <italic>hlh-30a</italic> cDNA driven by the 2 kb sequence upstream of that isoform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>EIF-3.G(C130Y) impairs HLH-30 expression in ACh-MNs of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Gene models of <italic>hlh-30</italic> isoforms <italic>a</italic> (pink), <italic>b</italic> (blue), and <italic>d</italic> (green), with presumptive promoters for each isoform depicted as right-pointing arrows and the 5′UTR of <italic>isoform d</italic> in green to the right of its promoter. (<bold>B</bold>) seCLIP read density tracks of footprints on the 5′ end of <italic>hlh-30 isoform b</italic> and <italic>d</italic> (left) and the 5′ end of <italic>hlh-30 isoform a</italic> (right) in each indicated EIF-3.G dataset. Purple arrows show footprints on the 5′UTR of <italic>hlh-30 isoform d.</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) Top: Illustration of the <italic>wgIs433</italic> fosmid locus with <italic>hlh-30</italic> coding exons in black and 5′UTR of <italic>isoform d</italic> in green to the right of the promoter. Bottom: Representative single-plane confocal images of the fosmid translational reporter <italic>wgIs433</italic>[<italic>hlh-30</italic>::EGFP::3xFLAG] in ACh-MNs in animals of indicated genotypes. Quantification of GFP intensity is shown on the right (n = eight for each genotype). Animals are oriented with anterior to the left. Scale bar = 4 µm. Red dashes indicate labeled ACh-MN soma. Each data point is the average fluorescence intensity quantified from the three ACh-MN soma per animal and normalized to the mean intensity obtained from <italic>wgIs433</italic> in the wild type background. Statistics: (***) p&lt; 0.001, (ns) not significant, one-way Anova with Bonferroni’s post hoc test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6sdata1"><label>Figure 6—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of relative fluorescence intensity in strains of the indicated genotypes.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig6-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig6-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>EIF-3.G (C130Y) has no effect on translation of <italic>hlh-30.a</italic> in the ACh-MNs.</title><p>Representative single-plane confocal images of <italic>hlh-30a</italic> isoform-specific reporter (<italic>sqIs17</italic>, with the expression construct illustrated above) in ACh-MNs in animals of the indicated genotypes. Scale bar = 4 µm. Average GFP intensities quantified from the soma of ACh-MNs in animals (n = 8) expressing <italic>hlh-30a</italic>::GFP are shown to the right. Data are normalized to the mean <italic>hlh-30a</italic>::GFP fluorescence in a wild-type background. Red dashes indicate positions of labeled ACh-MN soma. Statistics: (***) p&lt; 0.001, (ns) not significant, one-way Anova with Bonferroni’s post hoc test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6s1sdata1"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of relative fluorescence intensity in strains of the indicated genotypes.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig6-figsupp1-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig6-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>We found that HLH-30a::GFP intensity was comparable between <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) and <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). These data strengthen the conclusion that enhanced HLH-30 translation in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) partly involves the complex 5′UTR of <italic>hlh-30d</italic>.</p><p>The Neuronal Calcium Sensor protein encoded by <italic>ncs-2</italic> promotes calcium-dependent signaling in ACh-MNs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Zhou et al., 2017</xref>). We identified strong and specific association of EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) overlapping the 5′UTR of <italic>ncs-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). To evaluate NCS-2 expression, we examined a single-copy translational reporter (<italic>juSi260</italic>) expressing NCS-2::GFP under its endogenous promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Zhou et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>). NCS-2::GFP localized primarily to the neuronal processes in ventral nerve cord, because of the N-terminal myristoylation motif. Quantification of NCS-2::GFP showed that the fluorescence intensity in <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) double mutants was significantly reduced, compared to those in wild type, <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>), and <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>). <italic>ncs-2</italic> mRNA is SL1 trans-spliced, and the mature 5′UTR has 37 nt that is especially abundant in GC nucleotides (47% GC) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>). Moreover, the <italic>ncs-2</italic> 5′UTR sequence is highly conserved with other nematode species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1A</xref>). By RNAfold prediction, we found this sequence could form a strong stem-loop structure (∆G = −5.10 kcal/mol). To test if NCS-2::GFP expression was regulated specifically through its 5′UTR, we replaced it with the 5′UTR of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>, which is comparatively reduced in GC-content (37% GC) and with much less folding stability (∆ = −1.95 kcal/mol) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref>). The <italic>eif-3.G</italic> 5′UTR is also less conserved across nematodes compared to that of <italic>ncs-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1A</xref>). We found that the NCS-2::GFP reporter with the 5′UTR of <italic>eif-3.G</italic> was expressed at similar levels in all genetic backgrounds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Regulation of NCS-2 expression by EIF-3.G depends on its GC-rich 5′UTR.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Illustration of the <italic>ncs-2</italic> genomic region. Dark blue represents 5′UTR, green boxes are coding exons, and gray is the 3′UTR. The inset below shows the read density track of seCLIP footprints on the 5′ region of <italic>ncs-2</italic> mRNA. (<bold>B</bold>) Top: Schematic of the NCS-2(cDNA)::GFP translation reporter, including its 5′UTR (dark blue), driven by the 4 kb promoter <italic>Pncs-2</italic>. The 5′UTR sequences are GC rich (purple). <italic>Bottom:</italic> Representative single-plane confocal images of NCS-2::GFP in ventral nerve chord processes in young adult animals of the indicated genotypes. GFP intensity quantification is shown to the right. (<bold>C</bold>) Top: The <italic>ncs-2</italic>(5′UTR mutant)::GFP translational reporter has the 5′UTR of <italic>eif-3.G</italic> (red boxed sequence) replacing the <italic>ncs-2</italic> 5′UTR, driven by <italic>Pncs-2. Bottom:</italic> Representative single-plane confocal images of ventral nerve chord processes expressing the NCS-2(5′UTR mutant)::GFP translation reporter in young adult animals of the indicated genotypes. GFP intensity quantification is shown to the right. For (B) and (C), data points are normalized to the average fluorescence intensity of the respective translation reporter in the wild-type background. ROIs used for fluorescence quantification are boxed. Scale bar = 15 µm. Statistics: (**) P&lt; 0.01, (ns) not significant by one-way Anova with Bonferroni’s post hoc test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata1"><label>Figure 7—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of relative fluorescence intensity in strains of the indicated genotypes.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig7-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata2"><label>Figure 7—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref>.</title><p>Quantification of relative fluorescence intensity in the indicated strains.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig7-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig7-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>EIF-3.G(C130Y) reduces NCS-2 expression in the ACh-MNs of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals dependent on its conserved 5′UTR.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Plot shows conservation of nucleotides (by phyloP135way scores) in the 5′UTR sequences of <italic>ncs-2</italic> (blue) and <italic>eif-3.G</italic> (red), with higher scores indicating greater conservation. Genomic position (x-axis) is relative to the start codon (AUG). The horizontal dashed line marks PhyloP score = 0. (<bold>B</bold>) Top: Schematic of the <italic>Pncs-2</italic>::GFP translation reporter containing the endogenous GC-rich (purple) <italic>ncs-2</italic> 5′UTR and the first 4aa of NCS-2 followed by GFP and driven by the <italic>Pncs-2</italic> promoter. <italic>Bottom:</italic> Representative single-plane confocal images of <italic>Pncs-2</italic>::GFP expression in the VA10, VB11, DB7 soma in animals of the indicated genotypes. GFP intensity quantification are shown to the right (n = 8). (<bold>C</bold>) Top: The <italic>Pncs-2</italic>(5′UTR mutant)::GFP translation reporter contains the 5′UTR of <italic>eif-3.G</italic> (red, GC content is purple), followed by the <italic>ncs-2</italic> CDS 5′ end. <italic>Bottom:</italic> Representative single-plane confocal images of <italic>Pncs-2</italic>(5′UTR mutant)::GFP in VA10, VB11, DB7 soma in the indicated genetic backgrounds. GFP intensity quantification are shown to the right (n = 8). For GFP quantification in panels (B) and (C), data points are normalized to the mean intensity of the respective reporter in the wild type background. Red dashes indicate positions of labeled ACh-MN soma. Scale bar = 15 µm. Statistics: (***) p&lt; 0.001, (ns) not significant by one-way Anova with Bonferroni’s post hoc test.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7s1sdata1"><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Quantification of relative fluorescence intensity in the indicated strains.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig7-figsupp1-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7s1sdata2"><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Quantification of relative fluorescence intensity in the indicated strains.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig7-figsupp1-data2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-68336-fig7-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>To further determine the effects of the <italic>ncs-2</italic> 5′UTR in protein translation with neuronal type resolution, we generated a reporter in which the GFP coding sequence was fused in-frame after the first four amino acids of NCS-2, which retains the <italic>ncs-2</italic> 5′UTR but disrupts the myristoylation motif, thereby enabling visualization of NCS-2 in ACh-MNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Quantification of GFP fluorescence in the cell bodies of VA10, VB11, and DB7 ACh-MN showed significantly reduced expression in <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B</xref>). In contrast, a similar reporter but with the 5′UTR of <italic>eif-3.G</italic> displayed similar GFP levels in all genetic backgrounds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1C</xref>). Therefore, we conclude that <italic>eif-3.G</italic> regulates NCS-2 expression in the ACh-MNs through a mechanism involving its 5′UTR sequence.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The eIF3 complex has been extensively studied for its essential roles in general translation initiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cate, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Valášek et al., 2017</xref>). However, recent work gives support to the idea that eIF3 is also key to many of the specialized translational control mechanisms needed for tissue plasticity in vivo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Shah et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Rode et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lamper et al., 2020</xref>). Our work expands the landscape of eIF3’s regulatory functions, revealing an in vivo role of the eIF3g subunit in stimulating the translation of proteins that mediate neuronal activity changes.</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>EIF-3.G ensures the efficient translation of mRNAs with GC-rich 5′UTRs</title><p>Our study is the first application of seCLIP-seq to map transcriptome-wide protein binding sites in a specific neuronal subtype (ACh-MNs) in <italic>C. elegans</italic>. With stringent thresholding, we identified 225 genes with strong EIF-3.G occupancy at mRNA 5′ ends. We find that EIF-3.G generally associates with mRNAs harboring long and GC-rich 5′UTRs, implying its RNA-binding function is selective for stimulating translation initiation on 5′ leaders prone to secondary structure or other forms of translation regulation. Our data provide in vivo support to the finding that yeast eIF3g/TIF35 promotes scanning through 5′UTRs with stem-loop structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cuchalová et al., 2010</xref>). The RRM of yeast eIF3g/TIF35 also promotes re-initiation of 40S ribosomes upon terminating at uORF stop codons on GCN4, thereby allowing efficient induction of genes whose translation is regulated by uORFs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cuchalová et al., 2010</xref>). We did not observe uORFs in the 5′UTRs of <italic>ncs-2</italic> or <italic>hlh-30</italic>, suggesting that at least for these mRNAs, <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) involves reduced scanning through secondary structures or other yet undefined regulatory sequence elements.</p><p>It is worth noting that we also found EIF-3.G footprints in 3′UTRs, which could reflect molecular crosstalk between translation initiation and 3′UTR factors, given their proximity in the closed loop translation model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Imataka et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Wells et al., 1998</xref>). EIF-3.G might anchor the closed-loop mRNA form that stimulates multiple rounds of translation, as was shown to be the case with eIF3h (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Choe et al., 2018</xref>). It is also possible that EIF-3.G cooperates with 3′UTR interacting factors that regulate gene expression, as several <italic>C. elegans</italic> translation initiation factors co-immunoprecipitated with the miRISC complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Zhang et al., 2007</xref>) and accumulating evidence supports interplay between various translation factors and RISC proteins that mediate translational repression by microRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Ricci et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Fukaya et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Gu et al., 2014</xref>). Thus, further analysis is needed to examine the biological meaning of EIF-3.G association with 3′UTRs.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>The EIF-3.G zinc finger conveys a selective function to translation initiation</title><p>The function of the zinc finger of eIF3g remains undefined. Through analysis of EIF-3.G(C130Y), our data provides in vivo insights that the zinc finger contributes to translation efficiency of mRNAs harboring complex 5′UTRs. We establish that EIF-3.G(C130Y) behaves as a genetic gain-of-function mutation without disrupting EIF-3 assembly or otherwise impairing general translation, measured by both polysome levels and the health of cells, tissues, and animals. Additionally, mutating a different cysteine within the zinc finger (C127Y) causes equivalent effects, further strengthening the important role of the entire zinc finger. The effect of EIF-3.G(C130Y) on <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) behaviors depends on the RRM, suggesting that association with mRNA after assembly of the pre-initiation complex is required for EIF-3.G(C130Y) function. While we did not observe significant mis-positioning of EIF-3.G-mRNA interactions by EIF-3.G(C130Y), we acknowledge that seCLIP may not have the resolution required to reveal subtle differences in crosslinking sites caused by the C130Y alteration. Together, our data is consistent with a model where EIF-3.G(C130Y) imposes a translational stall after EIF-3 complex assembly and mRNA recruitment. In this view, we speculate that the zinc finger of EIF-3.G mediates interactions with other proteins, such as the ribosome, that critically regulate translation events after mRNA binding. In support of this model, yeast eIF3g/TIF35 was found to directly bind to small ribosomal protein RPS-3, though the molecular basis for mediating this interaction is not identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cuchalová et al., 2010</xref>). Further studies are required to address the precise molecular mechanism by which the EIF-3.G zinc finger imparts regulatory control over translation initiation.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>EIF-3.G targets the translation of mRNAs that modulate neuronal function</title><p>Our study was driven by the genetic evidence that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) ameliorates convulsion behavior caused by the hyperactive ion channel ACR-2(GF). We show that EIF-3.G(C130Y) retains essential EIF-3.G function, yet it alters protein translation on select mRNAs in hyperactive ACh-MNs, as evidenced by its effects on NCS-2 and HLH-30 expression. We previously reported that complete loss-of-function of <italic>ncs-2</italic> strongly suppresses <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) behaviors to a similar degree as <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Zhou et al., 2017</xref>). However, 50% reduction of <italic>ncs-2</italic> expression does not cause detectable consequences and complete loss-of-function in <italic>hlh-30</italic> also has no effects in either wild type or <italic>acr-2(gf)</italic>. Thus, the small reduction of NCS-2 and HLH-30 waged by <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) is unlikely to account for the full extent of phenotypic suppression of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>). Our seCLIP data also revealed EIF-3.G interactions with many other genes that differentially impact <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) behavior (e.g. neuropeptide <italic>flp-18</italic>, endopeptidase <italic>egl-3</italic>) and cholinergic activity (e.g. G proteins <italic>goa-1</italic>, <italic>egl-30</italic>). Interestingly, many of the pre-synaptic genes that regulate <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) behavior, such as <italic>unc-13</italic>/Munc13, <italic>unc-17/VAChT</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Zhou et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Takayanagi-Kiya et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">McCulloch et al., 2017</xref>), do not have EIF-3.G footprints. Thus, our data is consistent with a model where <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) ameliorates behaviors of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) through the cumulative changes of select ACh-MN activity regulators.</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title><italic>eif-3.G</italic> function may be specialized for activity-dependent gene expression</title><p>The eIF3 complex is widely implicated in brain disorders, and deregulated eIF3g is specifically linked to narcolepsy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gomes-Duarte et al., 2018</xref>). However, given the essential role of eIF3 in protein translation in all tissues, investigation of its functions in the nervous system remains limited. Our results reveal that EIF-3.G permits normal activity-dependent protein expression changes, and suggest that dysregulated EIF-3.G might potentiate aberrant neuronal behavior in disorders such as epilepsy by altering the neuronal protein landscape. It is worth noting that pore-lining mutations in human nicotinic receptors that occur at similar positions as <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) are causally linked to epilepsy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Xu et al., 2011</xref>). We speculate that EIF-3.G may be a potential target for intervention of disorders involving abnormal neurological activity.</p><p>In summary, our findings echo the general notion that fine-tuning the activity of essential cellular machinery, such as ribosomes and translation complexes holds the key to balance cellular proteome under dynamic environmental challenges or disease conditions. Emerging studies from cell lines show that stress conditions can induce post-translational modification of eIF3 subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lamper et al., 2020</xref>) or cap-independent interactions with mRNAs to modify proteomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Meyer et al., 2015</xref>). Through characterization of the G subunit of eIF3, we reveal the first mechanistic insights into how the eIF3 complex regulates neuronal activity. It is likely that individual eIF3 subunits could each possess unique functions relevant in certain contexts, altogether providing the eIF3 complex with extensive utility to remodel the proteome in response to changing cellular environments.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Reagent type <break/>(species) or resource</th><th valign="top">Designation</th><th valign="top">Source or reference</th><th valign="top">Identifiers</th><th valign="top">Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">anti-FLAG (Rabbit)</td><td valign="top">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# F7425, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_439687">AB_439687</ext-link></td><td valign="top">WB (1:2000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">anti-Actin clone C4 (Mouse monoclonal)</td><td valign="top">MP Biomedicals</td><td valign="top">Cat# 08691002, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2335304">AB_2335304</ext-link></td><td valign="top">WB (1:2000)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Antibody</td><td valign="top">Anti-FLAG M2 Magnetic Beads</td><td valign="top">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td valign="top">Cat# M8823, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2637089">AB_2637089</ext-link></td><td valign="top">IP</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant protein reagent</td><td valign="top">Cas9-NLS (purified protein)</td><td valign="top">UC Berkely QB3</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>+</italic></td><td valign="top">CGC</td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/CGC_N2">CGC_N2</ext-link></td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jospin et al., 2009</xref></td><td valign="top">MT6241</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ22197</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1840</italic>) II</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28494</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ21759</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1840</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28495</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1327</italic>) / mnC1 II</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ22974</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7015</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ22976</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7016</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ22977</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807</italic>) I;<italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7045</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23125</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807) II</italic>; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7046</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23126</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807) II; acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7019</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ22980</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807) II; acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7020</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ22981</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807) II</italic>; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7439</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23791</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807) II</italic>; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7440</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23880</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807) II</italic>; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7021</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ22982</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807) II</italic>; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7022</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ22983</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx8062</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27881</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx8063</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27882</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1327</italic>) /mnC1 II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23310</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) / <italic>eif-3</italic>.<italic>G</italic>(<italic>ju1327</italic>) II</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ25714</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) / <italic>eif-3</italic>.<italic>G</italic>(<italic>ju1327</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26828</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi32</italic>0 IV</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ24063</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1327</italic>) /mnC1 II; <italic>juSi3</italic>20 IV</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ24079</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi32</italic>0 IV; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ24729</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807) II; juSi32</italic>0 IV; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28107</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi331</italic> IV</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ24651</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi331</italic> IV; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ24652</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1327</italic>) / mnC1 II; <italic>juSi331</italic> IV; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28497</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juIs14</italic> IV</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Wang et al., 2017</xref></td><td valign="top">CZ631</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>juIs14</italic> IV</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ24161</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juIs14</italic> IV; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref></td><td valign="top">CZ5808</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807) II; juIs14</italic> IV; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ8905</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>nuIs94</italic></td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Hallam et al., 2000</xref></td><td valign="top">KP2229</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807</italic>) II; <italic>nuIs94</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ24021</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>nuIs94</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ5815</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>)X; <italic>nuIs94</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ24021</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.E</italic>(<italic>ok2607</italic>) I / hT2 I,III; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27434</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.E</italic>(<italic>ok2607</italic>) I / hT2 I, III; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420)</italic> X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27433</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.H</italic>(<italic>ok1353</italic>) I / hT2 I, III; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27435</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.H</italic>(<italic>ok1353</italic>) I / hT2 I, III; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420)</italic> X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27436</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>oxSi3</italic>9 IV</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Qi et al., 2013</xref></td><td valign="top">CZ12338</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II; <italic>oxSi3</italic>9 IV</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23854</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7056</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23203</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7057</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23204</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; j<italic>uEx8100</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28152</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx8101</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28153</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juEx7113</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26777</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7114</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23304</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7115</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23305</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx8095</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28066</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx8096</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28067</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx8087</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28057</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx8088</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28058</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx8089</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28064</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx8090</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28065</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>unc-119</italic>(<italic>tm4063</italic>) III; <italic>wgIs433</italic></td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sarov et al., 2006</xref></td><td valign="top">OP433</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II; <italic>unc-119</italic>(<italic>tm4063</italic>)III; <italic>wgIs433</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28145</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2(n2420) X; unc-119</italic>(<italic>tm4063</italic>) III; <italic>wgIs433</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27913</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II<italic>; unc-119</italic>(<italic>tm4063</italic>) III; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>wgIs433</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27914</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>sqIs17</italic></td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Dittman and Kaplan, 2006</xref></td><td valign="top">MAH240</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>sqIs17</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28334</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>sqIs17</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28212</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>sqIs17</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28218</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>unc-13(s69)</italic> I; <italic>wgIs433</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28491</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>unc-13(s69)</italic> I; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>wgIs433</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28492</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>unc-13(s69)</italic> I; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>wgIs433</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28493</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi260 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Zhou et al., 2017</xref></td><td valign="top">CZ22459</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi260 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ23225</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi260 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ22345</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi260 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28110</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi391 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28213</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi391 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28340</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi391 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I;<italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28252</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi391 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I;<italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28253</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi392 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28277</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi392 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I;<italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28312</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi392 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28291</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi392 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28292</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi393 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28278</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi393 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28311</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi393 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28293</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi393 ncs-2</italic>(<italic>tm1943</italic>) I; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28294</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juEx2045</italic></td><td valign="top">---</td><td valign="top">CZ9635</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>hlh-30(tm1978) IV</italic></td><td valign="top">CGC</td><td valign="top">CZ23321</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>hlh-30(tm1978) IV; acr-2(n2420) X</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28174</td><td valign="top">Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II; <italic>hlh-30(tm1978) IV; acr-2(n2420) X</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28175</td><td valign="top">Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1327</italic>) II /mnC1; <italic>juSi363</italic> IV; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26759</td><td valign="top">Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1327</italic>) II / mnC1 II; <italic>juSi366</italic> IV; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26760</td><td valign="top">Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi364</italic> IV; <italic>acr-</italic>2(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26494</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>)II <italic>juSi364</italic> IV; <italic>acr-</italic>2(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26243</td><td valign="top">Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi365</italic> IV</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26588</td><td valign="top">Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>juSi365 IV; acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26565</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi365</italic> IV; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26566</td><td valign="top">Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi368</italic> IV</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26656</td><td valign="top">Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juSi368</italic> IV; <italic>acr-</italic>2<italic>(n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26623</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>juSi368 IV; acr-</italic>2(<italic>n242</italic>0) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ26480</td><td valign="top">Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>wgIs506</italic></td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sarov et al., 2006</xref></td><td valign="top">OP506</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>wgIs506</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27926</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>wgIs506</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27927</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>dhc-1::GFP(it45)</italic> I</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lapierre et al., 2013</xref></td><td valign="top">OD2955</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>dhc-1::GFP(it45)</italic> I; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27858</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent (<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>dhc-1::GFP(it45)</italic> I; <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju807</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27859</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>wgIs432</italic></td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sarov et al., 2006</xref></td><td valign="top">OP432</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X<italic>; wgIs432</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27915</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X<italic>; wgIs432</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28021</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>wgIs638</italic></td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sarov et al., 2006</xref></td><td valign="top">OP638</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>unc-119(tm4063)</italic> III;<italic>acr-2(n2420)</italic> X; <italic>wgIs638</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28108</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II; <italic>acr-2(n2420)</italic> X; <italic>wgIs638</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ27916</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>let-607(tm1423)</italic> I; <italic>unc-119</italic>(<italic>ed3</italic>) III; <italic>vrIs121</italic></td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sarov et al., 2006</xref></td><td valign="top">YL651</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II<italic>; let-607(tm1423)</italic> I; <italic>unc-119</italic>(<italic>ed3</italic>) III; <italic>vrIs121</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28143</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2(n2420)</italic> X<italic>; let-607(tm1423)</italic> I;<italic>unc-119</italic>(<italic>ed3</italic>) III; <italic>vrIs121</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28119</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic> II<italic>; acr-2(n2420) X; let-607(tm1423)</italic> I; <italic>unc-119</italic>(<italic>ed3</italic>) III; <italic>vrIs121</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28111</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juIs172</italic></td><td valign="top">CGC</td><td valign="top">EE86</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>egl-30(md186)</italic> I;<italic>dpy-20(e1282ts)</italic> IV; <italic>syIs105</italic></td><td valign="top">CGC</td><td valign="top">PS4263</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>juEx7964</italic></td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref></td><td valign="top">CZ27420</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7964</italic></td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref></td><td valign="top">CZ27217</td><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>C. elegans</italic>)</td><td valign="top"><italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) II; <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>n2420</italic>) X; <italic>juEx7964</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top">CZ28109</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">pCZGY2729</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Andrusiak et al., 2019</xref></td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/Addgene_135096">Addgene_135096</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Site-specific insertion using CRISPR/Cas9 editing of <italic>C. elegans</italic> ChrIV</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">pCZGY2750</td><td valign="top"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Andrusiak et al., 2019</xref></td><td valign="top">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/Addgene_135094">Addgene_135094</ext-link></td><td valign="top">Expresses Cas9 and sgRNA for editing of <italic>C. elegans</italic> ChrIV</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">pCZGY2727</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Site-specific insertion using CRISPR/Cas9 editing of <italic>C. elegans</italic> ChrI</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Recombinant DNA reagent (plasmid)</td><td valign="top">pCZGY2748</td><td valign="top">This work</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Expresses Cas9 and sgRNA for editing of <italic>C. elegans</italic> ChrI</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title><italic>C. elegans</italic> genetics</title><p>All <italic>C. elegans</italic> strains were maintained at 20°C on nematode growth media (NGM) plates seeded with OP50 bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Brenner, 1974</xref>). Compound mutants were generated using standard <italic>C. elegans</italic> genetic procedures and strain genotypes are listed in key resource table and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>. Primers for genotyping are in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Identification of <italic>eif-3.G(ju807)</italic></title><p>We employed a custom workflow on the GALAXY platform to identify SNPs unique to strains containing suppressor mutations of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>), compared to the N2 reference strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">McCulloch et al., 2017</xref>). Following SNP mapping using genetic recombinants, we located <italic>ju807</italic> to <italic>eif-3.G</italic> on chromosome II. We then performed transgenic expression experiments and found that both over-expression and single-copy expression of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+) in <italic>ju807; acr-2(gf)</italic> animals restored convulsions.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Quantification of convulsion behavior</title><p>Convulsions were defined as contractions that briefly shorten animal body length, as previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jospin et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="video" rid="video2">Video 2</xref>). L4 larvae were cultured overnight on fresh NGM plates seeded with OP50 bacteria at 20°C. The following day, each young adult was moved to a fresh seeded plate, and after climatized for 90 s, convulsions were counted over a subsequent 90 s. The average convulsion frequency represented data over 60 s. All statistical tests were performed using GraphPad Prism6 software and p-values &lt;0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>CRISPR-mediated genome editing</title><p>We used a previously described method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Dickinson et al., 2013</xref>) with minor modifications to generate <italic>eif-3.G(ju1327)</italic> deletion allele. Briefly, we designed sgRNA target sequence <sc><named-content content-type="sequence">CAATTCACAAGAAATCGCGC</named-content></sc>, and cloned it into a Cas9-sgRNA expression construct pSK136 (derived from pDD162, with site-directed mutagenesis). A DNA mixture containing 50 ng/µl pSK136, 1 ng/µl <italic>Pmyo-2::mCherry</italic> (pCFJ90), and 50 ng/µl 100 bp ladder (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) was microinjected into N2 adults. We screened F2 progenies from F1 animals carrying the co-injection marker for deletions in <italic>eif-3.G</italic> and identified a 19 bp deletion, designated <italic>ju1327</italic>. Heterozygous <italic>ju1327</italic> was twice outcrossed to N2 and then crossed to the <italic>mnC1</italic> balancer for stable strain maintenance (CZ22974).</p><p>The <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1840</italic>) allele, which causes a C127Y mutation in EIF-3.G, was generated using a co-CRISPR genome editing method with <italic>unc-58</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) as a selection marker (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Paix et al., 2017</xref>). We microinjected a Cas9 complex containing the sgRNA sequence <named-content content-type="sequence">GGTCGTTTCCTTTGCAATGA</named-content>, a DNA repair template incorporating TAT (encoding Y127) in place of TGC (C127), and a previously described sgRNA and repair template for <italic>unc-58</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) into N2 adult hermaphrodites. We genotyped for <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1840</italic>) among heterozygous <italic>unc-58</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) F1 progeny and subsequently identified F2 animals homozygous for <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>ju1840</italic>) and <italic>unc-58</italic>(<italic>+</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Molecular biology and transgenesis</title><p>All transgene constructs were cloned using the Gateway cloning system (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) or Gibson Assembly (NEB, Ipswich, MA), unless otherwise noted. Primers used in their construction are detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp3">Supplementary file 3</xref>. For single-copy insertion transgenes, we used a previously described CRISPR/Cas9 method to integrate a single genomic copy on chromosome IV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Andrusiak et al., 2019</xref>). For extrachromosomal transgenes, we microinjected a DNA mixture containing 2 ng/µl transgene plasmid, 2.5 ng/µl pCFJ90(<italic>Pmyo-2</italic>::mCherry), and 50 ng/µl 100 bp ladder (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) into young adults, following standard procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Mello et al., 1991</xref>).</p><p>To generate the <italic>eif-3.G(+)</italic> or <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) genomic constructs (pCZGY3006 or pCZGY3007), we amplified a 2223 bp region from genomic DNA of N2 or CZ21759 <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>), respectively, which includes 1714 bp upstream of the start codon of isoform A (F22B5.2a.1) and 331 bp downstream of the stop codon, and cloned the amplicon into the PCR8 vector (Invitrogen, CA).</p><p>To generate all <italic>eif-3.G</italic> cDNA expression clones, we made mixed-stage cDNA libraries with poly-dT primer for N2 or CZ21759 using Superscript III (ThermoFisher Scientific, San Diego, CA). We then amplified and <italic>eif-3.G</italic> cDNA using primers for the SL1 trans-splice leader (YJ74) and <italic>eif-3.G</italic> isoform A 3′UTR (YJ11560) and Phusion polymerase (Thermo Fisher Scientific, San Diego, CA). The cDNA clones in PCR8 vector were then used to generate tissue-specific expression constructs using Gateway cloning destination vectors (pCZGY1091 for <italic>Punc-17β</italic>, pCZGY925 for <italic>Pmyo-3</italic>, pCZGY66 for <italic>Prgef-1</italic>, and pCZGY80 for <italic>Punc-25</italic>).</p><p>We used PCR site-directed mutagenesis, in which the nucleotide changes are introduced by the primers to generate the <italic>Prgef-1::eif-3.G</italic>(∆RRM) and <italic>Prgef-1::eif-3.G</italic>(C130Y ∆RRM) constructs (pCZGY3026 and pCZGY3027, respectively) with primers YJ11561 and YJ11562 on the templates pCZGY2715 and pCZGY2716, respectively. The <italic>Prgef-1::eif-3.G</italic>(RFF/AAA) construct (pCZGY3512) was generated by two rounds site directed PCR mutagenesis on pCZGY3010, first using primers YJ12463 and YJ12464, then primers YJ12465 and YJ12466. To generate <italic>Pref-1::eif-3.I</italic>(+) (pCZGY3508), we amplified <italic>eif-3.I</italic> cDNA from N2 cDNA libraries using primers YJ12453 and YJ12454, and used Gibson Assembly to clone into the pCZGY66 backbone containing <italic>Prgef-1</italic>. We then performed site-directed mutagenesis on pCZGY3508 using primers YJ12457 and YJ12458 to generate the <italic>Prgef-1::eif-3.I</italic>(<italic>Q252R</italic>) construct (pCZGY3509).</p><p>We generated the GFP::EIF-3.G clones pCZGY3018 and pCZGY3019 via Gibson assembly, using <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+) or <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) cDNA amplified using primers YJ12604 and YJ12605, and the GFP-coding DNA amplified using primers YJ12602 and YJ12603.</p><p>To generate <italic>Punc-17β</italic>::EIF-3.G::3xFLAG::SL2::GFP constructs (pCZGY3538 for WT, pCZGY3539 for C130Y, and pCZGY3540 for ∆RRM) used in seCLIP experiments, <italic>Punc-17β</italic> promoter was amplified from pCZGY1091 using primers YJ12164 and YJ12418, each <italic>eif-3.G</italic> cDNA (wild type, C130Y, or ∆RRM) was amplified with an N-terminal 3xFLAG sequence from subclones using the primers YJ12419 and YJ12420, SL2 trans-splice sequence was amplified from N2 genomic DNA using primers YJ12421 and YJ12422, and GFP was amplified from pCZGY3018 using primers YJ12423 and YJ12424. These fragments were then Gibson Assembled into the pCZGY2729 backbone (RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/Addgene_135096">Addgene_135096</ext-link>), which facilitates CRISPR/Cas9 single copy insertion on chromosome IV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Andrusiak et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>All <italic>ncs-2</italic> transgenes were similarly cloned using primers for Gibson assembly into pCZGY2727. To generate the <italic>Pncs-2</italic>::5′UTR mutant::<italic>ncs-2</italic> cDNA construct (pCZGY3526), we amplified <italic>Pncs-2</italic> from N2 gDNA using primers YJ12554 and YJ12555. A fragment containing SL1 trans-spliced <italic>eif-3.G</italic> 5′UTR incorporated in the forward primer, <italic>ncs-2</italic> cDNA, GFP, and the <italic>ncs-2</italic> 3′UTR was amplified from CZ22459 gDNA using primers YJ12556 and YJ12557. The <italic>Pncs-2</italic>::GFP(+) construct (pCZGY3533) was cloned by amplifying <italic>Pncs-2</italic> through the first four codons of <italic>ncs-2</italic> CDS from N2 gDNA using primers YJ12554 and YJ12579, and GFP and the <italic>ncs-2</italic> 3′UTR from CZ22459 gDNA using YJ12580 and YJ12557. The <italic>Pncs-2</italic>::5′UTR mutant::GFP construct (pCZGY3534) was cloned by amplifying <italic>Pncs-2</italic> from N2 gDNA using primers YJ12554 and YJ12555, and the <italic>eif-3.G</italic> 5′UTR, the first four codons of the <italic>ncs-2</italic> CDS, GFP, and the <italic>ncs-2</italic> 3′UTR from CZ22459 gDNA using primers YJ12581 and YJ12557.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Fluorescence microscopy and GFP intensity quantification</title><p>L4 or young adult animals were immobilized in 1 mM levamisole in M9 and mounted on microscope slides with 2% agar. All images were collected on a Zeiss LSM800 confocal microscope, unless specified, with identical image acquisition settings: 1.25 µm pixel size with 0.76 µs pixel time, 50 µm pinhole, with genotype-blinding to observer when possible. The positions of VA10, VB11, and DB7 cholinergic motor neurons were identified using <italic>juEx2045</italic>(<italic>Pacr-2-mCherry</italic>), based on their stereotypical patterning in the posterior ventral nerve cord. These neurons were chosen for quantification because they were consistently visible in single focal plane images. All quantification of GFP intensity in these neurons was performed using the Integrated Density function in ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schindelin et al., 2012</xref>). We acquired the mean integrated density from the VA10, VB11, and DB7 cell bodies, subtracted background intensity from an equivalent area, and the resulting values were then normalized to the mean area of the cell bodies of the same animal. We similarly quantified fluorescence intensities in the ventral nerve cord of animals expressing GFP-tagged full-length <italic>ncs-2</italic> cDNA, except integrated densities were obtained from one ROI per image (red boxes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B and C</xref>). All data was normalized to the mean fluorescence intensity of the transgene in the wildtype background. All statistical analysis was performed with GraphPad Prism6 software.</p><p>Axon commissures, observed as fluorescent structures extending from the ventrally located neuron cell body to the dorsal body wall, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref> were visualized with <italic>juIs14</italic>[<italic>Pacr-2</italic>::GFP] and manually quantified. Imaging shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2B</xref> was performed using a Zeiss Axioplan two microscope installed with Chroma HQ filters and a 63x objective lens. Synaptic puncta labeled by <italic>nuIs94</italic>[SNB-1::GFP], were manually quantified in the region anterior to the ventral nerve chord between VD6 and VD7.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Polysome profiling</title><p>We prepared <italic>C. elegans</italic> lysates and sucrose gradients using the protocol described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Ding and Grosshans, 2009</xref>. To synchronize animals, gravitated adults were treated with 20% Alkaline Hypochlorite Solution and embryos were plated on four 30 cm NGM plates seeded with OP50, and grown to the L4 stage at 20°C. Approximately 200 µl packed L4 <italic>C. elegans</italic> were harvested by centrifugation in M9 media at 1500 RPM, washed three times in ice-cold M9 media supplemented with 1 mM cycloheximide, then once more in lysis buffer base solution (140 mM KCl, 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.5), 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5% NP-40, 1 mM DTT, 1 mM cycloheximide) followed by snap freezing in liquid nitrogen. The frozen pellets were resuspended in 450 µl lysis buffer (140 mM KCl, 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.5), 1.5 mM MgCl2, 0.5% NP-40, 2% PTE, 1% sodium deoxycholate, 1 mM DTT, 1 mM cycloheximide, 0.4 units/µl RNAsin) and crushed to a fine powder with a mortar and pestle pre-cooled with liquid nitrogen. Protein lysate concentrations were then determined using a Bradford assay (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). Fifteen to 60% sucrose gradients were prepared in 89 mm polypropylene centrifuge tubes (Beckman Coulter) using standard settings on a Foxy Jr. density gradient fractionation system (Teledyne ISCO, Lincoln, NE) and lysate volumes corresponding to equal protein amounts between samples were loaded on top of the gradients. Loaded gradients were then spun in an Optima L-80 ultracentrifuge (Beckman Coulter) at 36,000 rpm at 4°C for 3 hr. Fractions were then collected and RNA absorbance was continuously acquired using a UA-6 detector (Teledyne ISCO, Lincoln, NE) with a 70% sucrose chase solution. We calculated the area under the curve (AUC) for monosome (80S) and polysome absorbance traces using the Simpson’s rule method in SciPy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Virtanen et al., 2020</xref>) and used the AUC values to calculate the polysome to monosome ratios.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>A total of 500 µl of mixed staged worms were resuspended in lysis buffer (140 mM KCl, 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.5), 1.5 mM MgCl2, 0.5% NP-40, 1% sodium deoxycholate, 1 mM DTT) supplemented with protease inhibitors (Complete Ultra Tablets, Roche), frozen in liquid nitrogen, and crushed to a fine powder. The lysates were clarified by centrifugation at max speed in a tabletop centrifuge and protein levels were quantified using a Bradford assay (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). The resulting protein lysates were then boiled in Laemmli buffer with 10% 2-mercaptoethanol, run on SDS-PAGE gels, and transferred to PVDF blots, which were probed with anti-FLAG (F7425, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_439687">AB_439687</ext-link>) or anti-Actin (clone C4, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2335304">AB_2335304</ext-link>) antibodies.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>seCLIP library preparation and sequencing</title><p>We performed single-end enhanced CrossLink and ImmunoPrecipitation (seCLIP) experiments according to the published protocol in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Van Nostrand et al., 2017</xref>, with the following adjustments to ensure efficient immunoprecipitation yield from <italic>C. elegans</italic> lysates. Mixed stage animals were grown on ~12 NGM plates (30 cm) and washed twice with M9, spinning at 1500 rpm between washes. Animals were then resuspended in 5 ml M9 media and rocked on a rotator for 10 min to remove gut bacteria, followed by one more wash with M9 at 1500 rpm. The animals were spread on one NGM plate (30 cm) and then UV-crosslinked with a Spectrolinker XL-1000 (Spectronics, New Cassel, NY) using energy setting 3 kJ/m<sup>2</sup> according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Broughton and Pasquinelli, 2013</xref>. Afterwards, animals were resuspended in 4 ml lysis buffer [150 mM NaCl, 1 M HEPES, 100 mM DTT, 6.25 µl RNAsin (Promega) per 10 ml, 10% glycerol, 10% Triton X-100, one protease inhibitor tablet per 10 ml] and split into two tubes for each replicate. The resuspension was disrupted on an XL-2000 Sonicator (QSonica, Newtown, CT) with seven pulses (powersetting = 11, 10 s each, 50 s on ice in between) and immediately spun at 4750 RPM for 5 min at 4°C. All subsequent steps, beginning with RNAse A treatment of the supernatant, was performed according to the seCLIP protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Van Nostrand et al., 2017</xref>), except that high-salt and low-salt wash buffers were replaced with a single buffer (2M NaCl, 1M HEPES, 30% glycerol, 1% Triton X-100, one protease inhibitor tablet per 10 mL) optimized for anti-FLAG RNA IP from <italic>C. elegans</italic> lysates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Blazie et al., 2015</xref>). Immunoprecipitation was performed with anti-FLAG beads (Sigma, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2637089">AB_2637089</ext-link>). cDNA libraries were prepared from both the immunoprecipitated mRNA (CLIP) as well as the sample before immunoprecipitation (INPUT), such that crosslink sites can be defined by read enrichment in the CLIP sample over input as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Van Nostrand et al., 2017</xref>). seCLIP libraries were validated using the D1000 high sensitivity screen tape system (Agilent, La Jolla, CA) and quantified using a Qubit instrument (Thermo Fisher, San Diego, CA) before pooling and sequencing on HiSeq4000 (Illumina, San Diego, CA) at the IGM Genomics Center, University of California San Diego.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>seCLIP sequence mapping</title><p>After demultiplexing barcoded reads, we used the CLIPPER software pipeline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lovci et al., 2013</xref>) to trim barcodes, remove PCR duplicate reads, filter reads mapping to repetitive elements, and map the remaining reads to the <italic>C. elegans</italic> reference genome (ce10). The total number of uniquely mapped reads obtained after filtering is in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp4">Supplementary file 4</xref>. A large proportion of reads obtained from the ∆RRM and IgG samples mapped to repetitive elements and were discarded, explaining the smaller number of uniquely mapped reads in these samples. In seCLIP, RNA-binding sites are defined as read clusters enriched in the crosslink immunoprecipitated sample (CLIP) over the input control (INPUT) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Van Nostrand et al., 2017</xref>), which are comprehensively identified across each dataset using CLIPPER. Read clusters were reproducibly identified from independent biological replicates of seCLIP, except in the ∆RRM control reflecting background, supporting the specificity of our data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>EIF-3.G footprint identification from mapped seCLIP reads</title><p>We defined EIF-3.G footprints as seCLIP read clusters appearing in both replicates with 20 reads and 1.5 fold-change enrichment over the INPUT control in at least one replicate. Footprints matching these criteria in the IgG (no transgene) and the EIF-3.G(∆RRM) control samples were considered background and subtracted from the EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) datasets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp5">Supplementary files 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp6">6</xref>). We annotated footprints to their gene features (eg. 5′UTR, CDS) using a script (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Yee, 2021</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/byee4/annotator">https://github.com/byee4/annotator</ext-link>) that overlaps read clusters with the <italic>C. elegans</italic> genome annotation WS235. We grouped all clusters annotated in the CDS and 5'UTR into one category (5'UTR proximal), since clusters mapping in CDS were almost always located within 200nts of a 5'UTR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Gene ontology and KEGG pathway analysis</title><p>GO analysis was performed using 225 EIF-3.G target genes as input to the biological process annotation set within the Gene Ontology Resource tool (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Ashburner et al., 2000</xref>). A total 211 gene names were recognized by the database and GO term enrichment was defined using a threshold of p&lt; 0.05. Pathway analysis of EIF-3.G target genes was performed using the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) annotation tool within the DAVID bioinformatics resource (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jiao et al., 2012</xref>) using default settings.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Analysis of activity-dependent expression changes among EIF-3.G target mRNAs in cholinergic neurons</title><p>We studied activity-dependent transcript expression changes among the EIF-3.G target genes (n = 225) by re-analyzing the cholinergic neuron-specific transcriptomes reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref> using the Galaxy platform (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Afgan et al., 2018</xref>). We downloaded raw FASTA reads from transcriptome sequencing of wild type and <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) animals (n = two replicates each; accession #’s SRR10320705, SRR10320706, SRR10320707, SRR10320707) and mapped them to the <italic>C. elegans</italic> reference genome (ce10) using BWA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Li and Durbin, 2009</xref>). Differential expression among the EIF-3.G target genes was quantified using Feature Counts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Liao et al., 2014</xref>) and DeSeq2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Love et al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-14"><title>in silico analysis of 5′UTR sequence features, secondary structure, and conservation</title><p>We downloaded all <italic>C. elegans</italic> transcript 5'UTRs (WS271) from Parasite Biomart (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Howe et al., 2016</xref>), and calculated 5′UTR lengths as the sequence between the 5' distal end and the start codon of each transcript. To have meaningful length calculation, we only considered 5′UTRs annotated with at least 10nt and restricted our analysis to the longest 5′UTR isoform for each gene to avoid considering multiple transcripts of the same gene. By these criteria we identified 5′UTRs for 10,962 WS271 protein coding transcripts and 179 transcripts with EIF-3.G footprints. We used the same criteria to determine features of the <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) cholinergic transcriptome 5′UTRs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">McCulloch et al., 2020</xref>) for the analysis shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E–F</xref>.</p><p>For the analysis shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2D–E</xref>, the genomic coordinates of human gene 5′UTRs were downloaded from Ensembl and used to obtain 5′UTR sequences from the human genome reference sequence (hg38). eIF3g footprints from HEK293 cells were previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2015</xref>). We defined our analysis of 5′UTR sequences using the same criteria described for <italic>C. elegans</italic> and the data show the comparison between 5′UTRs of 255 genes with human eIF3g footprints and 19,914 total genes in the human genome annotation (hg38).</p><p>To calculate GC-enrichment, we used BEDTools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Quinlan and Hall, 2010</xref>) to generate a FASTA of 5′UTR sequences from their genomic coordinates and used Biopython (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Cock et al., 2009</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/biopython/biopython">https://github.com/biopython/biopython</ext-link>) to calculate the total %GC in their sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F</xref>) as well as %GC within 10nt bins incremented from the start codon ATG for the analysis shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2C</xref>.</p><p>To predict secondary structures of the 5′ ends of <italic>hlh-30d</italic>, <italic>ncs-2</italic>, and <italic>eif-3.G</italic> mRNAs, we used the RNAfold Web Server (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Gruber et al., 2008</xref>) with default settings. To better understand the contribution of gene-specific 5'UTR sequences, we excluded the SL1 sequences of <italic>ncs-2</italic> and <italic>eif-3.G</italic> from folding predictions. The free energies (∆G) for each sequence reported in our results were derived from the reported thermodynamic ensemble. Data showing conservation of <italic>eif-3.G</italic> and <italic>ncs-2</italic> 5′UTR sequences compared with 135 nematode species (phyloP135way scores) was obtained from the UCSC Genome Browser with the genomic position along the sequence of each 5′UTR as input.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Brian Yee, Eric Van Nostrand, Gabriel Pratt, and Gene Yeo for advice on adapting the seCLIP protocol to <italic>C. elegans</italic> and technical support with seCLIP data analysis; Timothy Shaw and Jens Lykke-Andersen for sharing equipment and invaluable assistance with polysome profile analysis; Yan Zhao, Ann Zhou and Ippei Ozaki for assistance in constructing expression clones and strains; Yunbo Li for advice on protein analysis; Malena Hansen, Josh Kaplan, and Keming Zhou for transgenes, Kenneth Miller for P<italic>unc-17β</italic> plasmid. Some strains used in this study were provided by the Caenorhabditis Genetics Center, which is funded by NIH Office of Research Infrastructure Programs (P40 OD010440). We acknowledge WormBase and UCSC Genome databases for genomic information resource. We thank Andrew D Chisholm and members of our laboratory for critical reading of the manuscript. S B was a trainee on the UCSD T32 training grant (NS007220). This work is funded by NIH grant (NS R37 035546 to Y J).</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Data curation, Writing - review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Conceptualization, Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Project administration, Writing - review and editing</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Strains used in this study.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-supp1-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp2"><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>Genotyping primers used in this study.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-supp2-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp3"><label>Supplementary file 3.</label><caption><title>Constructs and related primers used in this study.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-supp3-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp4"><label>Supplementary file 4.</label><caption><title>Number of mapped reads in seCLIP replicate datasets obtained after sequencing and CLIPPER filtering.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-supp4-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp5"><label>Supplementary file 5.</label><caption><title>Number of read clusters detected in each dataset after subtraction of IgG control background.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-supp5-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp6"><label>Supplementary file 6.</label><caption><title>Number of EIF-3.G footprints detected in each dataset after subtraction of background from both IgG and ∆RRM controls.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-supp6-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-68336-transrepform-v2.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Raw and processed seCLIP datasets from this study have been uploaded to the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) under accession number GSE152704.</p><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><element-citation id="dataset1" publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blazie</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Takayanagi-Kiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><data-title>seCLIP of C. elegans EIF-3.G in the cholinergic motor neurons</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id assigning-authority="NCBI" pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE152704">GSE152704</pub-id></element-citation></p><p>The following previously published dataset was used:</p><p><element-citation id="dataset2" publication-type="data" specific-use="references"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><data-title>Neuronal transcriptome analyses reveal novel neuropeptide modulators of excitation and inhibition imbalance in C. elegans</data-title><source>NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus</source><pub-id assigning-authority="NCBI" pub-id-type="accession" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE139212">GSE139212</pub-id></element-citation></p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afgan</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Batut</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Beek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cech</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chilton</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clements</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Coraor</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Grüning</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerler</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillman-Jackson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiltemann</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jalili</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasche</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Soranzo</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Goecks</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nekrutenko</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blankenberg</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>The galaxy platform for accessible, reproducible and collaborative biomedical analyses: 2018 update</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>W537</fpage><lpage>W544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29790989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname> <given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterston</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>A global analysis of <italic>C. elegans</italic> trans-splicing</article-title><source>Genome Research</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.113811.110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrusiak</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharifnia</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickey</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chisholm</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Inhibition of axon regeneration by Liquid-like TIAR-2 granules</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2019.07.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolinski</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwight</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eppig</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Issel-Tarver</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasarskis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matese</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringwald</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherlock</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology the gene ontology consortium</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/75556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blazie</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Babb</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilky</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawls</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Comparative RNA-Seq analysis reveals pervasive tissue-specific alternative polyadenylation in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> intestine and muscles</article-title><source>BMC Biology</source><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>4</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12915-015-0116-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25601023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1974">1974</year><article-title>The genetics of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broughton</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquinelli</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Identifying Argonaute binding sites in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> using iCLIP</article-title><source>Methods</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2013.03.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cate</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Human eIF3: from 'blobology' to biological insight</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><volume>372</volume><elocation-id>20160176</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2016.0176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28138064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choe</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez-Moya</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sliz</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Santisteban</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname> <given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Locker</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Slack</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregory</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>mRNA circularization by METTL3-eIF3h enhances translation and promotes oncogenesis</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>561</volume><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0538-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30232453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cock</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Antao</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalke</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedberg</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamelryck</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauff</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilczynski</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>de Hoon</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Biopython: freely available Python tools for computational molecular biology and bioinformatics</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>1422</fpage><lpage>1423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19304878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferraiuolo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodall</surname> <given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Higginbottom</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortiboys</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollinger</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartley</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockington</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burness</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Grierson</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ince</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirby</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Mutations in CHMP2B in lower motor neuron predominant amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS)</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e9872</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20352044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuchalová</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouba</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmannová</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dányi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Valásek</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The RNA recognition motif of eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3g (eIF3g) is required for resumption of scanning of posttermination ribosomes for reinitiation on GCN4 and together with eIF3i stimulates linear scanning</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Biology</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>4671</fpage><lpage>4686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.00430-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20679478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decressac</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattsson</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Weikop</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundblad</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobsson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Björklund</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>TFEB-mediated autophagy rescues midbrain dopamine neurons from α-synuclein toxicity</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>E1817</fpage><lpage>E1826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1305623110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23610405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dickinson</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiner</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Engineering the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> genome using Cas9-triggered homologous recombination</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1028</fpage><lpage>1034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23995389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosshans</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Repression of <italic>C. elegans</italic> microRNA targets at the initiation level of translation requires GW182 proteins</article-title><source>The EMBO journal</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2008.275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19131968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dittman</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Factors regulating the abundance and localization of synaptobrevin in the plasma membrane</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>11399</fpage><lpage>11404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0600784103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16844789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukaya</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwakawa</surname> <given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomari</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>MicroRNAs block assembly of eIF4F translation initiation complex in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2014.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25280104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia-Esparcia</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernández-Ortega</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koneti</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado-Morales</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Castaño</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmona</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrer</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Altered machinery of protein synthesis is region- and stage-dependent and is associated with α-synuclein oligomers in Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Acta neuropathologica communications</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>76</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40478-015-0257-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26621506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomes-Duarte</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacerda</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Romão</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>eIF3: a factor for human health and disease</article-title><source>RNA biology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476286.2017.1391437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29099306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruber</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenz</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhart</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuböck</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofacker</surname> <given-names>IL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>The Vienna RNA websuite</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>W70</fpage><lpage>W74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18424795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>The role of RNA structure at 5' untranslated region in microRNA-mediated gene regulation</article-title><source>RNA</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.044792.114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25002673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hallam</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Waring</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>The C. elegans NeuroD homolog cnd-1 functions in multiple aspects of motor neuron fate specification</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>4239</fpage><lpage>4252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.127.19.4239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10976055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanachi</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hershey</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vornlocher</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Characterization of the p33 subunit of eukaryotic translation initiation factor-3 from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source><volume>274</volume><fpage>8546</fpage><lpage>8553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.13.8546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10085088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holm</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Faraco</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostafavi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Battle</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Levinson</surname> <given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gammeltoft</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennum</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mignot</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornum</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>EIF3G is associated with narcolepsy across ethnicities</article-title><source>European journal of human genetics : EJHG</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>1573</fpage><lpage>1580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2015.4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25669430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howe</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolt</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cain</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Done</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Down</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grove</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishore</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomax</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuin</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulini</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raciti</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schindelman</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuli</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Auken</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yook</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Berriman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kersey</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sternberg</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>WormBase 2016: expanding to enable helminth genomic research</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>D774</fpage><lpage>D780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26578572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imataka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gradi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonenberg</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>A newly identified N-terminal amino acid sequence of human eIF4G binds poly(A)-binding protein and functions in poly(A)-dependent translation</article-title><source>The EMBO journal</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>7480</fpage><lpage>7489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/17.24.7480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9857202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname> <given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>daW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baseler</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempicki</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>DAVID-WS: a stateful web service to facilitate gene/protein list analysis</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>1805</fpage><lpage>1806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22543366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jospin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname> <given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Stawicki</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulin</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuske</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvitz</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessereau</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>A neuronal acetylcholine receptor regulates the balance of muscle excitation and inhibition in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>PLOS biology</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e1000265</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20027209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamath</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulin</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotta</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanapin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bot</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohrmann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Welchman</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipperlen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahringer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Systematic functional analysis of the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> genome using RNAi</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>421</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12529635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamper</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladd</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>ASY</given-names></name><name><surname>Asy</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>A phosphorylation-regulated eIF3d translation switch mediates cellular adaptation to metabolic stress</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>370</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb0993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33184215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lapierre</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>De Magalhaes Filho</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>McQuary</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Visvikis</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelino</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Irazoqui</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The TFEB orthologue HLH-30 regulates autophagy and modulates longevity in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>2267</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms3267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23925298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kranzusch</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cate</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>eIF3 targets cell-proliferation messenger RNAs for translational activation or repression</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>522</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25849773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kranzusch</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Doudna</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cate</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>eIF3d is an mRNA cap-binding protein that is required for specialized translation initiation</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>536</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature18954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27462815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leppek</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barna</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Functional 5' UTR mRNA structures in eukaryotic translation regulation and how to find them</article-title><source>Nature reviews. Molecular cell biology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm.2017.103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29165424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>1754</fpage><lpage>1760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>featureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>XX</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssens</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonslow</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgar</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroustrup</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Swoboda</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Riedel</surname> <given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>DAF-16/FOXO and HLH-30/TFEB function as combinatorial transcription factors to promote stress resistance and longevity</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>4400</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-06624-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30353013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lovci</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghanem</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marr</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parra</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname> <given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehman</surname> <given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoon</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Massirer</surname> <given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Conboy</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Rbfox proteins regulate alternative mRNA splicing through evolutionarily conserved RNA bridges</article-title><source>Nature structural &amp; molecular biology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>1434</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.2699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24213538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title><source>Genome biology</source><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>550</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Machado</surname> <given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Griesi-Oliveira</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kok</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Passos-Bueno</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sertie</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Collybistin binds and inhibits mTORC1 signaling: a potential novel mechanism contributing to intellectual disability and autism</article-title><source>European journal of human genetics : EJHG</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2015.69</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25898924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCulloch</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname> <given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Takayanagi-Kiya</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherra</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Novel Mutations in Synaptic Transmission Genes Suppress Neuronal Hyperexcitation in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>2055</fpage><lpage>2063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.117.042598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28468816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCulloch</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Neuronal transcriptome analyses reveal novel neuropeptide modulators of excitation and inhibition imbalance in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e0233991</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0233991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32497060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mello</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinchcomb</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambros</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Efficient gene transfer in <italic>C. elegans</italic>: extrachromosomal maintenance and integration of transforming sequences</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>3959</fpage><lpage>3970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1991.tb04966.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1935914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zinoviev</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skabkin</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Elemento</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pestova</surname> <given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffrey</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>5' UTR m(6)A Promotes Cap-Independent Translation</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>163</volume><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.10.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26593424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mi</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Muruganujan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Protocol Update for large-scale genome and gene function analysis with the PANTHER classification system (v.14.0)</article-title><source>Nature protocols</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>721</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41596-019-0128-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30804569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Emerson</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rand</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Goalpha and diacylglycerol kinase negatively regulate the Gqalpha pathway in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0896-6273(00)80847-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10571227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paix</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Folkmann</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seydoux</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Precision genome editing using CRISPR-Cas9 and linear repair templates in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Methods</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2017.03.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28392263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelletier</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonenberg</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1985">1985</year><article-title>Insertion mutagenesis to increase secondary structure within the 5' noncoding region of a eukaryotic mRNA reduces translational efficiency</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(85)90200-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2982496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polito</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Martini-Stoica</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Swartzlander</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmieri</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>di Ronza</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sardiello</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballabio</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Selective clearance of aberrant tau proteins and rescue of neurotoxicity by transcription factor EB</article-title><source>EMBO molecular medicine</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1142</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/emmm.201303671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25069841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pulos-Holmes</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Srole</surname> <given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Juarez</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>McSwiggen</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingolia</surname> <given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cate</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Repression of ferritin light chain translation by human eIF3</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e48193</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.48193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31414986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname> <given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Po</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mac</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawano</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Hyperactivation of B-type motor neurons results in aberrant synchrony of the Caenorhabditis elegans motor circuit</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>5319</fpage><lpage>5325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4017-12.2013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23516296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname> <given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ricci</surname> <given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Limousin</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Soto-Rifo</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubilar</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Decimo</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlmann</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>miRNA repression of translation in vitro takes place during 43S ribosomal scanning</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23161679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richmond</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>UNC-13 is required for synaptic vesicle fusion in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Nature neuroscience</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/14755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10526333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richmond</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Synaptic function</article-title><source>WormBook : The Online Review of C. elegans Biology</source><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>14</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1895/wormbook.1.69.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rode</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohm</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Anhäuser</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosing</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sin</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Leidel</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Storkebaum</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rentmeister</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rumpf</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Differential Requirement for Translation Initiation Factor Pathways during Ecdysone-Dependent Neuronal Remodeling in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Cell reports</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>2287</fpage><lpage>2299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.07.074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30157424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarov</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozniakovski</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roguev</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyman</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>A recombineering pipeline for functional genomics applied to <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Nature methods</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16990816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schindelin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arganda-Carreras</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Frise</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaynig</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Longair</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietzsch</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Preibisch</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rueden</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saalfeld</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinevez</surname> <given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartenstein</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliceiri</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomancak</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardona</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Fiji: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sertie</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>de Alencastro</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>De Paula</surname> <given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Passos-Bueno</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Collybistin and gephyrin are novel components of the eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3 complex</article-title><source>BMC research notes</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>242</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0500-3-242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20858277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheliga</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pluskal</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Motamedchaboki</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hidalgo</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagida</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>A Transcript-Specific eIF3 Complex Mediates Global Translational Control of Energy Metabolism</article-title><source>Cell reports</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1891</fpage><lpage>1902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2016.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27477275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Arake-Tacca</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nitido</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Montabana</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cate</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Assembly of eIF3 mediated by mutually dependent subunit insertion</article-title><source>Structure</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>886</fpage><lpage>896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.str.2016.02.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27210288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonenberg</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinnebusch</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Regulation of translation initiation in eukaryotes: mechanisms and biological targets</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>136</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2009.01.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19239892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stawicki</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Takayanagi-Kiya</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Neuropeptides function in a homeostatic manner to modulate excitation-inhibition imbalance in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>PLOS genetics</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e1003472</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23658528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takayanagi-Kiya</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Release-dependent feedback inhibition by a presynaptically localized ligand-gated anion channel</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e21734</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.21734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27782882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treinin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Cholinergic transmission in <italic>C. elegans</italic>: functions, diversity, and maturation of ACh-activated ion channels</article-title><source>Journal of Neurochemistry</source><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>15164</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jnc.15164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valášek</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeman</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beznosková</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavlíková</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammad</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hronová</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmannová</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashem</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunišová</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Embraced by eIF3: structural and functional insights into the roles of eIF3 across the translation cycle</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>10948</fpage><lpage>10968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28981723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Nostrand</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname> <given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelboin-Burkhart</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blue</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Louie</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Robust, Cost-Effective Profiling of RNA Binding Protein Targets with Single-end Enhanced Crosslinking and Immunoprecipitation (seCLIP)</article-title><source>Methods in molecular biology</source><volume>1648</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-7204-3_14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28766298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Virtanen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gommers</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliphant</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Haberland</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cournapeau</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Burovski</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Weckesser</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bright</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Walt</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Millman</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayorov</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>ARJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Polat</surname> <given-names>İ</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname> <given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>VanderPlas</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Laxalde</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Perktold</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cimrman</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriksen</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintero</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Archibald</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedregosa</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>van Mulbregt</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><collab>SciPy 1.0 Contributors</collab></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>SciPy 1.0: fundamental algorithms for scientific computing in Python</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-019-0686-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32015543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmannová</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hronová</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunišová</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname> <given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannan</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinnebusch</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirokikh</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Valášek</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Selective translation complex profiling reveals staged initiation and Co-translational assembly of initiation factor complexes</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>546</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2020.06.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lara-Gonzalez</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheerambathur</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Prevo</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chisholm</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Desai</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oegema</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>A toolkit for GFP-mediated tissue-specific protein degradation in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Development</source><volume>144</volume><fpage>2694</fpage><lpage>2701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.150094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28619826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillner</surname> <given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachs</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Circularization of mRNA by eukaryotic translation initiation factors</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1097-2765(00)80122-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9702200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dziewczapolski</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Panda</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lester</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinemann</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Contractor</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Altered activity-rest patterns in mice with a human autosomal-dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy mutation in the β2 nicotinic receptor</article-title><source>Molecular Psychiatry</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1048</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2010.78</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20603624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yee</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><source>Annotator</source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/byee4/annotator">https://github.com/byee4/annotator</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname> <given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname> <given-names>MQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sewell</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Systematic identification of <italic>C. elegans</italic> miRISC proteins, miRNAs, and mRNA targets by their interactions with GW182 proteins AIN-1 and AIN-2</article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2007.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18042455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stawicki</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncharov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Position of UNC-13 in the active zone regulates synaptic vesicle release probability and release kinetics</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e01180</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.01180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24220508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherra</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncharov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Asynchronous cholinergic drive correlates with Excitation-Inhibition imbalance via a neuronal Ca<sup>2+</sup> Sensor Protein</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2017.04.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28494862</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.68336.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>Anne E</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Duke University School of Medicine</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife publishes the most substantive revision requests and the accompanying author responses.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Acceptance summary:</bold></p><p>This study takes advantage of unbiased genetics to discover functions of EIF-3.G in neuronal protein synthesis. This is especially interesting and timely given the connection of the eIF3 complex with various diseases of the nervous system and a previous lack of detailed understanding of how EIF-3.G specifically plays a role in translation control.</p><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Eukaryotic initiation factor EIF-3.G augments mRNA translation efficiency to regulate neuronal activity&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by 3 peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Piali Sengupta as the Senior Editor. The reviewers have opted to remain anonymous.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed their reviews with one another, and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) The ∆RRM construct, which is a deletion, may have secondary effects on folding/stability of the encoded protein. Given that this EIF-3.G variant is used as an important control for seCLIP studies, the reviewers recommend that the authors confirm the RRM deletion mutant protein is at least expressed at similar levels as the EIF-3.G wild type and C130Y variants.</p><p>2) The reviewers encourage the authors to provide data ensuring the phenotype from the forward screen is due to the eif-3.g mutation either by i) using CRISPR to engineer a revertant of the C130Y eif-3.g mutation and asking whether this abolishes the phenotype, or alternately, ii) using the GFP tagged single copy insertion C130Y expressing strain in combination with any CRISPR mutant that disrupts the native eif-3.g locus.</p><p>3) The reviewers felt the CLIP data were an important part of the story and debated whether or not additional validations of these findings were needed. In the end the reviewers request only that the authors state whether additional GFP reporters in addition to hlh-30 and ncs-2 were tested to give the readers a sense of the potential false positive rate.</p><p>4) All of the reviewers thought that the following experimental suggestion would substantially strengthen the paper if the strains were easily available for testing. However if this study would substantially delay the publication of this work, it was not deemed essential. &quot;It is interesting that eif-3.g(C130Y) decreases translation of hlh-30 and ncs-2 only in acr-2(gf) mutants. Is this a direct consequence of elevated neural activity in Ach MNs? For example, does silencing of these neurons attenuate the ability of eif-3.g(C130Y) to decrease ncs-2 GFP reporter translation?&quot;</p><p>5) The reviewers had many questions about the ife-1 section of the study and felt that it was underdeveloped with respect to the rest of the paper. They suggest the authors consider removing this work from the current study and develop it further for a future publication.</p><p>6) All of the reviewers comments have been included below to provide feedback to the authors. However, only the 5 points above were determined by the consensus of the reviewers to be the major points that required addressing in the revision.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1:</italic></p><p>In general, I found this study to be both interesting and timely given the connection of the eIF3 complex with various diseases of the nervous system and a lack of detailed understanding of how EIF-3.G specifically plays a role in translation control. Moreover, the experiments are generally sound, rigorous, and conclusions made from the interpretation of the data are reasonable and not over-stated.</p><p>Strengths:</p><p>– The genetic screen identifying the mutation in the Zinc Finger domain provided the basis for a new line of inquiry into the role of this domain in translational control.</p><p>– The first use of the single-end enhanced CLIP protocol in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, which will be highly useful for those studying RNA binding proteins in this model organism</p><p>– Initial insights into the features associated with EIF-3.G regulation of translation and its link to target mRNAs that themselves control neuronal activity.</p><p>Weaknesses:</p><p>– Despite initial insights into the possible mechanism of action, it is still unclear how the mutation in the Zinc Finger domain or the Zinc Finger domain itself is acting to modulate translation of specific mRNAs.</p><p>– The authors propose a model that structured 5'UTRs are likely playing a key role in the regulation of translation by EIF-3.G, but further experiments would be required to more strongly confirm this model.</p><p>Overall, I found the quality of the science and the data presented to be very high. I have only two primary suggestions for experiments that I feel would strengthen the conclusions of the current manuscript.</p><p>1) The ∆RRM construct, which is a deletion, may have secondary effects on folding/stability of the encoded protein. Given that this EIF-3.G variant is used as an important control for seCLIP studies, I think it would be useful to check that this RRM deletion mutant protein is at least expressed at similar levels as the EIF-3.G wild type and C130Y variants. Since the authors already have FLAG-tagged versions of all three proteins for their CLIP experiments, it should not be too much work to perform a Western blot to compare protein levels.</p><p>2) The connection to structured 5'UTRs is intriguing but could be further strengthened by an experiment that more explicitly tests the role of secondary structure. For example, in addition to the UTR swapping experiments performed by the authors, it would also be informative to introduce mutations at nucleotides engaged in base-pairing interactions to see if eliminating these interactions influences regulation. If effects are observed, subsequent compensatory mutations that re-introduce base-pairing should be performed to revert back to patterns observed with the native 5'UTR.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2:</italic></p><p>In this manuscript, Blazie et al. examine the neuronal function of EIF-3.G, a RNA-binding subunit of the translation initiation complex eIF3. First, they recover a semi-dominant gain-of-function mutation in eif-3.g (a C130Y point mutation in its zinc finger domain) in a screen for suppressors of cholinergic motor neuron hyperactivity. The authors show that the eif-3.g(C130Y) phenotype can be reversed by expression of wild-type eif-3.g in Ach motor neurons and that the WT and C130Y mutant express at equal levels. The authors then show that loss of ife-1 suppresses the eif-3.g(c130y) effect and that eif-3.g's function vitally depends on its RRM domain. They then use transgenic expression of Flag-tagged-eif-3.g to profile eif-3.g binding to mRNAs in the Ach motor neurons. This reveals binding of eif-3.g to 5'UTR-proximal regions of mRNAs, particular in long, GC-rich 5'UTRs. The authors note that eif-3.g-bound mRNAs include several that show acr-2(gf)-dependent transcription, with an enrichment of genes involved in neuropeptide signaling and other categories. They then focus on two specific targets of eif-3.g. First, they show that hlh-30 translation is increased by acr-2(gf), which can be suppressed by eif-3.g(c130y). Second, they show that ncs-2 translation is unaffected by acr-2(gf), but reduced by eif-3.g(c130y) in an acr-2(gf) background.</p><p>This paper takes advantage of unbiased genetics to determine a function for eif-3.g in neuronal protein synthesis regulation. Its strengths are that it develops a new system in which eif-3.g can be studied, identifies neuronal targets of eif-3.g, and demonstrates a neuronal function for this important translational regulator. Its weaknesses are that it doesn't fully resolve how eif-3.g regulates Ach motor neuron excitability or bind together an understanding of how eif-3.g regulates its targets in a manner that depends on acr-2(gf).</p><p>In this manuscript, Blazie et al. examine the neuronal function of EIF-3.G, a RNA-binding subunit of the translation initiation complex eIF3. First, they recover a semi-dominant gain-of-function mutation in eif-3.g (a C130Y point mutation in its zinc finger domain) in a screen for suppressors of cholinergic motor neuron hyperactivity. The authors show that the eif-3.g(C130Y) phenotype can be reversed by expression of wild-type eif-3.g in Ach motor neurons and that the WT and C130Y mutant express at equal levels. The authors then show that loss of ife-1 suppresses the eif-3.g(c130y) effect and that eif-3.g's function vitally depends on its RRM domain. They then use transgenic expression of Flag-tagged-eif-3.g to profile eif-3.g binding to mRNAs in the Ach motor neurons. This reveals binding of eif-3.g to 5'UTR-proximal regions of mRNAs, particular in long, GC-rich 5'UTRs. The authors note that eif-3.g-bound mRNAs include several that show acr-2(gf)-dependent transcription, with an enrichment of genes involved in neuropeptide signaling and other categories. They then focus on two specific targets of eif-3.g. First, they show that hlh-30 translation is increased by acr-2(gf), which can be suppressed by eif-3.g(c130y). Second, they show that ncs-2 translation is unaffected by acr-2(gf), but reduced by eif-3.g(c130y) in an acr-2(gf) background.</p><p>This paper takes advantage of unbiased genetics to determine a function for eif-3.g in neuronal protein synthesis regulation. Its strengths are that it develops a new system in which eif-3.g can be studied, identifies neuronal targets of eif-3.g, and demonstrates a neuronal function for this important translational regulator. Its weaknesses are that it doesn't fully resolve how eif-3.g regulates Ach motor neuron excitability or bind together an understanding of how eif-3.g regulates its targets in a manner that depends on acr-2(gf).</p><p>1) The study provides a characterization of a new eif-3.g allele, which is interesting. However, the study does not come full circle and clarify how the eif-3.g mutation alters cholinergic neuron excitability. Nor does it show in a mechanistic sense how eif-3.g function depends on neuronal activity. It would be helpful if the authors could point to any efforts that they've made to revert the phenotype of eif-3.g via overexpression of eif-3.g(c130y)-downregulated target genes. If they were able to show such an effect, this would greatly enhance the study.</p><p>2) It is interesting that eif-3.g(C130Y) decreases translation of hlh-30 and ncs-2 only in acr-2(gf) mutants. Is this a direct consequence of elevated neural activity in Ach MNs? For example, does silencing of these neurons attenuate the ability of eif-3.g(C130Y) to decrease ncs-2 GFP reporter translation?</p><p>3) A couple of extra genetic controls would bolster the paper: (i) using CRISPR to engineer a revertant of the C130Y eif-3.g mutation and asking whether this abolishes the phenotype; and (ii) overexpressing eif-3.g(C130Y) in Ach MNs and asking whether this is sufficient to induce the phenotype.</p><p>4) The use of neuronal cell type-specific seCLIP is exciting, but only 2 replicates were conducted and there is no systematic validation of the detected binding sites. RT-qPCR should be used to validate detected binding sites on a handful of targets.</p><p>5) For Figure 4E-F and related analyses: the authors are comparing the eif-3.g targets to the full transcriptome to determine notable properties of the eif-3.g-bound gene set. I believe that for these analyses it would be more appropriate to compare the eif-3.g-bound gene set to the set of ACH MN-expressed genes (which the authors have measured in a previous study). In its current form, it is unclear whether the length and GC content of the eif-3.g-bound genes is a general property of cholinergic neuron gene expression. The same idea also applies to the GO analyses.</p><p>6) Related to the length of the eif-3.g-bound 5'UTRs, longer RNA sequences have a higher probability of having a detected binding site (i.e. the number of detected binding sites along any region of DNA/RNA should scale with length). It is not clear whether the authors correct for this in their analysis.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #3:</italic></p><p>The authors demonstrate the cholinergic motor neurons (ACh-MN)-specific function of EIF-3.G in a previously well-developed <italic>C. elegans</italic> model of acetylcholine receptor-2 gain-of function [acr-2(gf)], showing spontaneous seizure-like convulsions. C130Y mutation of the zinc finger domain in EIF-3.G ameliorates hyperactivity induced by acr-2(gf), while it does not affect global translation, neuronal development, and synaptic formation. EIF-3.G preferentially associates with long and GC-enriched 5'UTR genes involved in the regulation of ACh-MN synaptic activity and modulates neuronal protein synthesis in an activity-dependent manner.</p><p>The authors provide strong genetic evidence that the eif-3. g(C130Y) allele suppresses the convulsion phenotype in acr-2(gf) in a semi-dominant, gain-of-function manner in the ACh-MN neuron. The analyses using homozygous and heterozygous forms of the allele, as well as transgenic rescue experiments were expertly performed, and the data were well described. This study documents a comprehensive and detailed insight into neuronal activity-dependent mRNA translation using diverse approaches</p><p>1. The statistical representation in Figure 1E is somewhat misguided. In order to show that eif3.G increases convulsion in acr-2 (gf); eif-3.G(C130Y) in an ACh-MN-specific manner, the statistical analysis of the right 4 samples should be done with WT or (-), not with Ex[eif-3.G(+)].</p><p>2. The statement 'Both GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3G(C130Y) showed cytoplasmic fluorescence throughout somatic cells and across all developmental stages' is not well-presented in Figure 1—figure supplement 1B, since only the wild-type and one developmental stage (L4) was shown. It is also unclear if the bright puncta across the animal actually correspond to Peif-3.g::GFP or is a result of autofluorescence from the gut. It will be useful to include arrows and insets to highlight the pattern of interest (e.g., cytoplasmic, specific somatic tissues). To elaborate on the tissue specificity suggested in Figure 1E, whether EIF-3.G WT and C130Y are expressed in ACh-MN neuron should be discussed – This will differentiate whether the C130Y effect is cell-autonomous or non-autonomous. The authors also referred to Figure supplement 1B and Figure 2B as assessments of EIF-3.G protein stability – Expression pattern/localization would be more appropriate than protein stability here.</p><p>3. In Figure 3A, the potential involvement of ife-1 (one of the eIF4E homologs) in eif-3.g(C130Y) suppression of acr-2(gf) is interesting. Some experiments are needed to discern the direct/indirect nature of this genetic interaction.</p><p>A. Does ife-1(0) cause convulsion in eif-3.G(C130Y) alone (acr-2 wild-type)?</p><p>B. Does ife-1(0) alter eif-3.G WT and C130Y expression?</p><p>C. ife-1 was shown to be predominantly expressed in the germline where it is important for germ cell development (Henderson et al., Journal of Cell Science 2009; Amiri et al., Development 2001). Moreover, the protein is undetectable by western blot from germline-deficient glp-4(bn2) animal (Amiri et al. 2001), potentially indicating exclusive germline expression. Thus, it will be important to look at whether IFE-1 is co-expressed with EIF-3.G WT and C130Y in the soma and ACh-MN.</p><p>4. EIF-3.G preference for long 5' UTR with high GC content was nicely dissected from the seCLIP data in Figure 4. For consistency, the authors could provide information of 5'UTR length and GC content between upregulated and downregulated genes in acr-2(gf) over WT, shown in Figure 5B. hlh-30 and ncs-2 were further linked to eif-3.g-mediated suppression of acr-2(gf) by examining their expression using GFP reporters in Figures 6 and 7. Polysome profiling can be done to differentiate the effect of C130Y on the translation efficiency of these transcripts, as opposed to their transcription and protein stability. It would also be informative to show the preference of these genes for <italic>C. elegans</italic> eIF4E homologs, IFE-1, IFE-2, and IFE-4.</p><p>5. A heatmap in Figure 4—figure supplement 2C needs hierarchical clustering, even though genes in the map are already clustered top to bottom by increasing positional GC-density near the start codon. It may help extract additional meaningful information. The authors also need to point out the genes described in the text (pmt-2, let-607, unc-43, and gsa-1).</p><p>6. The statistical representation in the graph in Figure 6D needs to be corrected.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.68336.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) The ∆RRM construct, which is a deletion, may have secondary effects on folding/stability of the encoded protein. Given that this EIF-3.G variant is used as an important control for seCLIP studies, the reviewers recommend that the authors confirm the RRM deletion mutant protein is at least expressed at similar levels as the EIF-3.G wild type and C130Y variants.</p></disp-quote><p>We appreciate the reviewers’ comment. As suggested by Reviewer #1, we carried out western blot analysis on protein extracts made from the three transgenic lines. We present this data in the revised Figure 4—figure supplement 1A, which shows that the EIF-3.G(∆RRM) truncated protein is expressed, but at reduced levels compared to EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y). It is important to note that during seCLIP we immunoprecipitated the truncated EIF-3.G(∆RRM) protein at the same level as full-length EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) proteins. We obtained nearly 3 times more reads from seCLIP of 3XFLAG::EIF-3.G(∆RRM) animals (543,913 reads) than from N2 animals that lack any transgene (192,259 reads; IgG(-) negative control in Supplementary File 4).</p><p>Together, these data support that the 3XFLAG::EIF-3.G(∆RRM) transgene is expressed and serves as an effective reagent to detect RNAs specifically bound by the RRM of EIF-3.G(WT and C130Y).</p><p>We describe the results in the revised results (lines 220-226) and methods (lines 652-661).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) The reviewers encourage the authors to provide data ensuring the phenotype from the forward screen is due to the eif-3.g mutation either by i) using CRISPR to engineer a revertant of the C130Y eif-3.g mutation and asking whether this abolishes the phenotype, or alternately, ii) using the GFP tagged single copy insertion C130Y expressing strain in combination with any CRISPR mutant that disrupts the native eif-3.g locus.</p></disp-quote><p>We appreciate the suggestion. While our attempt to edit C130Y back to wild type EIF-3.G was not successful, likely due to inefficiency of sgRNAs, we generated animals expressing the GFP-tagged EIF-3.G(C130Y) single copy transgene in a <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>) background (following the suggestion ii). We found that GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) rescued the early larval arrest phenotype of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>), supporting its functionality, and additionally suppressed <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) convulsion behavior at levels similar to endogenous <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>). The new results are shown in Figure 2A and described in the revised text (lines 158-163).</p><p>We performed an additional experiment to change the first cysteine (C127) of the zinc finger CCHC motif to tyrosine and found that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C127Y</italic>) behavior was identical to <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>). This result is shown in revised Figure 1 and discussed in the text (lines 107-113, 432-434, and 528-535).</p><p>Together, these results strengthen our conclusion that the suppression of <italic>acr2(gf)</italic> by <italic>eif-3.g(C130Y)</italic> isolated from the forward screen is due to the C130Y mutation in <italic>eif-3.G</italic>, and the integrity of the Zinc Finger domain is important for EIF-3.G function.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) The reviewers felt the CLIP data were an important part of the story and debated whether or not additional validations of these findings were needed. In the end the reviewers request only that the authors state whether additional GFP reporters in addition to hlh-30 and ncs-2 were tested to give the readers a sense of the potential false positive rate.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with the comment, and have revised our manuscript to include additional details on how our test of other GFP reporters led us to focus on <italic>hlh-30</italic> and <italic>ncs-2</italic>. We screened ten GFP reporter lines and found six lines with detectable expression in ACh-MNs. In addition to NCS-2 and HLH-30, we characterized effects of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) and <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) on four other reporter lines (for genes ZIP-2, ATF-7, LET607, and FLP-12). We have now documented these observations in the revised Supplementary File 1 and in lines 325-328 of the revised text.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) All of the reviewers thought that the following experimental suggestion would substantially strengthen the paper if the strains were easily available for testing. However if this study would substantially delay the publication of this work, it was not deemed essential. &quot;It is interesting that eif-3.g(C130Y) decreases translation of hlh-30 and ncs-2 only in acr-2(gf) mutants. Is this a direct consequence of elevated neural activity in Ach MNs? For example, does silencing of these neurons attenuate the ability of eif-3.g(C130Y) to decrease ncs-2 GFP reporter translation?&quot;</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewers for raising this point. We have examined HLH-30::GFP reporter translation in an <italic>unc-13</italic>(<italic>0</italic>) background, which is deficient for the synaptic priming factor and severely impairs synaptic transmission in all neurons (Richmond <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999) and abolishes <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) convulsion behavior (Zhou <italic>et al.,</italic> 2013). We found that <italic>unc-13</italic>(<italic>0</italic>) prevents enhanced HLH-30 expression in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) single mutants and also attenuates the ability of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) to decrease HLH-30 expression in <italic>acr2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>). This new data suggests that the observed <italic>eif-3.G(C130Y)</italic> is specific for elevated neuronal activity in ACh MNs. This analysis is now reported in Figure 6C and lines 347350 of the revised text.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) The reviewers had many questions about the ife-1 section of the study and felt that it was underdeveloped with respect to the rest of the paper. They suggest the authors consider removing this work from the current study and develop it further for a future publication.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with reviewers’ suggestion, and have removed this data from the revised manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #1:</p><p>[…] Overall, I found the quality of the science and the data presented to be very high. I have only two primary suggestions for experiments that I feel would strengthen the conclusions of the current manuscript.</p><p>1) The ∆RRM construct, which is a deletion, may have secondary effects on folding/stability of the encoded protein. Given that this EIF-3.G variant is used as an important control for seCLIP studies, I think it would be useful to check that this RRM deletion mutant protein is at least expressed at similar levels as the EIF-3.G wild type and C130Y variants. Since the authors already have FLAG-tagged versions of all three proteins for their CLIP experiments, it should not be too much work to perform a Western blot to compare protein levels.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for suggesting this important control. As responded to essential point 1: we have performed western blots as suggested. The results are shown in (Figure 4—figure supplement 1A). While we found that by western blotting the 3XFLAG::EIF-3.G(∆RRM) transgene is expressed at reduced levels compared to that of the EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) transgenes, we immunoprecipitated EIF3.G(∆RRM) at roughly equivalent levels to EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3.G(C130Y) during seCLIP due to the saturating effect of overnight immunoprecipitation. Furthermore, replicate seCLIP experiments using the EIF-3.G(∆RRM) transgene generated roughly three times the number of reads compared to seCLIP from the no transgene control (Supplementary File 4). We hope the reviewer agrees that the EIF-3.G(∆RRM) transgene serves as an effective control in our seCLIP analysis to identify binding sites specific to the RRM of EIF-3.G.</p><p>We describe the results in the revised results (lines 220-226) and methods (lines 652-661).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) The connection to structured 5'UTRs is intriguing but could be further strengthened by an experiment that more explicitly tests the role of secondary structure. For example, in addition to the UTR swapping experiments performed by the authors, it would also be informative to introduce mutations at nucleotides engaged in base-pairing interactions to see if eliminating these interactions influences regulation. If effects are observed, subsequent compensatory mutations that re-introduce base-pairing should be performed to revert back to patterns observed with the native 5'UTR.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree with the reviewer on the idea to strengthen the connection of structured 5’UTRs in regulating translation levels by <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>). We selected the <italic>ncs-2</italic> 5’UTR to test the idea. Using RNAfold, we identified a potential stem-loop/hairpin near the initiation codon ATG. While we used mutagenesis to alter this potential structure, after analyzing a number of transgenic lines, we encountered an unexpected outcome that the mutated 5’UTR led to mis-expression in other tissues. We speculate that these nucleotides may critically contribute to tissue-specific gene expression patterns in addition to the regulation of NCS-2 translation via EIF-3.G. Therefore, we did not further pursue this approach, although we will continue to investigate mechanistic basis of the 5’UTR-mediated regulation by EIF-3.G in our future studies.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #2:</p><p>[…] 1) The study provides a characterization of a new eif-3.g allele, which is interesting. However, the study does not come full circle and clarify how the eif-3.g mutation alters cholinergic neuron excitability. Nor does it show in a mechanistic sense how eif-3.g function depends on neuronal activity. It would be helpful if the authors could point to any efforts that they've made to revert the phenotype of eif-3.g via overexpression of eif-3.g(c130y)-downregulated target genes. If they were able to show such an effect, this would greatly enhance the study.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for this suggestion and agree that showing such an effect would enhance our study. We generated strains overexpressing transgenes of the EIF3.G target genes <italic>ncs-2</italic>, <italic>flp-18</italic>, and <italic>sbt-1</italic>, but none of the transgenes reverted convulsion behavior in <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) double mutants. These observations are in-line with our previous and recent publications (Stawicki et al., 2013, and McCulloch et al., 2020) showing that it takes co-expression of multiple insulin genes or multiple <italic>flp</italic> and <italic>nlp</italic> genes to affect <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>). Our data supports <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) modulation of convulsion behavior as the result of altered expression of many genes that together affect ACh-MN activity.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) It is interesting that eif-3.g(C130Y) decreases translation of hlh-30 and ncs-2 only in acr-2(gf) mutants. Is this a direct consequence of elevated neural activity in Ach MNs? For example, does silencing of these neurons attenuate the ability of eif-3.g(C130Y) to decrease ncs-2 GFP reporter translation?</p></disp-quote><p>We appreciate the reviewer’s suggestion for testing this model. As responded above in essential point 4: We found that <italic>unc-13</italic>(<italic>0</italic>) prevents HLH-30 upregulation in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) and attenuates the ability of <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) to decrease HLH-30 expression in <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>). The new data suggests that the observed <italic>eif-3.G(C130Y)</italic> is specific for elevated neuronal activity in ACh MNs, and is shown in Figure 6C and described in the revised text (lines 347-350).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) A couple of extra genetic controls would bolster the paper: (i) using CRISPR to engineer a revertant of the C130Y eif-3.g mutation and asking whether this abolishes the phenotype; and (ii) overexpressing eif-3.g(C130Y) in Ach MNs and asking whether this is sufficient to induce the phenotype.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for proposing these controls. As responded above in essential point 2: We took the reviewers suggestion (point ii) and expressed the GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) transgene in the <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>0</italic>) background, which is deficient of endogenous EIF-3.G, and found that it strongly suppresses <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) convulsions. This result is reported in Figure 2A and described in the revised text (lines 158-163).</p><p>In addition, we used CRISPR editing to change the first cysteine of the EIF-3.G zinc finger CCHC motif to tyrosine (C127Y) and found that it affects <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) behavior to the same extent as <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>), suggesting <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) behavior is generally affected by altered EIF-3.G zinc finger function. The new result is reported in Figure 1C and in the revised manuscript (lines 107-113, 432-434, and 528-535).</p><p>Together, these results further support the conclusion that <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) is the mutation causing suppression of <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) The use of neuronal cell type-specific seCLIP is exciting, but only 2 replicates were conducted and there is no systematic validation of the detected binding sites. RT-qPCR should be used to validate detected binding sites on a handful of targets.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree that a validation of seCLIP targets using an RT-qPCR approach would improve confidence in our seCLIP results. However, as most of the targets show broad expression in multiple tissues, including intestine, the RNA isolated from the entire worm have very low or little representation of neuronal transcripts. This is why we chose to examine GFP reporter expression for EIF-3.G target genes. As responded to the essential point 3, we screened ten reporters of EIF-3.G target genes reporters (including <italic>hlh-30</italic> and <italic>ncs-2</italic>), and found six showing detectable expression in ACh-MNs. As with NCS-2 and HLH-30, we found that ATF-7 and LET-607 expression in the ACh-MNs is reduced specifically in the <italic>eif-3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>); <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>) background. We have added our observations of these reporters in the revised Supplementary File 1.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) For Figure 4E-F and related analyses: the authors are comparing the eif-3.g targets to the full transcriptome to determine notable properties of the eif-3.g-bound gene set. I believe that for these analyses it would be more appropriate to compare the eif-3.g-bound gene set to the set of ACH MN-expressed genes (which the authors have measured in a previous study). In its current form, it is unclear whether the length and GC content of the eif-3.g-bound genes is a general property of cholinergic neuron gene expression. The same idea also applies to the GO analyses.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for this suggestion. In our revised Figures 4E-F, we now show that the length and GC-content of 5’UTRs among EIF-3.G targets (n=179) is significantly longer than that of the cholinergic transcriptome (n= 4,573; McCulloch et al., 2020). The results are described in the revised text (lines 270-278).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>6) Related to the length of the eif-3.g-bound 5'UTRs, longer RNA sequences have a higher probability of having a detected binding site (i.e. the number of detected binding sites along any region of DNA/RNA should scale with length). It is not clear whether the authors correct for this in their analysis.</p></disp-quote><p>The reviewer raises a valid concern that the number of seCLIP detected binding sites should scale with transcript length. Our initial detection of read clusters comprising EIF-3.G footprints in 5’UTRs was independent of their length. This is because we grouped all clusters located in either the CDS or 5’UTR into one category (5’UTR proximal), since CDS clusters in our seCLIP data were almost always located within 200nts of a 5’UTR (Figure 4D). We now clearly state this detail in the revised methods (lines 717-719).</p><p>It is also important to note that we identified one cluster per gene on average for each EIF-3.G transgene (Supplementary File 5). Furthermore, we identified EIF-3.G binding sites in many small transcripts such as neuropeptide genes, which are among the shortest transcripts in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> transcriptome and were among the most highly enriched in our dataset of EIF-3.G targets (Figure 5A). Together, these data suggest that EIF-3.G binding sites are detected independent of transcript length.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #3:</p><p>[…] 1. The statistical representation in Figure 1E is somewhat misguided. In order to show that eif3.G increases convulsion in acr-2 (gf); eif-3.G(C130Y) in an ACh-MN-specific manner, the statistical analysis of the right 4 samples should be done with WT or (-), not with Ex[eif-3.G(+)].</p></disp-quote><p>Thank you for pointing us to this error. We have now corrected Figure 1E with statistical analysis against the WT control instead of with Ex[<italic>eif-3.G</italic>(+)].</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2. The statement 'Both GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) and EIF-3G(C130Y) showed cytoplasmic fluorescence throughout somatic cells and across all developmental stages' is not well-presented in Figure 1—figure supplement 1B, since only the wild-type and one developmental stage (L4) was shown. It is also unclear if the bright puncta across the animal actually correspond to Peif-3.g::GFP or is a result of autofluorescence from the gut. It will be useful to include arrows and insets to highlight the pattern of interest (e.g., cytoplasmic, specific somatic tissues). To elaborate on the tissue specificity suggested in Figure 1E, whether EIF-3.G WT and C130Y are expressed in ACh-MN neuron should be discussed – This will differentiate whether the C130Y effect is cell-autonomous or non-autonomous. The authors also referred to Figure supplement 1B and Figure 2B as assessments of EIF-3.G protein stability – Expression pattern/localization would be more appropriate than protein stability here.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for pointing out the issue and for suggestions. We have added new images of L4 animals expressing GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) and GFP::EIF-G(C130Y) to the revised manuscript (Figure 1—figure supplement 1B), which shows that both GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) and GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) show indistinguishable tissue expression pattern through somatic cells.</p><p>We revised our description of the data in the revised text (lines 153-155) to</p><p>“Fluorescence from both GFP::EIF-3.G(WT) and GFP::EIF-3.G(C130Y) was observed</p><p>in all somatic cells (Figure 1—figure supplement 1B). In ACh-MNs, both proteins showed cytoplasmic localization (Figure 2B).”</p><p>We also edited the Figure 1—figure supplement 1B legend in the revised text (lines 958-962) to make clear that the bright punctae observed across the animal midbody are auto-fluorescent gut granules.</p><p>In addition, our conclusions regarding EIF-3.G protein stability now refer exclusively to the analysis in Figure 2B (lines 163-166 of the revised text).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3. In Figure 3A, the potential involvement of ife-1 (one of the eIF4E homologs) in eif-3.g(C130Y) suppression of acr-2(gf) is interesting. Some experiments are needed to discern the direct/indirect nature of this genetic interaction.</p><p>A. Does ife-1(0) cause convulsion in eif-3.G(C130Y) alone (acr-2 wild-type)?</p><p>B. Does ife-1(0) alter eif-3.G WT and C130Y expression?</p><p>C. ife-1 was shown to be predominantly expressed in the germline where it is important for germ cell development (Henderson et al., Journal of Cell Science 2009; Amiri et al., Development 2001). Moreover, the protein is undetectable by western blot from germline-deficient glp-4(bn2) animal (Amiri et al. 2001), potentially indicating exclusive germline expression. Thus, it will be important to look at whether IFE-1 is co-expressed with EIF-3.G WT and C130Y in the soma and ACh-MN.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for posing these questions. As recommended in the editorial summary, we have removed data pertaining to <italic>ife</italic> genes. We will keep reviewer’s questions in mind in our future analyses of these genes.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4. EIF-3.G preference for long 5' UTR with high GC content was nicely dissected from the seCLIP data in Figure 4. For consistency, the authors could provide information of 5'UTR length and GC content between upregulated and downregulated genes in acr-2(gf) over WT, shown in Figure 5B. hlh-30 and ncs-2 were further linked to eif-3.g-mediated suppression of acr-2(gf) by examining their expression using GFP reporters in Figures 6 and 7. Polysome profiling can be done to differentiate the effect of C130Y on the translation efficiency of these transcripts, as opposed to their transcription and protein stability. It would also be informative to show the preference of these genes for <italic>C. elegans</italic> eIF4E homologs, IFE-1, IFE-2, and IFE-4.</p></disp-quote><p>We appreciate this suggestion. We performed an analysis of 5’UTR length and GC-content among GO categories as well as up- and down-regulated genes, but did not observe significant correlation between them and therefore did not include this data.</p><p>We performed qRT-PCR for <italic>ncs-2</italic> and <italic>hlh-30</italic> transcripts from polysome fractions prepared from whole worm lysates, as the reviewer suggested. Unfortunately, we did not obtain meaningful results from this analysis, partly due to technical limitation as polysome profiles from whole worm lysates lack specificity to the ACh-MNs where <italic>eif3.G</italic>(<italic>C130Y</italic>) acts to suppress <italic>acr-2</italic>(<italic>gf</italic>).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5. A heatmap in Figure 4 —figure supplement 2C needs hierarchical clustering, even though genes in the map are already clustered top to bottom by increasing positional GC-density near the start codon. It may help extract additional meaningful information. The authors also need to point out the genes described in the text (pmt-2, let-607, unc-43, and gsa-1).</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for suggesting this analysis. We have added hierarchical clustering to the heatmap in Figure 4—figure supplement 2C, which has highlighted interesting examples of GC-density positioning for the genes (<italic>zip-2</italic>, <italic>sec-61</italic>, <italic>pdf-1</italic>, and <italic>kin-10</italic>). We now discuss in the revised text (lines 278-283) and point out genes described in the text within the figure as suggested.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>6. The statistical representation in the graph in Figure 6D needs to be corrected.</p></disp-quote><p>Thank you! We have corrected the statistical representation in the revised Figure 6D.</p></body></sub-article></article>