<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.2" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">69544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.69544</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biochemistry and Chemical Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Chromosomes and Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Crosstalk between repair pathways elicits double-strand breaks in alkylated DNA and implications for the action of temozolomide</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-199111"><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>Robert P</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1098-4325</contrib-id><email>robert.fuchs@inserm.fr</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-235007"><name><surname>Isogawa</surname><given-names>Asako</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-23686"><name><surname>Paulo</surname><given-names>Joao A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-235008"><name><surname>Onizuka</surname><given-names>Kazumitsu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-235009"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Tatsuro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-235010"><name><surname>Amunugama</surname><given-names>Ravindra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-235011"><name><surname>Duxin</surname><given-names>Julien P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa2">‡</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-235012"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Shingo</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5800-7235</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Biological Chemistry and Molecular Pharmacology, Harvard Medical School</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Boston</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Cancer Research Center of Marseille, UMR7258, CNRS</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Marseille</named-content></addr-line><country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Cell Biology, Harvard Medical School</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Boston</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Institute of Multidisciplinary Research for Advanced Materials, Tohoku University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Sendai</named-content></addr-line><country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Faculty of Science, Kyushu University</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Fukuoka</named-content></addr-line><country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>Wolf-Dietrich</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of California, Davis</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Struhl</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>Harvard Medical School</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa1"><label>†</label><p>Marseille Medical Genetics, UMR1251, Marseille, France</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa2"><label>‡</label><p>The Novo Nordisk Foundation Center for Protein Research, University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>08</day><month>07</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e69544</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2021-04-19"><day>19</day><month>04</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2021-07-07"><day>07</day><month>07</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a preprint at bioRxiv.</event-desc><date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2020-11-22"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.11.21.391326"/></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021, Fuchs et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Fuchs et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-69544-v2.pdf"/><abstract><p>Temozolomide (TMZ), a DNA methylating agent, is the primary chemotherapeutic drug used in glioblastoma treatment. TMZ induces mostly N-alkylation adducts (N7-methylguanine and N3-methyladenine) and some O<sup>6</sup>-methylguanine (O<sup>6</sup>mG) adducts. Current models propose that during DNA replication, thymine is incorporated across from O<sup>6</sup>mG, promoting a futile cycle of mismatch repair (MMR) that leads to DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs). To revisit the mechanism of O<sup>6</sup>mG processing, we reacted plasmid DNA with N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU), a temozolomide mimic, and incubated it in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg-derived extracts. We have shown that in this system, MMR proteins are enriched on MNU-treated DNA and we observed robust, MMR-dependent, repair synthesis. Our evidence also suggests that MMR, initiated at O<sup>6</sup>mG:C sites, is strongly stimulated in cis by repair processing of other lesions, such as N-alkylation adducts. Importantly, MNU-treated plasmids display DSBs in extracts, the frequency of which increases linearly with the square of alkylation dose. We suggest that DSBs result from two independent repair processes, one involving MMR at O<sup>6</sup>mG:C sites and the other involving base excision repair acting at a nearby N-alkylation adduct. We propose a new, replication-independent mechanism of action of TMZ, which operates in addition to the well-studied cell cycle-dependent mode of action.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>mismatch repair</kwd><kwd>base excision repair crosstalk</kwd><kwd>sn1 versus sn2</kwd><kwd>alkylating agents</kwd><kwd>unbiased dna</kwd><kwd>binding proteins discovery</kwd><kwd>protein-dna</kwd><kwd>pull-down assay</kwd><kwd>closely-spaced dna lesions</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd><italic>Xenopus</italic></kwd><kwd>Other</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R01 GM132129</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Paulo</surname><given-names>Joao A</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001691</institution-id><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>JP20H03186</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Tatsuro</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001691</institution-id><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>JP20H05392</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Tatsuro</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>DNA lesions formed by alkylating agents trigger double-strand breaks, in the absence of replication, by the action of MMR and BER at nearby O-alkyl and N-alkyl adducts, respectively.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Alkylating agents, a class of important environmental carcinogens, have been widely used in molecular biology to study fundamental repair processes and in the clinic to treat cancer patients. Among the DNA adducts produced by methylating agents such as N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU) and temozolomide (TMZ), a clinically used mimic, the most abundant are two N-alkylation adducts, at the N7 position of guanine (7mG: 70–75% of total alkyl adducts) and the N3 position of adenine (3mA: 8–12%). Importantly, both reagents also produce 8–9% O-alkylation adducts in the form of O<sup>6</sup>-methylguanine (O<sup>6</sup>mG). This feature contrasts with another common methylating agent, methyl-methane sulfonate (MMS), which forms a much lower level of O<sup>6</sup>mG (&lt;0.3%) while producing similarly high proportions of 7mG (81–83%) and 3mA (10–11%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Beranek, 1990</xref>). For many years, the differences in O versus N reactivities have been rationalized by differences in chemical reaction mechanisms; on one side, compounds such as MMS, with very low O-reactivity, were classified as SN2 agents (bimolecular nucleophilic substitution) while other agents, such as MNU and TMZ, with increased O adduct formation, were called SN1 agents (monomolecular nucleophilic substitution). While this classification turned out not to be mechanistically accurate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Loechler, 1994</xref>), we will nevertheless use this nomenclature throughout this paper for the sake of simplicity. The major N-alkylation (N-alkyl) adducts (7mG and 3mA) are repaired by base excision repair (BER), using N-methylpurine DNA glycosylase (MPG), also known as 3-alkyladenine DNA glycosylase (AAG), and alkylpurine DNA N-glycosylase (APNG) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Chakravarti et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lindahl, 1976</xref>). O-alkylation adducts (O<sup>6</sup>mG, O<sup>4</sup>mT) can be directly repaired by O<sup>6</sup>-methylguanine DNA methyl transferase (MGMT), a protein that transfers the methyl group from these adducts to one of its cysteine residues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Demple et al., 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Olsson and Lindahl, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Tano et al., 1990</xref>). In addition, alkylating agents also produce a variety of other minor (1–2%) N-alkyl adducts, namely 1mA, 3mC, 3mT, and 1mG that are directly demethylated by AlkB homologs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aas et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Duncan et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Falnes et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Trewick et al., 2002</xref>). In summary, SN1 and SN2 alkylating agents produce a diverse array of DNA adducts, but they differ greatly in the amount of O<sup>6</sup>mG produced.</p><p>Agents such as MMS mostly induce N-alkyl adducts that lead to DSBs during S-phase as a consequence of BER repair. Indeed, inactivation of the AAG glycosylase, the BER-initiating enzyme, suppresses DSB while inactivation of Polβ leads to their exacerbation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Simonelli et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Tang et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Trivedi et al., 2005</xref>). In rodent cells, it was proposed that MMS-induced DSBs arise when replication meets BER-induced single-strand breaks (SSBs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Ensminger et al., 2014</xref>). The toxicity of N-alkyl adducts was found to depend on cell type. AAG-mediated repair of N-alkyl adducts was found to mitigate toxicity in mouse ES cells and HeLa cells, while repair was shown to cause toxic intermediates in retina and bone marrow cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Meira et al., 2009</xref>). In all cell types, O-alkyl adducts were found to be highly cytotoxic and mutagenic. While the mutagenicity of O<sup>6</sup>mG is easily accounted for by its high propensity to mispair with T during DNA synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bhanot and Ray, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Loechler et al., 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Mazon et al., 2010</xref>), its cytotoxicity is intriguing since O<sup>6</sup>mG per se does not interfere with DNA synthesis. A seminal paper, published 50 years ago by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Plant and Roberts, 1971</xref>, noted that when synchronized HeLa cells are treated in G1 with MNU, they continue through the first cell cycle almost normally and with little effect on DNA synthesis. On the other hand, there is a dramatic effect on DNA synthesis in the second cell cycle after MNU exposure. These data led the authors to surmise that cytotoxicity stems from a secondary lesion that forms when DNA synthesis occurs across O<sup>6</sup>mG template adducts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Plant and Roberts, 1971</xref>). It was demonstrated later that MNU-mediated inhibition of DNA synthesis, in the first and the second cycle, is due to the action of the MMR machinery that acts on O<sup>6</sup>mG:T lesions that form upon DNA synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Goldmacher et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kat et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Noonan et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Plant and Roberts, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Quiros et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>Indeed, O<sup>6</sup>mG:T lesions were found to be excellent substrates for MMR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Duckett et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Yoshioka et al., 2006</xref>). During MMR gap-filling, the O<sup>6</sup>mG:T mispair is reformed, potentially leading to another round of MMR, thus entering so-called futile MMR cycles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Kaina et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Karran and Bignami, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Olivera Harris et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">York and Modrich, 2006</xref>). The MMR cycling model has received experimental support in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">York and Modrich, 2006</xref>) and in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Mazon et al., 2010</xref>). Studies with synchronized cells have shown that the critical events related to cytotoxicity occur in the second cell cycle post-treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Quiros et al., 2010</xref>). However, as discussed in recent review articles, the precise mechanism by which MMR leads to DSBs has yet to be established (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gupta and Heinen, 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Kaina and Christmann, 2019</xref>).</p><p>While most studies have been devoted to MNU-induced cell cycle effects, in the present paper we wanted to investigate the early response to MNU treatment, that is, in the absence of replication. We addressed this question using <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg-derived extracts, which recapitulate most forms of DNA repair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wühr et al., 2014</xref>). Upon incubation in these extracts, plasmids treated with MNU exhibit robust repair synthesis in the absence of replication. Repair synthesis occurs at O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesions, depends on MMR, and involves an excision tract of several hundred nucleotides. MMR events at O<sup>6</sup>mG:C sites are robustly stimulated by additional processing at N-alkylation lesions, most likely via BER. Previous studies have described activation of MMR in the absence of replication in cells treated by SN1-methylating agents, a process termed noncanonical MMR (ncMMR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Peña-Diaz et al., 2012</xref>). Interestingly, we observed replication-independent induction of DSBs in MNU-treated plasmids. The kinetics of DSB formation obeys a quadratic MNU dose-response, suggesting the involvement of two independent repair events. We propose that DSBs occur when the gap generated at an O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct during MMR overlaps with a BER intermediate initiated at an N-alkyl adduct in the opposite strand.</p><p>These data reveal a novel facet of MNU-induced damage to DNA that is replication independent. Extrapolation of the in vitro data led us estimate that ≈ 10 DSBs per cell can be induced by a single daily dose of TMZ used in the clinic in the absence of replication.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Reaction conditions leading to similar levels of DNA alkylation</title><p>Our goal is to determine the DNA proteome for distinct alkylating agents. For the sake of comparison, we needed to determine the reaction conditions for different alkylating agents that lead to similar levels of total alkylation. As a proxy for total alkylation, we monitored the amount of N-alkyl adducts, namely 7mG and 3mA, that together represents &gt;80% of alkylation for MMS and MNU. Estimation of the N-alkyl adduct level is achieved by converting these adducts to single-stranded DNA (ssDNA) breaks by a combination of heat depurination and alkali cleavage treatments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Maxam and Gilbert, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>). The resulting plasmid fragmentation patterns were resolved and analyzed by agarose gel electrophoresis. The reaction conditions were adjusted (by trial and error) as to generate a median fragment size of 500 nt, corresponding to one alkylated base every 500 nucleotides on average (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Identification of the proteins that specifically bind to DNA alkylation damage in nucleoplasmic extracts</title><p>In order to identify the proteins binding to O<sup>6</sup>mG-containing base pairs in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg-derived extracts, we used a recently developed plasmid pull-down procedure, IDAP, for the identification of DNA-associated proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Isogawa et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Isogawa et al., 2018</xref>). As outlined above, MNU produces twenty- to twentyfivefold more O<sup>6</sup>mG lesions than MMS (0.3% and 7–8% of total alkylation, respectively), while the relative amounts of N-alkyl lesions produced by the two agents are similar (&gt;80% of N7mG+N3mA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Beranek, 1990</xref>). These agents react chemically with DNA under neutral pH conditions, and we established in vitro reaction conditions that trigger comparable levels of plasmid alkylation (see above and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>).</p><p>The pull-down procedure involves immobilization of plasmid DNA on magnetic beads by means of a triple helix-forming probe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Isogawa et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Isogawa et al., 2018</xref>). The same amount of untreated or alkylated plasmids was coupled to magnetic beads and incubated in nucleoplasmic extracts (NPE) derived from <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Walter et al., 1998</xref>). The reaction was stopped by dilution into a formaldehyde-containing buffer, which fixes protein-DNA complexes. After washing the beads and reversing the cross-links, the recovered proteins were visualized by silver staining following sodium dodecyl sulphate–polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>). As a negative control, mock-conjugated beads (noDNA control lane) exhibit a low-protein background, illustrating efficient removal of non-specific proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Proteins captured on the different plasmid samples were analyzed by label-free mass spectrometry (MS) as described in 'Materials and methods'. The MS data are presented in the form of volcano plots. When comparing MNU-treated to undamaged control plasmids, the MMR proteins (labeled in red) were highly enriched in the MNU sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). All six canonical MMR proteins (MSH2, MSH3, MSH6, MLH1, PMS1, and PMS2) were specifically enriched on MNU plasmids. These proteins form the MutSα, MutSβ, MutLα, and MutLβ heterodimers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Jiricny, 2006</xref>). Other proteins known to participate in MMR, RAD18, POLη, EXO1, and two subunits of Pol delta (POLD2 and POLD3), were also specifically enriched on MNU plasmids. Previously, it was shown that purified MutSα does not bind to O<sup>6</sup>mG:C base pairs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Yoshioka et al., 2006</xref>). Our present experiments involve extracts containing many proteins, and there is probably synergy between MutSα and MutLα (and other proteins) to achieve full MMR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ortega et al., 2021</xref>). Activation of MMR by a single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion has been reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Duckett et al., 1999</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Pull-down of proteins that bind to alkylated versus untreated plasmid DNA.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental workflow. Plasmid DNA (pAS04, 6.5 kb) was treated with alkylating agents under conditions leading to a similar extent of N-alkylation (<bold>≈</bold> one alkaline cleavage site every 500 nt) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>). Immobilized plasmid DNA was incubated in <italic>Xenopus</italic> nucleoplasmic extracts (NPE) for 10 min at room temperature under mild agitation. The reaction was stopped by addition of formaldehyde (0.8% final) to cross-link the protein-DNA complexes. The beads were processed and analyzed by polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) or by mass spectrometry (MS) as described in 'Materials and methods'. (<bold>B</bold>) Relative abundance of proteins captured on N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU)-treated versus -untreated DNA0. Proteins captured on equal amounts of MNU-treated or -untreated plasmid were analyzed by label-free MS in triplicate. For all proteins, average spectral count values in the MNU-treated plasmid sample were divided by the average spectral count values in the DNA0 sample. The resulting ratio is plotted as its log<sub>2</sub> value along x-axis. The statistical significance of the data is estimated by the p-value in the Student’s t-test and plotted as -log<sub>10</sub>p along y-axis. Proteins enriched on MNU versus untreated plasmid DNA appear on the right-side top corner and essentially turn out to be mismatch repair (MMR) proteins labeled in red (<bold>B</bold>). Data shown are analyzed using Xenbase database. (<bold>C</bold>) Relative abundance of proteins captured on methyl-methane sulfonate (MMS)-treated versus -untreated DNA0. Proteins captured on equal amounts of MMS-treated or -untreated plasmid were analyzed by label-free MS in triplicate. The data are analyzed and plotted as in panel (<bold>B</bold>) for MNU using Xenbase database. Proteins (labeled in green in <bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold>) are found enriched or excluded in both MMS versus DNA0 and MNU versus DNA0 plasmids. We suggest these proteins are recruited or excluded from binding to DNA by the abundant class of N-alkylation adducts that both MMS- and MNU-treated plasmids share in common (~27 N-alkyl adducts per plasmid).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Alkylation reaction conditions and differential protein capture data.</title><p>( <bold><bold>A</bold></bold>) Alkylation reaction conditions and alkaline cleavage. The alkylation reaction conditions (concentration, reaction temperature, and time) were adjusted by successive trials until an average of one N-alkyl adduct per 500 nt was reached. The desired level of alkylation (≈1 N-alkyl adduct/500nt) was attested using the alkaline cleavage procedure, followed by neutral agarose gel electrophoresis (for details, see 'Materials and methods'). (<bold>B</bold>) Polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) analysis and silver staining of the captured proteins. Proteins captured on equal amounts of immobilized plasmid DNA incubated in nucleoplasmic extracts (NPE) (as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>) were resolved by denaturing gel electrophoresis and silver stained. Samples, corresponding to ≈30 ng of immobilized input plasmid DNA, were loaded on a 4–15% PAGE (Biorad pre-cast) gel, run at 200 volts for 32 min, and silver stained. Lanes DNA0, MMS, MNU, and ENU display a complex pattern of proteins (total amount of proteins per lane estimated at 100–200 ng). To monitor non-specific protein binding to beads, we included a negative control containing the same amount of M280 beads in the absence of plasmid DNA (noDNA). Importantly, in the noDNA lane, only a low amount of residual protein is visible, indicating efficient removal of non-specifically bound proteins during the washing procedure. (<bold>C</bold>) Relative abundance of proteins captured on N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU)- versus methyl-methane sulfonate (MMS)-treated plasmids. Proteins captured on equal amounts of MNU- or MMS-treated plasmids were analyzed by label-free mass spectrometry (MS) in triplicate. The data are analyzed and plotted as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref> using Xenbase database. Proteins enriched on MNU- versus MMS-treated DNA appear on the right-side top corner and essentially turn out to be mismatch repair (MMR) proteins labeled in red (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig1-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>It was previously noted that upon oxidative stress, produced by hydrogen peroxide treatment, RAD18 and Polη are recruited to chromatin in a MSH2-MSH6 (MutSα)-dependent manner in human cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Zlatanou et al., 2011</xref>). While MutSα, MutSβ, and MutLα functionally participate in MMR, the role of MutLβ (MLH1-PMS1) remains unknown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Jiricny, 2006</xref>). No MMR proteins were enriched on MMS-treated plasmids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). As MNU treatment induces 20–30 times more O<sup>6</sup>mG adducts than MMS, we postulate that recruitment of MMR proteins depends on O<sup>6</sup>mG. Comparison of proteins captured on MNU- versus MMS-treated plasmids indeed reveals specific enrichment of MMR proteins. Proteins specifically recruited at N-alkyl adducts (in green in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B and C</xref>) are absent in the MMS versus MNU volcano plot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1C</xref>), since N-alkyl adducts are equally present in both MMS- and MNU-treated plasmids.</p><p>In addition, compared to the lesion-free control plasmid, some proteins were enriched on or excluded from both MMS- and MNU-treated plasmids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B and C</xref>, green labels). We suggest that the recruitment or exclusion of these proteins depends on the abundant 7mG and 3mA adducts formed by both MMS and MNU. The reason why BER proteins, normally involved in the repair of these N-alkyl adducts, were not captured is unclear. One possibility is that BER proteins interact too transiently with DNA to be efficiently captured.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Repair of alkylated plasmid DNA in NPE</title><p>We next investigated the repair of DNA treated by the different alkylating agents in NPE. Plasmids were alkylated with MMS, MNU, or ENU to a density of one lesion every ≈500 nt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>). The alkylated plasmids were incubated in NPE in the presence of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP. These extracts contain high levels of geminin, an inhibitor of replication licensing. Therefore, any observed DNA synthesis occurs independently of DNA replication and corresponds to the so-called ‘unscheduled DNA synthesis’ (UDS) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). Undamaged plasmids exhibited a low level of background DNA synthesis, whereas MNU- and ENU-treated plasmids sustained robust, time-dependent UDS equivalent to 3–4% of the synthesis needed for a full round of replication (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). MMS-treated plasmids exhibited UDS that was just twofold above the background seen in undamaged plasmids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Given that the assay measures incorporation of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP, long-patch BER events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Sattler et al., 2003</xref>) will be detected, while short-patch BER events (1 nt patch) will only be detected at 3mA but not at 7mG adducts. The assay is clearly biased toward the detection of events such as MMR that involve repair patches hundreds of nucleotides long.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>DNA repair synthesis in alkylated and undamaged control plasmid DNA in NPE.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Outline of the spot assay. Plasmids were incubated in nuclear extracts supplemented with α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP; at various time points, an aliquot of the reaction mixture was spotted on DEAE paper (see 'Materials and methods'). The dot blot is shown for the sake of illustration only. (<bold>B</bold>) Plasmid DNA pBR322 (4.3 kb) samples, modified to a similar extent with -MMS, -MNU and -ENU, were incubated in nucleoplasmic extracts (NPE) supplemented with α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP at room temperature; incorporation of radioactivity was monitored as a function of time using the spot assay described above (<bold>A</bold>). Undamaged plasmid DNA0 was used as a control. At each time point, the average values and standard deviation from three independent experiments were plotted. The y-axis represents DNA repair synthesis expressed as a fraction of input plasmid replication (i.e., 10% means that the observed extent of repair synthesis is equivalent to 10% of input plasmid replication). This value was determined knowing the average concentration of dATP in the extract (50 μM) and the amount of added α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP. (<bold>C</bold>) N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MMS)- and N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU)-treated plasmids were incubated in NPE, supplemented or not, by aphidicolin (150 μM final). After 1 hr of incubation, plasmids were purified and analyzed by agarose gel electrophoresis under neutral loading conditions. The gel was imaged by fluorescence (left: ethidium bromide image) and by autoradiography (right: <sup>32</sup>P image). The number below each lane indicates the total amount of signals per lane (expressed in arbitrary units [AU]). Aphidicolin treatment decreases incorporation into MNU-treated plasmid close to fourfold, while it affected incorporation into MMS-treated plasmid only 1.6-fold. (<bold>D</bold>) Samples as in (<bold>C</bold>). Gel loading is performed under alkaline conditions to denature DNA before entering the neutral agarose gel, allowing single-stranded nicks present in DNA to be revealed. The number below each lane indicates the amount of signals per lane (AU).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Involvement of mismatch repair in repair synthesis and effect of aphidicolin.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Analysis by western blotting (WB) of the nucleoplasmic extracts (NPE) depleted for mismatch repair (MMR) proteins. Antibodies against Mlh1, Pms2, and Pms1 were used as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kato et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kawasoe et al., 2016</xref>). Extracts were depleted, with the respective antibodies, for three rounds at 4°C at a ratio bead: antibody: extract = 1:3:5. (<bold>B</bold>) Depletion experiments show that α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP incorporation into N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU) plasmid is mediated by mismatch repair. NPE was depleted by antibodies against Pms1, Pms2, Mlh1, or mock depleted. Upon incubation at room temperature in different NPE, incorporation of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP in MNU plasmid was monitored by the spot assay as a function of time. At each time point, the average values and standard deviations from two independent experiments were plotted. As expected from previous data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), robust incorporation was observed for MNU plasmid incubated in mock-depleted extracts. In contrast, radioactive dATP incorporation was severely reduced when the plasmid was incubated in extracts depleted with antibodies against Mlh1 or Pms2. These data strongly suggest that the incorporation seen in mock-depleted NPE is mediated by MMR, as both Mlh1 and Pms2 assemble into the functional MMR complex MutLα. In contrast, depletion with antibodies against Pms1 did not affect incorporation kinetics as Pms1 is reported not to function in MMR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Jiricny, 2006</xref>). (<bold>C</bold>) Effect of aphidicolin: alkylated plasmids (pEL97: 11.3 kb) were incubated in NPE supplemented or not by aphidicolin (150 μM final) in the presence of <sup>32</sup>P-dATP for 1 hr at room temperature (RT). Analysis was performed by spot assay as described in 'Materials and methods'. The y-axis represents the percentage of radioactive DNA synthesis expressed in % of full plasmid replication. Addition of aphidicolin to NPE (150 μM final) more severely reduces incorporation in MNU+, MNU++, and ENU plasmids, compared to control and methyl-methane sulfonate (MMS) plasmids. Fold reduction in incorporation under aphidicolin conditions is shown.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig2-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Repair synthesis in HSS extracts.</title><p>Plasmid treated with N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU) (≈1N-alkyl adduct/500nt) was incubated in high-speed supernatant (HSS) extracts in the presence of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP; repair synthesis was monitored at room temperature as a function of time using the spot assay. Both DNA0 and MNU plasmids exhibited background incorporation levels. Robust unscheduled DNA synthesis (UDS) was observed in MNU plasmid upon addition of hAAG glycosylase (150 nM). Average values and standard deviations from two independent experiments were plotted.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig2-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>We asked whether the observed UDS in MNU- and ENU-treated plasmids was MMR dependent, as suggested by the MS results. To test this idea, we depleted MMR proteins from extracts using antibodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A</xref>), whose specificity was previously validated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kato et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kawasoe et al., 2016</xref>). Depletion of MLH1 or PMS2 severely reduced UDS in MNU-treated plasmids, while no reduction was observed in PMS1-depleted extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1B</xref>). This observation is consistent with the fact that MutLα (composed of MLH1 and PMS2) is involved in canonical mismatch repair whereas MutLβ (composed of MLH1 and PMS1) is not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Jiricny, 2006</xref>). Aphidicolin (Aph), an inhibitor of B-family DNA polymerases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Baranovskiy et al., 2014</xref>), decreased incorporation, on average, by 3.5-fold on MNU and ENU plasmids while it had a more modest effect on MMS-treated plasmids (1.5-fold) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1C</xref>). These results support the notion that UDS on MNU- and ENU-treated plasmids involves MMR, including a gap-filling event that most likely depends on DNA Polδ, the only B family polymerase detected in the MS analysis described above. Short-patch BER events are mediated by Polβ (X family), which are insensitive to aphidicolin. The modest sensitivity of MMS-induced UDS to aphidicolin is probably due to a fraction of BER events that belong to the long-patch BER pathway mediated by Polδ/ε (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Sattler et al., 2003</xref>).</p><p>We wanted to estimate the average amounts of DNA synthesis associated with MMR at O<sup>6</sup>mG:C sites and BER at N-alkyl sites, respectively. At the 90 min time point (i.e., at near-plateau value), the difference in UDS between MNU- and MMS-treated plasmids, that is attributable to repair at O<sup>6</sup>mG:C sites, was equivalent to ≈3.1% of the input DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>) or ≈270 nt (pBR322 plasmid is 4363 bp long). With an estimated ≈1.7 O<sup>6</sup>mG adducts per plasmid, the average repair patch per O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct is ≈160 nt provided all O<sup>6</sup>mG lesions are targeted by MMR. Evidence obtained with G:T and O<sup>6</sup>mG:T constructs (see below) indicates that, under present experimental conditions, only about ≈30% of O<sup>6</sup>mG are substrates for MMR, suggesting that, on average, an MMR patch is ≈500 nt long. Importantly, the MGMT inhibitor Patrin-2 had no effect on UDS of MNU-treated plasmid, even at a dose of 200 μM (data not shown). Surprisingly, inhibition of MGMT by Patrin-2 was previously shown to occur in <italic>Xenopus</italic> extracts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Olivera Harris et al., 2015</xref>). Two possibilities may account for the lack of any measurable effect of MGMT inhibition: (i) the number of MGMT molecules present in the extract is small compared to the number of O<sup>6</sup>mG lesions introduced in the incubation mix or (ii) our batch of Patrin inhibitor is inactive. In all cases, if partial demethylation of O<sup>6</sup>mG by MGMT occurs, the observed amount of UDS would be under-estimated. Thus, the conclusion reached in the paper, namely that O<sup>6</sup>mG:C sites are substrates for MMR, remains correct.</p><p>With respect to N-alkyl adduct repair in MMS plasmid, repair synthesis above the lesion-free DNA control is equivalent to ≈0.5% of input DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), corresponding to 43 nt total synthesis per plasmid. With ≈17 N-alkyl adducts per plasmid, the average DNA synthesis patch per adduct, in case all N-alkyl lesions are repaired, is ≈2.6 nt, a value consistent with a mixture of long (≈2–8 nt)- and short-patch (1 nt) BER events at N-alkyl adducts. In summary, the average DNA repair patch sizes at O<sup>6</sup>mG:C (≈500 nt) and N-alkyl (2–3 nt) sites are compatible with MMR and BER, respectively.</p><p>To learn more about UDS in this system, we analyzed repair products via gel electrophoresis. Plasmid pBR322 treated with MMS or MNU was incubated in NPE, supplemented or not with aphidicolin in the presence of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP, and analyzed on a neutral agarose gel. As already noticed above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1C</xref>), addition of aphidicolin led to more severe reduction in incorporation into MNU (≈3.7-fold)- compared to MMS-treated plasmids (≈1.6-fold) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). We also note that in MNU-treated plasmids, in the absence of Aph, open circular repair products were threefold more abundant than closed circular products (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>; <sup>32</sup>P image). This observation suggests that MMR repair was complete in only ≈25% of plasmid molecules while 75% of molecules contained at least one nick (or a gap). Interestingly, there was a ≈50% loss of total DNA in the MNU+Aph lane compared to the other lanes, suggesting massive DNA degradation in NPE due to polymerase inhibition by Aph. Indeed, the observed DNA degradation can specifically be linked to repair events as the loss in radioactivity in MNU lanes -Aph versus +Aph is &gt;70% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>; <sup>32</sup>P image). Under alkaline loading conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>), repair products (<sup>32</sup>P image) in MNU-treated plasmids appeared mostly as a single-stranded linear band form. In addition, there was a large smear (&gt;25% of material) of shorter fragments. These results show that most plasmids contain one nick and some contain several nicks. In the +Aph samples, the open circular (oc) form, seen in the gel loaded under neutral conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>), disappears under alkaline loading conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). This suggests that these oc molecules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>) contain many nicks that run as short fragments upon denaturation. In conclusion, MNU-treated plasmids undergo robust repair synthesis that is more sensitive to aphidicolin inhibition than MMS-treated plasmids.</p><p>We next examined O<sup>6</sup>mG-induced DNA synthesis in a different extract, namely high-speed supernatant (HSS) of total egg lysate. Unmodified pBR322 plasmids (DNA0) or those treated with MNU to an extent of ≈1 N-alkyl adduct/500nt were incubated in the presence of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP. Repair synthesis was monitored at room temperature (RT) as a function of time using the spot assay described above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). In HSS extract, MNU-treated plasmids did not exhibit significant repair synthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>), in contrast to the robust repair synthesis seen in NPE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Although, HSS contains lower concentrations of most DNA repair enzymes compared to NPE, HSS was shown to be proficient for MMR at a single O<sup>6</sup>mG provided a nick is present in proximity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Olivera Harris et al., 2015</xref>). We reasoned that HSS might not contain adequate concentrations of the DNA glycosylase AAG, which initiates BER at N-alkyl sites. When HSS extract was supplemented with purified AAG glycosylase (150 nM) (NEB, Biolabs), robust repair synthesis is observed in MNU-treated plasmids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>). These observations suggest the involvement of BER in stimulating MMR at O<sup>6</sup>mG lesions.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>MMR at single O<sup>6</sup>mG-containing base pairs is enhanced by the presence of N-alkylation adducts</title><p>Next, we explored a possible crosstalk between repair pathways acting on alkylated DNA. In MNU-treated plasmids, there is on average one O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct for every 9–10 N-alkyl adducts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Beranek, 1990</xref>). To investigate the repair response triggered by a single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion alone or in the presence of additional N-alkyl adducts, we implemented a reconstitution experiment. For that purpose, a single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C construct (mGC) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Isogawa et al., 2020</xref>) was treated with MMS to introduce ≈9–10 N-alkyl adducts per plasmid molecule, generating plasmid mGC+MMS, which is expected to recapitulate adduct distribution found in MNU-treated plasmids. Control plasmid GC was treated with the same concentration of MMS, to generate GC+MMS. These in vitro manipulations did not affect plasmid topology as all four constructs exhibit a similar migration pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1A</xref>).</p><p>Plasmid constructs GC and mGC and the corresponding two MMS-treated constructs (GC+MMS and mGC+MMS) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>) were incubated with NPE in the presence of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP to monitor repair synthesis (i.e., UDS). We observed incorporation of radioactivity specifically attributable to the single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion (compare mGC with GC in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). Activation of MMR by a single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion has been reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Duckett et al., 1999</xref>). The specific involvement of MMR in O<sup>6</sup>mG-dependent incorporation was re-assessed, by incubating the single adducted O<sup>6</sup>mG:C construct in MLH1-depleted NPE; radioactive incorporation above background was fully abolished in mGC plasmids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1E</xref>). How MMR may get engaged in a repair reaction on a closed circular template will be considered in the 'Discussion' section.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Stimulation of MMR at a single O<sup>6</sup>mG site by N-alkyl adducts in cis.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Covalently closed circular (ccc) plasmids (pAS200.2, 2.1 kb) containing a site-specific O<sup>6</sup>mG:C base pair (plasmid mGC) and the corresponding lesion-free control (plasmid GC) were constructed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Isogawa et al., 2020</xref>). Similarly, plasmids with a site-specific GT or a O<sup>6</sup>mG:T mismatch were constructed. All the four constructs were treated with methyl-methane sulfonate (MMS) in order to introduce random N-alkyl (7mG and 3mA) adducts, generating plasmids GC+MMS, mGC+MMS, GT+MMS, and mGT+MMS. We adjusted the MMS reaction conditions as to introduce <bold>≈</bold> nine adducts per plasmid (i.e., one N-alkylation adduct every ≈500 nt). The resulting proportion of O-alk and N-alkyl adducts mimics the proportion in N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU)-treated plasmids. The single O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct and the randomly located N-alkyl adducts are represented by a star and red dots, respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) Plasmids described above were incubated in nucleoplasmic extracts (NPE) supplemented with α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP at room temperature; incorporation of radioactivity was monitored as a function of time using the spot assay. The y-axis represents the percentage of DNA repair synthesis with respect to input DNA (i.e., 10% means that the observed extent of repair synthesis is equivalent to 10% of input plasmid replication). Overall, incorporation into GT and mGT plasmids is higher than incorporation into their GC and mGC counterparts. Incorporation attributable to repair at the O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion is increased close to threefold due to the presence of random N-alkyl lesions introduced by MMS treatment. The stimulatory effect of random N-alkyl lesions on GT and mGT repair is observed but is slightly less pronounced than for mGC. (<bold>C</bold>) The same plasmids were incubated for 2 hr in NPE, purified, resolved by agarose gel electrophoresis, and revealed by ethidium bromide fluorescence and <sup>32</sup>P autoradiography. The total amount of signals per lane is indicated (arbitrary units [AU]). As expected, the amount of plasmid extracted from each incubation mix is relatively constant, as quantified below the ethidium bromide image. Increase in repair at the O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion due to MMS treatment (2.8-fold) is in good agreement with data in (<bold>B</bold>).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Mapping repair synthesis in the vicinity of a single O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Agarose gel electrophoresis of the native form of GC, mGC, GC+MMS, and mGC+MMS. (<bold>B</bold>) Restriction map of pAS201; the two single cutter enzymes <italic>BmtI</italic> and <italic>BaeGI</italic> yield a short S (589 bp) and a long L (1525 bp) fragment, respectively. Fragment S contains the single O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct. (<bold>C</bold>) Plasmids GC, mGC, GC+MMS, and mGC+MMS were incubated in nucleoplasmic extracts (NPE) in the presence of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP and extracted after 2 hr. The purified plasmids were digested with restriction enzymes <italic>BmtI</italic> and <italic>BaeGI</italic>. Digested plasmids were analyzed by agarose gel electrophoresis and visualized by ethidium bromide staining and by <sup>32</sup>P imaging. (<bold>D</bold>) The specific activity (SA) of a given fragment (S or L) was quantified as the amount of <sup>32</sup>P incorporated divided by the amount of DNA deduced from the ethidium bromide fluorescence image (expressed in arbitrary units [AU]). In control plasmid GC, a similar SA value was observed for both fragments as expected for residual background incorporation; similarly, in methyl-methane sulfonate (MMS)-treated plasmids (GC+MMS), the SA value was similar for S and L fragments. The slightly increased SA value in GC+MMS compared to GC is compatible with repair synthesis by base excision repair (BER) at randomly located MMS-induced lesions. For plasmids containing a single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion (mGC and mGC+MMS), there is a robust increase in SA of the short compared to the long fragments. Incorporation, above background, due to O<sup>6</sup>mG, in the absence of MMS, amounts to 0.065 and 0.495 AU for long and short fragments, respectively (signal above the dotted line in S3D). Similarly, in the context of MMS lesions, incorporation, above background, due to O<sup>6</sup>mG, amounts to 0.115 and 1.17 AU for long and short fragments, respectively (signal above the dotted line in S3D). Taken together, these results clearly show that O<sup>6</sup>mGC-mediated repair specifically takes place in the S fragment, with only modest spill-over into the L fragment (10–15%). (<bold>E</bold>) Plasmids with a single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion site (mGC) and control plasmids (GC) were incubated in NPE depleted with anti-Mlh1 antibodies and mock-treated NPE. Incorporation was measured into whole plasmids. The increase in incorporation into mGC compared to GC observed upon incubation in NPE fully disappeared when Mlh1 was depleted. This experiment shows that the increase in incorporation observed in mGC compared to incorporation in control GC plasmid can specifically be attributed to mismatch repair activity at the single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig3-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>Importantly, repair synthesis, due to the single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion, is strongly enhanced by the presence of MMS adducts (compare mGC+MMS with GC+MMS in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). At the 2 hr time point, incorporation, above background, due to the single O<sup>6</sup>mG, expressed in % replication equivalent, represents 0.64% (difference between mGC and GC), while it amounts to 1.85% in the presence of MMS lesions (compare mGC+MMS with GC+MMS). One can thus estimate that, incorporation due to a single O<sup>6</sup>mG lesion, is stimulated about 2.9-fold (1.85/0.64) by the presence in cis of MMS adducts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>).</p><p>Finally, we wanted to compare the relative MMR repair efficiencies triggered by O<sup>6</sup>mG:C and O<sup>6</sup>mG:T (or GT) mismatches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A and B</xref>). These constructs were used as single adducted constructs or, after additional reaction with MMS, similarly to the procedure described for the corresponding GC or mGC constructs. The main observation is that GT-containing constructs trigger a much stronger MMR response than their GC counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). In the absence of MMS, at the 120′ time point, the level of UDS in mGC represents 23% of the level in mGT. In the presence of MMS, at the 120′ time point, the level of UDS in mGC+MMS represents 38% of the level in mGT+MMS. In conclusion, supposing that 100% of mGT mispairs are fully repaired, the extent of mGC repair would be in the range of 30%.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Nucleotide incorporation occurs in the vicinity of the single O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct</title><p>The plasmids described above were incubated in α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP-supplemented NPE for 2 hr, purified, and analyzed by agarose gel electrophoresis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). Covalently closed circular (ccc) and relaxed forms (oc) were quantified in each lane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). In the presence of MMS adducts, the single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion contributes to a 2.8-fold increase in radioactive incorporation compared to its contribution in the absence of MMS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>) in good agreement with the UDS data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>).</p><p>We wanted to map the repair patches with respect to the O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct position by restriction enzyme analysis. Digestion of the purified plasmids with <italic>BmtI</italic> and <italic>BaeGI</italic> restriction enzymes generates fragment S (589 bp) that encompasses the O<sup>6</sup>mG:C site and fragment L (1525 bp) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Following separation by agarose gel electrophoresis, the DNA was imaged by ethidium bromide fluorescence and <sup>32</sup>P autoradiography (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1C</xref>). For each fragment, we determined its specific activity by dividing the radioactivity signal by its amount as determined from the ethidium bromide image (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1D</xref>). As expected, the specific activities of S and L fragments were similar in GC (random background incorporation: 0.125±0.015 AU [arbitrary units]) and MMS-treated (GC+MMS) (0.235±0.025 AU) control plasmids. In GC+MMS, the specific activity was slightly higher than in control plasmids, probably reflecting BER-mediated incorporation at randomly distributed N-alkyl adducts. In the two O<sup>6</sup>mG:C-containing plasmids (mGC and mGC+MMS), the S fragment exhibits a significantly higher specific activity than the L fragment, indicating that MMR activity is centered around the O<sup>6</sup>mG:C site. In the absence of MMS, incorporation in mGC above background (dotted line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1D</xref>), attributable to O<sup>6</sup>mG, amounts to 0.065 and 0.495 AU for L and S fragments, respectively. Similarly, in the presence of random MMS lesions (mGC+MMS), incorporation, above background (dotted line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1D</xref>), attributable to O<sup>6</sup>mG, amounts to 0.115 and 1.17 AU for L and S fragments, respectively. These results clearly show that O<sup>6</sup>mGC-induced repair essentially takes place within the S fragment, with only modest spill-over into the L fragment (10–15%). This observation appears to be in good agreement with the estimated average MMR patch size (~500 nt). Thus, MMS adducts do not modify the repair pattern, that is, the relative distribution of <sup>32</sup>P incorporation in S and L fragments, but they increase the frequency of repair centered at O<sup>6</sup>mG sites. In conclusion, we show that stimulation of repair synthesis by N-alkyl adducts specifically occurs in the vicinity of the O<sup>6</sup>mG adducts, illustrating that processing of N-alkyl adducts enhances MMR activity.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>MNU-treated plasmids undergo double-strand breaks during incubation in extracts</title><p>Work in <italic>E. coli</italic> provided elegant genetic evidence that the cytotoxicity of alkylating agents forming O<sup>6</sup>mG adducts (such as N-methyl-N’-nitrosoguanidine and MNU), including formation of replication-independent DSB, was strongly influenced by the status of the MMR pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Karran and Marinus, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Nowosielska and Marinus, 2008</xref>). We wondered whether MNU can induce formation of DSBs independently of DNA replication. To increase the sensitivity of our assay toward DSB detection, we used a larger plasmid, pEL97 (11.3 kb), and treated it with MMS or MNU to introduce one alkylation event, on average, every 500 nt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). We also treated one sample with double the concentration of MNU to achieve a twofold higher lesion density. Quantification of N-alkyl adducts by alkaline cleavage and subsequent agarose gel electrophoresis led to the expected lesion density of one N-alkyl adduct every 500 nt for MMS and MNU+, and one N-alkyl adduct every 250 nt for MNU++ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1C</xref>).</p><p>Alkylated and control plasmids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2A</xref>) were incubated in NPE for 60' in the presence of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP, resolved by agarose gel electrophoresis, and visualized by ethidium bromide staining and <sup>3<bold>2</bold></sup>P imaging (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Both MMS and MNU caused substantial conversion of the plasmid from the supercoiled to the open circular form, as expected during repair synthesis. Consistent with our results above, MNU induced much more repair synthesis than MMS. Strikingly, in both ethidium bromide and <sup>32</sup>P images, a linear plasmid was detected after exposure to MNU, but not MMS. For a twofold increase in MNU exposure, the linear plasmid band increased approximately fourfold (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). This quadratic dose-response strongly suggests that DSBs occur as a consequence of two independent repair events at neighboring lesions, for example a BER event at an N-alkyl adduct leading to a nick in one strand that is encountered by a gap formed by an MMR event initiated at an O<sup>6</sup>mG site in the opposite strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). To reveal SSBs, the same samples were denatured prior to native gel electrophoresis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2B</xref>). In the MNU++ sample, no linear ssDNA was left, all the DNA molecules running as a smear centered around the 3000 nt position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2B</xref>). The observed smear reveals that the double-stranded DNA running as open circular plasmid molecules in the neutral loading gel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>) contain each, on average, three to four nicks per plasmid strand. The data reveal that repair of MNU-treated plasmids in NPE causes SSBs and that once the density of SSBs is high enough, DSBs result.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Double-strand breaks occur in MNU-treated plasmids during incubation in extracts.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Analysis by agarose gel electrophoresis (AGE) of alkylated plasmids (pEL97: 11.3 kb) incubated in nucleoplasmic extracts (NPE) in the presence of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP. Plasmid pEL97 was treated with methyl-methane sulfonate (MMS), N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU)+, and ENU as to introduce ≈ one alkylation event, on average, every 500 nt. For MNU, a plasmid with twice the level of alkylation (MNU++, one lesion every 250 nt) was also produced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). Alkylation of these plasmids essentially not affected their migration on agarose gels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2A</xref>). After 2 hr of incubation, the reaction was stopped and a known amount of pBR322 (10 ng) plasmid was added as an internal standard. Ethidium bromide image: in different lanes, the internal standard band, pBR (covalently closed circular [ccc]), appears to be of similar intensity (1158 +/- 95 arbitrary units [AU]), assessing reproducible DNA extraction. For the alkylated plasmids, incubation in NPE led to massive conversion from ccc to relaxed plasmids. <sup>32</sup>P image: little incorporation of <sup>32</sup>P-dATP is seen in DNA0 and in MMS-treated plasmids compared to MNU- and ENU-treated plasmids as shown by the relative incorporation levels normalized to one for untreated plasmid (DNA0). As expected, the MNU++ sample exhibits about twice the amount of incorporated radioactivity compared to MNU+. In both ethidium bromide and <sup>32</sup>P images, a small amount of linear plasmid is seen mostly in the MNU++ sample. This band is also visible in the MNU+ and ENU lanes although at a weaker intensity. (<bold>B</bold>) Quadratic dose-response for double-strand break (DSB) formation. When the % of linear form (linear/(linear + oc)) is plotted as a function of the square dose of MNU (mM<sup>2</sup>) for untreated, MNU+, and MNU++ plasmids, we observed a straight line (y = 1.4173x - 0.0288; R² = 0.9999).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Estimation of N-alkylation levels of modification by MMS and MNU.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Alkaline fragmentation of alkylated plasmid (pEL97, 11.3 kb) DNA is analyzed by agarose gel electrophoresis. (<bold>B</bold>) Densitometry of the ethidium bromide-stained agarose gel. (<bold>C</bold>) Estimation of the average number of alkali cleavage sites per plasmid strand. The data reveal that the average number of cleavage sites per plasmid strand is 21–23 for both methyl-methane sulfonate (MMS) and N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU)+ reaction conditions (the average distance between two sites is ≈510 nt). For MNU++, the average distance between two cleavage sites is ≈254 nt.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig4-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Fragmentation of alkylated plasmid as analyzed on AGE loaded under alkaline conditions.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Alkylation did not affect plasmid topology except for ENU treatment that increases relaxation as seen in the agarose gel electrophoresis (AGE) image. (<bold>B</bold>) Analysis by AGE, under alkaline loading conditions, of alkylated plasmids (pEL97: 11.3 kb) incubated in nucleoplasmic extracts (NPE) in the presence of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP (same samples as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Loading under alkaline conditions allowed single-stranded nicks to be revealed. In the different lanes, an internal standard band, pBR (covalently closed circular [ccc]), was introduced before the extraction procedure in order to assess the consistent recovery of DNA during extraction (as seen by ethidium bromide staining). For the alkylated plasmids, incubation in NPE led to massive conversion of plasmid DNA into a smear with a low amount of DNA present as a single-stranded linear band (doublet). For the MNU++ sample, no linear single-stranded DNA (ssDNA) was seen; all DNA was converted into a smear. The smearing can best be seen in the <sup>32</sup>P image. We suggest that the ssDNA fragments that form the smear arise between a gap caused by a mismatch repair (MMR) event at an O<sup>6</sup>mG site and an uncompleted base excision repair (BER) event at a neighboring lesion. It cannot be excluded that some fragments result from MMR attempts at two O<sup>6</sup>mG lesions. The intense <sup>32</sup>P labeling of the fragments in the smear results from incorporation of up to several hundred nt during a single MMR repair synthesis. Relative <sup>32</sup>P incorporation normalized to one for DNA0 is indicated below the <sup>32</sup>P image.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig4-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Simultaneous repair of two closely spaced MNU-induced lesions may lead to a DSB.</title><p>Such a situation occurs when an N-alkyl lesion located within ≈500 nt of an O<sup>6</sup>mG lesion is processed simultaneously (‘Lesion Arrangement at-risk’). Note that the mismatch repair (MMR) excision track can occur on either strand as described for noncanonical MMR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Peña-Diaz et al., 2012</xref>). Reaction of N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU) with double-stranded DNA induces N-alkylation adducts, mostly 7mG and 3mA shown as * and O-alkylation adducts (O<sup>6</sup>mG), at a ratio of 10:1 approximately. Step 1: a base excision repair (BER) event is initiated at an N-alkyl adduct, creating a nick. Step 2: concomitantly, an MMR event takes place, in the opposite strand, at a nearby O<sup>6</sup>mG:C site. Step 3: the MMR machinery extends the nick into a several hundred nt-long gap by means of Exo1 action. Step 4: the two independently initiated repair events lead to a double-strand break (DSB), if the MMR gap reaches the BER-initiated nick before resealing.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-69544-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>With respect to the biological responses to SN1 alkylating agents, most attention has so far been devoted to responses that occur in the first or second cell cycle following treatment as mentioned in the 'Introduction' section (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Noonan et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Plant and Roberts, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Quiros et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>In the present paper, we focus on early processing of DNA alkylation adducts by repair pathways before the event of replication. Interestingly, we identified the formation of DSB as the result of a putative crosstalk between repair pathways.</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>Late responses to SN1 agents</title><p>Response of cells to SN1 methylating agents was shown to be initiated at O<sup>6</sup>mG:T mispairs that form upon DNA replication of O<sup>6</sup>mG-containing DNA template and shown to involve the MMR machinery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Goldmacher et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Day et al., 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Karran et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Yarosh et al., 1983</xref>). The O<sup>6</sup>mG:T mispair is efficiently recognized by MutSα, the key MMR initiator protein. Following removal of the nascent T residue across O<sup>6</sup>mG, T will be re-inserted at a high frequency during the MMR gap-filling step, thus re-forming the initial O<sup>6</sup>mG:T mispair. This iterative process, called ‘futile cycling’, has received experimental support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Mazon et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">York and Modrich, 2006</xref>). However, it is not yet clear how these futile cycles lead to DSBs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Ochs and Kaina, 2000</xref>), apoptosis, and cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gupta and Heinen, 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Kaina and Christmann, 2019</xref>). Two mutually non-exclusive models have been proposed: (i) a direct model where the encounter of the replication fork with the MMR intermediates leads to fork collapse and to subsequent cytotoxic events and (ii) a signaling model where the MutSα complex acts as a sensor leading to ATR recruitment and subsequent initiation of the ATR-Chk1 signaling pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Duckett et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Yoshioka et al., 2006</xref>). However, presently, there is more evidence that the critical cytotoxic response to methylating agents is the consequence of direct MMR processing rather than being mediated by a mere signaling model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Cejka and Jiricny, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Karran, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Liu et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">York and Modrich, 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Early responses to SN1 agents</title><p>While all biological responses described above require replication of O<sup>6</sup>mG-containing DNA templates as the first step, we wanted to investigate the processing of MNU-alkylated DNA in the absence of replication. Interestingly, we detected robust, MMR-dependent, UDS upon incubation of MNU-treated plasmids in NPE. This observation reveals that, not only are O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesions recognized by MutSα as previously noted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Duckett et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Karran et al., 1993</xref>), but also the whole MMR repair process is engaged and proceeds to completion. We would also like to stress the high sensitivity of the pull-down assay with respect to MMR protein capture. Indeed, the whole MMR machinery is enriched (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>) using a plasmid that on average carries only 2–3 O<sup>6</sup>mG lesions/plasmid. In striking contrast, despite their abundance, ≈26 N-alkyl lesions/plasmid, N-alkyl lesions only recruit few specific proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>).</p><p>We wanted to investigate the potential effect that N-alkyl adducts may have on MMR processing at O<sup>6</sup>mG:C base pairs. For that purpose, we compared a plasmid with a single site-specific O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion to a plasmid additionally treated with MMS, an agent known to induce essentially only N-alkyl adducts. The MMS treatment was adjusted as to produce the same amount of N-alkyl adduct as generated by MNU. The single-adducted O<sup>6</sup>mG:C plasmid triggered MMR-mediated repair synthesis centered around the O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct. Interestingly, the presence of randomly distributed N-alkyl adducts led to a threefold increase of the MMR repair activity in the vicinity of the O<sup>6</sup>mG adduct. These data raise two questions: first, how the MMR machinery gets engaged in ccc plasmid and second, how MMR activity is further stimulated by N-alkyl adducts. In current models, functional engagement of MMR involves a mismatch recognized by MutSα, and the subsequent recruitment of MutLα and PCNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Jiricny, 2006</xref>). Loading of PCNA by RFC normally requires a single-stranded nick but it was also shown to occur, although less efficiently, on ccc DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Pluciennik et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pluciennik et al., 2010</xref>). Under these conditions, PCNA loading and MMR processing lack strand directionality. With respect to the mechanism by which MMR activity, at a single O<sup>6</sup>mG:C lesion, becomes stimulated several folds by the presence of N-alkyl adducts, we propose that processing of N-alkyl adducts by BER creates repair intermediates (nicks) that stimulate PCNA loading. It was previously shown that BER intermediates formed at oxidized purines or U residues can stimulate MMR processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Repmann et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Schanz et al., 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>DSBs form in MNU-treated DNA in the absence of replication: potential therapeutic significance</title><p>Interestingly, incubation of MNU-treated plasmids in extracts leads to DSBs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>) that arise with a quadratic dose-response, suggesting the occurrence of two independent repair activities taking place simultaneously in opposite strands at lesions that may be up to several hundred nucleotides apart (see scenario in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). Similarly, in vitro processing of neighboring G/U mispairs by BER and ncMMR was shown to lead to DSBs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bregenhorn et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>The extent of DNA alkylation triggered by MNU in vitro, as deduced from our alkaline cleavage determination, fits surprisingly well with the amount of alkylation induced by TMZ in cells at equal concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Moody and Wheelhouse, 2014</xref>). According to the model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>), formation of a DSB may occur when an N-alkyl lesion is located within the repair track mediated by MMR at an O<sup>6</sup>mG:C site. In the clinic, a daily dose of TMZ results in 50 μM serum concentration and was shown to induce 5.2 x 10<sup>4</sup> and 7.3 x 10<sup>5</sup> O-alkyl and N-alkyl lesions per human genome, respectively (Kaina, personal communication). We can estimate the number of events (per genome) where an N-alkyl lesion is located within 500 nt on either side of an O<sup>6</sup>mG:C site. Given the N-alkyl lesion density (7.3 x 10<sup>5</sup>/6 x 10<sup>9</sup> = 1.2 x 10<sup>−4</sup>), the probability of presence of an N-alkyl lesion within an MMR track is 0.12. In other words, among the 5.2 x 10<sup>4</sup> O<sup>6</sup>mG lesions, ≈6240 are likely to contain an N-alkyl lesion within a 1000 nt excision track. We will refer to such a lesion configuration as a ‘Lesion Arrangement at-risk’ for DSB formation.</p><p>Let us now estimate the level of DSB that may occur in a human genome, by extrapolation of our in vitro data. In the present work, ≈6% of plasmid DNA (11.3 kb) treated by MNU at 2 mM exhibits a DSB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). The observed amount of DSBs may in fact only reflect a steady-state level since efficient re-ligation mechanisms are known to operate in NPE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Graham et al., 2016</xref>). As MNU and TMZ exhibit similar reactivities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Moody and Wheelhouse, 2014</xref>) (Kaina personal communication), a dose of 2 mM MNU would lead to 3 x 10<sup>9</sup> x 0.06/11,300 = 16,000 DSBs per genome. In the clinic, the level of TMZ in the serum reaches up to 50 μM, that is 40 times less than the 2 mM dose used in vitro. Given the quadratic dose-response, the estimated amount of DSBs per genome would be 1600 times less, that is ≈10. Let’s note that the conversion rate of a lesion arrangement at-risk into an actual DSB appears to be quite low (10/6240 ≈0.16%), reflecting the requirement for simultaneous occurrence of two repair events (MMR and BER).</p><p>The alkylating agent TMZ, a chemical mimic of MNU, is presently the first-line and only anti-cancer drug in glioblastoma therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Moody and Wheelhouse, 2014</xref>). The cytotoxic mode of action of alkylating agents such as TMZ is believed to result from iterative MMR cycles. Iterative MMR cycles are deemed to lead to DSBs via a mechanism that is not yet established (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Ochs and Kaina, 2000</xref>). Indeed, it is not known whether DSBs occur spontaneously at these sites or as a consequence of the replication fork running into the MMR intermediates. Induction of these putative DSBs is presently thought to be the primary mode-of-action of TMZ when administered to patients with glioblastoma.</p><p>Understanding both early and late cellular responses to MNU/TMZ appears thus to be critical. During cancer treatment, a dose of TMZ is delivered concomitantly with a radiotherapy session daily, for 6 weeks (for a recent review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Strobel et al., 2019</xref>). As estimated above, a daily dose of TMZ may lead to an ≈10 DSBs/cell resulting from BER/MMR crosstalk, a number comparable to the number of DSBs induced by 0.5–1 Gy of ionizing radiations (IR). Moreover, it was established empirically that the treatment TMZ plus radiotherapy exhibits supra-additive cytotoxicity as long as TMZ administration <italic>precedes</italic> radiotherapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bobola et al., 2010</xref>). Our data may provide some rationales for this empirically determined regimen. Indeed, the ssDNA stretches formed at early time points during MMR processing at O<sup>6</sup>mG:C sites (step three in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>) constitute preferential targets for the conversion of the numerous SSBs induced by IR into DSBs, thus providing an explanation for the observed supra-additivity in the treatment when TMZ <italic>precedes</italic> IR. A commonly used radiotherapy session involves an IR dose of 2 Gy that predominantly induces ≈2000 SSBs and ≈40 DSBs/cell.</p><p>As the majority of cells in a glioblastoma tumor are not proliferating, insights into attacking non-dividing cells might be very useful in treating this almost always fatal tumor. This pre-replicative mechanism for TMZ cytotoxicity will need to be investigated in cellular systems. In conclusion, the present work offers a novel mechanistic insight into the cytotoxicity of TMZ via induction of DSBs, at early time points following exposure, before replication. This early response comes in complement to the late, replication and cell cycle-dependent, responses that have been described over the years.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Plasmids</title><p>Alkylated plasmids as used in the present paper are outlined below.</p><p><table-wrap id="inlinetable1" position="anchor"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Name</th><th valign="top">Size (kb)</th><th valign="top">Assay</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">pAS200.2</td><td valign="top">2.1</td><td valign="top">Site-specific O<sup>6</sup>mG lesion</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">pBR322</td><td valign="top">4.3</td><td valign="top">Random alkylation/UDS repair assay</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">pAS04</td><td valign="top">6.5</td><td valign="top">IDAP pull-down assay/MS analysis of bound proteins</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">pEL97</td><td valign="top">11.3</td><td valign="top">Random alkylation/UDS assay/post-incubation analysis</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>Akylation reactions were conducted as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>, at a plasmid concentration of 10 ng/μl in CE buffer (citrate 10mM, pH 7, ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) 1 mM) + 10% dimethyl sulfoxide final.</p><p>Alkylation reactions were terminated by addition of STOP buffer (5x: 1.5 M sodium acetate, 1 M mercapto-ethanol) followed by ethanol precipitation. The DNA pellet was washed with ethanol 90% and re-dissolved in TE at 50 ng/μl.</p><sec id="s4-1-1"><title>Cleavage reactions at 7-alkylG and 3-alkylA adducts</title><p>Alkylated plasmids (50 ng in 10 μl of CE buffer) were first incubated for 90°C during 15′ at pH 7 (PCR machine). Following addition of 1 μl of NaOH 1N, the sample was further incubated at 90°C for 30′. Following addition of 2 μl of alkaline 6x loading buffer (NaOH 300 mM, EDTA 6 mM, Ficoll (Pharmacia type 400) 180 mg/ml, 0.15% (w/v) bromocresol green, 0.25% (w/v) xylene cyanol), the cleaved plasmid samples were loaded on a neutral agarose gel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-1-2"><title>NPE and HSS <italic>Xenopus</italic> extracts</title><p>Two types of extracts derived from <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> eggs were used throughout the paper, namely NPE and HSS, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lebofsky et al., 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-1-3"><title>Western blot</title><p>Antibodies used against Mlh1, Pms2, and Pms1 are as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kato et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kawasoe et al., 2016</xref>). For western blotting, primary antibodies were used at 1:5000 dilution.</p></sec><sec id="s4-1-4"><title>Single adducted plasmids</title><p>Covalently closed circular plasmids containing a site-specific O<sup>6</sup>mG:C base pair (plasmid mGC) and the corresponding lesion-free control (plasmid GC) were constructed. We also constructed similar plasmids with a single GT or a single O<sup>6</sup>mG:T mismatch located at the same position (plasmids GT and mGT, respectively). All constructs were derived from the plasmid vector pAS200.2 (2.1 kb) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Isogawa et al., 2020</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Plasmid immobilization on magnetic beads and pull-down procedure</title><p>Alkylated plasmid samples (250 ng of each -MMS, -MNU, and -ENU), as well as a non-alkylated control sample (DNA0), were immobilized on magnetic beads at a density of 10 ng plasmid/μl of M280 bead slurry using a triple helix-based capture methodology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Isogawa et al., 2018</xref>). The TFO1 probe used here was 5’ Psoralen – C6 – <named-content content-type="sequence">TTTTCTTTTCTCCTCTTCTC</named-content>– C124 – Desthiobiotin (20 mer) with C124:hexaethylene glycol ×6. Underlined C is for 5mC; it was synthesized by using DNA/RNA automated synthesizer and purified with conventional methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Nagatsugi et al., 2003</xref>).</p><p>Immobilized plasmid DNA was incubated in NPE (final volume, 16 μl) for 10 min at RT under mild agitation. To monitor non-specific protein binding to beads, we included a negative control (noDNA sample) containing the same amount of M280 beads treated under the same conditions but in absence of plasmid DNA. Reactions were stopped by addition of 320 μl of a 0.8% HCHO solution to cross-link the protein-DNA complexes for 10 min at RT. The beads were subsequently washed at RT with 200 μl of 100 mM NaCl-containing buffer (ELB buffer), re-suspended in 70 μl of extract dilution buffer, and layered on top of a 0.5 M sucrose cushion in Beckman Coulter tubes (Ref: 342867). The beads were quickly spun through the cushion (30 s at 10,000 rpm), the bead pellet re-suspended into 40 μl of ELB sucrose, and further analyzed by PAGE or by MS.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>PAGE/silver staining</title><p>An aliquot of each incubation experiment, corresponding to 30 ng of immobilized plasmid, was treated at 99°C for 25 min in a PCR machine to revert HCHO cross-linking in LLB, 50 mM dithiothreitol (DTT). Samples were loaded on a 4–15% PAGE (Biorad pre-cast) gel at 200 volts for 32 min and stained using the silver staining kit (silver StainPlus, Biorad).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Incorporation of α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP into DNA: spot assay</title><p>Plasmids were incubated in nuclear extracts supplemented with α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP; at various time points, an aliquot of the reaction mixture was spotted on DEAE paper (DE81). The paper was soaked in 100 ml 0.5 M Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> (pH≈9) and shaked gently for 5′ before the buffer was discarded; this procedure was repeated twice. Finally, the paper was washed for an additional two times in 50 ml ethanol, air dried, and analyzed by <sup>32</sup>P imaging and quantification. The extent of DNA repair synthesis is expressed as a fraction of input plasmid replication (i.e., 10% means that the observed extent of repair synthesis is equivalent to 10% of input plasmid replication). This value is determined knowing the average concentration of dATP in the extracts (≈50 μM) and the amount of added α<sup>32</sup>P-dATP.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Mass spectrometry</title><p>Label-free MS analysis was performed using on-bead digestion. In-solution digestion was performed on beads from plasmid pull-downs. We added 20 µl of 8 M urea, 100 mM EPPS, pH 8.5, to the beads, then 5 mM TCEP, and incubated the mixture for 15 min at RT. We then added 10 mM of iodoacetamide for 15 min at RT in the dark. We added 15 mM DTT to consume any unreacted iodoacetamide. We added 180 µl of 100 mM EPPS, pH 8.5, to reduce the urea concentration to &lt;1 M, 1 µg of trypsin, and incubated at 37°C for 6 hr. The solution was acidified with 2% formic acid and the digested peptides were desalted via StageTip, dried via vacuum centrifugation, and reconstituted in 5% acetonitrile, 5% formic acid, for liquid chromatography (LC)-MS/MS processing.</p><p>All label-free mass spectrometry data were collected using a Q Exactive mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, San Jose, CA) coupled with a Famos Autosampler (LC Packings) and an Accela600 LC pump (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Peptides were separated on a 100-μm inner diameter microcapillary column packed with ∼20 cm of Accucore C18 resin (2.6 μm, 150 Å; Thermo Fisher Scientific). For each analysis, we loaded ~2 μg onto the column. Peptides were separated using a 1 hr gradient of 5–29% acetonitrile in 0.125% formic acid with a flow rate of ∼300 nl/min. The scan sequence began with an Orbitrap MS1spectrum with the following parameters: resolution 70,000, scan range 300–1500 Th, automatic gain control (AGC) target 1 × 10<sup>5</sup>, maximum injection time 250 ms, and centroid spectrum data type. We selected the top 20 precursors for MS2 analysis, which consisted of high-energy collision dissociation (HCD) with the following parameters: resolution 17,500, AGC 1 × 10<sup>5</sup>, maximum injection time 60 ms, isolation window 2 Th, normalized collision energy (NCE) 25, and centroid spectrum data type. The underfill ratio was set at 9%, which corresponds to a 1.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> intensity threshold. In addition, unassigned and singly charged species were excluded from MS2 analysis and dynamic exclusion was set to automatic.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Mass spectrometric data analysis</title><p>Mass spectra were processed using a Sequest-based in-house software pipeline. MS spectra were converted to mzXML using a modified version of ReAdW.exe. Database searching included all entries from the <italic>X. laevis</italic>, which were concatenated with a reverse database composed of all protein sequences in the reverse order. Searches were performed using a 50 ppm precursor ion tolerance. Product ion tolerance was set to 0.03 Th. Carbamidomethylation of cysteine residues (+57.0215 Da) was set as static modifications, while oxidation of methionine residues (+15.9949 Da) was set as a variable modification. Peptide spectral matches (PSMs) were altered to a 1% FDR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Elias and Gygi, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Elias and Gygi, 2007</xref>). PSM filtering was performed using a linear discriminant analysis, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Huttlin et al., 2017</xref>), while considering the following parameters: XCorr, ΔCn, missed cleavages, peptide length, charge state, and precursor mass accuracy. PSMs were identified, quantified, and collapsed to a 1% FDR and then further collapsed to a final protein-level FDR of 1%. Furthermore, protein assembly was guided by principles of parsimony to produce the smallest set of proteins necessary to account for all observed peptides.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Johannes Walter (Harvard Medical School) for providing space, advice, and materials, and Paul Modrich (Duke Univ) and Bernd Kaina (Medical Univ, Mainz) for insightful reading and suggestions. This work was partially supported by NIH/NIGMS grant R01 GM132129 (to JAP) and MEXT/JSPS KAKENHI JP20H03186 and JP20H05392 (to TT).</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Investigation, Methodology</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Investigation, Methodology</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Resources</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Resources</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Resources, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>Resources, Methodology</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>Validation, Investigation, Writing - review and editing</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="sdata1"><label>Source data 1.</label><caption><title>Original image data used in Figures and Figure supplements.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="zip" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-69544-data1-v2.zip"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sdata2"><label>Source data 2.</label><caption><title>Image data before trimming used in Figures and Figure supplements.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="zip" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-69544-data2-v2.zip"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sdata3"><label>Source data 3.</label><caption><title>Resource data of MS analysis.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-69544-data3-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-69544-transrepform-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Source data files have been provided for MS data, gels and blots in main or figure supplements.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aas</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Otterlei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Falnes</surname> <given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Vågbø</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Skorpen</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbari</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundheim</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjørås</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Slupphaug</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeberg</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Krokan</surname> <given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Human and bacterial oxidative demethylases repair alkylation damage in both RNA and DNA</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>421</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12594517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baranovskiy</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Babayeva</surname> <given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Suwa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavlov</surname> <given-names>YI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahirov</surname> <given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Structural basis for inhibition of DNA replication by aphidicolin</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>14013</fpage><lpage>14021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25429975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beranek</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year><article-title>Distribution of methyl and ethyl adducts following alkylation with monofunctional alkylating agents</article-title><source>Mutation Research/Fundamental and Molecular Mechanisms of Mutagenesis</source><volume>231</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0027-5107(90)90173-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2195323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhanot</surname> <given-names>OS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1986">1986</year><article-title>The in vivo mutagenic frequency and specificity of O6-methylguanine in phi X174 replicative form DNA</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>7348</fpage><lpage>7352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.83.19.7348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2945203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bobola</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolstoe</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Blank</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Silber</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Minimally cytotoxic doses of temozolomide produce radiosensitization in human glioblastoma cells regardless of MGMT expression</article-title><source>Molecular Cancer Therapeutics</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>1208</fpage><lpage>1218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-10-0010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20457618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bregenhorn</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallenberger</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Artola-Borán</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peña-Diaz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Non-canonical uracil processing in DNA gives rise to double-strand breaks and deletions: relevance to class switch recombination</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>2691</fpage><lpage>2705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26743004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cejka</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Interplay of DNA repair pathways controls methylation damage toxicity in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>179</volume><fpage>1835</fpage><lpage>1844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.108.089979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18579505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakravarti</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibeanu</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tano</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Cloning and expression in Escherichia coli of a human cDNA encoding the DNA repair protein N-methylpurine-DNA glycosylase</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>266</volume><fpage>15710</fpage><lpage>15715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(18)98467-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1874728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziolkowski</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Scudiero</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubiniecki</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Girardi</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Galloway</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bynum</surname> <given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1980">1980</year><article-title>Defective repair of alkylated DNA by human tumour and SV40-transformed human cell strains</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>288</volume><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/288724a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6256643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demple</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsson</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robins</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1982">1982</year><article-title>Repair of alkylated DNA in Escherichia coli. physical properties of O6-methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>257</volume><fpage>13776</fpage><lpage>13780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(18)33516-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6754717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duckett</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bronstein</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Taya</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Modrich</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>hMutSalpha- and hMutLalpha-dependent phosphorylation of p53 in response to DNA methylator damage</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>12384</fpage><lpage>12388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.22.12384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10535931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Trewick</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Koivisto</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedgwick</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Reversal of DNA alkylation damage by two human dioxygenases</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>16660</fpage><lpage>16665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.262589799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12486230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elias</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Target-decoy search strategy for increased confidence in large-scale protein identifications by mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth1019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17327847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elias</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Target-decoy search strategy for mass spectrometry-based proteomics</article-title><source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source><volume>604</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-60761-444-9_5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20013364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ensminger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iloff</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebel</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolova</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaina</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Löbrich</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>DNA breaks and chromosomal aberrations arise when replication meets base excision repair</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>206</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201312078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falnes</surname> <given-names>PØ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeberg</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>AlkB-mediated oxidative demethylation reverses DNA damage in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>419</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12226668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldmacher</surname> <given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuzick</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thilly</surname> <given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1986">1986</year><article-title>Isolation and partial characterization of human cell mutants differing in sensitivity to killing and mutation by methylnitrosourea and N-methyl-N'-nitro-N-nitrosoguanidine</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>261</volume><fpage>12462</fpage><lpage>12471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(18)67110-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3745200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Loparo</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Two-Stage Synapsis of DNA ends during Non-homologous end joining</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2016.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26990988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinen</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>The mismatch repair-dependent DNA damage response: mechanisms and implications</article-title><source>DNA Repair</source><volume>78</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dnarep.2019.03.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huttlin</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruckner</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulo</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannon</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ting</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltier</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Colby</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebreab</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Parzen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Szpyt</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarraga</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontano-Vaites</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Swarup</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweppe</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rad</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Obar</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guruharsha</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Artavanis-Tsakonas</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Architecture of the human interactome defines protein communities and disease networks</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>545</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature22366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28514442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isogawa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Versatile and efficient chromatin pull-down methodology based on DNA triple Helix formation</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>5925</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-24417-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29651103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isogawa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Chromatin Pull-Down methodology based on DNA triple Helix formation</article-title><source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source><volume>2119</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-0716-0323-9_16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31989525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiricny</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>The multifaceted mismatch-repair system</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm1907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16612326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaina</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Christmann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Naumann</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>MGMT: key node in the battle against genotoxicity, carcinogenicity and apoptosis induced by alkylating agents</article-title><source>DNA Repair</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1099</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dnarep.2007.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaina</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Christmann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Corrigendum to “DNA repair in personalized brain cancer therapy with temozolomide and nitrosoureas” [DNA Repair 78 (2019) 128–141]</article-title><source>DNA Repair</source><volume>80</volume><elocation-id>93</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dnarep.2019.06.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karran</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Macpherson</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceccotti</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogliotti</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bignami</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>O6-methylguanine residues elicit DNA repair synthesis by human cell extracts</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>268</volume><fpage>15878</fpage><lpage>15886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(18)82335-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8340413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karran</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Mechanisms of tolerance to DNA damaging therapeutic drugs</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1931</fpage><lpage>1937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/carcin/22.12.1931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karran</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bignami</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>DNA damage tolerance, mismatch repair and genome instability</article-title><source>BioEssays</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.950161110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7840761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karran</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marinus</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1982">1982</year><article-title>Mismatch correction at O6-methylguanine residues in E. coli DNA</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>296</volume><fpage>868</fpage><lpage>869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/296868a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7040986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kat</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thilly</surname> <given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Longley</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Modrich</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>An alkylation-tolerant, mutator human cell line is deficient in strand-specific mismatch repair</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>6424</fpage><lpage>6428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.90.14.6424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8341649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasoe</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Beese</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schärer</surname> <given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Sensing and processing of DNA interstrand crosslinks by the mismatch repair pathway</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>1375</fpage><lpage>1385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2017.10.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29091773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawasoe</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsurimoto</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Masukata</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>MutSα maintains the mismatch repair capability by inhibiting PCNA unloading</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e15155</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.15155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27402201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebofsky</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>DNA replication in nucleus-free <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts</article-title><source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source><volume>521</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-60327-815-7_13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19563110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindahl</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1976">1976</year><article-title>New class of enzymes acting on damaged DNA</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>259</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/259064a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">765833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsey-Boltz</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sancar</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Modrich</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Interactions of human mismatch repair proteins MutSalpha and MutLalpha with proteins of the ATR-Chk1 pathway</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>285</volume><fpage>5974</fpage><lpage>5982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.076109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20029092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loechler</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Essigmann</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1984">1984</year><article-title>In vivo mutagenesis by O6-methylguanine built into a unique site in a viral genome</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>6271</fpage><lpage>6275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.81.20.6271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6093094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loechler</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>A violation of the Swain-Scott principle, and not SN1 versus SN2 reaction mechanisms, explains why carcinogenic alkylating agents can form different proportions of adducts at Oxygen versus nitrogen in DNA</article-title><source>Chemical Research in Toxicology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/tx00039a001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8075356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maxam</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1977">1977</year><article-title>A new method for sequencing DNA</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>560</fpage><lpage>564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.74.2.560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">265521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazon</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippin</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadet</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasparutto</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Modesti</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Alkyltransferase-like protein (eATL) prevents mismatch repair-mediated toxicity induced by O6-alkylguanine adducts in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>18050</fpage><lpage>18055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1008635107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20921378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meira</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Moroski-Erkul</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bronson</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Samson</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Aag-initiated base excision repair drives alkylation-induced retinal degeneration in mice</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>888</fpage><lpage>893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0807030106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19139400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moody</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheelhouse</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>The medicinal chemistry of imidazotetrazine prodrugs</article-title><source>Pharmaceuticals</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ph7070797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25014631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagatsugi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidman</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Site-specific mutagenesis by triple helix-forming oligonucleotides containing a reactive nucleoside analog</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>31e</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gng031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12626730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noonan</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaffe</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauffenburger</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Samson</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title><italic>O</italic> 6-Methylguanine DNA lesions induce an intra-S-phase arrest from which cells exit int<italic>o</italic> apoptosis governed by early and late multi-pathway signaling network activation</article-title><source>Integrative Biology</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>1237</fpage><lpage>1255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c2ib20091k</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nowosielska</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marinus</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>DNA mismatch repair-induced double-strand breaks</article-title><source>DNA Repair</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dnarep.2007.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17827074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochs</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaina</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Apoptosis induced by DNA damage O6-methylguanine is Bcl-2 and caspase-9/3 regulated and fas/caspase-8 independent</article-title><source>Cancer Research</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>5815</fpage><lpage>5824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11059778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivera Harris</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallenberger</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Artola Borán</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Enoiu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Costanzo</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Mismatch repair-dependent metabolism of O 6 -methylguanine-containing DNA in <italic>Xenopus</italic> laevis egg extracts</article-title><source>DNA Repair</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dnarep.2015.01.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olsson</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1980">1980</year><article-title>Repair of alkylated DNA in Escherichia coli. methyl group transfer from O6-methylguanine to a protein cysteine residue</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>255</volume><fpage>10569</fpage><lpage>10571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(19)70341-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7000780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ortega</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Mispair-bound human MutS-MutL complex triggers DNA incisions and activates mismatch repair</article-title><source>Cell Research</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-021-00468-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33510387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peña-Diaz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bregenhorn</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghodgaonkar</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Follonier</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Artola-Borán</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castor</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartori</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Noncanonical mismatch repair as a source of genomic instability in human cells</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2012.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22864113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plant</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1971">1971</year><article-title>A novel mechanism for the inhibition of DNA synthesis following methylation: the effect of N-methyl-N-nitrosourea on HeLa cells</article-title><source>Chemico-Biological Interactions</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0009-2797(71)90013-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5156328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pluciennik</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzantiev</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyer</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantin</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadyrov</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Modrich</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>PCNA function in the activation and strand direction of MutLα endonuclease in mismatch repair</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>16066</fpage><lpage>16071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1010662107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20713735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pluciennik</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burdett</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Baitinger</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyer</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Modrich</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Extrahelical (CAG)/(CTG) triplet repeat elements support proliferating cell nuclear antigen loading and MutLα endonuclease activation</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>12277</fpage><lpage>12282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1311325110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23840062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quiros</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaina</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Processing of O6-methylguanine into DNA double-strand breaks requires two rounds of replication whereas apoptosis is also induced in subsequent cell cycles</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cc.9.1.10363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20016283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Repmann</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivera-Harris</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Influence of oxidized purine processing on strand directionality of mismatch repair</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>290</volume><fpage>9986</fpage><lpage>9999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.629907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25694431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sattler</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Frit</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Salles</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Calsou</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Long-patch DNA repair synthesis during base excision repair in mammalian cells</article-title><source>EMBO Reports</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.embor.embor796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schanz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Castor</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Interference of mismatch and base excision repair during the processing of adjacent U/G mispairs may play a key role in somatic hypermutation</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>5593</fpage><lpage>5598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0901726106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19307563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simonelli</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Leuzzi</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Basile</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Errico</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortini</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Franchitto</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Viti</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Parlanti</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascucci</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Palli</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuliani</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Palombo</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobol</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogliotti</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Crosstalk between mismatch repair and base excision repair in human gastric Cancer</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>84827</fpage><lpage>84840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.10185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29156686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strobel</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Baisch</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzel</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilberg</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegelin</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Karpel-Massler</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Debatin</surname> <given-names>K-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Westhoff</surname> <given-names>M-A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Temozolomide and other alkylating agents in glioblastoma therapy</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>69</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biomedicines7030069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Svilar</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Trivedi</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Goellner</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Banze</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobol</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>N-methylpurine DNA glycosylase and DNA polymerase beta modulate BER inhibitor potentiation of glioma cells to temozolomide</article-title><source>Neuro-Oncology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/neuonc/nor011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21377995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tano</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiota</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Collier</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Foote</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year><article-title>Isolation and structural characterization of a cDNA clone encoding the human DNA repair protein for O6-alkylguanine</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.87.2.686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2405387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trewick</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Henshaw</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausinger</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedgwick</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Oxidative demethylation by Escherichia coli AlkB directly reverts DNA base damage</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>419</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature00908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trivedi</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornsaglio</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schamus</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobol</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>The role of base excision repair in the sensitivity and resistance to temozolomide-mediated cell death</article-title><source>Cancer Research</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>6394</fpage><lpage>6400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-05-0715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16024643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Newport</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Regulated chromosomal DNA replication in the absence of a nucleus</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1097-2765(00)80052-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9660936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wühr</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Presler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Horb</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Peshkin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschner</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Deep proteomics of the <italic>Xenopus</italic> laevis egg using an mRNA-derived reference database</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1467</fpage><lpage>1475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.05.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24954049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yarosh</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Foote</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1983">1983</year><article-title>Repair of O6-methylguanine in DNA by demethylation is lacking in mer- human tumor cell strains</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/carcin/4.2.199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6825208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>York</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Modrich</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Mismatch repair-dependent iterative excision at irreparable O6-methylguanine lesions in human nuclear extracts</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>281</volume><fpage>22674</fpage><lpage>22683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M603667200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16772289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshioka</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshioka</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>ATR kinase activation mediated by MutSalpha and MutLalpha in response to cytotoxic O6-methylguanine adducts</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2006.04.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zlatanou</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Despras</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Braz-Petta</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boubakour-Azzouz</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pouvelle</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname> <given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasui</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishchenko</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannouche</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>The hMsh2-hMsh6 complex acts in concert with monoubiquitinated PCNA and pol η in response to oxidative DNA damage in human cells</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2011.06.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21855803</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.69544.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>Wolf-Dietrich</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>University of California, Davis</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>Wolf-Dietrich</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>University of California, Davis</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Van Houten</surname><given-names>Bennett</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>University of Pittsburgh</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Seidman</surname><given-names>Michael M</given-names></name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>National Institute on Aging, NIH</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>Our editorial process produces two outputs: i) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2020.11.21.391326">public reviews</ext-link> designed to be posted alongside <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.11.21.391326v3">the preprint</ext-link> for the benefit of readers; ii) feedback on the manuscript for the authors, including requests for revisions, shown below. We also include an acceptance summary that explains what the editors found interesting or important about the work.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Acceptance summary:</bold></p><p>Glioblastomas, like many tumors, consist of a cohort of actively dividing cells and a substantially larger fraction of non-proliferating cells. The standard of care involves administration of a chemotherapy drug (temozolomide (TMZ)) whose antitumor activity is thought to be dependent on a toxic intermediate produced during DNA replication. This reports highlights the importance of the O6mG:C lesion independent of replication which leads to DSBs through coupling of MMR and BER.</p><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Crosstalk between repair pathways elicits Double-Strand Breaks in alkylated DNA: implications for the action of temozolomide&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by 3 peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Kevin Struhl as the Senior Editor. The following individuals involved in review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Wolf-Dietrich Heyer (Reviewer #1); Bennett Van Houten (Reviewer #2); Michael M Seidman (Reviewer #3).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed their reviews with one another, and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>This paper calls attention to an overlooked feature of TMZ chemotherapy- that intermediates produced by two separate DNA repair pathways, operating on different adducts produced by the same compound, can produce a potentially toxic structure (DSBs). The message of the paper would be strengthened, and have greater impact, by a few additional experiments that would further support the contribution of BER in the extract system and provide some insight as to how to exploit these findings.</p><p>However, the reviewers consider the claims to be sufficiently supported by the present data. No new experiments are required for the resubmission, although the authors may want to consider enhancing the impact of their study.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) The authors state on page 6 without showing the data that the MGMT inhibitor Patrin-2 has no effect on DNA repair-associated DNA synthesis in their system. This contradicts earlier findings in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts by Olivera Harris et al. 2015 DNA Repair. This discrepancy cannot be left unexplained, as direct reversal affects the interpretation of the data in this manuscript.</p><p>2) A table of specific plasmids, lengths and the assays/justification that they were used for would be helpful to the reader as the authors switch from one plasmid to another in different experiments and it is not always clear which plasmid is being used in which experiments.</p><p>3) Figure 2B, page 6: What is evidence that only less than 30% of O6mG sites are substrates for MMR?</p><p>4) The data in supplemental Figure 2 is intriguing. However, I am having difficult reconciling the repair synthesis shown in Figure 2 supplement 1 with supplement 2. Why was NPE used in one experiment and HSS in the other? What happens when human AAG is added back?</p><p>5) Page 6 bottom, Page 7 top: What is the rationale for using different extracts? It is not always clear why and when the used total <italic>Xenopus</italic> extracts versus the supernatant from a high-speed centrifugation (HSS). Is it possible that some DNA binding proteins are spun down in the pellet?</p><p>6) Figure 1 should have an accompanying series of tables showing ALL the data from these volcano plots with proper annotation and p-values for significance. Just showing dots on a plot is not adequate. Also was the same experiment repeated with both nuclear extracts and the HSS? A direct comparison would be helpful.</p><p>7) Figure 4A: What is the evidence that the bands labeled linear are indeed linear? The interpretation rests on the migration behavior but additional evidence is needed to show these species are linear. For example, are they sensitive to ExoV or other dsDNA exonucleases.</p><p>8) Figure 4B: A major conclusion rests on the quadratic relationship between linear DNA and MNU concentration, but the titration has only two data points. Is this sufficient?</p><p>9) The figures measuring repair synthesis show ethidium stained gels that display the covalently closed circular and open circular forms of the plasmids. In light of the substantial labeling of control (unmodified) plasmids it would be helpful to show the plasmids after exposure to MMS or MNU and before they are introduced to the extracts. This was done in Figure 4 supplement 2A in which open circular forms are clearly present in the plasmid samples. Given the importance of nicks for MMR, and as potential targets for opportunistic polymerases, pre-existing nicks could be a confounding variable in the interpretation of &quot;repair&quot; synthesis.</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were suggested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><p>Thank you for resubmitting your work entitled &quot;Crosstalk between repair pathways elicits Double Strand Breaks in alkylated DNA and implications for the action of temozolomide&quot; for further consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your revised article has been evaluated by Kevin Struhl (Senior Editor) and a Reviewing Editor.</p><p>The manuscript has been improved but there are some remaining issues that need to be addressed, as outlined below:</p><p>In their rebuttal and in this revision, the authors clarified many of the concerns raised and made a number of text changes. However, the revision would have benefited from more extensively addressing these issues.</p><p>1) Discrepancy with earlier work: It would be helpful to the reader to incorporate the rebuttal response about the Hsieh et al. paper in the manuscript.</p><p>2) Essential revision #1: This clarification is fine, but this should be stated in the manuscript, in particular the argument about the underestimate of the UDS.</p><p>3) Essential revision #3: The clarification is helpful, and the GT/mGT data should be added to the manuscript.</p><p>4) Point #12: The addition to the discussion is minimal and should be expanded.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.69544.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>This paper calls attention to an overlooked feature of TMZ chemotherapy- that intermediates produced by two separate DNA repair pathways, operating on different adducts produced by the same compound, can produce a potentially toxic structure (DSBs). The message of the paper would be strengthened, and have greater impact, by a few additional experiments that would further support the contribution of BER in the extract system and provide some insight as to how to exploit these findings.</p><p>However, the reviewers consider the claims to be sufficiently supported by the present data. No new experiments are required for the resubmission, although the authors may want to consider enhancing the impact of their study.</p><p>Essential revisions</p><p>1) The authors state on page 6 without showing the data that the MGMT inhibitor Patrin-2 has no effect on DNA repair-associated DNA synthesis in their system. This contradicts earlier findings in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts by Olivera Harris et al. 2015 DNA Repair. This discrepancy cannot be left unexplained, as direct reversal affects the interpretation of the data in this manuscript.</p></disp-quote><p>MGMT inhibition issue: as mentioned in the text, upon addition of Patrin to the NPE extract, we did not see any increase in UDS in MNU treated plasmid. There are two formal possibilities: (i) the number of MGMT molecules present in the extract is small compared to the number of O<sup>6</sup>mG lesions introduced in the incubation mix or (ii) our Patrin inhibitor sample is inactive. In all cases, if partial demethylation of O<sup>6</sup>mG by MGMT occurs, the observed amount of UDS would be under-estimated. Thus, the conclusion reached in the paper, O<sup>6</sup>mG:C sites are substrates for MMR, remains correct.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) A table of specific plasmids, lengths and the assays/justification that they were used for would be helpful to the reader as the authors switch from one plasmid to another in different experiments and it is not always clear which plasmid is being used in which experiments.</p></disp-quote><p>At the beginning of Materials and methods, we have introduced a table listing the different plasmids and their respective usage. Moreover, the name of the plasmid that was used is now indicated in each figure.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) Figure 2B, page 6: What is evidence that only less than 30% of O6mG sites are substrates for MMR?</p></disp-quote><p>The hypothesis that ≈30% of 06mG are MMR substrates is based on the data described below. We have monitored UDS activity in plasmids containing a single GT or mGT mispair. These plasmids have been treated (or not) with MMS similarly to the description of the corresponding GC or mGC constructs. The GT, mGT, GT+MMS and mGT+MMS data have been added to the corresponding GC data shown in Figure 3B.</p><p>The main observation is that GT containing constructs trigger a much stronger MMR response than their GC counterparts. In the absence of MMS, at the 120’ time point, the level of UDS in mGC represents 23% of the level in mGT. In the presence of MMS, at the 120’ time point, the level of UDS in mGC+MMS represents 38% of the level in mGT+MMS. If one supposes that mGT mispair are fully repaired by MMR (close to 100%), then repair at mGC mispairs is in the range of 1 in 3 (30-40%).</p><p>The main emphasis of the paper is to describe the existence of MMR at mGC sites (in the absence of replication). As GT and mGT mispairs only occur following replication we decided not to include these data in the initial version of the paper. We are open to discuss whether the GT ad mGT data should or not be added.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) The data in supplemental Figure 2 is intriguing. However, I am having difficult reconciling the repair synthesis shown in Figure 2 supplement 1 with supplement 2. Why was NPE used in one experiment and HSS in the other? What happens when human AAG is added back?</p></disp-quote><p>Two type of extracts derived from <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> eggs are used throughout the paper, namely NucleoPlasmic Extract (NPE) and High-Speed Supernatant (HSS) as described previously (Lebofsky et al., 2009). For sake of clarity, we will avoid the terminology “egg extract” and specify throughout the text whether we used NPE or HSS. All experiments use NPE except for data in Figure 2—figure supplement 2 that use HSS. This point is clarified in the text. We have also indicated in the figures whether NPE or HSS are used.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>5) Page 6 bottom, Page 7 top: What is the rationale for using different extracts? It is not always clear why and when the used total <italic>Xenopus</italic> extracts versus the supernatant from a high-speed centrifugation (HSS). Is it possible that some DNA binding proteins are spun down in the pellet?</p></disp-quote><p>We observed that, in contrast to NPE, HSS do not support UDS on MNU-treated plasmid. However, a previous paper (Harris, 2015) had shown that HSS was proficient for O6mC:C repair provided a preformed nick was present in the substrate. We reasoned that perhaps our HSS extract was deficient in AAG glycosilase and thus implemented experiments in which purified hAAG was added in order to create the BER intermediate able to stimulate MMR at the O6mG:C sites.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>6) Figure 1 should have an accompanying series of tables showing ALL the data from these volcano plots with proper annotation and p-values for significance. Just showing dots on a plot is not adequate. Also was the same experiment repeated with both nuclear extracts and the HSS? A direct comparison would be helpful.</p></disp-quote><p>An excel table showing the details for the construction of the Volcano plots has been added. The x-axis is log base 2 of the ratio between average spectral counts for MNU divided by average spectral counts for MMS. The p-value was obtained using the TEST.STUDENT function in excel; parameters uni/bilateral and type were set to 2 and 3, respectively. The y-axis is -log base 10 of the p-values. The volcano plot shown in the xlsx file corresponds to comparison between MMS and MNU (i.e. the results shown in Figure 1—figure supplement 1C). The data have been obtained using Xenbase.</p><p>We did not perform an MS analysis comparing HSS to NPE.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>7) Figure 4A: What is the evidence that the bands labeled linear are indeed linear? The interpretation rests on the migration behavior but additional evidence is needed to show these species are linear. For example, are they sensitive to ExoV or other dsDNA exonucleases.</p></disp-quote><p>Unfortunately, we did not perform additional experiments such as sensitivity to dsDNA exonucleases. Besides the band migrating at the position expected for the linear form of the plasmid (Figure 4A), another evidence stems from Figure 4—figure supplement 2B. Indeed, in the MNU++ lane, the ss linear forms disappear in both Ethidium bromide and <sup>32</sup>P images, suggesting that the oc band in the MNU++ lane (<sup>32</sup>P image in Figure 4B) is formed of circular DNA having multiple nicks (or gaps). Thus, DNA carrying multiple nicks or gaps maintains a circular form under neutral condition unless closely spaced ss breaks lead to linearization. Therefore, the band indicated as a linear in Figure 4A could not maintain its circular form due to two closely spaced ss breaks that led to its linearization.</p><p>Also see response to point 8 below.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>8) Figure 4B: A major conclusion rests on the quadratic relationship between linear DNA and MNU concentration, but the titration has only two data points. Is this sufficient?</p></disp-quote><p>We agree that additional data points would be of value. However, the 0,0 point is also an experimental point as there is no band visible in non-treated plasmid sample. Moreover, in a different experiment using pBR322 (4,3kb) instead pEL97 (11,3kb) we observe a band migrating at 4,3kb in the MNU treated sample, thus confirming that MNU induces DSB’s.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>9) The figures measuring repair synthesis show ethidium stained gels that display the covalently closed circular and open circular forms of the plasmids. In light of the substantial labeling of control (unmodified) plasmids it would be helpful to show the plasmids after exposure to MMS or MNU and before they are introduced to the extracts. This was done in Figure 4 supplement 2A in which open circular forms are clearly present in the plasmid samples. Given the importance of nicks for MMR, and as potential targets for opportunistic polymerases, pre-existing nicks could be a confounding variable in the interpretation of &quot;repair&quot; synthesis.</p></disp-quote><p>Native and alkylated plasmids before incubation in extracts exhibit a small amount of relaxed form that is similar for DNA0, MMS, MNU+ and MNU++ (Figure 4 supplement 2A). Thus, the alkylation reaction <italic>per se</italic> did not induce relaxation in addition to the pre-existing amount in DNA0 (except for ENU treatment). Total incorporation into DNA0 (1) is small compared to MNU+ (7.8) and MNU++ (16.6) as indicated in Figure 4A (relative amounts of incorporation). Moreover, data of Figure 4—figure supplement 2 indicate that nicks pre-existing in MNU treated plasmid are not able to stimulate MMR; only addition of hAAG triggers MMR.</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were suggested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>The manuscript has been improved but there are some remaining issues that need to be addressed, as outlined below:</p><p>In their rebuttal and in this revision, the authors clarified many of the concerns raised and made a number of text changes. However, the revision would have benefited from more extensively addressing these issues.</p><p>1) Discrepancy with earlier work: It would be helpful to the reader to incorporate the rebuttal response about the Hsieh et al. paper in the manuscript.</p></disp-quote><p>This issue is discussed p5.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) Essential revision #1: This clarification is fine, but this should be stated in the manuscript, in particular the argument about the underestimate of the UDS.</p></disp-quote><p>This issue is discussed p6.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) Essential revision #3: The clarification is helpful, and the GT/mGT data should be added to the manuscript.</p></disp-quote><p>GT and mGT data have been introduced in Figure 3B; GT and mGT plasmid construction has been introduced in Mat &amp; Methods; GT and mGT UDS data are discussed p 8</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) Point #12: The addition to the discussion is minimal and should be expanded.</p></disp-quote><p>Point 12 is raised in the Discussion section p 11. As the mechanism of DSB formation as a result of futile cycling has not been established precisely we did not want to discuss it at length.</p></body></sub-article></article>