<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">60047</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.60047</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cell Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Physics of Living Systems</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Co-movement of astral microtubules, organelles and F-actin by dynein and actomyosin forces in frog egg cytoplasm</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-192929"><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>James F</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8064-0259</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-193523"><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>Christine M</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6433-7804</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-189014"><name><surname>Fürthauer</surname><given-names>Sebastian</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9581-5963</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-193524"><name><surname>Sonnett</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-8716"><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>Timothy J</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7781-1897</contrib-id><email>Timothy_Mitchison@hms.harvard.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Systems Biology, Harvard Medical School</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Boston</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Marine Biological Laboratory</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Woods Hole</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Physics, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Cambridge</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Flatiron Institute, Center for Computational Biology</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">New York</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Surrey</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Centre for Genomic Regulation (CRG)</institution><country>Spain</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>Vivek</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>The Barcelona Institute of Science and Technology</institution><country>Spain</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>07</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e60047</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2020-06-15"><day>15</day><month>06</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2020-12-05"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020, Pelletier et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pelletier et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-60047-v2.pdf"/><abstract><p>How bulk cytoplasm generates forces to separate post-anaphase microtubule (MT) asters in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> and other large eggs remains unclear. Previous models proposed that dynein-based, inward organelle transport generates length-dependent pulling forces that move centrosomes and MTs outwards, while other components of cytoplasm are static. We imaged aster movement by dynein and actomyosin forces in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts and observed outward co-movement of MTs, endoplasmic reticulum (ER), mitochondria, acidic organelles, F-actin, keratin, and soluble fluorescein. Organelles exhibited a burst of dynein-dependent inward movement at the growing aster periphery, then mostly halted inside the aster, while dynein-coated beads moved to the aster center at a constant rate, suggesting organelle movement is limited by brake proteins or other sources of drag. These observations call for new models in which all components of the cytoplasm comprise a mechanically integrated aster gel that moves collectively in response to dynein and actomyosin forces.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>microtubule</kwd><kwd>dynein</kwd><kwd>ER</kwd><kwd>actin</kwd><kwd>cytoplasm</kwd><kwd>mechanics</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd><italic>Xenopus</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000057</institution-id><institution>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R35GM131753</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>Timothy J</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100005883</institution-id><institution>Hertz Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>James F</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100009677</institution-id><institution>Ed Evans Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MBL fellowships</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>Christine M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>Timothy J</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Live imaging of multiple cytoplasmic networks in frog egg extracts calls for new models for how egg cytoplasm is physically organized during cleavage divisions.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cytokinesis requires drastic reorganization of the cell and provides a window into cytoplasmic mechanics and principles of sub-cellular organization. Here, we focus on organization of the cytoplasm by MT asters between mitosis and cytokinesis in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> eggs. The large size of eggs and the availability of an optically tractable egg extract system make <italic>Xenopus</italic> a good model for analysis of cytoplasmic organization. The first mitotic spindle is centrally located and much smaller than the egg. After mitosis, a pair of MT asters grow out from the centrosomes, reaching the cortex ~20 min later. These asters are composed of a branched network of short, dynamic MTs ~15 µm long and oriented approximately radially, with plus ends outward (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Ishihara et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Ishihara et al., 2014</xref>). Interphase egg asters have several organizational and mechanical functions. Where the paired asters meet, at the midplane of the egg, the MTs form an antiparallel interaction zone which recruits the chromosomal passenger complex (CPC) and centralspindlin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Field et al., 2015</xref>). In this way, a pair of asters defines the cleavage plane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Basant and Glotzer, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Carmena et al., 2012</xref>). The focus of this paper is on how asters move centrosomes and nuclei away from the future cleavage plane, so each daughter blastomere inherits one of each. This separation movement transports centrosomes and nuclei hundreds of microns away from the midplane over tens of minutes, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A–C</xref>. In common with other authors, we often refer to centrosome and aster movement as the same process. The reality is more complex due to continuous MT growth and turnover. As centrosomes move away from the midplane, the interaction zone between the asters remains stationary, while the outer aster periphery grows outwards due to a combination of MT polymerization and outward sliding.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>MTOC separation movement in <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs and egg extract.</title><p>Panels A-C are fixed embryos, and panels D-F are in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract. (<bold>A</bold>) Cartoon illustrating MTOC movement away from the CPC-positive midplane before astral microtubules (MTs) reach the cortex in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> eggs. MTs shown in cyan and CPC-positive interaction zone in magenta. Note the CPC is shown in the cartoon panels A and D, but not in the rest of the figure. (<bold>B,C</bold>) Anti-tubulin immunofluorescence of eggs fixed ~70 and ~85 min post-fertilization (pf). Diagonal lines connecting different eggs in panels B and C emphasize centrosome separation movement and the growing aster periphery. (<bold>B’,C’</bold>) Anti-LNPK (ER) immunofluorescence of the same eggs. (<bold>D</bold>) Cartoon illustrating aster separation movement in an extract system. MTs and CPC as in panel A. Asters were reconstituted from artificial microtubule organizing centers (MTOCs) in interphase <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts. (<bold>E,F</bold>) MTOCs moved apart as asters grew and interacted with one another over time. Time is defined with respect to perfusing the sample and warming to 20°C, so the start of aster growth occurred soon after 0 min. (<bold>F’</bold>) A fraction of the ER became enriched around MTOCs, and (<bold>F’’</bold>) F-actin was disassembled locally along interaction zones.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Higher magnification imaging around MTOCs included signatures of both co-movement and relative movement of astral MTs, ER, and F-actin.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video1">Video 1</xref>) (<bold>A</bold>) MTs imaged at near-speckle concentrations with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER labeled with DiI, and F-actin labeled with Lifeact-GFP. Images taken on a spinning disk confocal microscope with 60x objective. (<bold>B</bold>) Radial kymographs generated by averaging the intensity over 10° sectors originating at the MTOC. One end remained pinned at the MTOC, and the other end rotated with the average flow of ER, so features would remain in the sector, and the kymograph would highlight their radial movement. To guide the eye, the solid lines indicate the growing aster periphery (slope corresponds to 30 µm/min), and the dotted lines track with outward sliding of tubulin speckles away from the MTOC (slope corresponds to 3 µm/min). (<bold>C</bold>) Tangential kymographs generated along a circle centered on the MTOC, so moving features represent tangential displacement with respect to the MTOC.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig1-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>The forces that act on MTs to move asters, centrosomes, and nuclei differ between systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Garzon-Coral et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Grill and Hyman, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kotak and Gönczy, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Meaders and Burgess, 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Xie and Minc, 2020</xref>). Centration movement of the sperm aster after fertilization and movement of sister asters away from the midzone after mitosis are thought to involve similar mechanics (ibid). Our focus is on post-mitotic movement to avoid the complication of MT-plasma membrane interactions. In <italic>Xenopus</italic> and zebrafish zygotes, which are unusually large cells, aster movement away from the midplane is driven by dynein-dependent pulling forces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Wühr et al., 2010</xref>). Since movement occurs before astral MTs reach the cortex, the dynein must be localized throughout the cytoplasm, presumably attached to organelles, but this was not tested. The most prominent model for aster movement of this kind proposes that dynein attached to organelles throughout the aster generates pulling forces that increase with MT length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hamaguchi and Hiramoto, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kimura and Kimura, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Tanimoto et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tanimoto et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Wühr et al., 2010</xref>). In this ‘length-dependent pulling’ model, dynein transports organelles along astral MTs toward the centrosome, then viscous or elastic drag on the organelles imparts a counter force on the MTs, pulling them away from the centrosome. The flux of organelles, and thus the net pulling force, is thought to scale with MT length. Although length-dependent pulling models are widely discussed, many aspects remain unclear, for example, net forces may not scale with MT length due to hydrodynamic interactions between MTs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Nazockdast et al., 2017</xref>). The organelles that anchor dynein in the cytoplasm of large egg cells have not been fully identified and the spatiotemporal distribution of organelle transport has not been mapped. Candidate dynein anchor organelles include the ER, which moves inwards as sperm asters center in sea urchin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Terasaki and Jaffe, 1991</xref>), acidic organelles which were implicated in nematode eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kimura and Kimura, 2011</xref>) and mitochondria which are abundant in early embryos.</p><p>Contractile activity of actomyosin can cause centrosome and aster movement in eggs and embryos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Field and Lénárt, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Telley et al., 2012</xref>), but its contribution to centrosome separation movement in <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs is unclear. Bulk cytoplasmic F-actin is a major mechanical element in <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Elinson, 1983</xref>) and egg extracts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Field et al., 2011</xref>). In egg extracts, F-actin can impede centrosome movement in meiotic extracts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Colin et al., 2018</xref>), but F-actin is not required for centrosome separation movement in cycling extracts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Cheng and Ferrell, 2019</xref>). Caution is required when extrapolating from drug studies to the mechanics of unperturbed cytoplasm. F-actin depolymerization softens the cytoplasm and presumably decreases the drag on moving asters as well as dynein anchors. Thus, F-actin depolymerization may modulate dynein-based forces on asters, in addition to removing actomyosin-based forces. Furthermore, effects of cytochalasins in <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs are hard to interpret because they only permeate the <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg cortex during first cleavage, when new membrane becomes exposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">de Laat et al., 1973</xref>).</p><p>Considering both the length-dependent pulling model, and the role of actomyosin, one important question has not been rigorously addressed in any system: do centrosomes and associated astral MTs move <italic>through</italic> a static cytoplasm, as predicted by the length-dependent pulling model? Or do they move <italic>with</italic> other components of cytoplasm, such as organelles, F-actin and cytosol? If organelles anchor dynein, the length-dependent pulling model predicts that they must move in the opposite direction as the centrosome, or at least remain stationary. Inward movement of organelles in moving asters has been reported in some systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hamaguchi and Hiramoto, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hamaguchi and Hiramoto, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kimura and Kimura, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Terasaki and Jaffe, 1991</xref>), but to our knowledge, there are no quantitative studies relating organelle flux to forces on asters. The dynamics of F-actin and cytosol in moving asters have not been addressed to our knowledge. Theoretical models of the length-dependent force model implicitly assume that these components are static and homogenous and contribute to viscous drag on moving asters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Tanimoto et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tanimoto et al., 2018</xref>). Live observation of multiple components of cytoplasm is required to address these questions. This is not possible in opaque frog eggs so we turned to actin-intact egg extracts. Growth and interaction of interphase asters were previously reported in this system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Ishihara et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Nguyen et al., 2014</xref>), but aster movement was not systematically investigated. Here, we report methods for observing aster movement in egg extract and use them to measure relative movement of MTs, organelles, and F-actin. We observed all cytoplasmic networks mostly moved together inside asters. The highest velocity differences between networks occurred at the aster periphery. Mechanical integration between all cytoplasmic components inside asters requires new models for aster movement.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Centrosome separation and ER distribution in fixed eggs</title><p>As a first test of how centrosomes and organelles move relative to one another, we fixed frog eggs before first cleavage, stained for tubulin and ER, and imaged by confocal microscopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A–C</xref>). Centrosome separation movement is represented by the diagonal lines connecting different eggs in panels B and C. As centrosomes move away from the midplane, the centrioles within them replicate and split, visible as the pair of bright cyan spots within each aster in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>. We probed the ER distribution by staining for the ER membrane marker Lunapark (LNPK) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B’,C’</xref>). The ER luminal marker PDIA3 had a similar distribution (not shown). The ER was distributed all over the asters, with some enrichment near centrosomes and the cortex. Lack of strong ER enrichment at centrosomes called into question the length-dependent pulling model with the ER as a dynein anchor. However, organelle transport dynamics could not be measured from fixed images, so we turned to an egg extract system for live imaging.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Microtubule organizing center (MTOC) separation movement in egg extract by dynein and actomyosin</title><p>To model aster separation movement in a cell-free system suitable for live imaging, we filled chambers consisting of two PEG-passivated coverslips spaced ~20 µm apart with actin-intact interphase egg extract containing artificial MTOCs, imaging probes and drugs. We then imaged aster growth and movement over ~30 min. For most experiments we used widefield microscopy with a 20x objective to collect data on overall organization and flows, in some cases stitching multiple image fields. To illustrate structural details of the components we studied, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video1">Video 1</xref> show MTs, ER, and F-actin near an MTOC by spinning disk confocal microscopy with a 60x objective. In 20x magnification fields, we routinely noted that MTOCs that were close together at early time points tended to move apart. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref> illustrates the extract system, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E,F</xref> show an example of MTOCs moving apart as asters grew and interacted with one another. This kind of separation movement was observed in hundreds of image sequences, such as in <xref ref-type="video" rid="video2">Video 2</xref>, and we believe it models centrosome separation movement in eggs.</p><media id="video1" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video1.mp4"><label>Video 1.</label><caption><title>Dynamic reorganization of cytoplasmic networks during the initial stages of aster nucleation and growth imaged at 60x.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>) MTs were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER with DiI, and F-actin with Lifeact-GFP. Imaged on a spinning disk confocal with 60x objective lens. Cytoplasmic networks were highly dynamic, and astral MTs dynamically reorganized the ER and F-actin networks. Parts of the ER exhibited abrupt and transient motion toward the MTOC, presumably driven by dynein, and the F-actin transitioned from random to radial entrainment with MTs.</p></caption></media><media id="video2" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video2.mp4"><label>Video 2.</label><caption><title>Co-movement of MTs, ER, and F-actin during aster separation movement.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>) MTs were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER with DiI, F-actin with Lifeact-GFP, and organelles were shown in differential interference contrast (DIC). All cytoplasmic networks moved together. Note the flow of organelles visible in DIC: inside asters, where the density of F-actin, MTs, and ER was higher, organelles flowed with the asters; whereas along interaction zones between asters where the density of F-actin was lower, organelles flowed in the opposite direction, into the space on the right that was vacated by the asters moving to the left.</p></caption></media><p>When asters grew to touch each other, they formed CPC-positive interaction zones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>) as previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Nguyen et al., 2014</xref>), modeling similar zones in eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Field et al., 2015</xref>). CPC-positive interaction zones cause local disassembly of both MTs and F-actin, which locally softens the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Field et al., 2019</xref>). The resulting anisotropies in MT and F-actin density may lead to generation of directed forces on MTOCs by both dynein and actomyosin.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>MTOC separation movement in egg extract by dynein and actomyosin.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The CPC localized to interaction zones between neighboring asters, blocking mutual interpenetration of MTs and disassembling F-actin locally. Time is defined with respect to perfusing the sample and warming to 20°C, so the start of aster growth occurred soon after 0 min. (<bold>B</bold>) Four aster growth reactions were followed in parallel under control vs inhibitor conditions. The first column in each condition shows an early time point, and the second column shows a time point 30 min later. MT growth was similar and CPC-positive interaction zones formed under all conditions (see <xref ref-type="video" rid="video3">Video 3</xref>). (<bold>C</bold>) Maximum speed of separation with respect to initial distance between the MTOCs. Red lines indicate linear fits to red points.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata1"><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>MTOC trajectories and Delaunay triangulations for panels B and C.</title><p>The ‘beads’ variables are structures that contain the MTOC trajectories. Some MTOCs enter or exit the image during the movie, and the ‘t’ field within each element represents the frames during which an MTOC was present, with 1 the first frame and 10 the last frame. The ‘x’ and ‘y’ fields represent the MTOC position, and the ‘nn’ field represents the indices of the nearest neighbor MTOCs defined by the Delaunay triangulation. The ‘pairs’ variables enumerate all pairs of nearest neighbor MTOCs, that is, the edges in panel B. The last column is 0 if the corresponding interaction zone was not CPC-positive, and 0.5 or 1 if the corresponding interaction was CPC-positive. The ‘edges’ variables list all neighboring edges for each edge.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="octet-stream" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig2-data1-v2.mat"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig><p>To quantify MTOC movement, and determine the role of forces from different motors, we picked random locations and imaged large fields over time in up to four conditions in parallel. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video3">Video 3</xref> show a typical experiment, where only the CPC channel is shown for simplicity. At early times points, the spatial distribution of MTOCs was random and the CPC signal was diffuse, except some signal on the MTOCs. As asters grew and interacted, they recruited CPC to zones between them under all conditions. We quantified MTOC movements with respect to their nearest neighbors, which were defined by the Delaunay triangulation between MTOCs at the earliest time point and followed over the video (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Red edges indicate when neighboring MTOCs formed a CPC-positive interaction zone between them, and blue edges indicate when they did not. We then measured the maximum separation speed as a function of the initial separation distance between the MTOCs. Under control conditions, MTOCs that were initially closer together tended to move farther apart, while those initially farther apart tended to move closer together, leading to MTOCs becoming more regularly spaced at the end of the sequence. This directionality is evident from the strong negative correlation between the maximum speed of separation movement and starting distance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). We focused on separation movement of MTOCs in separate asters with a CPC-positive interaction zone between them (red points), since this models post-anaphase centrosome separation movement in eggs.</p><media id="video3" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video3.mp4"><label>Video 3.</label><caption><title>Both dynein and actomyosin contribute to aster separation movement.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>) We compared four conditions: control with F-actin intact, dynein inhibited by p150-CC1, F-actin fragmented by Cytochalasin D, and double inhibition of dynein and F-actin. F-actin was labeled with Lifeact-GFP, ER was labeled with DiI, organelles were shown in differential interference contrast (DIC), and CPC-positive interaction zones were labeled with anti-INCENP-Alexa Fluor 647. MTs grew and CPC-positive interaction zones formed between asters in all conditions. F-actin and ER were imaged instead of MTs because local disassembly of F-actin along CPC-positive interaction zones is thought to help aster separation movement, and inward transport of ER and other organelles is thought to drive dynein-based aster movement.</p></caption></media><p>To test the role of dynein and actomyosin in MTOC movement, we inhibited dynein using the p150-CC1 fragment of dynactin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">King et al., 2003</xref>) or fragmented F-actin using Cytochalasin D. Inhibiting either motile system alone caused a partial block to aster movement, and inhibiting both caused an almost complete block (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). Inhibiting CPC recruitment with an AURKB inhibitor also completely blocked MTOC movement (not shown). The contributions of dynein and actomyosin forces to aster movement were similar, as judged by similar effects of single inhibition on the slopes of separation speed vs initial distance plots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). These findings were qualitatively confirmed by visual inspection and partial analysis of more than 10 experiments using multiple extracts. We interpret these data as showing that MTOC movement in our extract system is driven by a combination of dynein and actomyosin forces. We investigate sites of dynein-based pulling below. We hypothesize actomyosin-based separation movement is driven by actomyosin contraction away from regions of lower F-actin density along interaction zones and will analyze this model in detail elsewhere. With a reliable system for aster separation movement in hand, we next interrogated organelle and F-actin dynamics.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>ER and F-actin move with MTs in separating asters</title><p>Aster separation trajectories were longest, and most unidirectional, when MTOCs were clustered at the initial time point. In these cases, MTOCs moved predictably outwards from the cluster as asters grew out and CPC-positive interaction zones formed between them (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A,B</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video2">Video 2</xref>). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>, future MTOC trajectories are superimposed on an early time point to illustrate separation movement. To investigate how ER and F-actin moved with respect to moving astral MTs, we first used kymograph analysis. We picked a pair of MTOCs that moved apart, indicated by stars in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A–C</xref>. Then we generated kymographs in all channels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>) along the line passing through the MTOCs, indicated by the grey line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A,B</xref>. Visual inspection revealed features in all three channels that tracked parallel to the separating MTOCs, suggesting all the networks were moving together away from the interaction zone, on both the leading and trailing sides of the aster indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>. Organelles visible in differential interference contrast (DIC) images also moved away from the interaction zone (<xref ref-type="video" rid="video2">Video 2</xref>). These features are most evident in the F-actin kymograph, but can be seen in all channels by magnifying the figure and inspecting closely. Visual inspection and kymograph analysis of image sequences from more than 10 independent experiments confirmed that all components of asters tend to move together during separation movement, and that the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> are typical.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>ER and F-actin move with MTs in separating asters.</title><p>(<bold>A,B</bold>) Asters grew until they reached their neighbors, formed interaction zones approximately equidistant between the MTOCs, then moved away from the interaction zones (see <xref ref-type="video" rid="video2">Video 2</xref>). MTOC trajectories are represented by contours colored from blue to yellow. Time is defined with respect to perfusing the sample and warming to 20°C, so the start of aster growth occurred soon after 0 min. (<bold>C</bold>) Intensity kymographs along the gray line shown in panels A and B, passing through the MTOCs marked with a white star. To show relative movement of the MTOCs, each row of the kymograph was computationally translated to keep stationary the midpoint between the MTOCs, where the interaction zone formed. Solid curves indicate the MTOCs, the dashed curve indicates the growing aster periphery, and the dash-dotted line indicates the interaction zone. (<bold>D</bold>) Velocity maps in the same frame of reference as in panel C. 2D flow fields were measured by particle image velocimetry (PIV), projected onto the line passing through the MTOCs, then the projected velocity of the midpoint between the MTOCs was subtracted, again to show movement relative to the interaction zone. A white color indicates stationary with respect to the midpoint, blue indicates moving to the left, and red to the right. PIV outliers were filtered and shown in beige. (<bold>E</bold>) Velocity of the MTOCs based on particle tracking, as well as the velocity of ER and F-actin in the neighborhood of the MTOCs based on PIV. (<bold>F</bold>) Velocity of ER with respect to the moving MTOCs, not with respect to the interaction zone as in panel D.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata1"><label>Figure 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Velocity maps for panel D, as well as the full 2D velocity fields from PIV used to generate the velocity maps.</title><p>Velocities in the neighborhood of the MTOCs (from PIV for the ER and F-actin, and from particle tracking for the MTOC) for panel E.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="octet-stream" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig3-data1-v2.mat"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Higher magnification imaging around zones included signatures of both co-movement and relative movement of astral MTs, ER, and F-actin.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video4">Video 4</xref>) (<bold>A</bold>) MTs labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER labeled with DiI, and F-actin labeled with Lifeact-GFP. Images taken on a spinning disk confocal microscope with 60x objective. (<bold>B</bold>) Kymographs along the line indicated in panel A. (<bold>C</bold>) Velocity maps in the same frame of reference as panel B. Velocity maps represent the horizontal component of the velocity estimated by PIV. (<bold>D</bold>) Temporal montage of the box indicated in panel A’ showing an example of deformation of the ER. Time with respect to the start of the montage.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig3-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>To better quantify movement of MTs, ER, and F-actin as asters separated, we measured 2D flow fields by particle image velocimetry (PIV). All three cytoplasmic networks moved in the same direction at similar speeds of up to 7 µm/min. Movement was always directed away from the interaction zone on both leading and trailing sides of the aster, as shown by blue on both sides annotated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C,D</xref>. This is inconsistent with the length-dependent pulling model, in which organelles on the leading side must move toward the interaction zone (red) or at least remain stationary with respect to the interaction zone (white). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref> compares the MTOC velocity from particle tracking to the ER and F-actin velocities from PIV, again consistent with all three cytoplasmic networks moving outwards at similar speeds. To highlight relative movement within asters, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref> shows the ER velocity relative to the MTOC velocity. MTOCs and ER moved outwards at similar rates near the center of the asters, as evidenced by the pale colors in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>. In contrast, there was more relative movement at the external and internal peripheries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D,F</xref>). ER movement relative to MTs at the aster periphery is investigated in detail below.</p><p>Close inspection of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref> and similar analyses showed that velocities of all three networks away from the interaction zone were not constant throughout the aster, though different networks had similar velocities at any given location. Typically, the region near the interaction zones moved ~20% faster than the MTOC, and the leading edge of each aster moved ~20% slower. This spatial variation in velocity shows that the aster does not move as a completely rigid body. Rather, it deforms as a gel, locally compressing or stretching in response to forces and stresses.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Higher magnification imaging shows saltatory as well as correlated movement</title><p>Co-movement of cytoplasmic networks in image sequences collected with a 20x objective is in apparent disagreement with mechanisms known to transport networks relative to one another, for example, by motors or tip tracking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lane and Allan, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Wang et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Waterman-Storer et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Waterman-Storer et al., 1995</xref>). To resolve this discrepancy, we imaged asters at higher spatiotemporal resolution using 60x spinning disk confocal microscopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video1">Videos 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video4">4</xref>). At 60x, we observed that some local segments of the ER exhibited rapid, saltatory movement toward and away from the MTOC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B’</xref>) as well as rapid, transient deformation of the ER (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1D</xref>). Although these examples show that co-movement can break down on small spatiotemporal scales, we observed a predominance of co-movement even at 60x. In tangential kymographs, pivoting movement of MTs was mirrored by ER and F-actin features (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1C</xref>). In radial kymographs, MT speckles, ER, and F-actin features slid outwards together, likely driven by dynein because dynein inhibition blocks such outward MT sliding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Ishihara et al., 2014</xref>). In moving asters, intensity features in all three networks largely tracked together even at 60x (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1B</xref>), confirmed by PIV velocity maps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1C</xref>). In summary, our data confirm literature reports that ER and F-actin can move rapidly relative to MTs on small spatiotemporal scales, but show that on scales of tens of microns and minutes, they tend to move together.</p><media id="video4" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video4.mp4"><label>Video 4.</label><caption><title>Signatures of both co-movement and relative movement in moving asters imaged at 60x.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>) MTs were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER with DiI, and F-actin with Lifeact-GFP. Imaged on a spinning disk confocal with 60x objective lens. All networks were highly dynamic. Some ER and F-actin features moved relative to astral MTs, deformed, or otherwise changed structure, which provide examples where co-movement breaks down on small spatiotemporal scales; however, the dominant trend was co-movement of the networks.</p></caption></media></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>ER and F-actin move with MTs on coverslips functionalized with dynein</title><p>To provide a complementary system for dynein-dependent MTOC movement, we artificially anchored dynein to the coverslip via a biologically relevant linkage. Endogenous HOOK2, a coiled-coil dynein-dynactin adapter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Reck-Peterson et al., 2018</xref>), was recruited to PEG-passivated coverslips via an antibody raised to its C-terminus (Materials and methods). To characterize the antibody and identify HOOK2 interacting proteins, we performed quantitative immunoprecipitation-mass spectrometry (IP-MS) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). We compared three conditions: anti-HOOK2 in interphase extracts (three separate extract repeats), anti-HOOK2 in mitotic extracts (two repeats), and as negative control, random IgG in interphase extracts (three repeats). HOOK2 was the most abundant protein recovered on anti-HOOK2 beads. HOOK3 was also detected, consistent with heterodimerization between HOOK family members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Redwine et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Xu et al., 2008</xref>). In interphase extracts, anti-HOOK2 pulled down multiple subunits of the dynein-dynactin complex, plus known interactors LIS1 and CLIP1. All these dynein-related proteins were greatly reduced in pulldowns from mitotic extracts, suggesting the interaction between HOOK2 and dynein-dynactin is negatively regulated by CDK1 activity. We concluded that the HOOK2 antibody offers a physiological linkage to dynein, and we proceeded to test its ability to serve as a dynein anchor for aster movement.</p><p>Dynein attached to coverslips via HOOK2 generated pulling forces on MTs directed away from the MTOC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). We previously reported that dynein non-specifically adsorbed to non-passivated coverslips increases the rate of aster growth due to outward microtubule sliding, but did not move MTOCs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Ishihara et al., 2014</xref>). Remarkably, on HOOK2-functionalized coverslips, asters exhibited rapid translational movement in a circular pattern with a diameter of 20–30 µm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B,C</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video5">Video 5</xref>). During this movement, MTOCs moved continuously at ~1 µm/s, approximately 10-fold faster than the separation movements described above and comparable to the maximum speed of dynein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Reck-Peterson et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). This 2D-oscillatory movement was observed in &gt;10 different experiments using different batches of extract, and was blocked by dynein inhibition with p150-CC1. We plan to investigate the instability that causes circular motion elsewhere. Here, we used the rapid aster movement as an alternative system to study how ER and F-actin move with respect to moving MTs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref> shows intensity kymographs along a horizontal line that tracks up and down with the MTOC, analogous to the kymographs in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4F</xref> shows velocity maps analogous to those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>. The intensity kymographs reveal many features that tracked with the MTOC, and the velocity plots show that indeed, all the cytoskeletal networks moved in the same direction, at the same speed, at any location inside the aster. In another experiment, keratin was also advected with moving asters (<xref ref-type="video" rid="video6">Video 6</xref>). From these observations, we conclude that cytoplasmic networks are mechanically integrated inside asters, and cytoplasmic networks move together with moving asters.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>ER and F-actin move with MTs on coverslips functionalized with dynein.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Coverslips were functionalized with an antibody against HOOK2, so the rigid coverslip substrate generated pulling forces on the astral MTs. (<bold>B</bold>) Circular oscillatory trajectory of the MTOC (see <xref ref-type="video" rid="video5">Video 5</xref>). (<bold>C</bold>) X coordinate of the MTOC. (<bold>D</bold>) Speed of the MTOC relative to the coverslip, including both X and Y components of motion. (<bold>E</bold>) Intensity kymographs along the horizontal line passing through the MTOC, indicated in panel B. (<bold>F</bold>) Velocity maps in the same frame of reference as in panel E. 2D velocity fields were measured by particle image velocimetry (PIV) then projected onto the horizontal line as in panel E. The MTOC position is shown as a black curve.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata1"><label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Velocity maps for panel F, as well as the full 2D velocity fields from PIV used to generate the velocity maps.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="octet-stream" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig4-data1-v2.mat"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Characterization of the HOOK2 C-terminal peptide antibody.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8</xref>) We performed immunoprecipitation-mass spectrometry (IP-MS) on Protein G Dynabeads functionalized with anti-HOOK2. In three repeat extracts, we measured three conditions: anti-HOOK2 in interphase extracts (columns 1 to 3), anti-HOOK2 in mitotic extracts (columns 4 and 5), and as negative control, random IgG in interphase (columns 6 through 8). HOOK2 conditions were normalized so the amount of HOOK2 was constant. Random IgG conditions were normalized to have the same IgG count as the average IgG count of the HOOK2 columns. Then for each protein, the sum across channels was normalized, so the abundance values represent relative enrichment across the eight channels. Abundances are shown on a log scale with base 2. We here show dynein subunits (blue), dynactin subunits (red), and other proteins known to interact with dynein-dynactin (yellow, green) that came down in the immunoprecipitations. The interaction between HOOK2 and the dynein-dynactin complex was stronger in interphase (left columns) than in mitosis (middle columns).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4s1sdata1"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Immunoprecipitation-mass spectrometry (IP-MS) counts for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig4-figsupp1-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig4-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><media id="video5" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video5.mp4"><label>Video 5.</label><caption><title>Co-movement of MTs, ER, and F-actin during oscillatory aster movement on coverslips functionalized with dynein.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>) MTs were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER with DiI, and F-actin with Lifeact-GFP. All cytoplasmic networks moved together. Dynein was recruited to coverslips via an antibody to the endogenous dynein adapter HOOK2.</p></caption></media><media id="video6" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video6.mp4"><label>Video 6.</label><caption><title>Co-movement of keratin with moving asters during oscillatory aster movement.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>) MTs were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, F-actin with Lifeact-GFP, and keratin with anti-keratin-Alexa Fluor 568. All cytoplasmic networks moved together.</p></caption></media></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>A small molecule probe is advected with moving asters</title><p>The high speed and predictability of oscillatory aster movement on HOOK2-functionalized coverslips enabled us to ask whether the cytosol was advected with the moving cytoplasmic networks. This question was inspired by recent experiments showing that moving actomyosin gels advect cytosol in <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Deneke et al., 2019</xref>). We functionalized artificial MTOCs with caged fluorescein, linked to the MTOCs via the caging group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). The fluorescein was uncaged upon shining 395 nm light, simultaneously activating its fluorescence and releasing it from the MTOCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A–C</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video7">Video 7</xref>). The cloud of photo-released fluorescein dispersed within tens of seconds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>). Rapid diffusive spread of the cloud validated that the fluorescein behaves as a freely diffusing small molecule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>) and enabled estimation of the viscosity of the cytosol at ~6 x that of water (Materials and methods), consistent with previous estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Luby-Phelps, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Valentine et al., 2005</xref>). We then fit the fluorescein cloud with a 2D Gaussian to track its center of mass, masking the bead so as not to bias the fit. The center of brightness of the diffusing fluorescein cloud and the MTOC had similar trajectories (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref>), showing that cytosol advects with moving asters due to hydrodynamic interactions inside asters. Similar results were obtained in &gt;10 experiments in three extracts. The cloud center did not precisely track with the moving MTOC, rather it tended to drift. Statistical analysis suggested this drift was probably not caused by tracking error (Materials and methods). We suspect that forces outside the aster can drive bulk flow of sol through the aster gel, carrying the diffusing fluorescein cloud with it. Consistent with this hypothesis, computationally translating the cloud center to remove the effect of a hypothetical constant flow field greatly improved registration between the cloud center and MTOC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>A small molecule is advected with moving asters.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) To track the flow of a small molecule within moving asters, MTOCs were functionalized with caged fluorescein. (<bold>B</bold>) Caged fluorescein, before uncaging. (<bold>B’</bold>) Astral MTs radiating from the MTOC filled the region. The aster was oscillating on a coverslip functionalized with anti-HOOK2 as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>. (<bold>C</bold>) Fluorescein, after uncaging. (<bold>D</bold>) Within tens of seconds, the fluorescein diffused away from the MTOC and approached the background intensity (see <xref ref-type="video" rid="video7">Video 7</xref>). 2D Gaussian fits to estimate the width and center of the fluorescein cloud. The bright MTOC was excluded from the Gaussian fit, so uncaged fluorescein that remained bound to the MTOC did not bias the fitted position. (<bold>E</bold>) Expansion of the fluorescein cloud width fit to a model of diffusion. (<bold>F</bold>) Several replicate trajectories of the MTOC (circle) and the center of the fluorescein cloud (plus).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Hypothetical constant flow permeating asters can improve registration between MTOC and center of fluorescein cloud.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>) (<bold>A</bold>) Trajectory of MTOC (circle) and center of the fluorescein cloud, within aster oscillating on HOOK2-functionalized coverslip, same as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Trajectory of MTOC (circle) and center of the fluorescein cloud after computationally subtracting a constant flow (square). Flow direction and magnitude shown as a black arrow above each panel. The hypothetical constant flow was optimized to minimize the difference between the MTOC and cloud trajectories.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5s1sdata1"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Width of the fluorescein cloud vs time for panel E, and MTOC and cloud center trajectories for panel F.</title><p>The ‘driftVec’ variables are the hypothetical constant flow that was optimized to minimize the difference between the MTOC and cloud trajectories for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="octet-stream" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig5-figsupp1-data1-v2.mat"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig5-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Separating asters exhibited saddle-shaped flow fields, consistent with advection of cytosol by moving asters.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>) (<bold>A,B</bold>) F-actin labeled with Lifeact-GFP, CPC labeled with anti-INCENP-Alexa Fluor 647, and MTs labeled with Tau-mCherry. (<bold>C</bold>) Differential interference contrast to visualize mitochondria and other small vesicles. (<bold>D</bold>) Flow fields of the DIC channel estimated by PIV exhibited a saddle shape, with flow along the interaction zone toward the midpoint between the asters. F-actin and MTs exhibited similar flow fields. Color represents direction (legend in upper right of first panel), and brightness represents velocity. Note that arrows are downsampled from full flow fields. Time with respect to warming the sample and the onset of aster polymerization.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig5-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><media id="video7" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video7.mp4"><label>Video 7.</label><caption><title>Advection of fluorescein with moving asters during oscillatory aster movement.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>) The first frames show MTs labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, and the aster filled the region. The next few frames show the caged fluorescein attached to the MTOC. Then, the fluorescein was simultaneously photo-released from the MTOC as its fluorescence was uncaged, releasing a cloud of fluorescent fluorescein around the MTOC. The fluorescein cloud was fit with a 2D Gaussian. The center of the cloud is indicated at the intersection of the red and green lines, and the standard deviation of the cloud is indicated by the black circle. The plots above and to the right indicate the intensity values along the lines, and the black curves show the 2D Gaussian fit along the lines.</p></caption></media><p>If separating asters on passivated coverslips also advect cytosol we would expect them to generate hydrodynamic forces and compensatory flows outside the asters. Disassembly of F-actin by CPC makes the cytoplasm between separating asters more permeable to bulk flow of cytosol than the rest of the aster (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Field et al., 2019</xref>). Thus, compensatory flows are expected to be directed inwards along interaction zones. We measured 2D flow fields around separating asters using PIV analysis of DIC image sequences. We indeed observed inward flow along the interaction zone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2</xref>). Advection of cytosol suggests moving asters constitute a poroelastic regime and places an upper bound of ~100 nm on their effective pore size (Materials and methods) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mitchison et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Moeendarbary et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Dynein-mediated organelle movement is restricted by F-actin and interior MTs</title><p>Returning to passivated surfaces, we next investigated which organelles recruit dynein, and where they might exert forces that drive aster movement. To facilitate detailed analysis of organelle transport, we imaged isolated asters that remained stationary as they grew. ER and mitochondria are the most abundant organelles in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts based on proteomics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Wühr et al., 2014</xref>), and acidic organelles were implicated in centrosome movement in <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kimura and Kimura, 2011</xref>).</p><p>In control extracts with F-actin intact, almost all the ER, mitochondria, and acidic organelles remained evenly distributed over asters as they grew. A small fraction of the ER accumulated near MTOCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7A,D</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video8">Videos 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video9">9</xref>). The ER intensity around MTOCs increased to ~2-fold higher than the intensity outside the aster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A’</xref>) in &gt;5 examples scored. Although the majority of ER remained stationary, astral MTs did induce a subtle change in the texture of the ER, from coarser outside the aster, to finer and more tubular in appearance inside the aster (<xref ref-type="video" rid="video8">Videos 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="video" rid="video9">9</xref>). Astral MTs also affected the structure of the F-actin network, from random orientation of filaments outside the aster, to transient radial alignment of a subpopulation of bundles inside the aster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>) as we reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Field et al., 2019</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Dynein-mediated organelle movement is restricted by F-actin.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) In control with intact F-actin, a small amount of ER became concentrated around the MTOC, but the majority of the ER and mitochondria remained distributed over the aster (see <xref ref-type="video" rid="video8">Video 8</xref>). The white arc indicates the growing aster periphery, and the box indicates the zoomed region in the lower panels. (<bold>A’</bold>) Average intensity with respect to distance from the MTOC over time, from black to gray. (<bold>B</bold>) When F-actin was fragmented with Cytochalasin D, a greater fraction of the ER was transported toward the MTOC, and a fraction of mitochondria was transported as well. Higher magnification: ER started to move when MTs indicated by growing +TIPs first grew into the cytoplasm, and ER and mitochondria co-localized with one another. (<bold>C</bold>) When dynein was inhibited with p150-CC1, the ER was not transported, neither toward nor away from the MTOC.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6sdata1"><label>Figure 6—source data 1.</label><caption><title>ER and mitochondria intensity profiles for panels A’, B’, and C’.</title><p>Intensity profiles were normalized to the average intensity outside the aster to correct for photobleaching.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="octet-stream" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig6-data1-v2.mat"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig6-v2.tif"/></fig><fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Dynein-mediated organelle movement is maximal on the aster periphery.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Stationary asters were grown from isolated MTOCs. The growing aster periphery is indicated by a white arc, and the ER was largely distributed but slightly depleted just inside the growing aster periphery. The ER exhibited a change in texture from slightly coarser outside the aster to finer inside the aster (see <xref ref-type="video" rid="video9">Video 9</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) Kymographs along a line extending away from the MTOC. The MTOC corresponds to the left column, and the growing aster periphery corresponds to the diagonal line where soluble tubulin is depleted upon incorporation into the growing aster. (<bold>C</bold>) Mass transport map for ER averaged over a quadrant, in the same frame of reference as the kymographs in panel B. Mass transport analysis is described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s2">Figure 7—figure supplement 2</xref>. (<bold>D–F</bold>) Similar experiment with F-actin intact, in a different batch of extract that exhibited less organelle movement. (<bold>G–J</bold>) Similar experiment with F-actin fragmented by Cytochalasin D (see <xref ref-type="video" rid="video10">Video 10</xref>). (<bold>J</bold>) Average speed based on PIV, in the same frame of reference as panels H,I and averaged over a quadrant. PIV is not shown for control because movement was too slow to be reliably quantified.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata1"><label>Figure 7—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Mass transport maps for panels C, F, and I (in units of % of total per min), and PIV maps for panel J (in µm/s).</title></caption><media mime-subtype="octet-stream" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig7-data1-v2.mat"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig7-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Like other organelles, mitochondria exhibited a burst of organelle movement near the growing aster periphery.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video11">Video 11</xref>) (<bold>A</bold>) F-actin was fragmented by Cytochalasin D. Microtubules were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER with DiD, and mitochondria with TMRE. (<bold>B</bold>) Kymographs along a line from the MTOC. (<bold>C</bold>) Mass transport map for ER and mitochondria averaged over a quadrant, in the same frame of reference as the kymographs in panel B. Mass transport analysis is described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s2">Figure 7—figure supplement 2</xref>. (<bold>D</bold>) Average speed based on PIV, in the same frame of reference as panels B and C, and averaged over a quadrant. In all analysis methods, mitochondria behaved similar to acidic organelles and likewise exhibited a burst of movement at the growing aster periphery.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig7-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Explanation of flux analysis of organelle transport.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>) (<bold>A,B</bold>) Subsequent frames in a video to measure dynein-based flux of organelles along astral MTs. The flux analysis requires that the region of interest (ROI) contains the entire aster at all times, so there is no transport of organelles into or out of the ROI, just radial redistribution of organelles along astral MTs within the ROI. Images were flat field corrected, then normalized to constant total intensity to correct for photobleaching. (<bold>C</bold>) Kymograph of average organelle intensity in concentric rings away from the MTOC. Frames 31 (green, panel A) and 32 (purple, panel B) correspond to the rows of the kymograph indicated by horizontal dotted lines. The distance to the aster periphery at this time, indicated by the white dotted arc in panels A and B, is indicated by the vertical white dotted line. (<bold>D</bold>) Average organelle intensity in concentric rings away from the MTOC. (<bold>E</bold>) Total intensity in concentric rings away from the MTOC. The total intensity increases roughly linearly with the circumference. (<bold>F</bold>) Cumulative total intensity away from the MTOC. Zoomed inset shows where the cumulative total intensity at frame 32 most exceeds that at frame 31. (<bold>G</bold>) Flux of fluorescence intensity toward the MTOC, calculated as the cumulative total intensity at frame 32 minus that at frame 31. Flux was normalized to the percentage of the total fluorescence intensity moving across each bin edge (10 µm) per min. (<bold>H</bold>) Flux map in the same frame of reference as the kymograph in panel C. Panel G corresponds to the row indicated by the horizontal black dotted line.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig7-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig7s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Dextran was excluded in organelle-rich region within ~50 µm of MTOCs.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figures 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video13">Video 13</xref>) (<bold>A</bold>) The growing +TIPs of MTs were labeled with EB1-GFP, the relative concentration of cytosol was inferred from 10 kDa dextran labeled with Alexa-Fluor 568, and organelles were visualized with differential interference contrast (DIC). Images taken 18.3 min after warming to 20°C and the onset of aster growth. (<bold>B,C</bold>) Intensity profiles away from the MTOC colored by time point. In the EB1 graph, the wavefront corresponds to the growing aster periphery. To correct for photobleaching, dextran profiles were normalized to the intensity at the point farthest from the MTOC.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig7-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><media id="video8" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video8.mp4"><label>Video 8.</label><caption><title>F-actin reduced dynein-based transport of ER and mitochondria on stationary asters.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>) The growing aster is indicated by growing +TIPs labeled with EB1-GFP, ER was labeled with DiI, and mitochondria with TMRE. In control with intact F-actin, some ER accumulated around the MTOC, and little to no mitochondria accumulated around the MTOC. When F-actin was fragmented, a greater fraction of ER and mitochondria were transported toward the MTOC. When dynein was inhibited, organelles were not transported, neither toward nor away from the MTOC.</p></caption></media><media id="video9" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video9.mp4"><label>Video 9.</label><caption><title>Burst of ER movement at the growing aster periphery in control with F-actin intact.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>) MTs were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER with DiI, and F-actin with Lifeact-GFP. The ER exhibited a burst of movement toward the MTOC at the growing aster periphery, resulting in transient depletion of the ER intensity near the aster periphery.</p></caption></media><p>When F-actin was fragmented with Cytochalasin D, all organelles exhibited inward movement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7G</xref>), which was fastest at the growing periphery of the aster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>). Compared to control, a greater fraction of the ER was transported inwards (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B’</xref>), and average transport speeds were an order of magnitude faster with F-actin fragmented than intact (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>). The ER intensity around MTOCs accumulated to ~6 fold higher than the intensity outside the aster and continued to increase with time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B’</xref>). Due to the burst of movement at the periphery of the growing aster, the intensity of organelles was ~30% lower there than outside the aster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B’</xref>). Compared to control, the texture of the ER was coarser when F-actin was fragmented, both inside and outside asters, and MTs appeared more bundled. Mitochondria and acidic organelles moved inwards and accumulated near the MTOC. These organelles appeared to physically associate with ER in higher magnification images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figs 6B,C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7G</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>), so all organelles may be physically connected in this system. These findings show that the ER, and perhaps all organelles, recruit dynein, and can move toward the MTOC. Inward movement is restrained by F-actin under control conditions. However, even with F-actin fragmented, the majority of the ER, mitochondria, and acidic organelles were still evenly distributed over the aster.</p><p>We next added p150-CC1 to test for a role of dynein in organelle transport. With p150-CC1 present, with or without F-actin, organelles moved neither inwards nor outwards, and did not accumulate at MTOCs. This result is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref> for the p150-CC1 plus Cytochalasin D condition. We conclude that dynein generates the majority of force on organelles, and that other known forces, for example, from kinesins or tip tracking, do not induce significant net transport in our system, although they may drive transient saltatory motion.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Dynein-mediated organelle movement is maximal near the aster periphery</title><p>To infer outward forces on MTs as a function of time and location, we needed a measure of the total inward organelle flux. Kymographs and PIV provide direct visualization of movement but have limitations for this inference, because they measure movement of local gradients in fluorescence intensity, not mass transport. We therefore developed an analysis to measure mass transport of organelles based on flux of fluorescence intensity (analysis described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s2">Figure 7—figure supplement 2</xref> and Materials and methods). This analysis quantifies the amount of fluorescence signal crossing a given circumference at a given time, normalized by the total fluorescence in a region containing the aster. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref> shows examples with ER and acidic organelles. Mitochondria exhibited similar movement as acidic organelles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>All analysis methods revealed a burst of inward organelle movement when the growing aster periphery reached them, followed by slowing down inside asters (<xref ref-type="video" rid="video9">Videos 9</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video11">11</xref>). This burst can be visualized as inward diagonal features in kymographs, and red values on the diagonal corresponding to the growing aster periphery in mass transport and PIV plots. Under control conditions, with F-actin intact, the amount of organelle movement at the aster periphery was variable between extracts. Out of 11 extract preps, we observed a burst of inward ER movement at the aster periphery in seven extracts (64%) as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref>, and observed weaker or no burst in the remaining extracts as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7F</xref>. Factors that seem to lessen the burst of inward movement include higher concentrations of spontaneously nucleated MTs outside the aster, and insufficient passivation of the coverslips. Lack of fast organelle movement in control asters with intact F-actin is consistent with co-movement of cytoplasmic networks in moving asters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>).</p><media id="video10" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video10.mp4"><label>Video 10.</label><caption><title>Burst of ER and acidic organelle movement at the growing aster periphery with F-actin fragmented.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>) Transport of ER and acidic organelles with F-actin fragmented by Cytochalasin D. MTs were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER with DiD, and acidic organelles with LysoTracker Red. Unlike in control with F-actin intact, the burst of movement near the aster periphery was highly reproducible when F-actin was fragmented with Cytochalasin D.</p></caption></media><media id="video11" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video11.mp4"><label>Video 11.</label><caption><title>Burst of ER and mitochondria movement at the growing aster periphery with F-actin fragmented.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>) MTs were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 647, ER with DiD, and mitochondria with TMRE.</p></caption></media><p>When F-actin was fragmented, a burst of organelle transport at the growing aster periphery was observed in all experiments (&gt;10 repeats with different extracts). Inward movement at the periphery was faster than control conditions and therefore easier to visualize and quantify. Velocity values for ER moving inwards at the aster periphery reached ~0.25 µm/s with F-actin fragmented (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7J</xref>), and mass transport reached 2% of total per min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7I</xref>). Mass transport values were more peaked at the aster periphery than PIV values, in part because mass transport takes into account the increase in circumference as the aster radius increases. A smaller fraction of acidic organelles than ER was transported inwards (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7F,I</xref>), but with a similar bias toward more movement at the periphery. Although inward movement was faster with F-actin fragmented, it was still mostly confined to the periphery. More organelles accumulated at the aster center than in control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>), but most organelles were still uniformly spread over the aster and not moving, on average.</p></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>Dynein-coated beads move inwards at constant rates throughout asters</title><p>Slowing of organelle transport upon incorporation into the aster suggested dynein might be inhibited inside asters. To test this, we turned to an artificial system. 2.8 µm diameter beads were functionalized with the antibody against the dynein adapter HOOK2 used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>. Negative control beads were functionalized with random IgG. We then measured transport of the beads on isolated, stationary asters as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>. With F-actin intact, the anti-HOOK2 beads moved inwards at a constant speed of 0.2 ± 0.1 µm/s throughout asters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8A–D</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video12">Video 12</xref>). When F-actin was fragmented with Cytochalasin D, the anti-HOOK2 beads moved at 0.7 ± 0.2 µm/s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8E–H</xref>), threefold faster than with F-actin intact. Thus, artificial dynein-coated beads were slowed by F-actin, like endogenous organelles. However, these beads were transported all the way to the MTOC, unlike organelles which slowed or stopped inside asters.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>Unlike organelles, artificial cargoes functionalized with dynein move at constant speed throughout asters.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Artificial cargoes were functionalized with an antibody against the dynein adapter HOOK2, and negative control beads were functionalized with random antibody (see <xref ref-type="video" rid="video12">Video 12</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) Max intensity projections of beads functionalized with anti-HOOK2 (red) or random antibody (green). (<bold>C</bold>) Trajectories of anti-HOOK2 and negative control beads relative to the MTOC. The growing aster is indicated by the blue region. Anti-HOOK2 beads started to be transported when they were engulfed by the growing aster. (<bold>D</bold>) Velocity distribution of anti-HOOK2 beads inside the aster. (<bold>E–H</bold>) Similar experiment with F-actin fragmented by Cytochalasin D.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig8sdata1"><label>Figure 8—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Bead trajectories for panels C, D, G, and H.</title><p>The ‘beads’ variables are structures that contain the bead trajectories in XY, as well as the distance from the MTOC at the aster center. The ‘TinsideAster’ variables are the time index at which beads first enter the aster, which was used to generate the velocity distributions in panels D and H.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="octet-stream" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig8-data1-v2.mat"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig8-v2.tif"/></fig><media id="video12" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video12.mp4"><label>Video 12.</label><caption><title>Artificial cargoes, Dynabeads functionalized with dynein via anti-HOOK2, were transported at constant speeds throughout asters.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>) MTs were labeled with tubulin-Alexa Fluor 488, anti-HOOK2 beads with Fab fragment-Alexa Fluor 568, and negative control beads were functionalized with random rabbit IgG and labeled with Fab fragment-Alexa Fluor 647.</p></caption></media></sec><sec id="s2-10"><title>Volume exclusion is unlikely to block organelle movement inside asters</title><p>Organelles might slow down inside asters because the environment becomes too crowded with other organelles. To investigate volume exclusion by organelles, we quantified the intensity and flux of fluorescent dextran as a marker for the cytosol. As organelles were transported toward MTOCs, fluorescent dextran was displaced away from MTOCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s3">Figure 7—figure supplement 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="video" rid="video13">Video 13</xref>), consistent with volume conservation. However, the degree of steric exclusion was fairly small, since the dextran signal was only reduced by ~10%, and exclusion was only observed within ~50 µm of MTOCs, where the ER density is maximal. Outside that central region, the intensity of fluorescent dextran was similar inside and outside asters. We conclude that volume exclusion between organelles may be significant in the immediate neighborhood of MTOCs, but is unlikely to account for organelles becoming stationary inside asters.</p><media id="video13" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video13.mp4"><label>Video 13.</label><caption><title>Exclusion of 10 kDa dextran from the organelle-rich region around MTOCs.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s3">Figure 7—figure supplement 3</xref>) 10 kDa dextran labeled with Alexa Fluor 568 was excluded in a ~ 50 µm radius around the MTOC.</p></caption></media></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We tracked multiple cytoplasmic networks in moving asters using two different systems to promote movement, and found that the majority of organelles, F-actin, keratin, and even a small molecule probe moved coherently with astral MTs. Co-movement of cytoplasmic networks is consistent with mechanical integration between networks. MTs, F-actin and organelles mechanically interact via many motor and non-motor proteins, as reported in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lane and Allan, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Waterman-Storer et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Waterman-Storer et al., 1995</xref>) and other systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Dogterom and Koenderink, 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Gurel et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mandato and Bement, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Rodriguez et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Semenova et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Waterman-Storer and Salmon, 1998</xref>). Many such proteins described in other systems are present in the <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg proteome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Wühr et al., 2014</xref>). Furthermore, nonspecific steric and hydrodynamic interactions may contribute to mechanical integration between the entangled cytoplasmic networks. Coherent movement of cytoplasmic networks has been reported in other systems where the entire cytoplasm is driven from the boundary, such as cytoplasmic flows with respect to the cortex in <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Deneke et al., 2019</xref>), or rotation of <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos with respect to the egg shell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Schonegg et al., 2014</xref>). Here, though the aster is self-driven within cytoplasm before interacting with the cortical boundary, inside the aster all components still moved together.</p><p>Co-movement appears contradictory to many studies where organelles exhibit saltatory movement with respect to MTs, including in the egg extract system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lane and Allan, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Wang et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Waterman-Storer et al., 1995</xref>). Most reviews of organelle systems assume they move with respect to MTs at rest. Ironically, the standard length-dependent pulling model of aster movement in eggs assumes the opposite, that MTs move with respect to organelles at rest. Co-movement of organelles with a moving cytoskeleton has been less studied. When we imaged at higher magnification, we too observed saltatory movement of organelles and F-actin with respect to astral MTs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>) and transient deformation of the ER (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>), consistent with previous reports. By imaging at lower magnification, we averaged movement over entire asters and were able to quantify the net fluxes on scales of hundreds of microns and tens of minutes. We believe these net fluxes are most relevant to physical models of aster movement. Co-movement may be especially relevant in large eggs, while relative movement may be more significant in smaller cells. We did observe dynein-mediated inward organelle movement relative to MTs over a distance of ~50 µm at the aster periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>). This distance corresponds to a relatively thin peripheral layer in frog egg asters, but it is larger than the cell radius in sea urchin or <italic>C. elegans</italic> eggs.</p><p>An important question is how well our extract aster movement systems model movement in eggs. After anaphase in <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs, centrosomes move away from the midplane at ~10 µm/min, which is faster than the aster separation movement in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, and slower than the dynein-based movement over the coverslip in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>. Thus, neither of our extract movement systems precisely reconstituted the speed of aster movement in eggs, but they spanned a wide range of relevant velocities. As a preliminary test of co-movement of MTs and organelles in living eggs, we re-analyzed videos of aster growth and separation movement after first mitosis in live zebrafish eggs expressing a fluorescent MT-binding protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Wühr et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="video" rid="video14">Video 14</xref>). Lipid droplets are visible as large dark objects in these videos. These droplets move rapidly and randomly before the aster contacts them, then slowly outwards once they are embedded inside the aster. Using PIV analysis, we observed outward flow of structure in the MT channel at the same speed as the lipid droplets. This analysis suggests large asters in zebrafish eggs may also exhibit co-movement of MTs and organelles as they move apart after first mitosis.</p><media id="video14" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-60047-video14.mp4"><label>Video 14.</label><caption><title>Post-anaphase aster separation movement in a zebrafish embryo consistent with co-movement.</title><p>(Related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>) Video from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Wühr et al., 2010</xref> and analyzed with permission. Microtubules were labeled with microtubule-binding domain of Ensconsin fused to three GFPs (EMTB-3GFP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Faire et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">von Dassow et al., 2009</xref>). Flows of MTs were estimated by PIV (Materials and methods).</p></caption></media><p>Dynein located throughout the cytoplasm is thought to generate the force that moves asters in large egg cells, but the cytoplasmic cargoes to which dynein is anchored has been unclear. Here, we found that all the organelles in the extract can move inwards in a dynein-dependent manner, especially at the aster periphery. Thus, all the organelles may serve as dynein anchors, either by recruiting dynein directly, or by physical contact with the ER (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Guo et al., 2018</xref>). The ER and mitochondria are the most abundant organelles, and the ER moved inwards fastest and to the greatest extent. Thus, ER may be the predominant dynein anchor in frog eggs. The identity of the dynein adapter on egg organelles is unknown. Eggs contain abundant lipid droplets and yolk platelets that are removed during extract preparation and could constitute additional dynein anchors.</p><p>Organelles reproducibly exhibited a burst of inward movement when the growing aster periphery first contacted them, then slowed or halted upon incorporation into the aster, as shown in both mass transport and PIV analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figures 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>). Most organelles inside asters were stationary, which explains why the density of organelles in the bulk of the aster was similar to that outside the aster, as previously observed in egg extracts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hara and Merten, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Wang et al., 2013</xref>). The same is true in intact eggs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B’,C’</xref>). The molecular mechanism that slows dynein-mediated movement of organelles inside asters is unknown. F-actin decreased dynein-based transport of both organelles and dynein-coated beads, so it is partly responsible. Organelle transport, but not bead transport, slowed inside asters even when F-actin was fragmented. We hypothesize that non-dynein interactions between organelles and MTs cause a braking effect. Candidate brakes include opposing motors, tip tracking factors, non-motor ‘brake’ proteins, and nonspecific steric or hydrodynamic interactions. We did not observe significant mass transport away from MTOCs by kinesins or tip tracking when dynein was inhibited, which argues against opposing motors. The predominance of dynein as the organelle motor in <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs is consistent with previous studies using high-magnification DIC imaging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lane and Allan, 1999</xref>). ER transport by kinesin increases as the embryo develops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lane and Allan, 1999</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref> proposes a model for the flows associated with aster separation movement in eggs. At the growing aster periphery, organelles flow inwards rapidly but transiently, while astral MTs both grow and flow outwards. In the aster interior, organelles and MTs flow outwards together. Moving asters advect cytosol, generating hydrodynamic forces that displace cytoplasm around the asters and into the midplane (beige arrows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>). This convective flow supplies components to support aster growth at the midplane boundary. F-actin is not shown, but we believe it slows organelle movement relative to MTs throughout the aster and disassembles at the midplane, generating a spatial asymmetry that helps asters move apart. The new data in this paper report on flows, not forces, so we cannot immediately extrapolate from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref> to a force model. However, the flows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref> are incompatible with the classic length-dependent force model in its simplest form, where the MT component of the aster is conceptualized as a rigid body moving through a viscous cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hamaguchi and Hiramoto, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Palenzuela et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Sallé et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Tanimoto et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tanimoto et al., 2018</xref>). Our observations suggest that in frog eggs, where large asters are built from a network of short MTs entangled with ER and F-actin, the aster is better conceptualized as a deformable gel where the midplane is softer than the aster interior. In this framework, MTOCs could move in response to forces exerted on the surface of the gel, where vesicles move relative to MTs, and perhaps also in response to stresses within it. Inside the aster, organelles appear to interact with MTs using both dynein motors and unidentified brakes. Dynein on organelles anchored to the MT network could generate active stresses that deform the gel. We are not the first to propose that asters behave as a mechanically integrated gel. In early microneedle experiments in echinoderm eggs, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Chambers, 1917</xref> observed that asters behave as a gel and proposed that forces act on their surface. How surface and internal forces and stresses contribute to MTOC movement, and how each scales with aster size and shape, are interesting topics for further research.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><title>Model for component flows during aster separation movement in frog eggs.</title><p>Within moving asters, all cytoplasmic networks move together, advecting cytosol. Near the aster periphery, organelles flow rapidly inwards while MTs flow outwards. Outside the aster, cytosol is displaced around asters and into the midplane by hydrodynamic forces.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-60047-fig9-v2.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Reagent type (species) <break/>or resource</th><th>Designation</th><th>Source or reference</th><th>Identifiers</th><th>Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Strain, strain background <break/>(<italic>Escherichia coli</italic>)</td><td>Rosetta 2(DE3)pLysS <break/>competent cells</td><td>Novagen</td><td>Cat#: 71401</td><td>Competent cells</td></tr><tr><td>Strain, strain background <break/>(<italic>Escherichia coli</italic>)</td><td>BL21(DE3)pLysS <break/>competent cells</td><td>Promega</td><td>Cat#: L1195</td><td>Competent cells</td></tr><tr><td>Biological sample <break/>(<italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> <break/>adult females)</td><td>Eggs</td><td>Harvard Medical <break/>School <italic>Xenopus</italic> Colony</td><td/><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xenbase.org/entry/">http://www.xenbase.org/entry/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>Biological sample <break/>(<italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> <break/>adult females)</td><td>Egg extracts</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Field et al., 2017</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Biological sample <break/>(<italic>Bos taurus</italic>)</td><td>Fluorescently labeled <break/>tubulin from bovine brain</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Desai and Mitchison, 1998</xref>; <break/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Miller and Wilson, 2010</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Biological sample <break/>(<italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> <break/>adult females)</td><td>Fluorescently labeled <break/>tubulin from frog egg extract</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Groen and Mitchison, 2016</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Anti-tubulin, clone B-5-1-2. <break/>(Mouse monoclonal)</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat#: T6074 <break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_477582">AB_477582</ext-link></td><td>IHC (1:2000)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Anti-<italic>Xenopus</italic> LNPK, <break/>raised against cytosolic <break/>fragment of LNPK, aa 99–441. <break/>(Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Wang et al., 2016</xref></td><td/><td>IHC (1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Anti-PDIA3 (Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td>Boster Bio</td><td>Cat#: PB9772</td><td>IHC (1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Anti-<italic>Xenopus</italic> AURKA, raised <break/>against full-length protein <break/>(Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Field et al., 2017</xref>; <break/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Tsai and Zheng, 2005</xref></td><td/><td>IP (3 µL per 50 µL Dynabeads, <break/>to saturate Dynabeads)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Anti-INCENP, C-terminal peptide <break/>immunogen. <break/>CAVWHSPPLSSNRHHLAVGYGLKY <break/>(Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Sampath et al., 2004</xref></td><td/><td>IHC (1:1200)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Anti-cytokeratin pan, clone C-11 <break/>(Mouse monoclonal)</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat#: P2871 <break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_261980">AB_261980</ext-link></td><td>IHC (1:500)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Anti-HOOK2, C-terminal peptide <break/>immunogen. <break/>CSRSHTLLPRYTDKRQSLS <break/>(Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td>This paper</td><td/><td>See Materials and methods, <break/>‘HOOK2 antibody’ and <break/>‘Preparation of dynein <break/>on coverslips’</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>ChromPure rabbit IgG, <break/>whole molecule</td><td>Jackson ImmunoResearch</td><td>Cat#: 011-000-003 <break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2337118">AB_2337118</ext-link></td><td>IP (1 µL per 50 µL Dynabeads, <break/>to saturate Dynabeads)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>Goat anti-rabbit whole serum</td><td>Jackson ImmunoResearch</td><td>Cat#: 111-001-001 <break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2337909">AB_2337909</ext-link></td><td>See Materials and methods, <break/>‘Photo-release of <break/>fluorescein from MTOCs’</td></tr><tr><td>Peptide, recombinant <break/>protein</td><td>Tau MT-binding domain <break/>(mTMBD)-mCherry, <break/><italic>E. coli</italic> expression</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Mooney et al., 2017</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Peptide, recombinant <break/>protein</td><td>EB1-GFP, <italic>E. coli</italic> expression</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Nguyen et al., 2014</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Peptide, recombinant <break/>protein</td><td>Lifeact-GFP, <italic>E. coli</italic> expression</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Moorhouse et al., 2015</xref>; <break/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Riedl et al., 2008</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Peptide, recombinant <break/>protein</td><td>p150-CC1 fragment of <break/>dynactin, <italic>E. coli</italic> expression</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">King et al., 2003</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Peptide, recombinant <break/>protein</td><td>NeutrAvidin</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: 31000</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Peptide, recombinant <break/>protein</td><td>Biotinylated Protein A</td><td>GenScript</td><td>Cat#: M00095</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>2.8 µm Protein A <break/>coated Dynabeads</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: 10002D</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>2.8 µm Protein G <break/>coated Dynabeads</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: 10004D</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>Protein G UltraLink resin</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: 53125</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>Affi-Prep Protein A resin</td><td>Bio-Rad</td><td>Cat#: 1560006</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>HisPur cobalt resin</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: 89965</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay or kit</td><td>Superdex Increase <break/>75 10/300 GL column</td><td>GE Healthcare</td><td>Cat#: 29-1487-21</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Formamide</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat#: F9037</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Benzyl benzoate</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat#: B6630</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Benzyl alcohol</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat#: 402834</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>IGEPAL CA-630</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat#: I8896</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>DiI (1,1'-dioctadecyl-3,3,3',3'- <break/>tetramethylindocarbocyanine <break/>perchlorate, aka DiIC18(3))</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: D282</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>DiD (1,1'-dioctadecyl-3,3,3',3'- <break/>tetramethylindodicarbocyanine <break/>perchlorate, aka DiIC18(5))</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: D307</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Tetramethylrhodamine, <break/>ethyl ester (TMRE)</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: T669</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>LysoTracker Red DND-99</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: L7528</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Cytochalasin D</td><td>Cayman Chemical</td><td>Cat#: 11330</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Poly-L-lysine-g-polyethylene <break/>glycol (PLL-g-PEG)</td><td>SuSoS Chemicals</td><td>Cat#: [PLL(20)-g[3.5]- <break/>PEG(2)]</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Lanolin for VALAP (Vaseline, <break/>lanolin, paraffin 1:1:1 by mass)</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat#: L7387</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Paraffin</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat#: 327204</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Phenylmethylsulfonyl <break/>fluoride (PMSF)</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat#: 78830</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>AlexaFluor-488,–568, <break/>−647 NHS ester</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: A20100, <break/>Cat#: A20003, <break/>Cat#: A20106</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>Caged fluorescein</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Mitchison et al., 1998</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, drug</td><td>1-Ethyl-3-(3-dimethylaminopropyl) <break/>carbodiimide (EDC)</td><td>Thermo Fisher</td><td>Cat#: 22980</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Fiji</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Schindelin et al., 2012</xref></td><td>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/SCR_002285">SCR_002285</ext-link></td><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>PIVlab</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Thielicke and Stamhuis, 2014</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>2D Gaussian fitting in MATLAB</td><td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Nootz, 2020</xref></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Software, algorithm</td><td>Radial mass transport <break/>analysis in MATLAB</td><td>This paper</td><td/><td>See Materials and methods, <break/>‘Analysis of organelle <break/>mass transport’</td></tr><tr><td>Other</td><td>Extended Liner Tape, thickness <break/>25 µm, for flow cells</td><td>3M</td><td>Cat#: 920XL</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>Embryos were fixed and stained as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Field et al., 2019</xref>). Embryos were fixed in 90% methanol, 10% water, 50 mM EGTA pH 6.8 for 24 hr at room temperature with gentle shaking. After fixation, embryos were rehydrated in steps from 75%, 50%, 25%, to 0% methanol in TBS (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl) for 15 min each step with gentle shaking. Rehydrated embryos in TBS were cut in half on an agarose cushion using a small razor blade. Before staining, embryos were bleached overnight in 1% hydrogen peroxide, 5% formamide (Sigma-Aldrich #F9037), 0.5x SSC (75 mM NaCl, 8 mM sodium citrate pH 7). To stain, embryos were incubated with directly labeled antibodies at 0.5–2 µg/mL for at least 24 hr at 4°C with very gentle rotation. Antibodies were diluted in TBSN (10 mM Tris-Cl pH 7.4, 155 mM NaCl, 1% IGEPAL CA-630 (Sigma-Aldrich #I8896), 1% BSA, 2% FCS, 0.1% sodium azide). After antibody incubation, embryos were washed in TBSN for at least 48 hr with several solution changes, then washed once in TBS and twice in methanol, with methanol washes for 40 min each. Embryos were cleared in Murray clear solution (benzyl benzoate (Sigma-Aldrich #B6630)/benzyl alcohol (Sigma-Aldrich #402834) 2:1). Embryos were mounted in metal slides 1.2 mm thick with a hole in the center. The hole was closed by sealing a coverslip to the bottom of the slide using heated Parafilm.</p><p>Endoplasmic reticulum (ER) was labeled with an anti-LNPK antibody (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Wang et al., 2016</xref>) directly labeled with Alexa Fluor 568 NHS ester (Thermo Fisher #A20003). The ER was also probed with labeled anti-Protein disulfide-isomerase A3 (PDIA3) (Boster Bio #PB9772). PDIA3 is an ER lumen protein and had a similar distribution as the anti-LNPK antibody (not shown). MTs were labeled with an anti-tubulin antibody (Sigma-Aldrich #T6074, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_477582">AB_477582</ext-link>) directly labeled with Alexa Fluor 647 NHS ester.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Extract preparations</title><p>Actin-intact, CSF <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract was prepared as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Field et al., 2017</xref>). CSF extracts were stored at 4–10°C and flicked occasionally to disperse membranes. Extracts stored in this way were typically usable for ~8 hr. Before each reaction, extracts were cooled on ice to ensure depolymerization of cytoskeletal networks.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Interphase aster assembly reactions</title><p>In a typical reaction, fluorescent probes were added to CSF extract on ice. To trigger exit from CSF arrest and entry to interphase, calcium chloride was added to 0.4 mM final concentration. To ensure complete progression to interphase, the reaction was mixed well immediately after calcium addition by gently flicking and pipetting. Extracts were pipetted using 200 µL pipette tips manually cut to a wider bore to reduce shear damage, which can make membranes in the extract appear coarser by eye. Reactions were incubated in an 18°C water bath for 5 min then returned to ice for 3 min. Next, drugs or dominant negative constructs were added (see Perturbations below), and in some cases reactions were split for direct comparison between control and perturbed conditions. Last, Dynabeads Protein G (Thermo Fisher #10004D) functionalized with an activating anti-Aurora kinase A (anti-AURKA) antibody were added as artificial microtubule organizing centers (MTOCs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Tsai and Zheng, 2005</xref>). For experiments in which asters moved away from one another, unlabeled anti-INCENP antibody was included at a final concentration of 4 nM to promote zone formation by activating the CPC.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Coverslip passivation</title><p>Eighteen and 22 mm square coverslips were passivated with poly-L-lysine covalently grafted to polyethylene glycol (PLL-g-PEG) (SuSoS #PLL(20)-g3.5-PEG(2)) as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Field et al., 2019</xref>). Coverslips were cleaned by dipping them in 70% ethanol, igniting the ethanol with a gas burner, cooling the coverslips for several seconds, then the coverslips were passivated by placing them on a droplet of 0.1 mg/mL PLL-g-PEG in 10 mM HEPES pH 7.4 on Parafilm. Eighteen mm coverslips were placed on 90 µL droplets, and 22 mm coverslips were placed on 110 µL droplets. After 30 min incubation, excess PLL-g-PEG was rinsed by placing coverslips on droplets of distilled water twice for 5 min each, then drying them with a stream of nitrogen gas. To check the passivation, when we focused near the coverslips, we found no evidence of a surface layer of cytoskeletal filaments or organelles adsorbed to the coverslips. Quite the opposite, the density of cytoplasmic networks was typically lower near the coverslips and higher near the midplane between the coverslips, we suspect due to continuous contraction of actomyosin away from the coverslips sustained by continuous diffusion of monomer toward the coverslips.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Flow cell assembly</title><p>Flow cells were assembled from the passivated coverslips to increase physical stability of the system and reduce global flows. To a metal slide holder, 22 mm square coverslips were sealed via a thin layer of molten VALAP (Vaseline, lanolin (Sigma-Aldrich #L7387), paraffin (Sigma-Aldrich # 327204) 1:1:1 by mass). Then an 18 mm square coverslip was immobilized above the 22 mm coverslip using two pieces of thin double-sided tape (3M Extended Liner Tape #920XL) spaced ~1 cm apart. The tape has a nominal thickness of 25 µm and resulted in flow cells ~20 µm deep after pressing the coverslips together.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Imaging</title><p>Extract reactions were perfused into flow cells, then the edges were sealed with VALAP. In experiments with a single condition, imaging was started immediately. In experiments with multiple conditions imaged in parallel, the slide holder was first chilled on ice for several seconds, so aster growth would start at the same time across conditions. Extracts were imaged on a Nikon Eclipse Ti2-E inverted microscope with Nikon CFI Plan Apo Lambda 20x, NA 0.75 objective lens, SOLA SE V-nIR light engine, and with either a Nikon DS-Qi2 or Andor Zyla 4.2 PLUS sCMOS camera. The microscope room was cooled to less than 20°C, otherwise spontaneously nucleated MTs can overtake reactions. Throughout the paper, time is measured with respect to warming the reaction and the start of aster growth. Depending on the MTOC density, asters typically grew into contact at 8–15 min and formed CPC-positive interaction zones several minutes later.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Fluorescent probes</title><p>MTs were imaged with either bovine or frog tubulin directly labeled with Alexa Fluor 647 at a final concentration of 250 nM, or with a phosphodeficient version of the MT-binding domain of Tau fused to mCherry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Mooney et al., 2017</xref>) at a final concentration of 20 nM. Growing +TIPs of MTs were labeled with EB1-GFP at a final concentration of 110 nM. The chromosomal passenger complex (CPC) was labeled with an anti-INCENP antibody directly labeled with Alexa Fluor 647 at a final concentration of 4 nM. ER was labeled with DiI (1,1'-dioctadecyl-3,3,3',3'-tetramethylindocarbocyanine perchlorate, aka DiIC<sub>18</sub>(3)) (Thermo Fisher #D282) or DiD (1,1'-dioctadecyl-3,3,3',3'-tetramethylindodicarbocyanine perchlorate, aka DiIC<sub>18</sub>(5)) (Thermo Fisher #D307) at a final concentration of 4 µg/mL. Mitochondria were labeled with tetramethylrhodamine, ethyl ester (TMRE) (Thermo Fisher #T669) at a final concentration of 0.3 µg/mL. Acidic organelles were labeled with LysoTracker Red DND-99 (Thermo Fisher #L7528) at a final concentration of 130 nM. To allow these dyes to pre-incorporate into the membranous organelles, especially important for the DiI and DiD, stock solutions were first dissolved in DMSO to a concentration of 2 mg/mL (DiI/DiD), 0.2 mg/mL (TMRE), or 200 µM (LysoTracker Red), then diluted 50 fold into extract. These extract working solutions were incubated in an 18°C water bath for 45 min, flicking every 15 min to disperse membranes. Then the extract working solutions were stored on ice until use, then diluted an additional 10–30 fold into the final reaction. F-actin was imaged with Lifeact-GFP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Moorhouse et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Riedl et al., 2008</xref>) at a final concentration of 300 nM. More details on fluorescent probes are reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Field et al., 2017</xref>. Keratin was imaged with an anti-cytokeratin antibody (Sigma-Aldrich #P2871, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_261980">AB_261980</ext-link>) directly labeled with Alexa Fluor 568 at a final concentration of 3 µg/mL.</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Perturbations</title><p>To fragment F-actin, Cytochalasin D (CytoD) was added to a final concentration of 20 µg/mL. CytoD was diluted in DMSO to 10 mg/mL, then diluted 20-fold into extract. This extract working solution was stored on ice until use, then diluted an additional 25 fold into the final reaction. CytoD and other drugs or dominant negative constructs were typically added to actin-intact extracts after cycling to interphase, then reactions were split for direct comparison between control and perturbed extracts. Alternatively, CytoD may be added during extract preparations before the crushing spin, following the classic CSF extract protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Murray, 1991</xref>). The ER appeared coarser in CytoD extracts than in actin-intact extracts, and the ER appeared to coarsen over time in actin-intact extracts plus CytoD.</p><p>To inhibit dynein, the p150-CC1 fragment of dynactin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">King et al., 2003</xref>), which acts as a dominant negative for dynein function, was added to a final concentration of 40 µg/mL.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>HOOK2 antibody</title><p>An affinity-purified C-terminal peptide antibody was produced in rabbit against <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> HOOK2 (C-SRSHTLLPRYTDKRQSLS) (Cocalico Biologicals, Inc, PA).</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>HOOK2 immunoprecipitation-mass spectrometry (IP-MS)</title><p>Dynabeads Protein G (Thermo Fisher #10004D) (20 µL Dynabeads slurry per reaction) were saturated with rabbit IgG (anti-HOOK2 or random IgG; Jackson ImmunoResearch #011-000-003, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2337118">AB_2337118</ext-link>) by overnight binding, then washed 3x with CSF-XB (100 mM KCl, 2 mM MgCl2, 0.1 mM CaCl2, 10 mM K HEPES pH 7.7, 5 mM EGTA, 50 mM sucrose). Each immunoprecipitation reaction contained 150 µL interphase or CSF-arrested egg extract treated with 10 µg/mL Cytochalasin D to inhibit gelation. Extract plus Dynabeads was rotated gently for 60 min at 4°C, then washed 4x in 50 mM KCl, 1 mM MgCl2, 10 mM K HEPES pH 7.7, 1 mM EGTA at 0°C. The tubes were changed twice during the washes to remove extract protein bound to their walls. Protein bound to the Dynabeads was eluted in 20 µL of 5 M guanidine thiocyanate, 5 mM dithiothreitol (DTT) (US Biological #D8070) for 10 min at 60°C, then cysteines were alkylated with N-ethylmaleimide (NEM). The eluate was precipitated with chloroform-methanol then subjected to proteolysis followed by TMT labeling as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Sonnett et al., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Preparation of dynein on coverslips</title><p>Coverslips were passivated following the protocol above but using biotinylated PLL-g-PEG. NeutrAvidin (Thermo Fisher #31000) and biotinylated Protein A (GenScript #M00095) were mixed in a 1:1 ratio to a final concentration of 10 µM and stored at 4°C. Just before functionalizing the coverslips, the NeutrAvidin and biotinylated Protein A mixture was diluted 42-fold to 240 nM in 1x PBS with 0.0025% Tween 20. That concentration was found to be the smallest amount to decrease the surface tension enough to maintain a layer of solution on the coverslips, to reduce damage to the functionalized surfaces due to air-water interfaces when transferring the coverslips from one droplet to another. Coverslips were incubated with the NeutrAvidin and biotinylated protein A mixture at least 30 min on droplets on Parafilm at room temperature. Coverslips were incubated under a box with a damp paper towel, to block room light and to reduce evaporation. After the incubation, coverslips were rinsed twice on droplets of 1x PBS with 0.0025% Tween 20 for 5 min each, then incubated with anti-HOOK2 or random IgG diluted in 1x PBS with 0.0025% to a final concentration of 10 µg/mL at least 30 min. After the incubation with antibody, coverslips were rinsed twice on droplets of 1x PBS with 0.0025% Tween 20, then twice on droplets of distilled water, then swirled in a beaker of distilled water, then gently dried with a stream of nitrogen gas. Coverslips were often used same day, but could be stored overnight in the dark at 4°C and used the following day. After perfusing extracts into flow cells and sealing the edges with VALAP, the metal slide holders were chilled for 10 min on a metal block on ice, to allow endogenous HOOK2 and dynein-dynactin time to bind the anti-HOOK2 before the start of aster growth.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Photo-release of fluorescein from MTOCs</title><p>Caged fluorescein with -O-CH<sub>2</sub>-COOH functionality on the caging groups was synthesized as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Mitchison et al., 1998</xref>). Carboxylic acid groups were activated as sulfo-NHS esters in a small reaction containing 2 micromols caged fluorescein, 5 micromols sodium sulfo-NHS and 5 micromols 1-ethyl-3-(3-dimethylaminopropyl)carbodiimide (EDC) (Thermo Fisher #22980) in 10 µL of DMSO. After 1 hr at room temperature, this reaction mix was added directly to protein coated beads. Direct modification of anti-AURKA beads caused loss of nucleation activity, so we first biotinylated beads, then modified with caged fluorescein, then attached anti-AURKA IgG using a NeutrAvidin bridge. In particular, Dynabeads Protein A (Thermo Fisher #10002D) were sequentially incubated with goat anti-rabbit whole serum (Jackson ImmunoResearch #111-001-001, RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2337909">AB_2337909</ext-link>) then biotinylated rabbit IgG (homemade). They were labeled with the caged fluorescein reaction mix in 0.1 M K HEPES pH 7.7 for 1 hr, then washed again. We empirically titrated the amount of reaction mix added such that beads were maximally labeled while still retaining nucleation activity in extract. After labeling with caged fluorescein, beads were incubated sequentially with a mixture of NeutrAvidin and biotinylated protein A, then rabbit anti-AURKA to confer nucleation activity. Pure proteins were added at 10–20 µg/mL and serum was added at 1/20. All binding reactions were incubated for 20 min, and washes were in 1x PBS. Fluorescein was released from beads by exposing the microscope field to full illumination in the DAPI channel (395 nm) for 5 s.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Analyses</title><sec id="s4-13-1"><title>PIV</title><p>PIVlab (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Thielicke and Stamhuis, 2014</xref>) was used to estimate flow fields of cytoplasmic networks based on particle image velocimetry (PIV). Though PIV is primarily used to estimate flow fields based on tracer particles embedded in fluids, PIV has been used to estimate cortical or cytoplasmic flows in <italic>C. elegans</italic> cortices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Mayer et al., 2010</xref>), zebrafish epithelia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Behrndt et al., 2012</xref>), and <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Deneke et al., 2019</xref>). Likewise, cytoplasmic networks in the <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts included structures with sufficient contrast for PIV. The cytoplasmic networks exhibited dynamic turnover, so it was important to image with a time interval short enough to retain sufficient correlation between frames for PIV. For example, the time scale for F-actin turnover was ~1 min, based on recovery of F-actin in a region where F-actin had been mechanically cleared, consistent with estimates based on measurements of network density and flow in contractile actomyosin networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Malik-Garbi et al., 2019</xref>). Time intervals less than 20 s worked well for PIV.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13-2"><title>Gaussian fitting of photo-released fluorescein</title><p>2D Gaussian fitting of fluorescein photo-released from MTOCs was performed using a nonlinear least squares solver in MATLAB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Nootz, 2020</xref>). After photo-release the MTOCs were bright due to uncaged fluorescein that remained bound to the MTOCs. Thus the MTOCs were masked as not to bias the Gaussian fits. Positional error associated with Gaussian fitting is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf1"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Condon, 1997</xref>), where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.32</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the pixel size, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf3"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>20</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the standard deviation of the noise, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the peak amplitude. With these values, the positional error is on the order of a pixel, which is significantly smaller than the difference between the bead position and the center of the cloud. We fit expansion of the fluorescein cloud to a model of diffusion, and we assumed a diffusion coefficient of fluorescein in water of 425 µm<sup>2</sup>/s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Culbertson et al., 2002</xref>). Advection of cytosol with cytoplasmic networks is consistent with a poroelastic Péclet number <italic>VLµ</italic>/<italic>Eξ</italic><sup>2</sup> greater than unity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mitchison et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Moeendarbary et al., 2013</xref>). Given the oscillatory speed <italic>V</italic> ~ 1 µm/s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>) and amplitude <italic>L</italic> ~ 30 µm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>), and assuming a viscosity <italic>µ</italic> ~6 x water (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>) and an elastic modulus <italic>E</italic> ~ 10 Pa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Valentine et al., 2005</xref>), we estimate the upper bound on the effective pore size <italic>ξ</italic> of cytoplasmic networks in this system is ~100 nm.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13-3"><title>Analysis of organelle mass transport</title><p>The flux-based analysis of organelle transport is described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s2">Figure 7—figure supplement 2</xref>. In summary, images were background subtracted and flat field corrected, then a region of interest (ROI) was defined large enough to enclose the aster at all time points, so the total amount of ER in the ROI was conserved. Then, the total intensity was normalized across frames to correct for photobleaching. The net flux of organelle fluorescence intensity toward MTOCs was calculated as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s2">Figure 7—figure supplement 2</xref>. In particular, the average intensity was calculated in annular bins with a width of 10 µm, then the cumulative total intensity was calculated from the MTOC to outside the aster, then the net flux was calculated at each radial distance by subtracting subsequent cumulative total intensity profiles.</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by NIH grant R35GM131753 (TJM) and MBL fellowships from the Evans Foundation, MBL Associates, and the Colwin Fund (TJM and CMF). JFP was supported by the Fannie and John Hertz Foundation, the Fakhri lab at MIT, the MIT Department of Physics, and the MIT Center for Bits and Atoms. The authors thank the Nikon Imaging Center at Harvard Medical School and Nikon at MBL for imaging support, and the National <italic>Xenopus</italic> Resource at MBL for support. The authors thank Keisuke Ishihara and Luolan Bai for critical feedback on the manuscript, and thank Martin Wühr, Jay Gatlin, Nikta Fakhri, David Burgess, Fabian Romano-Chernac, Sam Reck-Peterson, and Mark Terasaki for helpful conversations. The authors thank Martin Wühr for the video showing post-anaphase separation movement of asters after first mitosis in zebrafish. The anti-LNPK antibody was a gift from Tom Rapoport (Harvard Medical School and Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Boston, MA). The Tau-mCherry construct was a gift from Jay Gatlin (University of Wyoming, Laramie, WY). The EB1-GFP construct was a gift from Kevin Slep (UNC Chapel Hill, NC). The Lifeact-GFP construct was a gift from David Burgess (Boston College, Newton, MA).</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Writing - original draft</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Investigation, Writing - original draft</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Formal analysis, Writing - review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Resources, Helped with sample preparations and performed mass spectrometry (MS) measurements for Fig 4-figure supplement 1</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Conceptualization, Investigation, Writing - original draft</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Animal experimentation: This study was performed in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. All of the animals were handled according to approved institutional animal care and use committee (IACUC) protocols (#IS00000519-3) of Harvard Medical School. The institution has an approved Animal Welfare Assurance on file with the Office of Laboratory Animal Welfare. The Assurance number on file is #D16-00270.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-60047-transrepform-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files, and related code has been uploaded to GitHub: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jamespelletier/Co-movement">https://github.com/jamespelletier/Co-movement</ext-link> (copy archived at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/swh:1:rev:8144aa215bad15e091e267fc2ba247ddc1c1db2d/">https://archive.softwareheritage.org/swh:1:rev:8144aa215bad15e091e267fc2ba247ddc1c1db2d/</ext-link>).</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basant</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Glotzer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Spatiotemporal regulation of RhoA during cytokinesis</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>R570</fpage><lpage>R580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2018.03.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29738735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behrndt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salbreux</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Campinho</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauschild</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oswald</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Roensch</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grill</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Heisenberg</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Forces driving epithelial spreading in zebrafish gastrulation</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>338</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1224143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23066079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmena</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheelock</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Funabiki</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Earnshaw</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>The chromosomal passenger complex (CPC): from easy rider to the godfather of mitosis</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm3474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23175282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chambers</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1917">1917</year><article-title>Microdissection studies. II. The cell aster: a reversible gelation phenomenon</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Zoology</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jez.1400230302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrell</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Spontaneous emergence of cell-like organization in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>366</volume><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aav7793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31672897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singaravelu</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Théry</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchoin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gueroui</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Actin-network architecture regulates microtubule dynamics</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>2647</fpage><lpage>2656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2018.06.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30100343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Condon</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Errors in elliptical gaussian fits</article-title><source>Publications of the Astronomical Society of the Pacific</source><volume>109</volume><elocation-id>166</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/133871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Culbertson</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael Ramsey</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Diffusion coefficient measurements in microfluidic devices</article-title><source>Talanta</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0039-9140(01)00602-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18968508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Laat</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Luchtel</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bluemink</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1973">1973</year><article-title>The action of cytochalasin B during egg cleavage in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic>: dependence on cell membrane permeability</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0012-1606(73)90327-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4787185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deneke</surname> <given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Puliafito</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Narla</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>De Simone</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Primo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergassola</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Renzis</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Talia</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Self-organized nuclear positioning synchronizes the cell cycle in <italic>Drosophila</italic> Embryos</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>177</volume><fpage>925</fpage><lpage>941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30982601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desai</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Preparation and characterization of caged fluorescein tubulin</article-title><source>Methods in Enzymology</source><volume>298</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0076-6879(98)98014-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9751877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dogterom</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koenderink</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Actin-microtubule crosstalk in cell biology</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-018-0067-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30323238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elinson</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1983">1983</year><article-title>Cytoplasmic phases in the first cell cycle of the activated frog egg</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0012-1606(83)90237-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6606589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faire</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterman-Storer</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruber</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Masson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulinski</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>E-MAP-115 (ensconsin) associates dynamically with microtubules in vivo and is not a physiological modulator of microtubule dynamics</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>4243</fpage><lpage>4255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10564643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wühr</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kueh</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickland</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Actin behavior in bulk cytoplasm is cell cycle regulated in early vertebrate embryos</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>2086</fpage><lpage>2095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.082263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21610091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Groen</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Spindle-to-cortex communication in cleaving, polyspermic <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>3628</fpage><lpage>3640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E15-04-0233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26310438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title><italic>Xenopus</italic> extract approaches to studying microtubule organization and signaling in cytokinesis</article-title><source>Methods in Cell Biology</source><volume>137</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.mcb.2016.04.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28065319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Disassembly of actin and keratin networks by aurora B kinase at the midplane of cleaving <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> eggs</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>1999</fpage><lpage>2008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2019.05.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31178324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lénárt</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Bulk cytoplasmic actin and its functions in meiosis and mitosis</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>R825</fpage><lpage>R830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2011.07.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21996509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garzon-Coral</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fantana</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>A force-generating machinery maintains the spindle at the cell center during mitosis</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>352</volume><fpage>1124</fpage><lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aad9745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27230381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grill</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyman</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Spindle positioning by cortical pulling forces</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2005.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groen</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Purification and fluorescent labeling of tubulin from <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> egg extracts</article-title><source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source><volume>1413</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-3542-0_3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27193841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Milkie</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tulu</surname> <given-names>US</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiehart</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippincott-Schwartz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Betzig</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Visualizing intracellular organelle and cytoskeletal interactions at nanoscale resolution on millisecond timescales</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>175</volume><fpage>1430</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2018.09.057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30454650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurel</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatch</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgs</surname> <given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Connecting the cytoskeleton to the endoplasmic reticulum and golgi</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>R660</fpage><lpage>R672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.05.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25050967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamaguchi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiramoto</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1980">1980</year><article-title>Fertilization process in the heart-urchin, <italic>Clypeaster</italic> japonicus observed with a differential interference microscope</article-title><source>Development, Growth and Differentiation</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-169X.1980.00517.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamaguchi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiramoto</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1986">1986</year><article-title>Analysis of the role of astral rays in pronuclear migration in sand dollar eggs by the colcemid‐uv method</article-title><source>Development, Growth &amp; Differentiation</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-169X.1986.00143.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hara</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Merten</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Dynein-based accumulation of membranes regulates nuclear expansion in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> Egg Extracts</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2015.04.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26004509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishihara</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Groen</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Microtubule nucleation remote from centrosomes may explain how asters span large cells</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>17715</fpage><lpage>17722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1418796111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25468969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishihara</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Korolev</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Physical basis of large microtubule aster growth</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e19145</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27892852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Intracellular organelles mediate cytoplasmic pulling force for centrosome centration in the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> early embryo</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1013275108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21173218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname> <given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintyne</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroer</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Analysis of the dynein-dynactin interaction in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>5089</fpage><lpage>5097</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.e03-01-0025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14565986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kotak</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gönczy</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Mechanisms of spindle positioning: cortical force generators in the limelight</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Cell Biology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2013.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23958212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Allan</surname> <given-names>VJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Microtubule-based endoplasmic reticulum motility in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic>: activation of membrane-associated kinesin during development</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1909</fpage><lpage>1922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.10.6.1909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10359605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luby-Phelps</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><chapter-title>Cytoarchitecture and physical properties of cytoplasm: volume, viscosity, diffusion, intracellular surface area</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jeon</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>International Review of Cytology</source><volume>192</volume><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0074-7696(08)60527-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malik-Garbi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ierushalmi</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu-Shah</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goode</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogilner</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Keren</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Scaling behaviour in steady-state contracting actomyosin networks</article-title><source>Nature Physics</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41567-018-0413-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31754369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandato</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bement</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Actomyosin transports microtubules and microtubules control actomyosin recruitment during <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocyte wound healing</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1096</fpage><lpage>1105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(03)00420-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12842008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Depken</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bois</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jülicher</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grill</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Anisotropies in cortical tension reveal the physical basis of polarizing cortical flows</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>467</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20852613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meaders</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Microtubule-based mechanisms of pronuclear positioning</article-title><source>Cells</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>505</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cells9020505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32102180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Preparation of microtubule protein and purified tubulin from bovine brain by cycles of assembly and disassembly and phosphocellulose chromatography</article-title><source>Methods in Cell Biology</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0091-679X(10)95001-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20466126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawin</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Theriot</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gee</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallavarapu</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Caged fluorescent probes</article-title><source>Methods in Enzymology</source><volume>291</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0076-6879(98)91007-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9661145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Charras</surname> <given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahadevan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Implications of a poroelastic cytoplasm for the dynamics of animal cell shape</article-title><source>Seminars in Cell &amp; Developmental Biology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2008.01.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18395478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moeendarbary</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Valon</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritzsche</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulding</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thrasher</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stride</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahadevan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Charras</surname> <given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The cytoplasm of living cells behaves as a poroelastic material</article-title><source>Nature Materials</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmat3517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23291707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mooney</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulerud</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dilsaver</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomschik</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Geisler</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatlin</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Tau-based fluorescent protein fusions to visualize microtubules</article-title><source>Cytoskeleton</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cm.21368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28407416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moorhouse</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gudejko</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>McDougall</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Influence of cell polarity on early development of the sea urchin embryo</article-title><source>Developmental Dynamics</source><volume>244</volume><fpage>1469</fpage><lpage>1484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.24337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26293695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname> <given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Cell cycle extracts</article-title><source>Methods in Cell Biology</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0091-679X(08)60298-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1839804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nazockdast</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimian</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Needleman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shelley</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Cytoplasmic flows as signatures for the mechanics of mitotic positioning</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>3261</fpage><lpage>3270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.e16-02-0108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28331070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Groen</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Loose</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihara</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wühr</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Spatial organization of cytokinesis signaling reconstituted in a cell-free system</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>346</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1256773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25301629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nootz</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Fit 2D gaussian function to data</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/37087-fit-2d-gaussian-function-to-data">https://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/37087-fit-2d-gaussian-function-to-data</ext-link><date-in-citation iso-8601-date="2020-06-12">June 12, 2020</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palenzuela</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacroix</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sallé</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Minami</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jegou</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Romet-Lemonne</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Minc</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>In vitro reconstitution of dynein force exertion in a bulk viscous medium</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>4534</fpage><lpage>4540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2020.08.078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32946749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reck-Peterson</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Redwine</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>The cytoplasmic dynein transport machinery and its many cargoes</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-018-0004-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29662141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Redwine</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>DeSantis</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollyer</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Htet</surname> <given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname> <given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Florens</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Washburn</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reck-Peterson</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>The human cytoplasmic dynein interactome reveals novel activators of motility</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e28257</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.28257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28718761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riedl</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crevenna</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessenbrock</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Neukirchen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bista</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradke</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenne</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Holak</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Werb</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sixt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedlich-Soldner</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Lifeact: a versatile marker to visualize F-actin</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18536722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname> <given-names>OC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaefer</surname> <given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandato</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Forscher</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bement</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterman-Storer</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Conserved microtubule-actin interactions in cell movement and morphogenesis</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb0703-599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12833063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sallé</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ershov</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacassin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dmitrieff</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Minc</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Asymmetric division through a reduction of microtubule centering forces</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>218</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201807102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30563876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sampath</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohi</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leismann</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Salic</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozniakovski</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Funabiki</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>The chromosomal passenger complex is required for chromatin-induced microtubule stabilization and spindle assembly</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2004.06.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15260989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schindelin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arganda-Carreras</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Frise</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaynig</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Longair</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietzsch</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Preibisch</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rueden</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saalfeld</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinevez</surname> <given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartenstein</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliceiri</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomancak</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardona</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Fiji: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schonegg</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyman</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Timing and mechanism of the initial cue establishing handed left–right asymmetry in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> embryos</article-title><source>Genesis</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>572</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvg.22749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25077289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semenova</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Burakov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berardone</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaliapin</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Slepchenko</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Svitkina</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashina</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodionov</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Actin dynamics is essential for myosin-based transport of membrane organelles</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1581</fpage><lpage>1586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2008.08.070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18951026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonnett</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeung</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wühr</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Accurate, sensitive, and precise multiplexed proteomics using the complement reporter ion cluster</article-title><source>Analytical Chemistry</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>5032</fpage><lpage>5039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.7b04713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29522331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanimoto</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minc</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Shape-motion relationships of centering microtubule asters</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>212</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201510064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27022090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanimoto</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sallé</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Minc</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Physical forces determining the persistency and centering precision of microtubule asters</article-title><source>Nature Physics</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>848</fpage><lpage>854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41567-018-0154-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30079097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Telley</surname> <given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gáspár</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ephrussi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Surrey</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Aster migration determines the length scale of nuclear separation in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> syncytial embryo</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>197</volume><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201204019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22711698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terasaki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Organization of the sea urchin egg endoplasmic reticulum and its reorganization at fertilization</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>114</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.114.5.929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1874789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thielicke</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamhuis</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>PIVlab – Towards User-friendly, Affordable and Accurate Digital Particle Image Velocimetry in MATLAB</article-title><source>Journal of Open Research Software</source><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>1</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/jors.bl</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname> <given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Aurora A kinase-coated beads function as microtubule-organizing centers and enhance RanGTP-induced spindle assembly</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>2156</fpage><lpage>2163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2005.10.054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16332542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valentine</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlman</surname> <given-names>ZE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weitz</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Mechanical properties of <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg cytoplasmic extracts</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.104.048025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Dassow</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbrugghe</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sider</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bement</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Action at a distance during cytokinesis</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>187</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200907090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20008563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Multiple mechanisms determine ER network morphology during the cell cycle inn <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>203</volume><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201308001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tukachinsky</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Cooperation of the ER-shaping proteins atlastin, Lunapark, and reticulons to generate a tubular membrane network</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e18605</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.18605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27619977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterman-Storer</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregory</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Membrane/microtubule tip attachment complexes (TACs) allow the assembly dynamics of plus ends to push and pull membranes into tubulovesicular networks in interphase <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>130</volume><fpage>1161</fpage><lpage>1169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.130.5.1161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7657700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterman-Storer</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Duey</surname> <given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Keech</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheney</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Bement</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Microtubules remodel actomyosin networks in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts via two mechanisms of F-actin transport</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><volume>150</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.150.2.361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10908578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterman-Storer</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Endoplasmic reticulum membrane tubules are distributed by microtubules in living cells using three distinct mechanisms</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>798</fpage><lpage>807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(98)70321-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9663388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wühr</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Detrich</surname> <given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>A model for cleavage plane determination in early amphibian and fish embryos</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>2040</fpage><lpage>2045</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2010.10.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21055946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wühr</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Presler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Horb</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Peshkin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschner</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Deep proteomics of the <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> egg using an mRNA-derived reference database</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1467</fpage><lpage>1475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.05.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24954049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Minc</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Cytoskeleton force exertion in bulk cytoplasm</article-title><source>Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>69</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcell.2020.00069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32117991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sowa</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>An FTS/Hook/p107(FHIP) complex interacts with and promotes endosomal clustering by the homotypic vacuolar protein sorting complex</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>5059</fpage><lpage>5071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.e08-05-0473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18799622</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.60047.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Surrey</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Centre for Genomic Regulation (CRG)</institution><country>Spain</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Di Talia</surname><given-names>Stefano</given-names> </name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>Duke University</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife publishes the most substantive revision requests and the accompanying author responses.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Acceptance summary:</bold></p><p>This study reports elegant quantitative measurements demonstrating that in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg cytoplasm filament and organelle networks are to a large extent mechanically integrated. This observation is important with respect to proposed models of the mechanism responsible for moving microtubule asters apart after anaphase of mitosis in large embryonic cells.</p><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Co-movement of astral microtubules, organelles and F-actin suggests aster positioning by surface forces in frog eggs&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Vivek Malhotra as the Senior Editor. The following individual involved in review of your submission has agreed to reveal their identity: Stefano Di Talia (Reviewer #1).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>As the editors have judged that your manuscript is of interest, but as described below that additional experiments are required before it is published, we would like to draw your attention to changes in our revision policy that we have made in response to COVID-19 (https://elifesciences.org/articles/57162). First, because many researchers have temporarily lost or reduced access to the labs, we will give authors as much time as they need to submit revised manuscripts. We are also offering, if you choose, to post the manuscript to bioRxiv (if it is not already there) along with this decision letter and a formal designation that the manuscript is &quot;in revision at <italic>eLife</italic>&quot;. Please let us know if you would like to pursue this option. (If your work is more suitable for medRxiv, you will need to post the preprint yourself, as the mechanisms for us to do so are still in development.)</p><p>Summary:</p><p>This study aims to understand the driving forces responsible for microtubule aster movement in <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs. A prominent model for aster movement in large cells, where microtubules do not contact the cell cortex, is that dynein-attached organelle movement generates a net drag-force that moves the aster in the opposite direction. Here the authors test this model by imaging the dynamics of aster separation in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract. They show for the first time that asters, actin filaments, ER and bulk cytoplasm move together in the same direction, contrary to what a prevalent model predicts. Conversely, they find subtle but significant organelle movement at the &quot;surface of the aster&quot; where microtubules grow and penetrate the cytoplasm. Therefore, they propose a modified model which posits that vesicle movements exclusively in the aster periphery, instead of everywhere within the aster, drive aster movement in extract. While all reviewers agreed that this manuscript presents new and very interesting observations that argue against the &quot;length-dependent pulling model&quot; in egg extract, most reviewers concluded that a coherent biophysical picture explaining the observed aster movements is still missing. Specifically, it remains unclear if the source of the forces is related to the vesicle movement at the periphery of the asters.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) The authors need to provide a clearer biophysical picture supporting their model of the origin of the forces for aster movements being dynein-dependent vesicle movements at the periphery of the asters. An attempt should be made to provide a more quantitative model to support the authors' claim more conclusively. For example, what does the model of the authors predict for the speed of aster movement as asters grow? Does one expect an increase of the speed of aster movement as a consequence of the aster surface increasing with time? Is the prediction of the model in agreement with the experimental data? How is this different from a model in which the force is generated throughout the aster? Does one expect different scaling for different types of models with different force generation mechanisms that could help to discriminate between models?</p><p>2) &quot;We observed no outward movement of organelles when dynein was inhibited with CC1, so dynein is the dominant microtubule motor in egg asters.&quot; – but interestingly, in Video 13 one can see considerable back-and-forth movement of particles in the DIC channel, suggesting a tug-of-war of dynein and kinesins or myosins; when f-actin is fragmented, myosins cannot act as breaks, thus providing an explanation for faster organelle movement. It seems that the bead (artificial cargo) experiment supports the idea of tug-of-war, as beads only recruit dynein, and they move steadily toward the MTOC, while organelles may recruit different motors and after passing the aster surface, entering into a tug-of-war situation. Is it therefore justified to conclude that dynein is the dominant organelle motor? There should also be a better distinction, at least in the Discussion, between drag forces caused by network mesh density (e.g. f-actin) and effective viscosity due to transient interactions of dynein-opposing motors acting as breaks. The bead experiment seems to suggest that there is no difference in network-based viscosity between the aster surface and the interior, since the bead velocity is roughly constant.</p><p>3) The authors quantify aster movement in egg extract in clusters containing many asters, with obvious interaction between the different asters. This complicates the interpretation of the data since there are multiple external forces on each aster pair measured which have a strong influence that is ignored. Can the authors exclude that aster growth and aster pushing originating in the CPC-rich overlapping regions causes/contributes to aster movement. In this scenario dynein could simply contribute to holding all networks together that move together and other plus directed microtubule motors might be responsible for pushing asters apart. Vesicle movement at the aster periphery would then be a &quot;consequence&quot; and not the &quot;cause&quot; for aster movement in a region where the various networks might not be as crosslinked/as dense yet as in the more central regions of the aster. Laser cutting experiments could test this &quot;pushing hypothesis&quot;. Laser cutting experiments (without and with dynein inhibition) could also test the existence of dynein-dependent stresses inside the aster that the authors predict to exist. This could support an important element of the authors' model. Analyzing the movements of asters with different numbers of neighboring asters in more or less &quot;aster-dense&quot; regions of the extract might be an alternative approach to test the alternative hypothesis of pushing forces playing a critical role in the movements of interconnected asters. Without such additional evidence, the current model of the authors remains rather speculative and some of the claims are not fully supported by the data.</p><p>4) How are the different boundary conditions in &quot;closed&quot; egg cells and &quot;open&quot; egg extract expected to affect the observed dynamics? Given the incompressibility of cytosol, how are aster movements and particularly cytosolic flows expected to differ between extract and egg cell? A more explicit discussion of how the results obtained from extract apply to the situation in a cell with a boundary will be useful.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.60047.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>1) The authors need to provide a clearer biophysical picture supporting their model of the origin of the forces for aster movements being dynein-dependent vesicle movements at the periphery of the asters. An attempt should be made to provide a more quantitative model to support the authors' claim more conclusively. For example, what does the model of the authors predict for the speed of aster movement as asters grow? Does one expect an increase of the speed of aster movement as a consequence of the aster surface increasing with time? Is the prediction of the model in agreement with the experimental data? How is this different from a model in which the force is generated throughout the aster? Does one expect different scaling for different types of models with different force generation mechanisms that could help to discriminate between models?</p></disp-quote><p>In the previous submission we proposed that asters are positioned by surface forces and even put that conclusion in the title. We agree with the reviewers that our data do not prove this point. As summarized above, in the revised manuscript we emphasize flows, which we measured, and de-emphasize forces, which we only inferred. This major change in response to review was implemented throughout the paper, starting with the title. In the Discussion, we still discuss the hypothesis that pulling forces are exerted primarily on the aster periphery, but now using language that clearly represents it as one possible interpretation of the data. We are currently developing formal mechanical models for aster movement, in which forces and stresses on astral MTs cause the aster to move as well as deform, using hydrodynamic theories of active gels. These models require multiple figures to describe and are not yet fully developed. We feel they go beyond the scope of the current paper.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) &quot;We observed no outward movement of organelles when dynein was inhibited with CC1, so dynein is the dominant microtubule motor in egg asters.&quot; – but interestingly, in Video 13 one can see considerable back-and-forth movement of particles in the DIC channel, suggesting a tug-of-war of dynein and kinesins or myosins; when f-actin is fragmented, myosins cannot act as breaks, thus providing an explanation for faster organelle movement. It seems that the bead (artificial cargo) experiment supports the idea of tug-of-war, as beads only recruit dynein, and they move steadily toward the MTOC, while organelles may recruit different motors and after passing the aster surface, entering into a tug-of-war situation. Is it therefore justified to conclude that dynein is the dominant organelle motor? There should also be a better distinction, at least in the Discussion, between drag forces caused by network mesh density (e.g. f-actin) and effective viscosity due to transient interactions of dynein-opposing motors acting as breaks. The bead experiment seems to suggest that there is no difference in network-based viscosity between the aster surface and the interior, since the bead velocity is roughly constant.</p></disp-quote><p>This comment reflects multiple questions about ER transport in our system, including details of movement noted by reviewers on which we had not commented, and differences between what we report and previous papers that reported outward movement of ER by kinesin and tip tracking. To address these questions, we added new data (Figure 3—figure supplement 1), additional analysis of existing data (new panels in Figure 1—figure supplement 1), and new paragraphs in the Results and Discussion.</p><p>We suspected that our inability to detect outward movement of the ER in asters was due to our reliance on low magnification imaging (typically 20x objective), which tends to average movement over space and time. The new data and analysis report on image sequences collected with a 60x spinning disk confocal microscope, which reveals details of ER movement at short length and time scales that are averaged out in 20x videos. Revised Figure 1—figure supplement 1 and new Figure 3—figure supplement 1 reveal rapid, bidirectional movement and deformation of ER that may suggest tug-of-war between motors, and that we term “saltatory movement” in line with literature. To visualize saltatory movement of ER with respect to astral MTs, we developed a new radial kymograph analysis, performed in a rotating reference frame that drifts with the average ER flow estimated by PIV (Figure 1—figure supplement 1B). To show tangential co-movement of MTs, ER, and F-actin, we performed a new tangential kymograph analysis (Figure 1—figure supplement 1C). We also repeated PIV analysis for higher magnification videos, in which all networks tracked together as in 20x videos (Figure 3—figure supplement 1C). To relate examples of saltatory movement at smaller scales to net organelle transport at larger scales, we consider our mass transport analysis to be particularly important (Figure 7, Figure 7—figure supplement 1, Figure 7—figure supplement 2). Papers on organelle movement in egg extract focus on subsets of organelles that move, and they largely ignore stationary populations. Our new mass transport analysis quantitatively accounts for both moving and stationary organelles. Comparing between high and low spatiotemporal resolution, we were able to determine that rapid, saltatory motion was common but did not cause significant mass transport away from the MTOC. At larger scales, the ER either moves inwards or is stationary, even when dynein is inhibited.</p><p>Regarding dynein dominance in our system, our conclusion was based on predominantly inward transport at 20x and cessation of organelle transport when dynein was inhibited. We stand by our conclusion after adding the new high magnification analysis. Our observation that dynein dominates organelle transport in our system is consistent with previous reports, particularly a nice 1999 paper from Lane et al. In that study, Lane and Allen concluded dynein is the dominant ER motor in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts prepared from unfertilized eggs and that kinesin is inactive at least until the fifth interphase following fertilization. We added to the Discussion:</p><p>“We did not observe significant mass transport away from MTOCs by kinesins or tip tracking when dynein was inhibited, which argues against opposing motors. The predominance of dynein as the organelle motor in <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs is consistent with previous studies using high magnification DIC imaging (Lane et al., 1999).”</p><p>Regarding possible changes in viscosity within the aster, we agree that the constant velocity of dynein-coated beads may suggest constant effective viscosity that is ~3.5x higher when F-actin is present. The role of MT and F-actin network turnover in permitting bead transport remains unclear. To interpret the cessation of organelle transport in the aster interior, we favor models where non-motor “brake” proteins engage organelles, rather than changes in viscosity. We modified the Discussion to more clearly reflect this hypothesis. Several candidate ER brake proteins are known, and we plan to test them in the future. That said, we cannot rule out the possibility that the more convoluted shape of the ER makes it more sensitive than beads to steric or hydrodynamic drag from astral MTs.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) The authors quantify aster movement in egg extract in clusters containing many asters, with obvious interaction between the different asters. This complicates the interpretation of the data since there are multiple external forces on each aster pair measured which have a strong influence that is ignored. Can the authors exclude that aster growth and aster pushing originating in the CPC-rich overlapping regions causes/contributes to aster movement. In this scenario dynein could simply contribute to holding all networks together that move together and other plus directed microtubule motors might be responsible for pushing asters apart. Vesicle movement at the aster periphery would then be a &quot;consequence&quot; and not the &quot;cause&quot; for aster movement in a region where the various networks might not be as crosslinked/as dense yet as in the more central regions of the aster. Laser cutting experiments could test this &quot;pushing hypothesis&quot;. Laser cutting experiments (without and with dynein inhibition) could also test the existence of dynein-dependent stresses inside the aster that the authors predict to exist. This could support an important element of the authors' model. Analyzing the movements of asters with different numbers of neighboring asters in more or less &quot;aster-dense&quot; regions of the extract might be an alternative approach to test the alternative hypothesis of pushing forces playing a critical role in the movements of interconnected asters. Without such additional evidence, the current model of the authors remains rather speculative and some of the claims are not fully supported by the data.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank and agree with the reviewers. Our evidence for pulling vs. pushing is based entirely on molecular inhibition in the case of asters moving apart on passivated surfaces, and on the location of dynein in the case of asters gliding on dynein-coated surfaces. In particular, simultaneously inhibiting dynein with CC1 and fragmenting F-actin with Cytochalasin D caused an almost complete block to aster movement in both systems. Laser cutting and magnetic tweezers are good suggestions but we lack the equipment to do this in house and also note that the manuscript is already long.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) How are the different boundary conditions in &quot;closed&quot; egg cells and &quot;open&quot; egg extract expected to affect the observed dynamics? Given the incompressibility of cytosol, how are aster movements and particularly cytosolic flows expected to differ between extract and egg cell? A more explicit discussion of how the results obtained from extract apply to the situation in a cell with a boundary will be useful.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank and agree with the reviewers. In response, we have added new experimental data and analyses in new Figure 5—figure supplement 2. Even in egg extracts with open boundary conditions, vesicles visible in DIC exhibited saddle-shaped flow fields with respect to separating asters: the separating asters advected these vesicles perpendicular to the midzone and away from the midpoint between the asters, while vesicles along the midzone flowed toward the midpoint between the asters. This latter flow could be consistent with incompressibility of cytosol. We added a new paragraph to the Results:</p><p>“If separating asters on passivated coverslips also advect cytosol we would expect them to generate hydrodynamic forces and compensatory flows outside the asters. […] We indeed observed inward flow along the interaction zone (Figure 5—figure supplement 2).”, and we echoed in the Discussion where we describe Figure 9. Similar compensatory flows are described in the legend of Video 2 as well.</p><p>In eggs with closed boundary conditions, we hypothesize similar saddle-shaped flow fields, displaced around separating asters and into the midzone between them. In revising the cartoon model at the end of the manuscript we explicitly draw in these hypothetical flows with the goals of spurring new experiments in systems where the egg is transparent.</p><p>This reviewer comment highlights a related question, how do cytoplasmic networks move relative to one another after astral MTs fill the cell? This situation is especially relevant in smaller cells, but also relevant to later stages of aster separation in larger cells. While co-movement likely breaks down at least somewhere after astral MTs fill the cell, the view developed here of asters as a deformable and porous gel may still provide a helpful framework. When astral MTs fill the cell, the detailed viscous, elastic, and poroelastic properties of asters may all be relevant, and continued experiments and modeling are needed.</p></body></sub-article></article>