<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.2" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">70858</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.70858</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Proximal and distal spinal neurons innervating multiple synergist and antagonist motor pools</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-241109"><name><surname>Ronzano</surname><given-names>Remi</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4927-9474</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">†</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-241110"><name><surname>Lancelin</surname><given-names>Camille</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">†</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-241111"><name><surname>Bhumbra</surname><given-names>Gardave Singh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-241112"><name><surname>Brownstone</surname><given-names>Robert M</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5135-2725</contrib-id><email>r.brownstone@ucl.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-33433"><name><surname>Beato</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7283-8318</contrib-id><email>m.beato@ucl.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Neuromuscular Diseases, University College London</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">London</named-content></addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Neuroscience Physiology and Pharmacology, University College London</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">London</named-content></addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Neuroscience, Physiology and Pharmacology, University College London</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">London</named-content></addr-line><country>United Kingdom</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Thoby-Brisson</surname><given-names>Muriel</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>CNRS Université de Bordeaux</institution><country>France</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>Ronald L</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>Emory University</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="equal-contrib1"><label>†</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>02</day><month>11</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e70858</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2021-05-31"><day>31</day><month>05</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2021-11-01"><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event><event-desc>This manuscript was published as a preprint at .</event-desc><date date-type="preprint" iso-8601-date="2021-06-03"><day>03</day><month>06</month><year>2021</year></date><self-uri content-type="preprint" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446906"/></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021, Ronzano et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ronzano et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-70858-v2.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="figures-pdf" xlink:href="elife-70858-figures-v2.pdf"/><abstract><p>Motoneurons (MNs) control muscle contractions, and their recruitment by premotor circuits is tuned to produce accurate motor behaviours. To understand how these circuits coordinate movement across and between joints, it is necessary to understand whether spinal neurons pre-synaptic to motor pools have divergent projections to more than one MN population. Here, we used modified rabies virus tracing in mice to investigate premotor interneurons projecting to synergist flexor or extensor MNs, as well as those projecting to antagonist pairs of muscles controlling the ankle joint. We show that similar proportions of premotor neurons diverge to synergist and antagonist motor pools. Divergent premotor neurons were seen throughout the spinal cord, with decreasing numbers but increasing proportion with distance from the hindlimb enlargement. In the cervical cord, divergent long descending propriospinal neurons were found in contralateral lamina VIII, had large somata, were neither glycinergic, nor cholinergic, and projected to both lumbar and cervical MNs. We conclude that distributed spinal premotor neurons coordinate activity across multiple motor pools and that there are spinal neurons mediating co-contraction of antagonist muscles.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><title>eLife digest</title><p>We are able to walk, run and move our bodies in other ways thanks to circuits of neurons in the spinal cord that control how and when our muscles contract and relax. Neurons known as premotor neurons receive information from other parts of the central nervous system and control the activities of groups (known as pools) of motor neurons that directly activate individual muscles.</p><p>To bend a joint or move our limbs, the movement of different muscles needs to be coordinated. Previous studies have focused on how premotor neurons activate a pool of motor neurons to contract a single muscle, but it remains unclear if and how some of these premotor neurons can co-activate different pools of motor neurons to control more than one muscle at the same time. Here, Ronzano, Lancelin et al. injected mice with modified rabies viruses labelled with different fluorescent markers to build a map of the premotor neurons that connect to motor neurons controlling the leg muscles.</p><p>The experiments revealed that many of the individual premotor neurons in the spinal cords of mice connected to different pools of motor neurons. In the upper region of the spinal cord – which is primarily responsible for controlling the front legs – some large premotor neurons activated motor neurons in this region as well as other motor neurons in a lower region of the spinal cord that controls the back legs. This suggests that these large premotor neurons may be important for coordinating muscles contraction within and between limbs.</p><p>Many neurological diseases are associated with difficulties in contracting or relaxing muscles. For example, individuals with a condition called dystonia experience disorganized and excessive muscle contractions that prevent them from being able to bend and straighten their joints properly. By helping us to understand how the body coordinates the activities of multiple limbs at the same time, the findings of Ronzano, Lancelin et al. may lead to new lines of research that ultimately improve the quality of life of patients with dystonia and other similar neurological diseases.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>spinal cord</kwd><kwd>trans-synaptic tracing</kwd><kwd>rabies</kwd><kwd>premotor interneurons</kwd><kwd>motoneurons</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Mouse</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000275</institution-id><institution>Leverhulme Trust</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>RPG-2013-176</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Beato</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000268</institution-id><institution>Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>BB/L001454</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Beato</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100004440</institution-id><institution>Wellcome Trust</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>110193</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Brownstone</surname><given-names>Robert M</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund4"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100013790</institution-id><institution>Brain Research UK</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Brownstone</surname><given-names>Robert M</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Populations of spinal cord neurons innervate motoneurons controlling local and distant synergist and antagonist muscles.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The spinal cord is ultimately responsible for organizing movement by controlling the activation pattern of motoneurons (MNs), which in turn produce appropriate patterns of muscle contractions to produce limb movement. Across any single limb joint, there are fundamentally three types of control – or three ‘syllables of movement’ – possible. The three basic syllables are: (1) changing a joint angle, (2) stiffening a joint, and (3) relaxing a joint. The concatenation of these syllables across joints within and between limbs ultimately produces behaviour (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Brownstone, 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Wiltschko et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>To change a joint angle, MNs innervating synergist muscle fibres are activated whilst those that innervate antagonist muscle fibres are inhibited. This ‘reciprocal inhibition’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Eccles, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Eccles et al., 1956</xref>) is mediated locally by spinal interneurons (INs) throughout the spinal cord; this syllable has been fairly well characterized, with responsible neurons identified and classified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Alvarez et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Benito-Gonzalez and Alvarez, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sapir et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>The other two syllables are less well studied, but it is clear that behavioural joint stiffening requires co-activation of MNs innervating antagonist muscle groups, while joint relaxation would require co-inhibition of these MNs. Co-contraction has largely been thought to result from brain activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Humphrey and Reed, 1983</xref>), whereas circuits mediating co-inhibition remain elusive. Since the spinal cord controls movement not only across single joints but throughout the body, it is natural to consider whether it contains the circuits necessary to produce these different syllables.</p><p>To identify whether these syllables are produced by spinal circuits, several questions can be asked: Does the spinal cord contain circuits that lead to co-activation or co-inhibition of different pools of MNs – either synergists or antagonists? Does each motor pool have its own dedicated population of premotor INs, and are these INs interconnected in such a way that they can produce contraction of different muscle groups? Or are there populations of INs that project to multiple motor pools in order to effect contraction (or relaxation) of multiple muscles? Indeed, INs that have activity in keeping with innervation of multiple synergists, leading to motor ‘primitives’ or synergies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bizzi and Cheung, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Giszter, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hart and Giszter, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Takei et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Tresch and Jarc, 2009</xref>) have been identified, but knowledge of their locations and identities remains scant.</p><p>Normal behaviours in quadrupeds as well as bipeds require coordination of syllables across joints between forelimbs and hindlimbs. This coordination relies on populations of propriospinal neurons projecting in either direction between the lumbar and cervical enlargements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Eidelberg et al., 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Giovanelli Barilari and Kuypers, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Miller and van der Meché, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ruder et al., 2016</xref>). Long descending propriospinal neurons (LDPNs) were first proposed in cats and dogs more than a century ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Sherrington and Laslett, 1903</xref>), and their existence has been confirmed in several other species including humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Alstermark et al., 1987a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Alstermark et al., 1987b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ballion et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Brockett et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Flynn et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Giovanelli Barilari and Kuypers, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jankowska et al., 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Mitchell et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Nathan et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Ni et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Reed et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ruder et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Skinner et al., 1979</xref>). While LDPNs that establish disynaptic connections to lumbar MNs have been identified, it was initially suggested that at least some cervical LDPNs could establish monosynaptic inputs to lumbar MNs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jankowska et al., 1974</xref>). This connectivity was later confirmed using monosynaptic modified rabies virus (RabV) tracing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Ni et al., 2014</xref>). More recently, descending and ascending spinal neurons and their involvement in the control of stability and interlimb coordination have been characterized, but these studies did not directly focus on monosynaptic premotor circuits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Pocratsky et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ruder et al., 2016</xref>). It is likely that LDPNs function to ensure coordination between forelimbs and hindlimbs, and they could be an important source of premotor input to MNs, providing a substrate for coordination between distant joints.</p><p>In the present study, we examine circuits underlying co-activation and co-inhibition in the spinal cord by assessing premotor neurons through the use of RabV tracing techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ronzano et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Ugolini, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Wickersham et al., 2007</xref>). We used glycoprotein (G)-deleted RabV (ΔG-Rab), and supplied G to MNs through crossing ChAT-Cre mice with RΦGT mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ronzano et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Takatoh et al., 2013</xref>). We injected ΔG-RabV tagged with two different fluorescent proteins into hindlimb muscle pairs of ChAT-Cre mice to retrogradely trace premotor circuits throughout the spinal cord. At the lumbar level, this method revealed apparent low rates of INs projecting to both MN pools targeted. As the distance from targeted MN pool to premotor INs increased, the density of infected premotor INs decreased. But the apparent rate of divergence to multiple pools was higher in thoracic and cervical regions than in the lumbar spinal cord. Interestingly, the extent of divergence throughout the spinal cord was similar whether injections were performed in flexor or extensor pairs, or in synergist or antagonist pairs of muscles. In addition, a population of premotor LDPNs was identified in the cervical spinal cord. These neurons had a high rate of divergence and large somata, projected contralaterally, were neither glycinergic nor cholinergic, located in lamina VIII, and projected to cervical MNs as well as lumbar MNs. Together, these data show that the spinal cord contains premotor INs that project to multiple motor pools (including antagonists), and could thus form substrates for the fundamental syllables of movement.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Lumbar premotor INs reveal similar divergence patterns to synergist and antagonist motor pools</title><p>Given evidence that INs are involved in motor synergies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hart and Giszter, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Levine et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Takei et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Takei and Seki, 2010</xref>), we would expect that there would be INs in the lumbar spinal cord that project to synergist motor pools. We thus first investigated whether such premotor INs could be infected with two RabVs expressing two different fluorescent proteins injected in pairs of muscles. We injected ΔG-Rab expressing eGFP or mCherry into synergist ankle extensors (lateral gastrocnemius [LG] and medial gastrocnemius [MG]) or synergist ankle flexors (tibialis anterior [TA] and peroneus longus [PL]) in ChAT-Cre;RΦGT P1-P3 mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ronzano et al., 2021</xref>). These mice selectively express rabies G in cholinergic neurons (including MNs), providing the necessary glycoprotein for retrograde trans-synaptic transfer from infected MNs to premotor INs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). After 9 days, we visualized the distribution of premotor INs that expressed one or both fluorescent proteins, specifying the premotor INs that make synaptic contact with two motor pools as ‘divergent’ premotor INs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A, B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A, B</xref>). We found divergent premotor INs distributed across the lumbar spinal cord (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s4">Figure 1—figure supplement 4A, B</xref>) bilaterally in the ventral quadrants and ipsilaterally in the dorsal quadrant of the spinal cord (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C, D</xref>), consistently across experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s5">Figure 1—figure supplement 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Across the lumbar spinal cord, we quantified infected MNs and found that 380 MNs were labelled from synergist injections (<italic>n</italic> = 4, two extensor and two flexor pairs). Notably, five MNs were double labelled, most likely due to secondary infection of synaptically connected MNs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bhumbra and Beato, 2018</xref>). We then quantified premotor INs on one of every three sections and found that 4.0% ± 0.3% (276/7043, <italic>n</italic> = 4, two extensor and two flexor pairs, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1C, D</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2C, D</xref>) of labelled premotor INs were double labelled, confirming that INs can be infected by more than one RabV. We would expect this to be an underestimate of the number of INs that have divergent projections since RabV is not expected to label 100 % of presynaptic neurons and as there is a reduced efficiency of double infections compared to single infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Ohara et al., 2009</xref>; see Discussion).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Organization of divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the lumbar spinal cord.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental strategy to describe divergent premotor INs that project to two motor pools of synergist (injection in tibialis anterior [TA] and peroneus longus [PL] or lateral gastrocnemius [LG] and medial gastrocnemius [MG]) or antagonist (TA and LG) pair of muscles. (<bold>Bi</bold>) Representative example of a lumbar transverse section following an injection in the TA (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) and LG (ΔG-Rab-eGFP), showing ChAT (grey blue), GFP (Green Fluorescent Protein, green), and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. Filled arrowheads show divergent premotor INs and contour arrowheads show infected motoneurons (MNs). The dashed line drawn outlines the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) eGFP, (<bold>iii</bold>) mCherry, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. More representative examples of lumbar sections following injections in LG and MG, TA and PL, and LG and TA are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplements 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">3</xref>, respectively. Distribution of the lumbar divergent premotor INs following injections in (<bold>C</bold>) LG and MG (<italic>n</italic> = 2), (<bold>D</bold>) PL and TA (<italic>n</italic> = 2), and (<bold>E</bold>) LG and TA (<italic>n</italic> = 3). (<bold>F</bold>) Asymmetric violin plots showing the medio-lateral and dorso-ventral distributions of divergent premotor INs. The halves correspond, respectively, to the dorsal (top) and ventral (bottom) distributions and to the ipsilateral (right) and contralateral (left) distributions of divergent premotor INs in the lumbar cord. Violin areas were normalized on the number of divergent INs. (<bold>G</bold>) Distribution of the premotor INs within each quadrant of the lumbar cord, with pie sizes proportional to the percentage of premotor INs in each quadrant of the lumbar cord. Numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm). Scale bars: (Bi) 200 µm; (Biv) 10 µm. Raw number of eGFP, mCherry, and double-labelled premotor neurons per samples per muscle pair injected, is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplements 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">3</xref>.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1sdata1"><label>Figure 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C-G</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig1-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the lumbar spinal cord following injections in synergists lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and medial gastrocnemius (MG).</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Representative examples of lumbar transverse sections following injections in the LG (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and MG (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) showing GFP (green) and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. Filled arrowheads show divergent premotor INs and contour arrowheads show infected motoneurons (MNs). The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C, D</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the distributions of lumbar infected premotor INs in the two samples injected in LG and MG. Scale bars: (Ai, Bi) 200 µm; (Aiv, Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig1-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the lumbar spinal cord following injections in synergists peroneus longus (PL) and tibialis anterior (TA).</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Representative examples of lumbar transverse sections following injections in the PL (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and TA (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) showing GFP (green) and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. Filled arrowheads show divergent premotor INs. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C, D</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the distributions of lumbar infected premotor INs in the two samples injected in PL and TA. Scale bars: (Ai, Bi) 200 µm; (Aiv, Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig1-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the lumbar spinal cord following injections in antagonists lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and tibialis anterior (TA).</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Representative examples of lumbar transverse sections following injections in the LG (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and TA (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) showing GFP (green) and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. Filled arrowheads show divergent premotor INs and contour arrowheads show infected motoneurons (MNs). The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C–E</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the distributions of lumbar infected premotor INs in the three samples injected in LG and TA. Scale bars: (Ai, Bi) 200 µm; (Aiv, Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig1-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Rostro-caudal distributions of divergent lumbar premotor interneurons (INs).</title><p>Rostro-caudal distributions of divergent premtor INs along the sagittal and coronal axis of the lumbar cord following injections in (<bold>A</bold>) lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and medial gastrocnemius (MG) (<italic>n</italic> = 2), (<bold>B</bold>) peroneus longus (PL) and tibialis anterior (TA) (<italic>n</italic> = 2), and (<bold>C</bold>) LG and TA (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig1s4sdata1"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s4">Figure 1—figure supplement 4A-C</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig1-figsupp4-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig1-figsupp4-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s5" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 5.</label><caption><title>Medio-lateral and dorso-ventral distributions of divergent premotor neurons across individual experiments.</title><p>Boxplo showing the medio-lateral and the dorso-ventral distributions of divergent premotor neurons in the (<bold>A</bold>) lumbar, (<bold>B</bold>) thoracic, and (<bold>C</bold>) cervical regions across individual experiments. The distributions are consistent across experiment and pairs of muscles injected. Numbers along the axis indicate the sample codes and distances (in µm).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig1-figsupp5-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig1s6" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 6.</label><caption><title>Excitatory boutons from infected premotor neurons and apposed to motoneurons (MNs) reveal divergence through different segments and regions of the spinal cord.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic showing experimental design to visualize projections of excitatory boutons to MNs. Representative images of transverse sections in the (<bold>B</bold>) thoracic region and (<bold>D</bold>) L1 (upper lumbar) segment, following an injection of ΔG-Rab-mCherry in the tibialis anterior (TA), showing ChAT (blue grey) and mCherry (pink). MNs with vGluT2+ (yellow); mCherry+ boutons in apposition are highlighted in the dashed boxes. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter. (<bold>C, E</bold>) Dashed boxes from B and D at higher magnification. Dashed boxes (enlarged in panels ii, iii, and iv) indicate a ChAT−, vGluT2+, mCherry+ bouton and arrowheads (enlarged in v, vi, and vii) show ChAT−, vGluT2−, mCherry+ boutons in apposition to (<bold>C</bold>) L1 and (<bold>E</bold>) thoracic MNs. Scale bars: (<bold>B, D</bold>) 100 µm; (Ci, Ei) 10 µm; (Civ–vii, Eiv–vii) 0.5 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig1-figsupp6-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>We next sought to determine whether this divergence was restricted to synergist motor pools or whether there are also premotor INs that diverge to antagonist pools and could thus be involved in co-contraction or joint stiffening. Following injections into flexor (TA) and extensor (LG) muscles, 260 MNs were labelled (<italic>n</italic> = 3 antagonist pairs), one of them being double labelled (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Following these injections, we also found divergent INs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3A, B</xref>). We found a similar rate of divergence to antagonist pools as to synergist muscles, with 4.7% ± 0.5 % (206/4341, <italic>n</italic> = 3 antagonist pairs, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3C–E</xref>) double labelled. The mapping of all divergent INs in every section revealed that, whether injections were in synergist (<italic>n</italic> = 4, two extensor and two flexor synergist pairs) or antagonist (<italic>n</italic> = 3 pairs) pairs of muscles, double-labelled premotor INs were distributed similarly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F, G</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s4">Figure 1—figure supplement 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s5">Figure 1—figure supplement 5A</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref> for summary of individual experiments). The proportion of divergent cells was calculated from the ratio of double and single infected cells in 1/3 sections, in order to avoid double counting cells present in consecutive sections (see Methods). Equal proportions of divergent premotor INs were found in the ventral ipsilateral quadrant synergists: 74/1913 (3.9%) vs antagonists: (46/1046 [4.4%]), ventral contralateral quadrant (46/1020 [3.8%] vs 21/502 [4.2%]), and dorsal ipsilateral quadrant (153/3874 [3.9%] vs 134/2651 [5.1%]). There were few labelled neurons in the dorsal contralateral quadrant following either synergist or antagonist injections and a similarly low proportion were double labelled (in 1/3 sections: 3/236 [1.3%] and 5/142 [3.5%], respectively). Divergence in premotor circuits is thus common, with at least 1/25 (see Discussion) premotor INs diverging to two MN pools, whether synergists or antagonists.</p><p>Since motor synergies can span across more than a single joint, it is possible that divergent premotor INs could project to motor pools other than those injected. Indeed, following injection of ΔG-Rab-mCherry into the TA muscle, we could visualize mCherry-positive excitatory (vGluT2+) boutons in apposition to L1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s6">Figure 1—figure supplement 6A, D–E</xref>), as well as to thoracic (as rostral as at least T10) MNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s6">Figure 1—figure supplement 6B, C</xref>), that is, three to seven segments rostral to the infected motor pool. mCherry-positive excitatory boutons on MNs were consistently observed in all upper lumbar and thoracic sections taken from three injected mice (three to four sections in each region). This observation, in agreement with a previous study that described premotor INs coordinating the activity of multiple lumbar motor groups from L2 to L5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Levine et al., 2014</xref>), supports the possibility that thoraco-lumbar premotor circuits comprise a substrate for multi-joint synergies.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Thoracic premotor neurons project to multiple lumbar motor pools</title><p>In order to maintain posture and stability, trunk muscles are coordinated with hindlimb movements. Neurons in the thoracic cord that are premotor to lumbar MNs have previously been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Ni et al., 2014</xref>); we thus next examined the projections of thoracic premotor neurons to lumbar motor pools. These premotor neurons were found with decreasing density from T11 through T3 whether the injections were in extensor (LG and MG; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A, B</xref>) or flexor (TA and PL, Figure 2A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2A-B</xref>) pairs of muscles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4A, B</xref>). The distributions of single labelled as well as divergent premotor neurons were similar whether injections were performed in flexor, extensor, or antagonist pairs of muscles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B–H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4A–C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s5">Figure 1—figure supplement 5B</xref>). Divergence rates calculated from the whole thoracic spinal cords were similar between synergist and antagonist injections with 16.2% ± 5.7% (77/497, <italic>n</italic> = 4, 2 extensor and two flexor pairs, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B, C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1C, D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2C, D</xref>) and 9.0% ± 0.7% (59/401, <italic>n</italic> = 3 antagonist pairs, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3C, E</xref>), respectively. In all animals (7/7), the overall proportion of double-labelled neurons in the thoracic spinal cord was higher than in the lumbar cord (13.1% ± 5.6%, Figure 7B).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Organization of divergent premotor neurons in the thoracic segments.</title><p>(<bold>Ai</bold>) Representative example of a thoracic transverse section following an injection in the peroneus longus (PL) (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and tibialis anterior (TA) (ΔG-Rab-mCherry), showing ChAT (grey blue), GFP (green), and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor neuron is highlighted in the dashed box. The dashed line drawn outlines the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor neuron that has been infected by both ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) eGFP, (<bold>iii</bold>) mCherry, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. More representative examples of thoracic sections following injections in lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and medial gastrocnemius (MG), TA and PL, and LG and TA are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplements 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">3</xref>, respectively. Distribution of the thoracic premotor neurons infected following injections in (<bold>B</bold>) LG and MG (<italic>n</italic> = 2), (<bold>C</bold>) PL and TA (<italic>n</italic> = 2), and (<bold>D</bold>) LG and TA (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Divergent premotor neurons infected from both injections are labelled in black. The violin plots show the dorso-ventral and medio-lateral distributions of divergent (black), GFP-positive (green), and mCherry-positive (pink) premotor neurons along the medio-lateral and dorso-ventral axis. Each violin area is normalized to 1. (<bold>E</bold>) Pies showing the distribution of infected premotor neurons in each quadrant; the size of the pies is proportional to the number of infected neurons. (<bold>F</bold>) Plot showing the divergence rate in each quadrant of the thoracic cord. DI: dorsal ipsilateral; VC: ventral contralateral; VI: ventral ipsilateral. (<bold>G</bold>) Overlap of distributions of divergent thoracic premotor neurons followings each pair of muscles injected. (<bold>H</bold>) Asymmetric violin plots showing the medio-lateral and dorso-ventral distributions of divergent premotor neurons. The halves correspond, respectively, to the dorsal (top) and ventral (bottom) distributions and to the ipsilateral (right) and contralateral (left) distributions of divergent premotor neurons in the thoracic cord. Violin areas were normalized on the number of divergent neurons. When not specified numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm). Scale bars: (Ai) 100 µm; (Aiv) 10 µm. Raw number of eGFP, mCherry, and double-labelled premotor neurons per samples per muscle pair injected, is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplements 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">3</xref>.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata1"><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B–G</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig2-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the thoracic spinal cord following injections in synergists lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and medial gastrocnemius (MG).</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Representative examples of thoracic transverse sections following injections in the LG (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and MG (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) showing GFP (green) and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. The filled arrowhead shows an additional divergent premotor IN. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C, D</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the distributions of thoracic infected premotor INs in the two samples injected in LG and MG. Scale bars: (Ai, Bi) 100 µm; (Aiv, Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig2-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the thoracic spinal cord following injections in synergists peroneus longus (PL) and tibialis anterior (TA).</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Representative examples of thoracic transverse sections following injections in the PL (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and TA (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) showing GFP (green) and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. The filled arrowhead shows an additional divergent premotor IN. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C, D</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the distributions of thoracic infected premotor INs in the two samples injected in PL and TA. Scale bars: (Ai, Bi) 100 µm; (Aiv, Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig2-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the thoracic spinal cord following injections in antagonists lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and tibialis anterior (TA).</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Representative examples of thoracic transverse sections following injections in the LG (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and TA (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) showing GFP (green) and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. The filled arrowhead shows an additional divergent premotor IN. The dashed lines drawn ouline the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C–E</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the distributions of thoracic infected premotor INs in the three samples injected in LG and TA. Scale bars: (Ai, Bi) 100 µm; (Aiv, Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig2-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig2s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Rostro-caudal distributions of divergent thoracic premotor neurons.</title><p>Rostro-caudal distributions of divergent premotor interneurons (INs) shown in the coronal (top) and sagittal (bottom) axes of the thoracic cord following injections in (<bold>A</bold>) lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and medial gastrocnemius (MG) (<italic>n</italic> = 2), (<bold>B</bold>) peroneus longus (PL) and tibialis anterior (TA) (<italic>n</italic> = 2), and (<bold>C</bold>) LG and TA (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2s4sdata1"><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s4">Figure 2—figure supplement 4A–C</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig2-figsupp4-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig2-figsupp4-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><p>In all animals (7/7), most divergent premotor neurons in the thoracic cord were located in the ipsilateral dorsal quadrant (46/77, <italic>n</italic> = 4 synergist and 42/59, <italic>n</italic> = 3 antagonist pairs, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E–H</xref>), and within this quadrant 22.1% ± 8.6% (46/188 synergists and 42/211 antagonists, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E, F</xref>) of premotor neurons were double labelled. The divergence rates in the two ventral quadrants were lower: in the ventral cord, double-labelled neurons were observed in 5/7 animals (3/4 synergist; 2/3 antagonist in both quadrants) ipsilaterally (6.7% ± 4.8%; 10/118 synergist and 5/70 antagonist pairs), as well as contralaterally (11.1% ± 10.7%; 21/167 synergist and 12/104 antagonist pairs) to the injection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E, F</xref>). Thus, there are premotor neurons throughout the thoracic cord that project directly to more than one motor pool, including antagonist pairs, in the lumbar spinal cord, with most of these located in the ipsilateral dorsal quadrant.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Cervical premotor long propriospinal descending neurons diverge and share a typical location and morphology</title><p>Cervical long descending propriospinal neurons (LDPNs) have been shown to modulate interlimb coordination to provide stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Eidelberg et al., 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Miller and van der Meché, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Pocratsky et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ruder et al., 2016</xref>). Given that cervical premotor LDPNs projecting to TA MNs have previously been demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Ni et al., 2014</xref>), we asked whether these neurons could be premotor to hindlimb and/or hindlimb–forelimbs MN pairs.</p><p>We found that premotor LDPNs projecting to flexor (TA and PL) and extensor (LG and MG) MNs were localized throughout the rostro-caudal extent of the ventral cervical cord with an enrichment between C6 and T1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4</xref>). Of 92 premotor LDPNs, 88 were localized in the ventral quadrants, 68 of which were in contralateral lamina VIII (<italic>n</italic> = 7, four synergist and three antagonist pairs, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A–F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4</xref>). A substantial proportion of premotor LDPNs was double labelled, with the proportion and location of double labelling similar across experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s5">Figure 1—figure supplement 5C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>) whether injections were into synergist or antagonist pairs (42.4% ± 22.1 % per animal, total of 19/55 neurons, <italic>n</italic> = 4 synergist pairs and 47.9% ± 7.1 % per animal, total of 19/37 neurons, <italic>n</italic> = 3 antagonist pairs, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E, F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3</xref>). This apparent divergence rate of LDPNs in the cervical cord was higher than in the lumbar and thoracic cords in all animals (7/7, Figure 7B). These divergent premotor LDPNs exhibited a stereotypical morphology with an unusually large soma (774 ± 231 µm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 38 premotor LDPNs) compared to the double-labelled premotor neurons in the thoracic and lumbar cords (respectively, 359 ± 144 and 320 ± 114 µm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 135 premotor neurons [thoracic], <italic>n</italic> = 61 premotor INs [lumbar], p &lt; 0.0001 Kruskal–Wallis test, p &lt; 0.0001 [lumbar vs cervical], and p &lt; 0.0001 [thoracic vs cervical], Dunn’s multiple comparisons test). On average, the cross-sectional area of divergent cervical LDPNs was comparable to that of cervical MNs (661 ± 86 µm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 17 MNs, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3H</xref>). Their location and size suggest that these divergent, commissural cervical premotor LDPNs may constitute a somewhat homogenous population.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Organization of divergent premotor long descending propriospinal neurons (LDPNs) in the cervical spinal cord.</title><p>(<bold>Ai</bold>) Representative example of an upper cervical transverse section following an injection in the lateral gastrocnemius (LG) (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and tibialis anterior (TA) (ΔG-Rab-mCherry), showing ChAT (grey blue), GFP (green), and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor LDPN is highlighted in the dashed box. The dashed line drawn outlines the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of the divergent premotor LDPN, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) eGFP, (<bold>iii</bold>) mCherry, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. More representative examples of cervical sections following injections in LG and medial gastrocnemius (MG), TA and peroneus longus (PL), and LG and TA are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplements 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">3</xref>, respectively. (<bold>B–D</bold>) Distribution of the cervical premotor LDPNs following injections in (<bold>C</bold>) LG and MG (<italic>n</italic> = 2), (<bold>D</bold>) PL and TA (<italic>n</italic> = 2), and (<bold>E</bold>) LG and TA (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Divergent premotor LDPNs infected from both injections are labelled in black. The violin plots show the dorso-ventral and medio-lateral distributions of divergent (black), GFP-positive (green), and mCherry-positive (pink) premotor LDPNs along the medio-lateral and dorso-ventral axis. Each violin area is normalized to 1. (<bold>E</bold>) Overlap of the distribution of cervical divergent premotor LDPNs followings each pair of muscles injected. (<bold>F</bold>) Asymmetric violin plots showing the medio-lateral and dorso-ventral distributions of premotor divergent LDPNs. The halves correspond, respectively, to the dorsal (top) and ventral (bottom) distributions and to the ipsilateral (right) and contralateral (left) distributions of divergent premotor LDPNs in the cervical cord. Violin areas were normalized on the number of divergent neurons. (<bold>G</bold>) Pies showing the distribution of infected premotor LDPNs in each quadrant; the size of the pies is proportional to the number of infected premotor LDPNs in each quadrant. (<bold>H</bold>) Plot showing the distribution of the sectional areas of divergent premotor neurons in each region of the spinal cord. The dashed line (labelled cervical motoneuron [MN]) corresponds to the mean sectional area of cervical MNs (<italic>n</italic> = 17 MNs). When not specified numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm). Scale bars: (Ai) 200 µm; (Aiv) 20 µm. Raw number of eGFP, mCherry, and double-labelled premotor neurons per samples per muscle pair injected, are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplements 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">3</xref>.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3sdata1"><label>Figure 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B–H</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig3-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig3-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the cervical spinal cord following injections in synergists lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and medial gastrocnemius (MG).</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Representative examples of cervical transverse sections following injections in the LG (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and MG (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) showing GFP (green) and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C, D</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the distributions of cervical infected premotor INs in the two samples injected in LG and MG. Scale bars: (Ai, Bi) 200 µm; (Aiv, Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig3-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the cervical spinal cord following injections in synergists peroneus longus (PL) and tibialis anterior (TA).</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Representative examples of cervical transverse sections following injections in the PL (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and TA (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) showing GFP (green) and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C, D</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the distributions of cervical infected premotor INs in the two samples injected in PL and TA. Scale bars: (Ai, Bi) 200 µm; (Aiv, Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig3-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Divergent premotor interneurons (INs) in the cervical spinal cord following injections in antagonists lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and tibialis anterior (TA).</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Representative examples of cervical transverse sections following injections in the LG (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and TA (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) showing GFP (green) and mCherry (pink). A divergent premotor IN is highlighted in the dashed box. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of a divergent premotor IN that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-eGFP and ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C–E</bold>) Venn diagrams showing the distributions of cervical infected premotor INs in the three samples injected in LG and TA. Scale bars: (Ai, Bi) 200 µm; (Aiv, Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig3-figsupp3-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig3s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Rostro-caudal distributions of divergent cervical premotor neurons.</title><p>Rostro-caudal distributions of divergent premotor interneurons (INs) along the coronal (top) and sagittal (bottom) coronal axes of the cervical cord following injections in (<bold>A</bold>) lateral gastrocnemius (LG) and medial gastrocnemius (MG) (<italic>n</italic> = 2), (<bold>B</bold>) peroneus longus (PL) and tibialis anterior (TA) (<italic>n</italic> = 2), and (<bold>C</bold>) LG and TA (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig3s4sdata1"><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4A–C</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig3-figsupp4-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig3-figsupp4-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Cervical premotor LDPNs are neither glycinergic nor cholinergic</title><p>To determine the neurotransmitter phenotype of the premotor LDPNs, we used single ΔG-Rab-mCherry injections in ChAT-Cre;RΦGT mice crossed with mice expressing eGFP under the control of the promoter for the neuronal glycine transporter GlyT2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Zeilhofer et al., 2005</xref>). GlyT2 is expressed in the vast majority of spinal inhibitory INs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Todd et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Todd and Sullivan, 1990</xref>), making GlyT2-eGFP mice a suitable tool to determine whether premotor LDPNs are inhibitory. Given that at least 40 % of the labelled INs in the cervical region are divergent (see above), many of the neurons labelled following even single RabV injections would be expected to be divergent. Following injection into LG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>), we found that only 1/21 infected cervical commissural premotor LDPNs was eGFP positive (<italic>n</italic> = 3 LG injections, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B, C and F</xref>). Since none of the labelled neurons expressed ChAT, the majority of cervical premotor LDPNs are likely to be glutamatergic by exclusion. However, in agreement with previous results from TA injections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Ni et al., 2014</xref>), single-labelled thoracic premotor neurons comprised a mixed population of inhibitory and non-inhibitory neurons (34.4% ± 5.9%, 96/273, mCherry+ eGFP + premotor neurons, <italic>n</italic> = 3 LG injections, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D–F</xref>). We cannot determine whether the thoracic or lumbar GFP+ or GFP− premotor INs are divergent, as these data were obtained following single injections. However, in the lumbar cord, as expected, we observed that some divergent INs were cholinergic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Non-glycinergic, non-cholinergic cervical premotor long descending propriospinal neurons (LDPNs), and mixed populations of inhibitory and non-inhibitory thoracic premotor neurons revealed by injections in GlyT2-eGFP; RΦGT mice.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental strategy to determine whether thoracic and cervical premotor neurons are inhibitory. (<bold>B, D</bold>) Representative example of (Bi) a cervical and (Di) a thoracic transverse section following an injection in the lateral gastrocnemius (LG) (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) using GlyT2-eGFP; RΦGT mice, showing ChAT (blue), GFP (green), and mCherry (pink). The dashed boxes highlight the infected premotor LDPNs. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter contours. Higher magnification of the dashed box areas, highlighting (<bold>Bii–iv</bold>) a GFP−, mCherry+ cervical premotor LDPN on the contralateral lamina VIII and (<bold>Dii–iv</bold>) a GFP+, mCherry+ thoracic premotor neuron in ipsilateral intermediate lamina. Distribution of the (<bold>C</bold>) cervical and (<bold>E</bold>) thoracic premotor neurons infected, following injections in the LG of GlyT2-eGFP; RΦGT mice (<italic>n</italic> = 3). The violin plots show the dorso-ventral and medio-lateral distributions of GFP+, mCherry+ (black) and GFP−, mCherry+ (pink) premotor neurons along the medio-lateral and dorso-ventral axis. Each violin area is normalized to 1. (<bold>F</bold>) Proportions of inhibitory premotor neurons in the thoracic and the cervical region of GlyT2-eGFP; RΦGT mice following injections in the LG (<italic>n</italic> = 3). When not specified numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm). Scale bars: (Bi) 200 µm; (Di) 100 µm; (Biv, Div) 10 µm.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata1"><label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C, E,F</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig4-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig4-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Lumbar V0c interneurons (INs) innervate multiple motor pools.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative example of one of the few divergent V0c INs observed in the lumbar cord following injections in muscle pairs. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter. The higher magnifications show (ii) mCherry, (iii) eGFP, (iv) ChAT, and (v) the overlay. Scale bars: (Ai) 200 µm; (Av) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig4-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>A subset of cervical premotor LDPNs arise from the V0 or dI2 domain</title><p>We next sought to determine the genetic provenance of divergent cervical LDPNs. Among the classes of ventral INs defined by the early expression of transcription factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Lee and Pfaff, 2001</xref>), the V0 and V3 cardinal classes are known to project to contralateral MNs. These classes can be further subdivided, with all V3 subclasses being glutamatergic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Zhang et al., 2008</xref>), and V0 INs being neuromodulatory V0<sub>C</sub>, cholinergic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Miles et al., 2007</xref>), inhibitory V0<sub>D</sub>, dorsal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Talpalar et al., 2013</xref>), or excitatory V0<sub>V</sub>, ventral (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Talpalar et al., 2013</xref>), or V0<sub>G</sub>, medial glutamatergic neurons that project to dorsal and intermediate lamina but not to MNs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Zagoraiou et al., 2009</xref>). Since previous studies showed that none of the LDPNs with soma in the cervical cord belong to the V3 population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Flynn et al., 2017</xref>), we sought to determine whether these LDPNs were of the V0 class.</p><p>V0 INs are defined by their embryonic expression of the transcription factor Dbx1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Pierani et al., 2001</xref>) and Evx1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Moran-Rivard et al., 2001</xref>). However, neither of these two transcription factors can reliably be detected at the postnatal ages of our mice. On the other hand, Lhx1 is expressed throughout the V0 and V1 populations (as well as dI2, dI4, and dIL<sub>A</sub> populations) and may be detectable at this early postnatal stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Skarlatou et al., 2020</xref>). However, V1 and V0<sub>D</sub> INs are glycinergic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Alvarez et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Talpalar et al., 2013</xref>), V0<sub>C</sub> are cholinergic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Miles et al., 2007</xref>). Since we have shown that LDPNs are negative for GlyT2 and ChAT and dI4 and dIL<sub>A</sub> INs are dorsal neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Glasgow et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Pillai et al., 2007</xref>) expression of Lhx1 would point to cervical LDPNs belonging to either the V0<sub>V</sub> or dI2 class. In fact, it has very recently been shown that dorsally derived excitatory dI2 INs migrate to this region in the chick spinal cord and have divergent axons along the length of the cord and to the cerebellum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Haimson et al., 2021</xref>). While these neurons are not premotor in the chick (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Haimson et al., 2021</xref>), it is possible that they are in the mouse.</p><p>Following injection of gastrocnemius (GS, <italic>n</italic> = 4, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>), we detected 33 premotor LDPNs. Of these infected cervical premotor LDPNs, 8 (~24%) were clearly Lhx1 positive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B, C</xref>). Given that there is a decrease of Lhx1 expression along the course of postnatal development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>), it is possible that the proportion of premotor LDPNs that were positive for Lhx1 was underestimated. Nevertheless, although we cannot conclude that the identified LDPNs arise from a homogenous population, it is likely that at least a portion of them arise from V0<sub>v</sub> neurons and/or dI2 neurons.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>A subpopulation of cervical premotor long descending propriospinal neurons (LDPNs) expresses Lhx1.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental strategy to determine whether cervical premotor LDPNs express Lhx1. (<bold>Bi</bold>) Representative example of a transverse section from the cervical cord following an injection of ΔG-Rab-eGFP in the gastrocnemius (GS) muscles, showing a cervical premotor LDPN infected (pink) expressing Lhx1 (grey). The premotor LDPN expressing Lhx1 is highlighted in the dashed box. The dashed line drawn outlines the grey matter contour. Higher magnification of the premotor LDPN Lhx1+ that has been infected by the ΔG-Rab-mCherry, showing (ii) mCherry, (iii) Lhx1, and (iv) the overlay. (<bold>C</bold>) Distribution of the cervical premotor LDPNs following injections in GS whether they are Lhx1+ (black) or not (pink). Numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm). Scale bars: (Bi) 200 µm; (Biv) 20 µm. The efficiency of Lhx1 staining along postnatal development is shown <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata1"><label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig5-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig5-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>The number of neurons labelled with anti-Lhx1 antibody decreases in the spinal cord over postnatal development.</title><p>Lhx1 staining at P2, P6, and P10 showing the decrease in the number of Lhx1-positive cells in the spinal cord through early postnatal development. The dashed lines drawn outline the grey matter. Scale bars: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig5-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Cervical premotor LDPNs also project to local cervical MNs</title><p>Given that propriospinal neurons are involved in interlimb coordination, we next sought to determine whether the divergent cervical premotor LDPNs also project to cervical MNs. We therefore performed a series of experiments in which we injected forearm muscles (FMs) with ΔG-Rab-mCherry, and extensor hindlimb GS with ΔG-Rab-eGFP.</p><p>Since it has been suggested that LDPNs participate in ipsilateral control of forelimb and hindlimb (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Miller and van der Meché, 1976</xref>), we sought to determine if premotor LDPNs project to homolateral lumbar and cervical motor pools (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). When homolateral limbs were targeted, we found that some premotor LDPNs infected from ankle extensor injections were also infected from homolateral FMs injection (in 5/6 animals, 16/80 premotor LDPNs were also infected from FMs injection 18.7% ± 12.9%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B–D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>). These divergent premotor LDPNs that projected to lumbar and cervical MNs were all located in the ventral quadrants with 11/16 located in contralateral lamina VIII, and were distributed throughout the rostro-caudal extent of the cervical cord, including segments rostral (C4) to the MN pools innervating the injected forelimb muscles. Furthermore, they had a soma size similar to the premotor LDPNs double labelled by dual hindlimb injections (632 ± 236 µm<sup>2</sup>, p = 0.056, <italic>n</italic><sub>1</sub> = 16 premotor LDPNs infected from both homolateral forelimb and hindlimb injections vs <italic>n</italic><sub>2</sub> = 38 divergent premotor LDPNs infected from dual hindlimb injections (see above), Mann–Whitney test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref>).</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Cervical premotor long descending propriospinal neurons (LDPNs) innervate homolateral lumbar and cervical motoneurons (MNs).</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental strategy to determine whether divergent cervical premotor LDPNs that innervate homolateral lumbar and cervical MNs do exist. (<bold>Bi</bold>) Representative example of a transverse section from the cervical cord following an injection in forearm muscles (FMs) (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) and GS (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) muscles, showing a premotor LDPN infected from the two contralateral motor pools. The dashed box highlights the divergent premotor LDPN. The dashed line drawn outlines the grey matter contour. Dashed box area at higher magnification, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) eGFP, (<bold>iii</bold>) mCherry, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. (<bold>C</bold>) Distribution of the premotor LDPNs infected from the homolateral injections in GS and FMs. The violin and box plots show the distribution of divergent premotor LDPNs innervating homolateral local FMs and distant GS motor pools along the medio-lateral and dorso-ventral axis. Each violin area is normalized to 1. (<bold>D</bold>) Proportion of cervical premotor LDPNs that also project to FM motor pools per animal. (<bold>E</bold>) Plot showing the sectional area of the cervical divergent premotor LDPNs that diverge to two pools of lumbar MNs (hind_hind) and to the pools of GS and FM MNs (fore_hind). When not specified numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm). Scale bars: (Bi) 200 µm; (Biv) 10 µm.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6sdata1"><label>Figure 6—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C–E</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig6-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig6-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Cervical premotor long descending propriospinal neurons (LDPNs) innervate ipsilateral cervical and contralateral lumbar motoneurons (MNs).</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental strategy to examine whether divergent cervical premotor LDPNs innervate ipsilateral cervical and contralateral lumbar motor pools. (<bold>Bi</bold>) Representative example of a transverse section from the cervical cord following injections in contralateral GS (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and ipsilateral forearm muscle (FM) (ΔG-Rab-mCherry) muscles, showing a double-labelled premotor LDPN. The dashed box highlights the divergent premotor LDPN. The dashed line drawn outlines the grey matter. Dashed box area at higher magnification, showing (<bold>ii</bold>) mCherry, (<bold>iii</bold>) eGFP, and (<bold>iv</bold>) the overlay. Scale bars: (Bi) 200 µm; (Biv) 20 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig6-figsupp1-v2.tif"/></fig><fig id="fig6s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Premotor long ascending propriospinal neurons (LAPNs) are distributed in the thoracic, lumbar, and sacral spinal cord, and diverge to homolateral lumbar and cervical motoneurons (MNs).</title><p>(<bold>Ai, Ci, Ei</bold>) Representative examples of transverse sections from the (<bold>A</bold>) thoracic, (<bold>C</bold>) lumbar, and (<bold>E</bold>) sacral spinal cord following injections in homolateral GS (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and forearm muscles (FMs) (ΔG-Rab-mCherry), showing ChAT (blue grey), GFP (green), and mCherry (pink). Dashed boxes highlight INs that were infected from the injections in homolateral GS and FMs. The dashed lines drawn indicate the grey matter. High magnification of the dashed boxes showing double infected premotor neurons in the (Aii–iv) thoracic, (Cii–iv) lumbar, and (Eii–iv) sacral cord. Distributions of the ascending single-labelled (pink) and divergent (black) premotor neurons in the (<bold>B</bold>) thoracic, (<bold>D</bold>) lumbar, and (<bold>F</bold>) sacral cord following injections in homolateral GS (ΔG-Rab-eGFP) and FMs (ΔG-Rab-mCherry). (<bold>G</bold>) Plot showing the size of the sacral premotor LAPNs infected from GS and FMs injections (black) or from the injection in FMs only (pink). When not specified numbers along the axis indicate distances (in µm). Scale bars: (Ai, Ei) 100 µm; (Ci) 200 µm; (Aiv, Civ, Eiv) 10 µm.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6s2sdata1"><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2B, D, F, G</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig6-figsupp2-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig6-figsupp2-v2.tif"/></fig></fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Divergence rates throughout the spinal cord and circuits.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic summarizing the projections determined. (<bold>B</bold>) Plot showing the increase of the apparent divergence rate with the distance between innervated motoneurons (MNs) and premotor neurons.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7sdata1"><label>Figure 7—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Source data for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig7-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig7-v2.tif"/></fig><p>Given the involvement of LPDNs in the diagonal synchronization of forelimb and hindlimb during locomotion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bellardita and Kiehn, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ruder et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Sherrington et al., 1906</xref>), we also injected contralateral FMs and GS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1A</xref>). We found that 2/26 cervical premotor LDPNs were also infected from the FMs injection with one divergent LDPNs in the lamina VIII contralateral to the hindlimb injection in each of two of the three injected animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Thus, at least a few cervical premotor LDPNs monosynaptically project to diagonal lumbar and cervical MNs. However, given the paucity of these cervical premotor LDPNs projecting to local cervical MNs, we could not reliably determine whether this subpopulation shared the same morphology as described above.</p><p>While sharing similar features with the LDPNs infected from dual hindlimb injections, it remains to be determined whether these neurons premotor to hindlimb and forelimb muscles form a homogenous population with the divergent LDPNs.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Distribution of premotor long ascending propriospinal neurons differs from that of LDPNs</title><p>Having identified a population of divergent premotor LDPNs with projections from the cervical to the lumbar region, we next investigated whether ascending propriospinal neurons projecting from the lumbar or thoracic segments to cervical MNs could be identified. Following FMs injections, ascending premotor INs were observed throughout the cord (thoracic to sacral). There were very few (&lt;1%) bifurcating (ascending/descending) premotor neurons in the thoracic cord after injections in homolateral GS and FMs (4/523 double-labelled premotor neurons between T2 and T11, <italic>n</italic> = 3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2A, B</xref>).</p><p>We identified premotor long ascending propriospinal neurons (LAPNs) in the lumbar cord, about half of which were localized in the dorsal ipsilateral quadrant (56/117, <italic>n</italic> = 6 forelimb–hindlimb injections). This distribution of lumbar premotor LAPNs is different from that of cervical premotor LDPNs, which were almost exclusively ventral (164/172, <italic>n</italic> = 13 pair of injections, see above). Of the 117 lumbar premotor LAPNs identified, 10 were also labelled from GS injections, indicating that some neurons projected both to local lumbar MNs as well as to cervical MNs (<italic>n</italic> = 6 ipsilateral forelimb–hindlimb injections, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2C, D</xref>). However, the position of these particular divergent premotor LAPNs was different from that of the premotor LDPNs, in that they were not localized within one quadrant of the cord (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2D</xref>).</p><p>Finally, we turned our attention to the sacral spinal cord, where we found few premotor LAPNs (12 neurons in four of six mice). Of these, however, 10/12 were in the ventral contralateral quadrant (<italic>n</italic> = 6 ipsilateral forelimb–hindlimb injections, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2E, F</xref>), similar to the location of the cervical premotor LDPNs. Like these cervical neurons, the sacral LAPNs had strikingly large somata (710 ± 310 µm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>n</italic> = 11 premotor LAPNs, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2G</xref>). Of 12 labelled neurons, 3 were also infected from the hindlimb (LG) injections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2E–G</xref>). Given that the size and location of these sacral premotor LAPNs were similar to the population of cervical divergent premotor LDPNs, they may represent a ‘reverse counterpart’ of this descending system.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Animals perform rich repertoires of movements through controlling muscle contractions around joints to produce the fundamental syllables of movement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Brownstone, 2020</xref>). To understand how behavioural repertoires are formed, it is important to understand the organization of the neural circuits underlying the production of each syllable. By using monosynaptic restricted RabV tracing techniques, we investigated the presence of spinal premotor INs that project to multiple motor pools and could thus potentially comprise circuits underlying co-activation (joint stiffening) or co-inhibition (joint relaxation) of motor pools across joints and between limbs. We found that at least 1/25 local lumbar premotor INs projects to multiple motor pools, in similar proportions whether these pools were synergist or antagonist pairs. Furthermore, we found that whereas the density of premotor neurons decreases with distance rostral to the motor pool targeted, a high proportion of labelled cervical LDPNs projects to multiple motor pools. These premotor LDPNs are in contralateral lamina VIII, have large somata, are neither glycinergic nor cholinergic, and project to multiple motor pools including those in the lumbar and cervical enlargements. These divergent neurons could thus form a substrate for joint and multi-joint stiffening that contributes to the production of a fundamental syllable of movement.</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>Estimating proportions of divergent premotor INs</title><p>The control of MNs across motor pools through spinal premotor circuits is required for the performance of all motor tasks involving limb movements. Previous studies showed the importance of motor synergies in the production of complex movements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Giszter, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Takei et al., 2017</xref>), with the spinal cord identified as a potential site for muscle synergy organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bizzi and Cheung, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Levine et al., 2014</xref>). In this regard, it might be expected that a significant proportion of local spinal premotor INs innervate multiple motor pools, in particular those corresponding to synergist muscles. Perhaps surprisingly, we found similar rate of divergence throughout the spinal cord be the targeted MN pools synergist or antagonist. In the lumbar region, at least 4 % of the local premotor INs project to two motor pools. More remotely, in thoracic as well as cervical premotor circuits, the apparent rate of divergence was higher but with a decreased density of labelled premotor neurons. Regardless of the proportion of divergent premotor neurons amongst the total premotor population, it is possible that these neurons effectively modulate the synchrony of MN activation and participate in co-activation or co-inhibition of different MN populations.</p><p>What proportion of premotor neurons project to more than one motor pool? To investigate the presence of premotor neurons projecting to multiple motor pools in the spinal cord, we used RabV tracing, injecting ΔG-RabV expressing eGFP or mCherry into different pairs of muscles. Although this technique allowed for visualization of divergent premotor neurons throughout the spinal cord, the proportion of divergent premotor neurons has undoubtedly been underestimated. A divergent neuron will be double labelled only if each virus has been efficiently transmitted across its synapses with MNs from both motor pools. Therefore, due to the stochastic nature of the process of crossing a synapse, any given transfer efficiency lower than 100 % will inevitably give rise to an underestimate of the real number of divergent neurons. The efficiency of trans-synaptic jumps for the SADB19 RabV that we used is unknown, and may depend in part on the type of synapse, with stronger connections facilitating transmission of the virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Ugolini, 2011</xref>). The only indirect indication of efficiency comes from the direct comparison of the SADB19 and the more efficient CVS-N2c strains, for which there was at least a fourfold increase in the ratio of local secondary to primary infected premotor INs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Reardon et al., 2016</xref>). This result suggests that the trans-synaptic efficiency of SADB19 is no higher than 25 %. While there is no evidence for a bias towards stronger or weaker synapses (i.e., the actual number of physical contacts) between proximal and distal premotor INs, such a bias could affect efficiency of viral transmission, and could thus also have potentially skewed our relative estimate of divergence. With the simplifying assumption that the efficiencies of viral transfer are equal and independent from each other across spinal cord regions, we simulated a double injection experiment, extracting a binomial distribution, and calculated the relation between the observed and true rate of divergence. With a jump efficiency of 25%, the 4 % divergence rate we observed in the lumbar spinal cord would correspond to an actual rate of divergence of 18 % (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>). And this calculated rate is almost certainly an underestimate because of the phenomenon of viral interference, whereby there is a reduced probability of subsequent infection with a second RabV after a window of a few hours after the first infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Ohara et al., 2009</xref>). It is therefore likely that the actual rate of divergence of premotor circuit throughout the cord is substantially higher than we observed. Specifically, it is possible that the vast majority of, if not all, premotor LDPNs innervate more than one motor pool.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>Simulation comparing observed vs real rates of divergence depending on trans-synaptic mRV efficiency.</title><p>Simulation of the spreading of mRV in premotor circuits following double injections, extracted from a binomial distribution. Plot showing the relation between observed rate of divergence depending on the real rate of divergence within premotor spinal circuits. This simulation was run with the simplifying assumption that the efficiencies of viral transfer are equal and independent from each other across spinal cord regions.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-70858-fig8-v2.tif"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Mapping premotor circuits using the ChAT-Cre;RΦGT mouse</title><p>In our experimental model, the rabies glycoprotein is expressed only in neurons expressing ChAT, such as MNs. By restricting primary infection to specific MNs via intramuscular injection of RabV, trans-synaptic viral spread was thus restricted to neurons presynaptic to the infected MN population. It is therefore theoretically possible that there might be double jumps via other presynaptic cholinergic neurons such as medial partition neurons V0<sub>C</sub> neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Zagoraiou et al., 2009</xref>). MNs also form synapses with other MNs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bhumbra and Beato, 2018</xref>), so it could also be possible that specificity is lost due to second-order jumps via these cells. We consider double jumps unlikely for two main reasons: (1) following muscle injections, the first trans-synaptic labelling occurs after 5–6 days. Since the tissue was fixed 9 days after injections, it is unlikely that many secondary jumps could have occurred in such a brief time window. And (2) most presynaptic partners of V0<sub>C</sub> INs are located in the superficial dorsal laminae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Zampieri et al., 2014</xref>), a region in which we did not observe any labelled INs. We are thus confident that the labelled neurons are premotor. We also acknowledge the possibility that some of the labelled premotor cells might originate from tertiary infection originating from secondary infection of synaptically connected MNs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bhumbra and Beato, 2018</xref>). Such events might be rare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ronzano et al., 2021</xref>) and would not alter our findings on the organization of divergent premotor neurons, since we have shown that their distributions are similar, regardless of the particular pair of injected muscles.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Premotor INs innervating antagonist motor pools: implications for movement</title><p>The similar rate of divergence between synergist and antagonist pairs might be surprising. But divergence to agonist and antagonist motor pools has been shown in adult mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Gu et al., 2017</xref>), indicating that these circuits are not limited to an early developmental stage. Apart from the cervical divergent premotor LDPNs that are likely to represent a rather homogenous group of excitatory neurons, the divergent premotor neurons in the thoracic and lumbar regions could be comprised of different neural populations, with a mixed population of excitatory, inhibitory, and, in lower proportion, cholinergic neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s6">Figure 1—figure supplement 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). These INs that project to antagonist motor pools could thus be involved in modulating either joint stiffening (excitatory) or relaxation (inhibitory). For example, during postural adjustment and skilled movements, divergent excitatory premotor INs would lead to co-contraction of antagonist muscles to facilitate an increase in joint stiffness and to promote stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Hansen et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Nielsen and Kagamihara, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nielsen and Kagamihara, 1992</xref>). In invertebrates, co-contraction of antagonist muscles has also been described preceding jumping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Pearson and Robertson, 1981</xref>): co-contraction could thus also be important for the initiation of movement.</p><p>On the other hand, divergent inhibitory premotor neurons would lead to joint relaxation. This phenomenon is less well studied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Leis et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Manconi et al., 1998</xref>). One example could be their involvement in the loss of muscle tone that accompanies rapid eye movement sleep (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Uchida et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Valencia Garcia et al., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Projections of LDPNs to multiple motor pools</title><p>In the cat, long descending fibres originating in the cervical cord have been shown to innervate lumbar MNs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Giovanelli Barilari and Kuypers, 1969</xref>) and trigger monosynaptic potentials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jankowska et al., 1974</xref>). The existence of LDPNs has been confirmed anatomically in neonatal mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Ni et al., 2014</xref>) and functionally in adult cats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Alstermark et al., 1987a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Alstermark et al., 1987b</xref>), where they are thought to play a role in posture and stability. Our study confirms the existence of premotor LDPNs, and also indicates that they have a high rate of divergence (up to ~40 % compared to ~13 % for thoracic neurons). Most cervical LDPNs are clustered in contralateral lamina VIII, are virtually all excitatory, and have a distinct morphology with somal size ~twofold larger than other local cells (and similar to MNs). These findings contrast with the divergent premotor neurons found in the thoracic spinal cord: these are distributed in ipsilateral lamina VI and VII as well as in contralateral lamina VIII and thus clearly comprise multiple neuronal populations. In contrast to thoracic divergent premotor neurons, cervical LDPNs may thus have a more unifying function. Given their apparent widespread divergence, it is possible that these LDPNs are involved in producing widespread increases in muscle tone.</p><p>One step towards being able to further assess the function of this population of INs would be through understanding their lineage. Given the poor detection of the Lhx1 transcription factor in postnatal mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>), we could not conclude that the labelled cervical LDPNs are a population that derive from the V0<sub>v</sub> or dI2 class. Although in the chick, dI2 INs do not project to MNs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Haimson et al., 2021</xref>), it is possible that they could in the mouse: these are large neurons located in the ventromedial spinal cord (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Haimson et al., 2021</xref>), and express Lhx1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Avraham et al., 2009</xref>). Further experiments using a Dbx1-IRES-GFP mouse line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bouvier et al., 2010</xref>), for example, could help to determine the identity of these divergent cervical LDPNs. Genetic access to this particular set of INs would also allow the design of experiments aimed at acute and specific activation or inactivation of divergent LDPNs, and could unravel their anatomy and function in behaviour.</p></sec><sec id="s3-5"><title>Concluding remarks</title><p>The completion of movements requires well-controlled muscle contractions across multiple joints within and between limbs. The control of any one joint is analogous to the production of syllables of speech, with the three most fundamental syllables of movement being a change in joint angle (requiring reciprocal inhibition of flexors and extensor MNs), a stiffening of a joint (requiring co-activation of flexors and extensor MNs), and a relaxation of a joint (requiring co-inhibition of flexor and extensor MNs). While neural circuits for reciprocal inhibition have been well studied over many decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Eccles, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Eccles et al., 1956</xref>), circuits for stiffening or relaxation have not been. Our anatomical data identify neurons that could be potentially implicated in these circuits and show that they are present within and distributed throughout the spinal cord. Thus, the mechanisms that lead to the production of the fundamental syllables of movement could be contained within the spinal cord itself.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">Reagent type (species) or resource</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Designation</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Source or reference</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Identifiers</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (Rabies virus)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ΔG-Rab-eGFP</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gift from M. Tripodi lab, LMCB Cambridge</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">G-deleted Rabies <break/>virus</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (Rabies virus)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ΔG-Rab-mCherry</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gift from M. Tripodi lab, LMCB Cambridge</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">G-deleted Rabies <break/>virus</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ChAT-IRES-Cre</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Jackson Laboratory</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IMSR Cat# <break/>JAX:006410; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:IMSR_JAX:006410">IMSR_JAX:006410</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Allele symbol: Chat<sup>tm2(cre)Lowl</sup>; <break/>maintained <break/>on a C57BL6/J <break/>background</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RΦGT</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Jackson Laboratory</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IMSR Cat# <break/>JAX:024708; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:IMSR_JAX:024708">IMSR_JAX:024708</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Allele symbol: Gt(ROSA)26<break/>Sortm1<break/>(CAG-RABVgp4,-<break/>TVA)Arenk; maintained on <break/>a C57BL6/J background</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Strain, strain background (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">GlyT2-eGFP</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gift from H. Zeilhofer lab, University of Zurich</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IMSR Cat# <break/>RBRC04708; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:IMSR_RBRC04708">IMSR_RBRC04708</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Allele symbol: Tg(Slc6a5-EGFP)<break/>1Uze; maintained on <break/>a C57BL6/J background</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cell line (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, female)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">HEK293t/17</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gift from M. Tripodi lab, LMCB Cambridge</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:CVCL_1926">CVCL_1926</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ATCC, cat. no. CRL-1126</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cell line (<italic>Mesocricetus auratus</italic>, male)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">BHK-21</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gift from M. Tripodi lab, LMCB Cambridge</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:CVCL_1915">CVCL_1915</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ATCC # CCL-10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cell line (<italic>Mesocricetus auratus</italic>, male)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">BHK-G</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gift from M. Tripodi lab, LMCB Cambridge</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:CVCL_1915">CVCL_1915</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Modified <break/>from ATCC <break/>Cat# CCL-10; <break/>RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:CVCL_1915">CVCL_1915</ext-link> <break/>to express <break/>the rabies glycoprotein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">anti-ChAT <break/>(Goat polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Millipore</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat# AB144P; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2079751">AB_2079751</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">anti-mCherry <break/>(Chicken polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Abcam</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat# ab205402; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2722769">AB_2722769</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:2500)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">anti-GFP <break/>(Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Abcam</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat# ab290; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_303395">AB_303395</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:2500)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">anti-vGluT2 <break/>(Guinea pig polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Millipore</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat# AB2251-I; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2665454">AB_2665454</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:2500)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">anti-Lhx1 <break/>(Rabbit polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gift from T. Jessell lab, Columbia University, New York</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:5000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">anti-Rabbit IgG H&amp;L <break/>Alexa Fluor 647 <break/>(Donkey polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Abcam</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat# ab150079; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2722623">AB_2722623</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">anti-Goat IgG <break/>H&amp;L Alexa Fluor 405 <break/>(Donkey <break/>polyclonal preadsorbed)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Abcam</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Abcam Cat# AB175665; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2636888">AB_2636888</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:200)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">anti-Rabbit IgG H&amp;L <break/>Alexa Fluor488 <break/>(Donkey polyclonal <break/>Highly Cross-Adsorbed)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat# A-21206; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2535792">AB_2535792</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Antibody</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">anti-Chicken IgY (IgG) <break/>H&amp;L Cy3-<break/>AffiniPure <break/>(Donkey polyclonal)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Jackson Immuno<break/>Research Labs</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat# 703-165-155; RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:AB_2340363">AB_2340363</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IF (1:1000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Chemical compound, drug</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mowiol 4–88</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cat# 81381–250 G</td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ZEN Digital Imaging <break/>for Light <break/>Microscopy: Zen Blue 2.3</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Carl Zeiss light microscopy imaging systems</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:SCR_013672">SCR_013672</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Imaris 9.1</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Bitplane</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:SCR_007370">SCR_007370</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R 3.6.2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">R Project for Statistical Computing</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:SCR_001905">SCR_001905</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Prism 7.0</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">GraphPad</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:SCR_002798">SCR_002798</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Software, algorithm</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Adobe illustrator <break/>version CC2019</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Adobe</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://identifiers.org/RRID/RRID:SCR_010279">SCR_010279</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Mouse strains</title><p>All experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 27) were performed according to the Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act UK (1986) and certified by the UCL AWERB committee, under project licence number 70/7621. Homozygous ChAT-IRES-Cre mice (which have an IRES-Cre sequence downstream of the ChAT stop codon, such that Cre expression is controlled by the endogenous ChAT gene promoter without affecting ChAT expression; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rossi et al., 2011</xref>, Jackson lab, stock #006410) crossed with homozygous RΦGT mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Takatoh et al., 2013</xref>, Jackson lab, stock #024708), that have Cre dependent expression of the rabies glycoprotein and the avian viral receptor TVA, whose expression is not employed in this study were used for double injections (see the detail of animal use for each type of injection). For single injections, homozygous ChAT-IRES-Cre mice (termed ChAT-Cre here) were crossed with hemizygous GlyT2-eGFP mice (BAC transgene insertion in exon 2 of <italic>Slc6a5</italic> gene allowing specific eGFP expression in GlyT2-positive cells, MGI:3835459, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Zeilhofer et al., 2005</xref>) and their eGFP-positive offspring was mated with homozygous RΦGT (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp3">Supplementary file 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Virus production, collection, and titration</title><p>We used the glycoprotein G-deleted variant of the SAD-B19 vaccine strain rabies virus (a kind gift from Dr M. Tripodi). Modified RabV (ΔG-Rab) with the glycoprotein G sequence replaced by mCherry or eGFP (ΔG-Rab-eGFP/mCherry) was produced at a high concentration with minor modifications to the original protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Osakada et al., 2011</xref>). BHK cells expressing the rabies glycoprotein G (BHK-G cells) were plated in standard Dulbecco modified medium with 10 % foetal bovine serum (FBS) and split after 6–7 hr incubating at 37°C and 5 % CO<sub>2</sub>. They were inoculated at a multiplicity of infection of 0.2–0.3 with either ΔG-Rab-eGFP or mCherry virus in 2 % FBS, and incubated at 35°C and 3 % CO<sub>2</sub>. Plates were then split in 10 % FBS at 37°C and 5 % CO<sub>2</sub>. After 24 hr the medium was replaced by 2 % FBS medium and incubated at 35°C and 3 % CO<sub>2</sub> for 3 days (virus production). The supernatant was collected and medium was added for another cycle (three cycles maximum), after which the supernatant was filtered (0.45 µm filter) and centrifuged 2 hr at 19,400 rpm (SW28 Beckman rotor). The pellets were re-suspended in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and centrifuged together at 21,000 rpm, 4°C, 4 hr in a 20 % sucrose gradient. Pellets of each collection were then re-suspended and stored in 5–10 µl aliquots at –80°C.</p><p>Virus titration was performed on BHK cells plated in 10 % FBS medium at 1.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml and incubated overnight at 37°C and 10 % CO<sub>2</sub> (growth). The virus was prepared for two serial dilutions with two different aliquots and added in the well after an equal volume of medium had been removed (serial dilution from 10<sup>−3</sup> to 10<sup>−10</sup>) and incubated 48 hr at 35°C and 3 % CO<sub>2</sub>. The titre was determined from the count of cells in the higher dilution well and was between 10<sup>9</sup> and 10<sup>10</sup> infectious units (IU)/ml.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Intramuscular injections</title><p>A subcutaneous injection of analgesic (carprofen, 1 µl, 10% wt/vol) was given to the neonatal pups (P1–P3) prior to surgery and all procedures were carried out under general isoflurane anaesthesia. After a skin incision to expose the targeted muscle, the virus (1 µl) was injected intramuscularly using a Hamilton injector (model 7652-01) mounted with a bevelled glass pipette (inner diameter 50–70 µm). The mice were injected in TA and PL (ankle flexor pair), LG and MG (ankle extensor pair) for synergist pairs and TA and LG for antagonist pairs. In hindlimb/forelimb double injections, the LG and MG were both injected with 1 µl of one RabV to increase the number of long projecting cells infected. In addition, 1 µl of the second RabV was injected in FMs (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref>) without selecting a specific muscle. The injected viruses were used at a titre between 10<sup>9</sup> and 10<sup>10</sup> IU/ml. The incisions were closed with vicryl suture, and the mice were closely monitored for 24 hr post-surgery. Mice were perfused 9 days after the injections. Due to the proximity of synergist pairs of muscles, prior to spinal tissue processing, we dissected the injected leg and confirmed that there was no contamination of virus across the injected muscles or in adjacent muscles below or above the knee. When injecting FMs, we could not target a single muscle. To visualize which muscles had been infected, we carefully dissected each FM and assess for the presence of fluorescent signal (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref>). Three heterozygous RΦGT mice were also injected (LG muscle) with an EnvA pseudotyped RabV in order to test simultaneously for ectopic expression of G or of the TVA receptors. In three control animals we observed one to three labelled MNs, but no IN labelling. This indicates the presence of minimal ectopic TVA expression, but not of G (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Ronzano et al., 2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Tissue collection and immunohistochemistry</title><p>The mice were perfused with PBS (0.1 M) followed by PBS 4 % paraformaldehyde under terminal ketamine/xylazine anaesthesia (i.p. 80 and 10 mg/kg, respectively). The spinal cords were then collected through a ventral laminectomy and post-fixed for 2 hr. The cords were divided into the different parts of the spinal cord (cervical [C1–T1], thoracic [T2–T11], lumbar [L1–L6], and sacral [S1–S4]), cryoprotected overnight in 30 % sucrose PBS, embedded in optimal cutting temperature compound (Tissue-Tek) and sliced transversally (30 µm thickness) with a cryostat (Bright Instruments, UK). Sections were incubated with primary antibodies for 36 hr at 4°C and with secondary antibodies overnight at 4°C in PBS double salt, 0.2 % Triton 100-X (Sigma), 7 % donkey normal serum (Sigma). The primary antibodies used were: goat anti-choline acetyltransferase (ChAT, 1:100, Millipore, AB144P), chicken anti-mCherry (1:2500, Abcam, Ab205402), rabbit anti-GFP (1:2500, Abcam, Ab290), guinea pig anti-vGluT2 (1:2500, Millipore, AB2251-I), and rabbit anti-Lhx1 (1:5000, from Dr. T Jessell, Columbia University, New York); and the secondary antibodies: donkey anti-rabbit Alexa 647 (1:1000, Abcam, Ab150079), donkey anti-goat preadsorbed Alexa 405 (1:200, Abcam, Ab175665), donkey anti-rabbit Alexa 488 (1:1000, Thermo Fisher, A21206), and donkey anti-chicken Cy3 (1:1000, Jackson ImmunoResearch, #703-165-155). The slides were mounted in Mowiol (Sigma, 81381-250 G) and coverslipped (VWR, #631-0147) for imaging.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Confocal imaging and analysis</title><p>Images of the entire sections were obtained using a Zeiss LSM800 confocal microscope with a ×20 air objective (0.8 NA) and tile advanced set up function (ZEN Blue 2.3 software). A ×63 oil objective was used for Airy scan imaging of somata and excitatory boutons. Tiles were stitched using Zen Blue and analyses were performed using Zen Blue and Imaris (Bitplane, version 9.1) software packages. Location maps were plotted setting the central canal as (0,0) in the (<italic>x</italic>,<underline><italic>y</italic></underline>) Cartesian system and using the ‘Spots’ function of Imaris. The <italic>y</italic>-axis was set to the dorso-ventral axis. Positive values were assigned for dorsal neurons in the <italic>y</italic>-axis and ipsilateral (to the hindlimb injection) neurons in the <italic>x</italic>-axis. Coordinates were collected on every section and normalized through the cervical, thoracic, lumbar, and sacral parts separately using grey matter borders and fixing the width and the height of the transverse hemisections. To calculate divergence rates, given the high density of premotor INs infected in the lumbar cord all infected premotor INs (eGFP+, mCherry+ and eGFP+ mCherry+) were quantified in one of every three sections which further allowed to avoid counting the same cells twice on consecutive sections. In the cervical, thoracic, and sacral regions, all cells were quantified, as their low density allowed for manually excluding premotor neurons found in consecutive sections. Since MNs are big cells localized as a restricted column of the ventral spinal cord, we quantified them on every other sections, to avoid counting the same cell twice on consecutive sections.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Statistics</title><p>All statistical analyses and plots were made using R (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria, 2005, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>, version 3.6.2) and GraphPad PRISM (version 7.0). To compare cell sectional areas, non-parametric rank tests were used as specified in each related result. The numbers of animals/cells in each experiment and statistical tests used are reported in the figure legends or directly in the text. Results and graphs illustrate the mean ± standard deviation. Statistical significance levels are represented as follows: *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001, ****p &lt; 0.0001, and ns: not significant.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf2"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Software, Validation, Visualization, Funding acquisition, Project administration</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Visualization, Project administration</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Software, Resources, Project administration</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Writing – original draft, Investigation, Writing – review and editing, Supervision, Resources, Funding acquisition, Project administration</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Writing – original draft, Investigation, Methodology, Writing – review and editing, Supervision, Software, Resources, Funding acquisition, Project administration</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>All experiments were performed in strict adherence to the Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act UK (1986) and certified by the UCL AWERB committee, under project licence number 70/7621. All surgeries were performed under general isofluorane anaesthesia and before surgery animals were injected subcutaneously with an analgesic (carprofen, 1 μl, 10% wt/vol) and the mice were closely monitored for a 24-hr period following surgery to detect any sign of distress or motor impairment. Every effort was made to minimize suffering.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-transrepform1-v2.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp1"><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Numbers of MNs and premotor neurons, and medio-lateral and dorso-ventral distributions of divergent premotor neurons across individual experiments.</title><p>Distribution of divergent premotor neurons per region of the spinal cord across individual experiments, expressed as median± first/third quartile.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-supp1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp2"><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>Details of muscles infected following forearm injections.</title><p>(+) means that a fluorescent signal was found in muscle fibres, (−) means that no fluorescence was observed following muscle dissections.</p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-supp2-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp3"><label>Supplementary file 3.</label><caption><title>List of the mice used for each experiment, including genotype and figure in which they are shown.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-70858-supp3-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files. Source data files have been provided for Figures 1 to 7 in the main text and for Figure 1 – figure supplement 4-5, Figure 2 – figure supplement 4, Figure 3 – figure supplement 4, and Figure 6 – figure supplement 2.</p></sec><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to Dr N Zampieri and all the members of Brownstone and Beato labs for insightful comments on the manuscript. We want to thank S Morton for providing Lhx1 antibodies, Prof L Greensmith for access to her lab facilities, and Dr MG Özyurt for helping with immunostaining. This work was supported by a Leverhulme Trust grant (grant number RPG-2013-176) and a BBSRC grant (BB/L001454) to MB and a Wellcome Trust Investigator Award to RMB (110193). RMB is supported by Brain Research UK.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alstermark</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1987">1987a</year><article-title>Subpopulations and functions of long C3-C5 propriospinal neurones</article-title><source>Brain Research</source><volume>404</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(87)91402-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alstermark</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1987">1987b</year><article-title>Long C3-C5 propriospinal neurones in the cat</article-title><source>Brain Research</source><volume>404</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(87)91400-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapir</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Berrocal</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Postnatal phenotype and localization of spinal cord V1 derived interneurons</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>493</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.20711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16255029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avraham</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadas</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vald</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zisman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schejter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Klar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Transcriptional control of axonal guidance and sorting in dorsal interneurons by the Lim-HD proteins Lhx9 and Lhx1</article-title><source>Neural Development</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>21</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1749-8104-4-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19545367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballion</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Viala</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Forelimb locomotor generators and quadrupedal locomotion in the neonatal rat</article-title><source>The European Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>1727</fpage><lpage>1738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0953-816x.2001.01794.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11860467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellardita</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiehn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Phenotypic characterization of speed-associated gait changes in mice reveals modular organization of locomotor networks</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>1426</fpage><lpage>1436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2015.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25959968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benito-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Renshaw Cells and Ia Inhibitory Interneurons Are Generated at Different Times from p1 Progenitors and Differentiate Shortly after Exiting the Cell Cycle</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>1156</fpage><lpage>1170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3630-12.2012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22279202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhumbra</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Beato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Recurrent excitation between motoneurones propagates across segments and is purely glutamatergic</article-title><source>PLOS Biology</source><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>e2003586</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2003586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29538375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bizzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>VCK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The neural origin of muscle synergies</article-title><source>Frontiers in Computational Neuroscience</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncom.2013.00051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thoby-Brisson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Renier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubreuil</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ericson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Champagnat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chédotal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Hindbrain interneurons and axon guidance signaling critical for breathing</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20680010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brockett</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Seenan</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannatyne</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Ascending and descending propriospinal pathways between lumbar and cervical segments in the rat: Evidence for a substantial ascending excitatory pathway</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><volume>240</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2013.02.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23454541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brownstone</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Key Steps in the Evolution of Mammalian Movement: A Prolegomenal Essay</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><volume>450</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2020.05.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32446854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Landgren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1956">1956</year><article-title>CENTRAL PATHWAY FOR DIRECT INHIBITORY ACTION OF IMPULSES IN LARGEST AFFERENT NERVE FIBRES TO MUSCLE</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.1956.19.1.75</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13286723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1969">1969</year><source>The Inhibitory Pathways of the Central Nervous System</source><publisher-name>Springfield</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eidelberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Story</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nystel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1980">1980</year><article-title>Stepping by chronic spinal cats</article-title><source>Experimental Brain Research</source><volume>40</volume><elocation-id>e237787</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00237787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Conn</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasquez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Callister</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Anatomical and molecular properties of long descending propriospinal neurons in mice</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neuroanatomy</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnana.2017.00005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giovanelli Barilari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuypers</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1969">1969</year><article-title>Propriospinal fibers interconnecting the spinal enlargements in the cat</article-title><source>Brain Research</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(69)90113-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5794910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giszter</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Motor primitives--new data and future questions</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2015.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25912883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glasgow</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Henke</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>CVE</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Ptf1a determines GABAergic over glutamatergic neuronal cell fate in the spinal cord dorsal horn</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>5461</fpage><lpage>5469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.02167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16291784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Serradj</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baccei</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Skilled Movements Require Non-apoptotic Bax/Bak Pathway-Mediated Corticospinal Circuit Reorganization</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>94</volume><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2017.04.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28472660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haimson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadas</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kania</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cinnamon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lev-Tov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Klar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Spinal lumbar dI2 interneurons contribute to stability of bipedal stepping</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e62001</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.62001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34396953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>LOD</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Coupling of antagonistic ankle muscles during co-contraction in humans</article-title><source>Experimental Brain Research</source><volume>146</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00221-002-1152-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12232685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Giszter</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>A neural basis for motor primitives in the spinal cord</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>1322</fpage><lpage>1336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5894-08.2010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20107059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1983">1983</year><article-title>Separate cortical systems for control of joint movement and joint stiffness: reciprocal activation and coactivation of antagonist muscles</article-title><source>Advances in Neurology</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6419553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jankowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1974">1974</year><article-title>A long propriospinal system with direct effect on motoneurones and on interneurones in the cat lumbosacral cord</article-title><source>Experimental Brain Research</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00234388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4373265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaff</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Transcriptional networks regulating neuronal identity in the developing spinal cord</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>1183</fpage><lpage>1191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leis</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokic</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kofler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronenberg</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wissel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Glocker</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stetkarova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Nociceptive fingertip stimulation inhibits synergistic motoneuron pools in the human upper limb</article-title><source>Neurology</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>1305</fpage><lpage>1309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.55.9.1305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11087772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinckley</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilde</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaff</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Identification of a cellular node for motor control pathways</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24609464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manconi</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Syed</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Floeter</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Mechanisms underlying spinal motor neuron excitability during the cutaneous silent period in humans</article-title><source>Muscle &amp; Nerve</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>1256</fpage><lpage>1264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(sici)1097-4598(199810)21:10&lt;1256::aid-mus3&gt;3.0.co;2-a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9736053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstone</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Spinal cholinergic interneurons regulate the excitability of motoneurons during locomotion</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>2448</fpage><lpage>2453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0611134104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17287343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Meché</surname><given-names>FGA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1976">1976</year><article-title>Coordinated stepping of all four limbs in the high spinal cat</article-title><source>Brain Research</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(76)90541-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1276923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McCallum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugihara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Corticospinal and reticulospinal contacts on cervical commissural and long descending propriospinal neurons in the adult rat spinal cord; evidence for powerful reticulospinal connections</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e0152094</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0152094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moran-Rivard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saueressig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Burrill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Evx1 Is a Postmitotic Determinant of V0 Interneuron Identity in the Spinal Cord</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(01)00213-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Deacon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Vestibulospinal, reticulospinal and descending propriospinal nerve fibres in man</article-title><source>Brain</source><volume>119 (Pt 6)</volume><fpage>1809</fpage><lpage>1833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/119.6.1809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9009990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawabi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamichi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tedeschi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Characterization of Long Descending Premotor Propriospinal Neurons in the Spinal Cord</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>9404</fpage><lpage>9417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1771-14.2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25009272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagamihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>The regulation of disynaptic reciprocal Ia inhibition during co-contraction of antagonistic muscles in man</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>456</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.1992.sp019341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1338100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagamihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>The regulation of presynaptic inhibition during co-contraction of antagonistic muscles in man</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>464</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.1993.sp019652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8229819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Witter</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Iijima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Untangling neural networks with dual retrograde transsynaptic viral infection</article-title><source>Frontiers in Neuroscience</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/neuro.01.032.2009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20198151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osakada</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cetin</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshel</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Virgen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>New Rabies Virus Variants for Monitoring and Manipulating Activity and Gene Expression in Defined Neural Circuits</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>71</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21867879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1981">1981</year><article-title>Interneurons coactivating hindleg flexor and extensor motoneurons in the locust</article-title><source>Journal of Comparative Physiology</source><volume>144</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00612571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pierani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran-Rivard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunshine</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Littman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessell</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Control of interneuron fate in the developing spinal cord by the progenitor homeodomain protein Dbx1</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(01)00212-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Behringer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Lhx1 and Lhx5 maintain the inhibitory-neurotransmitter status of interneurons in the dorsal spinal cord</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.02717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17166926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pocratsky</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morehouse</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Beare</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Riegler</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsoulfas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>States</surname><given-names>GJR</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnuson</surname><given-names>DSK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Reversible silencing of lumbar spinal interneurons unmasks a task-specific network for securing hindlimb alternation</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e1963</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-02033-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29213073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reardon</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Turi</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirblich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessell</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Losonczy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Rabies Virus CVS-N2c(ΔG) Strain Enhances Retrograde Synaptic Transfer and Neuronal Viability</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2016.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26804990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shum-Siu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Onifer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnuson</surname><given-names>DSK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Anterograde labeling of ventrolateral funiculus pathways with spinal enlargement connections in the adult rat spinal cord</article-title><source>Brain Research</source><volume>1302</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2009.09.049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19766612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="preprint"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ronzano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Skarlatou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannatyne</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhumbra</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lancelin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocratsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Özyurt</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstone</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zampieri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Beato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>On the Distribution of Spinal Premotor Interneurons</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.02.10.430608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Balthasar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauzon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowell</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Melanocortin-4 Receptors Expressed by Cholinergic Neurons Regulate Energy Balance and Glucose Homeostasis</article-title><source>Cell Metabolism</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2011.01.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21284986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruder</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeoka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Long-Distance Descending Spinal Neurons Ensure Quadrupedal Locomotor Stability</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>1063</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2016.10.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27866798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sapir</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasquez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Pax6 and Engrailed 1 Regulate Two Distinct Aspects of Renshaw Cell Development</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1255</fpage><lpage>1264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3187-03.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14762144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherrington</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Laslett</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1903">1903</year><article-title>Observations on some spinal reflexes and the interconnection of spinal segments</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.1903.sp000946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16992657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherrington</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>New Haven</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Press</surname><given-names>YU</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1906">1906</year><article-title>The integrative action of the nervous system, New Haven</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>253</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2006.12.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skarlatou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hérent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Toscano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Afadin Signaling at the Spinal Neuroepithelium Regulates Central Canal Formation and Gait Selection</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>31</volume><elocation-id>107741</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2020.107741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32521266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Remmel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1979">1979</year><article-title>Cells of origin of long descending propriospinal fibers connecting the spinal enlargements in cat and monkey determined by horseradish peroxidase and electrophysiological techniques</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>188</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.901880307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">114558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takatoh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>MML</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenkiel</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>New Modules Are Added to Vibrissal Premotor Circuitry with the Emergence of Exploratory Whisking</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2012.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23352170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Spinal interneurons facilitate coactivation of hand muscles during a precision grip task in monkeys</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>17041</fpage><lpage>17050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4297-10.2010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21159974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Confais</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomatsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Neural basis for hand muscle synergies in the primate spinal cord</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>114</volume><fpage>8643</fpage><lpage>8648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1704328114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28739958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talpalar</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiehn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Dual-mode operation of neuronal networks involved in left-right alternation</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>500</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23812590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year><article-title>Light microscope study of the coexistence of GABA-like and glycine-like immunoreactivities in the spinal cord of the rat</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>296</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.902960312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2358549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Spike</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieghart</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Colocalization of GABA, glycine, and their receptors at synapses in the rat spinal cord</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>974</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.16-03-00974.1996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8558266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tresch</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>The case for and against muscle synergies</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2009.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19828310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>A Discrete Glycinergic Neuronal Population in the Ventromedial Medulla That Induces Muscle Atonia during REM Sleep and Cataplexy in Mice</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>1582</fpage><lpage>1596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0688-20.2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33372061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ugolini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Specificity of rabies virus as a transneuronal tracer of motor networks: Transfer from hypoglossal motoneurons to connected second-order and higher order central nervous system cell groups</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>356</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.903560312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7642806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ugolini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Rabies Virus as a Transneuronal Tracer of Neuronal Connections, Advances in Virus Research</article-title><source>Advances in Virus Research</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-387040-7.00010-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valencia Garcia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brischoux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Clément</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Libourel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arthaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luppi</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Ventromedial medulla inhibitory neuron inactivation induces REM sleep without atonia and REM sleep behavior disorder</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-02761-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickersham</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>RJO</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Finke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Conzelmann</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JAT</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Monosynaptic Restriction of Transsynaptic Tracing from Single, Genetically Targeted Neurons</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2007.01.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17329205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiltschko</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Iurilli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Katon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pashkovski</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraira</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Mapping Sub-Second Structure in Mouse Behavior</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>1121</fpage><lpage>1135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.11.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26687221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zagoraiou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Akay</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstone</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessell</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>A Cluster of Cholinergic Premotor Interneurons Modulates Mouse Locomotor Activity</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2009.10.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20005822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zampieri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessell</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Mapping sensory circuits by anterograde transsynaptic transfer of recombinant rabies virus</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2013.12.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24486087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeilhofer</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Studler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arabadzisz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweizer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Layh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bösl</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritschy</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Glycinergic neurons expressing enhanced green fluorescent protein in bacterial artificial chromosome transgenic mice</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>482</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.20349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15611994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanuza</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasquez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanks</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Akay</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosgnach</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>V3 Spinal Neurons Establish a Robust and Balanced Locomotor Rhythm during Walking</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2008.09.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18940590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanuza</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Britz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Siembab</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasquez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>V1 and V2b interneurons secure the alternating flexor-extensor motor activity mice require for limbed locomotion</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.02.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24698273</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="sa0"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.70858.sa0</article-id><title-group><article-title>Editor's evaluation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thoby-Brisson</surname><given-names>Muriel</given-names></name><role specific-use="editor">Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>CNRS Université de Bordeaux</institution><country>France</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><related-object id="sa0ro1" link-type="continued-by" object-id="10.1101/2021.06.03.446906" object-id-type="id" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2021.06.03.446906"/></front-stub><body><p>This manuscript uses viral tracing to identify interneurons, throughout the spinal cord, which synapse onto motoneurons innervating pairs of flexor and extensor hindlimb muscles. Importantly, the data identifies single premotor interneurons which travel to, and presumably regulate the activity of, multiple motor pools. It is possible that these premotor neurons are involved in regulating muscle stiffness across a joint.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.70858.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Thoby-Brisson</surname><given-names>Muriel</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>CNRS Université de Bordeaux</institution><country>France</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Gosgnach</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name><role>Reviewer</role><aff><institution>University of Alberta</institution><country>Canada</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text id="box1"><p>Our editorial process produces two outputs: i) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sciety.org/articles/activity/10.1101/2021.06.03.446906">public reviews</ext-link> designed to be posted alongside <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.06.03.446906v2">the preprint</ext-link> for the benefit of readers; ii) feedback on the manuscript for the authors, including requests for revisions, shown below. We also include an acceptance summary that explains what the editors found interesting or important about the work.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Spinal neurons innervating multiple local and distant motor pools&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by 3 peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Ronald Calabrese as the Senior Editor. The following individual involved in review of your submission has agreed to reveal their identity: Simon Gosgnach (Reviewer #1).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed their reviews with one another, and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>The three reviewers acknowledge that the paper is of a great interest for researchers working within the field of motor control, and more specifically at the level of the spinal cord. Despite the rather descriptive aspect of the study it might indeed set the foundation for future studies regarding the specific identities and functions of the premotor neurons investigated here. Their detailed comments are described below, but I would like to emphasize a few important points harvested from their reviews:</p><p>1) You should tone down the part on the V0v origin identification, or better do the appropriate characterization as suggested below;</p><p>2) You should further discuss the neurotransmitter characterization and eventually address this point experimentally if possible;</p><p>3) You should further describe the rostro-caudal extension of the labelled pre-motoneurons.</p><p>4) Also, a functional aspect is clearly missing, the more you can address this in your revised version the more it will strengthen the paper, but we are aware that fully investigating this would require too much time and represents a significant amount of work if the data are not available yet.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>1. More detail regarding rostra-caudal location in the spinal cord should be given in all cases. First I think a Figure describing the location of the motor pools for the 4 injected muscles should be included- this could be in the supplementary data or it could go as a panel in Figure 1. This is needed so we have a clear idea of how far the axons of the PMIs project. In my experience a motor pool can span several lumbar segments. More specific information should also be provided regarding the location of the sections which contain the PMIs being described. I realize this is not an exact science after cutting tissue, but given your care in counting every third section, you should have a pretty good idea of which segment houses the neurons. This would be preferred over the current description of &quot;rostral cervical&quot; or equivalent.</p><p>In the Figures the number of MNs infected with either virus is typically quite low so I assume the sections are not particularly close to the middle of the infected motor pools?</p><p>2. The amount of raw data shown is light. There is one immuno panel shown per Figure. I realize the take home message comes from the schematics, but it would be nice to see images of spinal sections with more single and double infected cells. Each immuno image contains just one divergent PMI and other than Figure 1 and 6 there are no other cells that seem to be infected with either the red or green expressing virus in the immuno image.</p><p>3. I get a little uncomfortable with the data interpretation at the back end of the Results- particularly with the section titled Cervical LDPNs are excitatory- this is speculation and should not be in the title. The data simply shows 95% of these cells are not glycinergic.</p><p>4. Related to point 3 – The next section is titled &quot;cervical premotor LDPNs likely arise from the V0v domain&quot;. In addition to V0 and V1 cells, Lhx1 is also expressed postmitotically in the dI2, dI4, dI6, and V2 populations, and even some V3 cells (Alanyick et al., 2012, Delile….Sagner biorxiv paper https://doi.org/10.1101/472415). It is thus extremely speculative to suggest that the V0v cells are the ones we are looking at here. Even more so when we factor in the finding that Lhx1 plays a key role in establishing GABAergic neuronal identity (Pillai et al., 2007).</p><p>Incidentally the current thinking on V0v cells is not that they contact MNs directly, but rather disynaptically via an inhibitory IN (see Kiehn 2016 Nat Rev Nsci review). Some V0 and V3 neurons have been shown to project to MNs (as is stated in line 200- shown in Lanuza et al., 2004 and Zhang et al., 2008), but V3 cells also have been shown to project to non MN targets recent (Chopek Cell Rep paper), and V0 cells very possibly have many other downstream targets, this simply has yet to be investigated.</p><p>I really think this part of the manuscript should not be included due to its preliminary nature. In order to be included there should be some sort of Evx1 staining, or a functional assay in the V0v deficient mice used in the Talpalar 2012 paper in which issues with muscle stiffness are seen in the absence of V0v cells.</p><p>The reason I have such an issue with this is that the identity of these cells as belonging to the V0v population is so very circumstantial based on the data here. If it were to be published as is, V0v cells would immediately be cited, in the work of others, as key regulators of muscle stiffness. Even in this manuscript – line 398 of the discussion the authors say that a subset of labeled LDPNs &quot;are clearly V0v derived&quot;. This is a problem.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>Could the author present data or mention that they have tested that pure RΦGT mice injected with virus injected do not labelled any premotor neurons?</p><p><italic>Reviewer #3 (Recommendations for the authors):</italic></p><p>– It should be mentioned earlier in the Results that this study was performed in neonates.</p><p>– Green and blue in the immuno figures (i.e. sections in Figure 1Bi, Figure 2Ai) are difficult to differentiate between due to low contrast between the two.</p><p>– Line 9-11: Divergent is used before it is defined. It works in the initial sentence (line 9) but is a bit deceptive in the next (lines 10-11) as it seems to imply that divergent is referring only to antagonist motor pools.</p><p>– Lines 37-42: I suggest adjusting the framing of this section. Most of those questions have answers, as mentioned in the last line of the paragraph and in the Discussion. Instead, highlighting that the location and identities of many of these neurons is unknown may better set up the results to follow.</p><p>– Lines 146-148: It is not clear what the 22% refers to. It may be &quot;where they make up 22% of the neurons labelled&quot;?</p><p>– The schematic in Figure S4 A implies that the ventral divergent interneuron in cervical cord is a double jump from the forelimb motor pool. It is likely that there is a 'mis-connection' in the schematic – the ventral neuron should synapse with the forelimb motor neurons, rather than the dorsal neuron to the ventral neuron.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.70858.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>1) You should tone down the part on the V0v origin identification, or better do the appropriate characterization as suggested below;</p></disp-quote><p>We have extensively edited the sections related to the identification of V0v interneurons. We agree with the referees that we do not have sufficient evidence to pinpoint the genetic lineage of the long range descending interneurons and have toned this down considerably. As suggested by Reviewer#1 we performed further experiments using an Evx1 antibody to selectively label V0v interneurons. However, while good labeling was obtained in neonatal (P0) tissue, no labelling was detected in tissue of the age we used in the present study (P9-P10), in line with downregulation of transcription factors during development – a feature that also reduced our sensitivity in the Lhx1 assay, albeit to a lesser extent. To compound our uncertainty, a recent study was published while we were revising our manuscript identifying a class of dI2 derived interneurons with morphological features similar to the LDPNs described in our study. And we note that dI2 INs also express Lhx1. Given this further uncertainty and the reduced level of detection of Lhx1 in more mature tissue, we have toned down any conclusion that may suggest we have identified the cardinal class of divergent LDPNs. But we prefer to keep the data in the manuscript since we give evidence that at least some LDPNs are Lhx1-expressing (and thus likely V0v or dI2 as discussed). Specific changes in the text are detailed in the response to reviewers #1 and #3.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) You should further discuss the neurotransmitter characterization and eventually address this point experimentally if possible;</p></disp-quote><p>Identifying the transmitter phenotype of all the divergent interneurons would have required a different protocol, e.g. with a genetically (non-cre) labelled mouse. While the excitatory nature of the divergent LDPNs is sufficiently established, divergent premotor INs in the lumbar and thoracic region are certainly both inhibitory and excitatory. We now demonstrate this point further by adding supplementary figures showing double labelled terminals that are positive or negative for VGlut2 and are localized throughout the thoracic and lumbar cord (Figure 1—figure supplement 6). Further work will be required to understand whether divergent excitatory and inhibitory premotor interneurons are segregated and whether they belong to homogeneous cardinal classes or not.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3) You should further describe the rostro-caudal extension of the labelled pre-motoneurons.</p></disp-quote><p>We have added new figures where the distribution of premotor interneurons is shown along the rostrocaudal axis for lumbar, thoracic and sacral cord (see response to reviewer #3 and Figure 1-supplementary figure 4, Figure 2-supplementary figure 4 and Figure 3-supplementary figure 4).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4) Also, a functional aspect is clearly missing, the more you can address this in your revised version the more it will strengthen the paper, but we are aware that fully investigating this would require too much time and represents a significant amount of work if the data are not available yet.</p></disp-quote><p>The question on the function of these LDPNs is clearly one of our top priorities. Our manuscript is focused on the discovery of these peculiar cells, but determining their function is a necessary next step. The finding of a precise anatomical location of LDPNs and the availability of tracing methods will now allow us to access and manipulate these cells, but this is clearly a separate project and in our opinion could not be reduced to an appendage to an already dense manuscript.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #1 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>1. More detail regarding rostra-caudal location in the spinal cord should be given in all cases. First I think a Figure describing the location of the motor pools for the 4 injected muscles should be included- this could be in the supplementary data or it could go as a panel in Figure 1. This is needed so we have a clear idea of how far the axons of the PMIs project. In my experience a motor pool can span several lumbar segments. More specific information should also be provided regarding the location of the sections which contain the PMIs being described. I realize this is not an exact science after cutting tissue, but given your care in counting every third section, you should have a pretty good idea of which segment houses the neurons. This would be preferred over the current description of &quot;rostral cervical&quot; or equivalent.</p></disp-quote><p>We have now added as supplementary figures the rostro-caudal distribution of divergent premotor INs of lumbar segments, and the rostral-caudal distribution of all premotor INs of the thoracic and cervical regions (Figure 1—figure supplement 4, Figure 2—figure supplement 4 and Figure 3—figure supplement 4). We also provided the number of motoneurons infected from each pair of muscles injected, a number that we note is underestimated due to the toxicity of the virus for starter cells (supplementary file 1).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>In the Figures the number of MNs infected with either virus is typically quite low so I assume the sections are not particularly close to the middle of the infected motor pools?</p></disp-quote><p>In Figure 1, the section presented is close to the middle of the infected motor pools. Indeed, 2 MNs infected on one single section, as in the example of Figure 1, represents the typical count of MNs within a single section within the labelled motor column. This is due partly to the sparseness or rabies infection, but, more importantly, to the fact that each section is only 30 μm thick. We have also added supplementary figures (figure supplement 1,2,3 to Figures 1,2,3) showing more examples of lumbar sections following injections in the different motor pools. Amongst the examples shown, there are up to 8 MNs infected on a single section, but this is a rare occurrence (Figure 1—figure supplement 1A).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2. The amount of raw data shown is light. There is one immuno panel shown per Figure. I realize the take home message comes from the schematics, but it would be nice to see images of spinal sections with more single and double infected cells. Each immuno image contains just one divergent PMI and other than Figure 1 and 6 there are no other cells that seem to be infected with either the red or green expressing virus in the immuno image.</p></disp-quote><p>On Figure 1, we highlighted the 3 divergent interneurons on the image shown. Due to the relative low density of divergent premotor neurons and the thinness of the sections, it is impossible to have more divergent neurons in a single section, particularly in the thoracic and cervical cord. To provide a broader perspective of divergent premotor neurons, we added more examples of stained sections from lumbar, thoracic, and cervical spinal cord showing divergent neurons. These are presented in figure supplements 1,2,3 linked to figure 1, 2, and 3.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>3. I get a little uncomfortable with the data interpretation at the back end of the Results- particularly with the section titled Cervical LDPNs are excitatory- this is speculation and should not be in the title. The data simply shows 95% of these cells are not glycinergic.</p></disp-quote><p>We have modified the title of this section: “Cervical LDPNs are neither inhibitory nor cholinergic” (line 201) since only 1/21 cervical LDPNs was eGFP positive and none of them were ChAT positive.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>4. Related to point 3 – The next section is titled &quot;cervical premotor LDPNs likely arise from the V0v domain&quot;. In addition to V0 and V1 cells, Lhx1 is also expressed postmitotically in the dI2, dI4, dI6, and V2 populations, and even some V3 cells (Alanyick et al., 2012, Delile….Sagner biorxiv paper https://doi.org/10.1101/472415). It is thus extremely speculative to suggest that the V0v cells are the ones we are looking at here. Even more so when we factor in the finding that Lhx1 plays a key role in establishing GABAergic neuronal identity (Pillai et al., 2007).</p><p>Incidentally the current thinking on V0v cells is not that they contact MNs directly, but rather disynaptically via an inhibitory IN (see Kiehn 2016 Nat Rev Nsci review). Some V0 and V3 neurons have been shown to project to MNs (as is stated in line 200- shown in Lanuza et al., 2004 and Zhang et al., 2008), but V3 cells also have been shown to project to non MN targets recent (Chopek Cell Rep paper), and V0 cells very possibly have many other downstream targets, this simply has yet to be investigated.</p><p>I really think this part of the manuscript should not be included due to its preliminary nature. In order to be included there should be some sort of Evx1 staining, or a functional assay in the V0v deficient mice used in the Talpalar 2012 paper in which issues with muscle stiffness are seen in the absence of V0v cells.</p><p>The reason I have such an issue with this is that the identity of these cells as belonging to the V0v population is so very circumstantial based on the data here. If it were to be published as is, V0v cells would immediately be cited, in the work of others, as key regulators of muscle stiffness. Even in this manuscript – line 398 of the discussion the authors say that a subset of labeled LDPNs &quot;are clearly V0v derived&quot;. This is a problem.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer and agree that our evidence for the identification of V0 interneurons is not definitive. While preparing the revision, we attempted to identify Evx1 derived interneurons using a specific antibody (a gift from Columbia University). However, while we obtained good staining in young (P0) tissue, no staining was observed in P9 tissue, the age at which the tissue was analyzed in this paper. Having tried many different concentrations and incubation times, with similar results, we conclude that Evx1 expression is downregulated, even more than Lhx1 (see Figure 5—figure supplement 1) and therefore, a posteriori identification of the long descending projection neurons is not possible. Only genetic labelling could resolve the issue, but this would not be possible since we do not have the relevant mouse line. To compound our uncertainty, a recent study was published while we were revising our manuscript identifying a class of dI2 derived interneurons with morphological features similar to the LDPNs described in our study. And we note that dI2 INs also express Lhx1. Given this further uncertainty and the reduced level of detection of Lhx1 in more mature tissue, we have toned down any conclusion that may suggest we have identified the cardinal class of divergent LDPNs and re-written the related section, (now starting at line 219). But we prefer to keep the data in the manuscript, since we give evidence that at least some LDPNs are Lhx1-expressing (and thus likely V0v or dI2 as discussed). See also answer to reviewer #2 related to the same point.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #2 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>4) Could the author present data or mention that they have tested that pure RΦGT mice injected with virus injected do not labelled any premotor neurons?</p></disp-quote><p>We tested for leaks of the rabies glycoprotein by performing injection of an EnvA pseudotyped rabies virus in heterozygous RΦGT mice. We chose to use a pseudotyped rabies in order to test for ectopic expression of both the rabies glycoprotein and the TVA receptor (since these mice contain a floxed cassette expressing both proteins, Takatoh et al., 2013). The example data are shown in our preprint in which we describe a similar approach (Ronzano et al., 2021). In summary, following the injections we observed scant motoneuron labelling (1, 1 and 3 motoneurons in each of the animals tested), but no interneurons. Since we used pseudotyped rabies, the infection of some motoneurons shows that there is some ectopic expression of TVA in motoneurons that gave rise to motoneuron infection due to the extremely high affinity of EnvA for the TVA receptor. However, no trans-synaptic labelling was observed, indicating that any leak of the G protein, was not sufficient to sustain transsynaptic jumps. We now state this at the end of Methods section on intramuscular injections (lines 504-508).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #3 (Recommendations for the authors):</p><p>– It should be mentioned earlier in the Results that this study was performed in neonates.</p></disp-quote><p>This has been clarified and is now mentioned line 95 of the results.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>– Green and blue in the immuno figures (i.e. sections in Figure 1Bi, Figure 2Ai) are difficult to differentiate between due to low contrast between the two.</p></disp-quote><p>Colors are unfortunately difficult to pick when taking into account the many ways people can actually see them. We spend far too much time in lab meetings discussing colours. We had to pick two colors that everyone could easily differentiate for eGFP (green) and mCherry (pink), while keeping colors close to their fluorescent emission spectrum to avoid misunderstanding. Also, since we are focusing on double labelled neurons, the colocalisation of the two colors needed to give a completely different tint (white in our case). Blue remained the only option as the fourth color so that it could readily be differentiated from the three others. It is true that blue is more difficult to visualize, however, since blue is used for motoneuron staining, which is not the focus of the study, we thought that the combination used was the best option.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>– Line 9-11: Divergent is used before it is defined. It works in the initial sentence (line 9) but is a bit deceptive in the next (lines 10-11) as it seems to imply that divergent is referring only to antagonist motor pools.</p></disp-quote><p>Divergent is now defined clearly in the abstract before its use.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>– Lines 37-42: I suggest adjusting the framing of this section. Most of those questions have answers, as mentioned in the last line of the paragraph and in the Discussion. Instead, highlighting that the location and identities of many of these neurons is unknown may better set up the results to follow.</p></disp-quote><p>We have included the referee’s suggestion and, while keeping the list of questions, we have stressed that what is not known are the location and identities of the interneurons mediating synergies (lines 46-48).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>– Lines 146-148: It is not clear what the 22% refers to. It may be &quot;where they make up 22% of the neurons labelled&quot;?</p></disp-quote><p>This has been clarified (line 164).</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>– The schematic in Figure S4 A implies that the ventral divergent interneuron in cervical cord is a double jump from the forelimb motor pool. It is likely that there is a 'mis-connection' in the schematic – the ventral neuron should synapse with the forelimb motor neurons, rather than the dorsal neuron to the ventral neuron.</p></disp-quote><p>We thank the reviewer for this comment and apologize. Indeed, we had made a mistake in the schematic of what is now Figure 6—figure supplement 1A. This has now been corrected.</p></body></sub-article></article>