<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">eLife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">19848</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biophysics and Structural Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cell Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcription leads to pervasive replisome instability in bacteria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-63005"><name><surname>Mangiameli</surname><given-names>Sarah M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-14086"><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>Christopher N</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-7261"><name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>Paul A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-12713"><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>Houra</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9956-9640</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2">*</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Physics</institution>, <institution>University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Seattle</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Microbiology</institution>, <institution>University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Seattle</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Bioengineering</institution>, <institution>University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Seattle</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Genome Sciences</institution>, <institution>University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Seattle</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>van Oijen</surname><given-names>Antoine M</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff5"><institution>University of Wollongong</institution>, <country>Australia</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><email>pwiggins@uw.edu</email> (PAW);</corresp><corresp id="cor2"><email>merrikh@uw.edu</email> (HM)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>16</day><month>01</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e19848</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>07</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2017, Mangiameli et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mangiameli et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-19848-v2.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.001</object-id><p>The canonical model of DNA replication describes a highly-processive and largely continuous process by which the genome is duplicated. This continuous model is based upon <italic>in vitro</italic> reconstitution and <italic>in vivo</italic> ensemble experiments. Here, we characterize the replisome-complex stoichiometry and dynamics with single-molecule resolution in bacterial cells. Strikingly, the stoichiometries of the replicative helicase, DNA polymerase, and clamp loader complexes are consistent with the presence of only one active replisome in a significant fraction of cells (&gt;40%). Furthermore, many of the observed complexes have short lifetimes (&lt;8 min), suggesting that replisome disassembly is quite prevalent, possibly occurring several times per cell cycle. The instability of the replisome complex is conflict-induced: transcription inhibition stabilizes these complexes, restoring the second replisome in many of the cells. Our results suggest that, in contrast to the canonical model, DNA replication is a largely discontinuous process <italic>in vivo</italic> due to pervasive replication-transcription conflicts.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.001">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.001</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Author Keywords</title><kwd>replisome</kwd><kwd>DNA replication</kwd><kwd>replication-transcription conflicts</kwd><kwd>replication rates</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research Organism</title><kwd><italic>B. subtilis</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>E. coli</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="par-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000001</institution-id><institution>National Science Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MCB1243492</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Mangiameli</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>Christopher N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>Paul A</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>Houra</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>elife-xml-version</meta-name><meta-value>2.5</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Replication-transcription conflicts cause pervasive replisome instability.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The rapid and faithful replication of the genome is essential to cell proliferation. Although the replisome, the cellular machinery responsible for DNA replication, has been extensively studied both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">O'Donnell et al., 2013</xref>), fundamental questions remain about the dynamics and stability of the replication complex in the context of the living cell, where replication is one of a number of essential cellular processes competing for the genetic material as a template. This competition results in <italic>replication conflicts</italic>, the stalling or pausing of the replication process in the face of obstacles, including transcription and tightly-bound DNA-binding proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Baharoglu et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bidnenko et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Boubakri et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Brewer, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Dutta et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Marsin et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Merrikh et al., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Mirkin and Mirkin, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Soultanas, 2011</xref>). Genetic evidence from bacterial studies suggests these replication conflicts can routinely necessitate a replication-restart process at highly-transcribed regions and genes transcribed in the opposite orientation to replication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Merrikh et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Million-Weaver et al., 2015a</xref>). However, whether the replisome disassembles in response to conflicts, the rapidity of the restart process, and the frequency of such events per cell cycle are unknown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bruand et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gabbai and Marians, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Lovett, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Marsin et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Zavitz and Marians, 1992</xref>). The current estimates for the number of replication restart events per cell cycle vary greatly, with numbers ranging from one per cell cycle to one in seven generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Beattie and Reyes-Lamothe, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Cox et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Maisnier-Patin et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">McGlynn and Lloyd, 2002</xref>). However, estimates of less than one event per cell cycle are in conflict with the essentiality of the restart protein PriA in (<italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> essentiality is demonstrated in rapid growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Polard et al., 2002</xref>]), and the synthetic lethality of PriB and PriC proteins in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (PriA mutants as well as PriB PriC double mutants are largely unviable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gabbai and Marians, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Sandler and Marians, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Sandler et al., 1999</xref>]). These observations are consistent with a more frequent requirement for replisome reactivation after conflicts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gabbai and Marians, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Polard et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Sandler and Marians, 2000</xref>) and provide indirect evidence against the canonical model that replication is continuous <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p>Our previous investigations using chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) of replication restart proteins determined the chromosomal locations of conflicts in very large ensembles of cells (in the population average) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Merrikh et al., 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">2011</xref>). However, due to population averaging over cells in various stages of the replication conflict and restart process, ChIP experiments are poor reporters of potential conflict-induced changes to the structure of the replisome complex, the frequency of conflicts in a single cell, and the rapidity of the replication restart process. Therefore understanding the fundamental character of DNA replication and conflicts necessitates a single-cell approach in which conflicts can be observed and quantitatively characterized one event at a time. The molecular-scale stoichiometry of the replisome further necessitates experiments with single-molecule sensitivity to detect any potential changes to replisome structure.</p><p>We visualized the replication process in single cells by <italic>in vivo</italic> Single-Molecule Fluorescence Microscopy (SMFM). We characterized the stoichiometry and lifetimes of the replicative helicase complexes (and other replication proteins) in growing <italic>B. subtilis</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> cells. These measurements revealed that a significant percentage of cells only have a single helicase complex and that many of the complexes are short-lived. These results are consistent with pervasive disassembly of replisomes. We find that transcription inhibition both increases the lifetimes and stoichiometry of several core replisome components, suggesting that endogenous replication-transcription conflicts frequently lead to disassembly of replisomes, potentially every cell cycle. The replication-conflict induced disassembly model suggests that conflicts may limit the rate of replication. Consistent with this model, we find that the inhibition of transcription, and the amelioration of conflicts, increases the replication rate as measured by thymidine incorporation assays.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Replicative helicase and DNA polymerase stoichiometries are consistent with a single active complex in a large population of cells</title><p>To probe replisome stoichiometry in single cells with single-molecule sensitivity, we employ SMFM. In short, the discrete transitions in fluorophore intensity due to bleaching can be detected and analyzed to deduce the stoichiometry of localized fluorophores with single-molecule resolution. The quantitative characterization of the molecular stoichiometry of the replisome in living <italic>E. coli</italic> cells was recently realized by SMFM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Reyes-Lamothe et al., 2010</xref>), and this SMFM analysis has been applied in many other contexts (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Leake et al., 2006</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Ulbrich and Isacoff, 2007</xref>]). However, SMFM has not been exploited to determine the impact of conflicts on the replisome, the continuity of the replication process, or frequency of disruptions to the replisome within living cells.</p><p>We analyzed replisome stoichiometry of the replicative helicase DnaC in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>. DnaC was chosen due to its essential role in the replication process, extensive biochemical characterization, its relatively large and well-accepted stoichiometry in the replisome, and because it is the first replisome protein reloaded onto the DNA during PriA-dependent replication restart (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bruand et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Marsin et al., 2001</xref>). The replicative helicase is responsible for facilitating replication by unzipping the two strands of DNA ahead of the replication forks. <italic>In vitro</italic> biochemical studies, including X-ray crystallography, reveal that the helicase forms a homo-hexameric ring encircling the lagging strand of the DNA template (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bailey et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Fass et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kaplan et al., 2013</xref>). <italic>In vivo</italic> measurements of stoichiometry in <italic>E. coli</italic> further support this model in the context of the living cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Reyes-Lamothe et al., 2010</xref>). For our studies, we used a DnaC-GFP fusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>), which was expressed from its endogenous promoter, at its endogenous locus. The fusion protein localized to midcell in a replication-dependent manner, consistent with association with the replisome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Lemon and Grossman, 1998</xref>). Under our experimental conditions (minimal arabinose medium), the growth rate (and the replication rate—see below) of the DnaC-GFP strain was indistinguishable from that in wild-type cells (During rapid growth in Luria-Bertani medium, DnaC-GFP strain has a minor growth defect [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A and B</xref>]).</p><p>To measure the <italic>in vivo</italic> stoichiometry of the replisome proteins, we performed SMFM bleaching analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A and B</xref>, and, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplements 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">3</xref>). Most bacteria have a circular chromosome and a single origin of replication. After initiation, DNA replication progresses bi-directionally around the chromosome, with two active replisomes in each cell. The two forks in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> often localize to a single <italic>replication factory</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Lemon and Grossman, 1998</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). The small fraction of cells (~16%) having focus localization inconsistent with a replication factory were excluded from analysis. It is expected that in cells where the replication forks are co-localized, two replicative helicase complexes, and therefore 12 molecules of DnaC, will be localized to the factory (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). However, stoichiometry analysis of DnaC at the replication factory in cells undergoing active replication reveals that just under half the cells (41%) have a factory with only 6 DnaC proteins, corresponding to a single helicase complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D and E</xref>). The rest of the population (59%) has 12 DnaC proteins, corresponding to two active helicases. Note that incomplete protein labeling cannot account for the low helicase stoichiometry since two sub-populations with an integer multiple of fundamental hexameric stoichiometry are observed, as has also been previously reported in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Reyes-Lamothe et al., 2010</xref>). Western-blot analyses further confirm that &gt;98% of DnaC protein in the cell is indeed labeled with GFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s4">Figure 1—figure supplement 4</xref>). The incorrect determination of the bleaching step size also cannot account for these observations since results can be reproduced by using an <italic>in vitro</italic> measure of the fluorophore step size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s5">Figure 1—figure supplement 5</xref>). These results are consistent with a model where elongating replisomes are frequently disrupted and disassembled.<fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.002</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Estimated stoichiometry distributions for core replisome proteins in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Photobleaching of DnaC-GFP in a replication factory. (<bold>B</bold>) A typical intensity trace (blue) is shown for a DnaC-GFP focus. Stepwise transitions are observed as the fluorescent protein bleaches. The intensity is filtered using Change-Point analysis (red) which determines the intensity step-size corresponding to the bleaching of single fluorophores (complete stoichiometry calculation is demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplements 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">3</xref>, and detailed in the materials and methods section). The image mosaic above shows the time-averaged image of the focus over each intensity level. (<bold>C</bold>) A schematic of the replication factory consisting of either one or two assembled replisomes (black dots) in a diffraction-limited spot (green). (<bold>D</bold>) Histogram of estimated factory DnaC-GFP stoichiometry in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>. Error bars represent counting error. The observed distribution is well fit by a two Gaussian model (solid blue), representing a mixed population of single-helicase (6 DnaC molecules) and two-helicase (12 DnaC molecules) factories. (Analysis for N = 213 factories.) (<bold>E</bold>) Relative abundance of factories with one and two helicases. (<bold>F</bold>) Estimated stoichiometry distribution for PolC-YPet in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> shows two populations (N = 125). Peak stoichiometries for each population (dashed blue) were determined by maximum likelihood fitting with a two Gaussian model (solid blue) to be 2 and 4 copies. (Note: the distribution included a small fraction (~5%) of factories with stoichiometries greater than 10 copies which were removed for the purpose of fitting.) (<bold>G</bold>) Relative abundance of factories with 2 and 4 copies of PolC-GFP.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.002">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.002</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.003</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Growth curves for DnaC-GFP.</title><p>For growth curves, the optical density of wild type and <italic>dnaC-gfp</italic> strains growing in minimal arabinose medium at 30°C were monitored for 5 hr. Linear regression to OD<sub>600</sub> readings were used to determine doubling time. (<bold>A</bold>) The <italic>dnaC-gfp</italic> allele does not confer a detectable growth defect in minimal medium. OD<sub>600</sub> readings for a representative culture of wild type and <italic>dnaC-gfp</italic> cells. (<bold>B</bold>) Calculated doubling times and OD<sub>600</sub> readings show a small growth defect for the <italic>dnaC-gfp</italic> strain relative to wild type in LB medium.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.003">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.003</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig1-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Identification of foci and determination of raw focus intensity.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The phase-contrast image of the cells was segmented to identify the cell boundaries (orange) surrounding each cell mask (black). (<bold>B</bold>) The integrated raw focus intensity (blue) and scaled background intensity (green) are plotted for a bleaching experiment. The intensity trace is computed by subtracting the background from the raw intensity. (<bold>C</bold>) The summed image is shown in yellow. The outline of the cell mask is shown in blue. The intensity regions (red outline) are determined by watersheding the summed intensity to divide the image into local maxima. The focus positions (points) are determined by fitting a Gaussian distribution in the intensity regions. (<bold>D</bold>) The raw focus intensity is determined by summing the intensity in a mask centered on the locus position. The background is computed by calculating the average intensity inside the cell (blue outline) but outside the intensity region (red).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.004">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.004</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig1-figsupp2-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.005</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Stoichiometry calculation demonstrated for a DnaC-GFP focus.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Intensity tracking of a DnaC-GFP focus in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>. A decaying exponential (solid blue) is fit to the background subtracted raw intensities (blue points) traced over a series of 120 fluorescence images. The value of the exponential fit in the first frame is taken as the initial intensity of the DnaC-GFP complex (see methods). (<bold>B</bold>) The raw intensities (solid blue) are filtered (mean value in red) to reveal stepwise transitions. Summed fluorescence images of the DnaC-GFP complex are shown corresponding to each level detected by the filter in the image strip above the plot area. (<bold>C</bold>) The PPDD of the filtered intensities (red) reveals peaks at integral multiples of the unitary intensity step that would not be detectable in PPDD of the raw intensities (blue). (<bold>D</bold>) The power spectrum is used to identify the location of the first order peak in the PPDD which corresponds to the highest peak in the power spectrum (dashed gray). The unitary intensity step determined by the power spectrum corresponds to the spacing of the dashed gray lines in panels B and C.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.005">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.005</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig1-figsupp3-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.006</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Western blots for DnaC-GFP.</title><p>Cells produce complete DnaC-GFP fusion protein. Western blot analysis indicates that DnaC-GFP is fully synthesized, and that potentially truncated DnaC proteins lacking GFP are not detected. Individual lanes were normalized by total protein, and separate western blots were probed with either (<bold>A</bold>) anti-DnaC polyclonal antibodies or (<bold>B</bold>) anti-GFP polyclonal antibodies.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.006">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.006</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig1-figsupp4-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s5" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.007</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 5.</label><caption><title>Comparison of <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> step sizes for GFP.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Bleaching traces for two different surface immobilized GFP proteins. Inserts show the mean fluorescence images in the bleached and unbleached states. (<bold>B</bold>) Maximum likelihood fits to unitary intensity step distributions for isolated GFP <italic>in vitro</italic>. (<bold>C</bold>) Example <italic>in vivo</italic> unitary step distribution for DnaC-GFP in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> and its maximum likelihood fit. For all experimental conditions in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, unitary step distributions were peaked within 19% found <italic>in vitro</italic> value.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.007">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.007</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig1-figsupp5-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s6" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.008</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 6.</label><caption><title>Growth curves for PolC-YPet.</title><p>For growth curves, the optical density of wild type and <italic>polC-YPET</italic> strains growing in minimal arabinose medium at 30°C were monitored for 5 hr. Linear regression to OD<sub>600</sub> readings were used to determine doubling time. (<bold>A–B</bold>) No growth defect is observed for <italic>polC-ypet</italic> in either minimal or LB growth medium.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.008">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.008</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig1-figsupp6-v2"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Additionally, we analyzed the stoichiometry of PolC-YPet, a fluorescent fusion to the leading strand polymerase in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>. Even in rapid growth, the PolC-YPet fusion confers no growth defect relative to wild type cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s6">Figure 1—figure supplement 6</xref>). We again find that the stoichiometry distribution for co-localized replication forks consists of two sub-populations, with the second (~4 copies) centered at roughly twice the stoichiometry of the first (~2 copies) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref>). Importantly, these sub-populations were similarly proportioned to those observed for DnaC, with roughly 47% of factories having stoichiometries consistent with localization of PolC to only a single replication fork (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1G</xref>). This implied disassembly of the DNA polymerase, in addition to the replicative helicase, further suggests that the replisome is frequently disrupted.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Replicative helicase complexes are short-lived</title><p>To test the frequent-disruption model, we measured the lifetimes (replisome dynamics) of replicative helicase complexes. This model predicts that any given replisome complex is shorter lived than the time required to traverse each arm of the chromosome. We visualized the helicase complexes over twenty-two minutes to estimate their lifetimes. In the replisome dynamics measurements, cells were imaged at two-minute intervals such that the helicase complexes can be tracked (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>, left image strip; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>) over the twenty-two minute time frame without significant bleaching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>). Disassembly events correspond to the cooperative loss of all fluorophores simultaneously. Although photobleaching affects our measurement only minimally over the course of the experiment, it would not be possible to visualize the replisome at this frame rate for the entire cell cycle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>). Using the complex lifetimes observed during these short time courses, we estimate the disassembly rate, predicting that roughly five disassembly events occur during each cell cycle.<fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.009</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Helicase complex dynamics in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> captured by time-lapse imaging.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Typical frame mosaics for dynamics of the helicase in three conditions: Untreated (WT), rifampicin-treated (Rif) and <italic>rpoB*</italic> cells (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>). (In this context, WT refers to cells carrying the <italic>dnaC-gfp</italic> allele but not the <italic>rpoB*</italic> allele.) The helicase complexes in WT cells were observed to be intermittent: assembling and disassembling on the timescale of minutes. The helicase complexes in rifampicin-treated and <italic>rpoB*</italic> cells were observed to be more persistent. The complexes were tracked by an automated algorithm (red, detailed description in material and methods). (<bold>B</bold>) Distribution of helicase complex lifetime in WT (gray, N = 327 complexes), rifampicin-treated (blue, N = 183 complexes) and <italic>rpoB*</italic> (red, N = 165 complexes) cells. Data collection is limited to 22 min. (<bold>C</bold>) Probability of helicase survival as a function of helicase complex lifetime. Solid lines represent the empirical survival curves. Dashed lines show fits determined by maximum likelihood estimation. (<bold>D</bold>) Estimated number of disassembly events per 40 min of replication using the Poisson process model (see also <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Error bars were generated by simulating 100,000 distributions with the same rate parameter and number of complexes as the observed distribution. Simulated distributions were then fit, and the width of the rate parameter distribution was used to quantify the error.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.009">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.009</ext-link></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD1-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.010</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title><italic>B. subtilis</italic> lifetimes.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.010">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.010</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig2-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig2-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.011</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Automatic tracking of helicase complexes using focus scoring.</title><p>Under normal growth conditions, a typical trajectory resulting from dynamics analysis shows rapid appearance and disappearance of DnaC-GFP foci. Both rifampicin treatment and a <italic>rpoB*</italic> mutation results in longer-lived foci. Image strips to the left show raw images with dashed red lines indicating automatically detected trajectories. Corresponding filtered images to the right additionally show focus scores for all automatically detected foci. Scores printed in red indicate that the focus is included in a trajectory. Low scoring foci not selected for a trajectory are indicated in white. A detailed description of scoring and automated focus tracking is included in the materials and methods section.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.011">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.011</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig2-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.012</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Photobleaching minimally affects the complex lifetime experiments in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) To isolate the effects of photobleaching, cells are imaged with the same intensity and exposure as in the dynamics measurement, but with no delay between frames. Red line indicates equivalent of the 12 frame time course used in the dynamics measurement for <italic>B. subtilis</italic>. (<bold>B</bold>) Automated tracking used for the dynamics measurement was applied to the bleaching data. Survival curve (blue) shows the fraction of (N = 132) complexes that were successfully tracked through a given number of frames. Survival curve for dynamics experiment (gray) is shown for comparison. (<bold>C</bold>) 92% of complexes were traceable for 12 frames. In contrast, only 9% of complexes survive the duration of the dynamics experiment.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.012">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.012</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig2-figsupp2-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig2s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.013</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Disruption of PriA leads to loss of DnaC-GFP foci.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Survival assays show that the depletion of PriA is lethal on LB medium, but the control strains (which contain either the <italic>sgRNA-priA</italic> or <italic>dcas9</italic>) survive under both conditions. We find the same result using minimal arabinose medium. (<bold>B</bold>) Sample snapshots showing the full PriA CRISPR strain, and the control (no sgRNA), both after induction with 1% xylose for approximately two hours. (<bold>C</bold>) Disruption of PriA results in a decrease in the number of cells with DnaC-GFP foci from 43% in the control strain (N = 518 cells) to 13% in the CRISPR strain (N = 413 cells). Error bars represent counting error.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.013">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.013</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig2-figsupp3-v2"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>We found that the majority of foci are short lived with a mean lifetime of roughly 8 min. The observed distribution of lifetimes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1-data">Figure 2—source data 1</xref>) appears roughly exponential, suggesting that the occurrence of disassembly events in individual cells may be approximated as a Poisson process, providing a method for roughly estimating the number disassembly events per cell cycle. (For simplicity, we will ignore the distinction between focus loss and fork disassembly. We present a more complicated model, that treats the number of forks per focus explicitly (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3-data">Supplementary file 1</xref>), but this model depends on a number of untested assumptions.) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref> shows the model (dashed gray) and empirical (solid gray) survival curves for the helicase complex as a function of lifetime, where the model survival curve was fit using by maximum likelihood estimation. Multiplying the calculated rate of conflicts by the accepted 40 min long replication cycle predicts five conflicts per cell cycle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). It is important to note that this estimate has significant systematic uncertainty since it depends on the length of the replication cycle (which depends on growth conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Helmstetter and Cooper, 1968</xref>) as well as the assumption made in the modeling (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3-data">Supplementary file 1</xref>). A summary of the calculated parameters for the dynamics experiment is included in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>. Disassembly of the replisome on the time scale of single replication cycle is consistent with the instability inferred from the analysis of the estimated factory stoichiometry. Furthermore, the inferred frequency of disassembly events is significantly higher than expected from the continuous replication model.<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.014</object-id><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Parameters used in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> complex lifetime calculation. The parameters summarized above are defined as follows: T is the duration of the experiment, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of complexes interpreted to disassemble before the end of the experiment, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of complexes surviving the length of the experiment, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the minimum observable complex lifetime, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf4"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the empirical mean of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> observable lifetimes, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf6"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the calculated disassembly rate, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf7"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the calculated mean lifetime (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf8"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>), and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf9"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the calculated number of conflicts per 40 min of replication.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.014">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.014</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top"/><th valign="top"><p>T (min)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf10"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf11"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf12"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (min)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf13"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (min)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf14"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (min<sup>-1</sup>)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf15"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (min)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf16"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>Wild-Type</p></td><td valign="top"><p>22</p></td><td valign="top"><p>296</p></td><td valign="top"><p>31</p></td><td valign="top"><p>4</p></td><td valign="top"><p>10.4</p></td><td valign="top"><p>0.12</p></td><td valign="top"><p>8.3</p></td><td valign="top"><p>4.8</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>Rif-Treated</p></td><td valign="top"><p>22</p></td><td valign="top"><p>86</p></td><td valign="top"><p>97</p></td><td valign="top"><p>4</p></td><td valign="top"><p>12.9</p></td><td valign="top"><p>0.03</p></td><td valign="top"><p>29.2</p></td><td valign="top"><p>1.4</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p><italic>rpoB*</italic></p> </td><td valign="top"><p>22</p></td><td valign="top"><p>93</p></td><td valign="top"><p>72</p></td><td valign="top"><p>4</p></td><td valign="top"><p>12.5</p></td><td valign="top"><p>0.04</p></td><td valign="top"><p>22.4</p></td><td valign="top"><p>1.8</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>The frequent disassembly model further predicts that disrupting the restart protein PriA would prevent replisome reassembly, leaving disassembled replisomes in the majority of cells during a single cell cycle. To test this, we depleted PriA using CRISPR interference and visualized the number of cells with DnaC-GFP foci using snapshot imaging. Consistent with the frequent disassembly hypothesis, after inducing PriA depletion in liquid culture for roughly one doubling time, only 13% of cells had foci compared with the roughly 43% of cells with foci in the precursor strain to the PriA CRISPR, which lacks the sgRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Transcription inhibition increases the lifetimes of DnaC complexes</title><p>The results described support a model in which replication is discontinuous, with pervasive replisome disassembly and assembly dynamics. Our lab and others have shown that transcription, especially at the highly-transcribed rDNA or head-on genes (those transcribed in the opposite orientation relative to replication), results in potentially severe replication-transcription conflicts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">De Septenville et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Merrikh et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Million-Weaver et al., 2015b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Wang et al., 2007a</xref>). Our previous work measuring chromosomal regions where replication conflicts were most prevalent suggested that transcription is the main obstacle to replication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Merrikh et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, if transcription-induced conflicts were the principal mechanism responsible for replisome disassembly, we would predict that inhibition of transcription would result in a significant increase in replisome stability, either as assayed by stoichiometry or direct characterization of complex stability. To test this hypothesis, we perturbed transcription by (i) the treatment of cells with rifampicin (Rif), an antibiotic that directly inhibits transcription initiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sensi, 1969</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">1983</xref>) and (ii) <italic>rpoB</italic>* mutants which destabilize RNA Polymerase - DNA association and/or rDNA expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bartlett et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Maughan et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Zhou and Jin, 1998</xref>). It has been previously shown that <italic>rpoB</italic>* mutations reduce severity of conflicts significantly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Baharoglu et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Boubakri et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Guy et al., 2009</xref>). Here, we observed that rifampicin treatment dramatically increases the lifetime of helicase complexes. For instance, the number of complexes that persisted longer than 20 min increased from 9% in untreated cells to 53% in rifampicin treated cells and the calculated number of conflicts per cell cycle decreased by a factor of four (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). We also isolated and examined an <italic>rpoB</italic>* mutant strain and found results consistent with those obtained from rifampicin-treated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). This second transcription perturbation ensures that the observed increase in replisome stability is not an artifact of rifampicin treatment. In general, the increased stability of the helicase complex is consistent with the increased stability of the replisome.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>More cells have helicase and DNA polymerase stoichiometries consistent with two active replisome complexes upon transcription inhibition</title><p>To provide additional support for the transcription-dependence of the observed instability, we measured the stoichiometry of the helicase complexes in cells post transcription inhibition. An increase in replisome stability would predict an increase in the ratio of cells with two helicase complexes (12 DnaC molecules) relative to the number of cells with one helicase complex (6 DnaC molecules). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref> shows the distribution of protein stoichiometry at the factory in cells with transcription inhibited by rifampicin. The data are clearly consistent with the majority of cells having two active replisomes. There was a significant increase in the percentage of cells containing two stable helicase complexes relative to cells containing one helicase complex in the <italic>rpoB</italic>* mutant backgrounds as well (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A and D</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). A similar shift towards the higher order stoichiometry is observed for PolC after transcription inhibition by rifampicin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B and D</xref>). Increased stability of the polymerase was also observed in the <italic>rpoB*</italic> mutant background. These results strongly support the model that the frequent dissociation of the replicative helicase complex during each cell cycle results from replication-transcription conflicts.<fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.015</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>The effect of perturbations to transcription on stoichiometry distributions.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Helicase complex stoichiometry under three conditions: Untreated (WT), rifampicin-treated (Rif) and <italic>rpoB*</italic> cells. Probability densities are represented as Kernel Density Estimates (KDEs). In contrast to WT (gray), in both rifampicin-treated (blue) and <italic>rpoB*</italic> (red) cells, a significant fraction of single-helicase complexes (6 DnaC molecules) are lost with all observations being consistent with two-helicase complexes (12 DnaC molecules). (N = 70–117) (<bold>B</bold>) Estimated PolC stoichiometry in untreated (gray), rifampicin-treated (blue), and <italic>rpoB* (red) </italic>cells (N = 81–125). The low stoichiometry peak is no longer resolvable after rifampicin treatment or in the <italic>rpoB*</italic> mutant background, implying increased stability of the polymerase. (Note: rifampicin treatment also increased the exceedingly high fluorescence population which was again removed for the purpose of fitting.) (<bold>C</bold>) The relative abundance of helicase complex stoichiometries in cells with an ectopic inducible head-on replication-transcription conflict (<italic>lacZ</italic>). An IPTG (induction)-dependent increase in the single-helicase stoichiometry was observed, consistent with the reduction in factory stoichiometry being conflict-induced. (N = 108–174) (<bold>D</bold>) Summary of stoichiometry for transcription-inhibition and ectopic-conflict experiments. Estimates for the relative abundance of first and second order stoichiometry sub-populations are determined by fitting the distributions of estimated stoichiometries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.015">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.015</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig3-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.016</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Control for head-on conflict experiment.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The observed stoichiometry of DnaC-GFP was not significantly altered by the addition of IPTG. Compare to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Addition of <italic>lacZ</italic> (transcription on) in the co-directional orientation causes a small decrease to replisome stability.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.016">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.016</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig3-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.017</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Maximum likelihood fits to <italic>B. subtilis</italic> stoichiometry distributions.</title><p>The most likely two Gaussian model is selected varying the Gaussian means, widths and peak intensities. Maximum likelihood models (blue) and comprising Gaussians (dashed blue) are shown over histogram distributions. Error bars represent counting error. Calculated maximum likelihood fit parameters are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.017">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.017</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig3-figsupp2-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig3s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.018</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>A schematic model illustrating the effects of perturbations to transcription on replisome stability.</title><p>Amelioration of conflicts both by rifampicin or an <italic>rpoB*</italic> mutant increases the stability of the replisome. Conversely, addition of a highly transcribed gene in the head-on orientation decreases replisome stability.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.018">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.018</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig3-figsupp3-v2"/></fig></fig-group><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.019</object-id><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Maximum likelihood fit parameters for <italic>B. subtilis</italic> count distributions.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.019">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.019</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th><p>N</p></th><th><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf17"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (copies)</p></th><th><p>F<sub>L</sub> (error)</p></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><p>DnaC-GFP</p></td><td><p>213</p></td><td><p>6.2,11.2</p></td><td><p>41 (9.1)%</p> </td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaC-GFP + Rif</p></td><td><p>69</p></td><td><p>N/A, 12.1</p></td><td><p>0 (14)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaC-GFP <italic>rpoB*</italic></p> </td><td><p>60</p></td><td><p>N/A,11.1</p></td><td><p>0 (10.0)%</p> </td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaC GFP <italic>lacZ</italic> off</p></td><td><p>108</p></td><td><p>5.6,11.5</p></td><td><p>65 (5.6)%</p> </td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaC GFP <italic>lacZ</italic> on</p></td><td><p>174</p></td><td><p>6.0, 10.9</p></td><td><p>88 (3.2)%</p> </td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaC-GFP CD <italic>lacZ</italic></p> </td><td><p>185</p></td><td><p>5.8, 10.2</p></td><td><p>59 (9)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaC-GFP + IPTG</p></td><td><p>261</p></td><td><p>6.3,11.2</p></td><td><p>54 (11)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>PolC-YPet</p></td><td><p>125</p></td><td><p>2.2,4.9</p></td><td><p>47 (13)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>PolC-YPet +Rif</p></td><td><p>117</p></td><td><p>N/A, 4.4</p></td><td><p>0 (14)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>PolC-YPet <italic>rpoB*</italic></p> </td><td><p>81</p></td><td><p>N/A, 4.7</p></td><td><p>0 (9%)</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>A severe head-on conflict disassembles helicase complexes</title><p>Our data imply that replication-transcription conflicts increase the instability of replisome complexes. To test this model, we introduced an IPTG inducible <italic>lacZ</italic> gene (P<italic><sub>spank(hy)</sub>-lacZ</italic>) onto the chromosome in the head-on orientation (strain <italic>lacZ</italic>). We hypothesized that the induction of this ectopic conflict would further destabilize the replisome, leading to a reduction in the fraction of cells containing two intact helicase complexes relative to the control cells. As predicted, analysis of the single-molecule stoichiometry of DnaC in cells experiencing the additional severe engineered conflict (after addition of IPTG to induce <italic>lacZ</italic> expression) decreases the number of cells containing two intact helicase complexes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C and D</xref>; &gt;80% of cells contain only 6 rather than 12 molecules of DnaC in the factory), demonstrating that replication-transcription conflicts indeed lead to the disassembly of the replicative helicase complexes. We note that insertion of the <italic>lacZ</italic> gene in the co-directional orientation leads to a small, but detectable decrease in the number of cells with two assembled helicase complexes under induced conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). This is consistent with previous reports from our lab showing that highly-transcribed co-directional genes can lead to conflicts as assayed by ChIP-qPCR experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Merrikh et al., 2015</xref>). Control experiments showed that the addition of IPTG to cells without the <italic>lacZ</italic> construct did not cause a significant shift in the stoichiometry distribution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). These results (summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>, see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>) altogether reveal that the inferred instability and disassembly of the helicase complexes, and potentially the replisome, is transcription-dependent. This is illustrated schematically in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title><italic>E. coli</italic> replisome stoichiometry and dynamics corroborate transcription-dependent instability</title><p>Given the universality of conflicts, we hypothesized that other bacteria, outside of <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, should experience this phenomenon. We therefore investigated the stoichiometry and lifetimes of three different replisome proteins in a second bacterial model organism, <italic>E. coli</italic>. The replisome localization patterns are similar in <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>B. subtilis,</italic> where both replication forks typically co-localize to a single diffraction limited focus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Koppes et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Lau et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Mangiameli et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>We measured stoichiometries of three different <italic>E. coli</italic> replication proteins in the replisome complexes: the replicative helicase (DnaB), clamp loader (DnaX), and DNA polymerase (DnaE), both before and after transcription inhibition with rifampicin. For the <italic>E. coli</italic> experiments, the fluorescent fusions were constructed with distinct linkers to the fluorescent protein (YPet) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Reyes-Lamothe et al., 2010</xref>). As observed previously, there are 6, 3, and 3 molecules of DnaB, DnaX, and DnaE respectively in a significant proportion of the localized replisome foci in growing cells, corresponding to single a replisome complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). However, as predicted, rifampicin treatment results in the low stoichiometry population shifting towards the higher stoichiometry peak in the majority of these replisome foci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). This suggests that there are indeed two co-localized replication forks in the observed foci in <italic>E. coli</italic>, but that one replisome is often at least partially dissociated from the DNA due to replication-transcription conflicts.<fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.020</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title><italic>E. coli</italic> stoichiometry distributions shift similarly to those in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> under transcription inhibition.</title><p>Stoichiometry distributions are represented using kernel density estimation (N = 53–178 factories). (<bold>A</bold>) Estimated DnaB stoichiometry suggests that two hexameric helicases are present in most replication factories in the absence of transcription (blue). However, under normal conditions (gray) roughly half of factories consist of only a single helicase. (<bold>B</bold>) Transcription-inhibition increases the number of factories having higher DnaX stoichiometry. (<bold>C</bold>) Transcription-inhibition increases the number of factories having higher DnaE stoichiometry. (<bold>D</bold>) Estimates for the relative abundance of first and second order stoichiometry sub-populations are determined by fitting the distributions of estimated stoichiometries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.020">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.020</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig4-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.021</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Maximum likelihood fits to <italic>E. coli</italic> stoichiometry distributions.</title><p>The most likely two Gaussian model is selected varying the Gaussian means, widths and peak intensities. Maximum likelihood models (blue) and comprising Gaussians (dashed blue) are shown over histogram distributions. Error bars represent counting error. Error bars represent counting error. Calculated maximum likelihood fit parameters are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.021">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.021</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig4-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.022</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Comparison of <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> step sizes for YPet.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Bleaching traces for two different surface immobilized YPet proteins. Inserts show the mean fluorescence images in the bleached and unbleached states. (<bold>B</bold>) Maximum likelihood fits to unitary intensity step distributions for isolated YPet <italic>in vitro</italic>. (<bold>C</bold>) Example <italic>in vivo</italic> unitary step distribution for DnaB-YPet in <italic>E. coli</italic> and its maximum likelihood fit. For all experimental conditions in <italic>E. coli</italic>, unitary step distributions were peaked within 18% found <italic>in vitro</italic> value.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.022">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.022</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig4-figsupp2-v2"/></fig></fig-group><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.023</object-id><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Maximum likelihood fit parameters for <italic>E. coli</italic> count distributions.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.023">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.023</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th><p>N</p></th><th><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf18"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (copies)</p></th><th><p>F<sub>L</sub> (error)</p></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><p>DnaB-YPet</p></td><td><p>146</p></td><td><p>6.6, 11.6</p></td><td><p>59 (15)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaB-YPet + Rif</p></td><td><p>53</p></td><td><p>N/A, 12.1</p></td><td><p>0 (13)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaX-YPet</p></td><td><p>125</p></td><td><p>2.8, 5.8</p></td><td><p>53 (13)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaX-YPet + Rif</p></td><td><p>154</p></td><td><p>2.8, 5.7</p></td><td><p>10.6 (17)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaE-YPet</p></td><td><p>178</p></td><td><p>2.8, 5.8</p></td><td><p>46 (15)%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>DnaE-YPet + Rif</p></td><td><p>144</p></td><td><p>2.8, 5.6</p></td><td><p>9.8 (9.3)%</p> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>Our replisome-stoichiometry measurements in <italic>E. coli</italic> predict that there is pervasive disassembly of replisomes in this species as well and therefore these protein complexes should also have short lifetimes. Because there are only 3 molecules of DnaE or DnaX, lifetimes of the localization of these components to the replisome foci cannot be reliably measured due to bleaching of a significant fraction of the fluorophores. However, because of the higher number of DnaB molecules in each complex, the helicase lifetimes can be measured over a twenty-minute time series without bleaching significantly affecting the results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>). The <italic>E. coli</italic> helicase complex lifetime measurements show that the majority of DnaB complexes are indeed short lived with a mean lifetime of about 9 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Figure 5—source data 1</xref>). Furthermore, treatment with rifampicin extends the lifetime of these complexes, increasing the number of complexes that persist for 20 min (or longer) from 21% to 46% and the predicted number of conflicts per (40 min) replication cycle decreases from roughly 4 to 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.024</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Helicase complex dynamics in <italic>E. coli</italic> captured by time-lapse imaging.</title><p>Helicase complex dynamics in <italic>E. coli</italic> captured by time-lapse imaging. (<bold>A</bold>) Typical frame mosaics for dynamics of the helicase in two conditions: Untreated (WT), rifampicin-treated (Rif). The helicase complexes in WT cells were observed to be intermittent: assembling and disassembling on the timescale of minutes. The helicase complexes in rifampicin-treated cells were observed to be more persistent. The complexes were tracked by an automated algorithm (red). (<bold>B</bold>) Distribution of helicase complex lifetime in WT (gray, N = 217 complexes), rifampicin-treated (blue, N = 77 complexes). Data collection is limited to 20 min. (<bold>C</bold>) Probability of helicase survival as a function of helicase complex lifetime. Solid lines represent the empirical survival curves. Dashed lines show fits determined by maximum likelihood estimation. (<bold>D</bold>) Estimated number of disassembly events per cell cycle using the Poisson process model (see also <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). Simulating 100,000 distributions with the same rate parameter and number of complexes as the observed distribution generated error bars. Simulated distributions were then fit, and the width of the rate parameter distribution was used to quantify the error.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.024">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.024</ext-link></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD2-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.025</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label><caption><title><italic>E. coli</italic> lifetimes.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.025">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.025</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig5-data1-v2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig5-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.026</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Photobleaching minimally affects the complex lifetime experiments in <italic>E. coli</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) To isolate the effects of photobleaching, cells are imaged with the same intensity and exposure as in the dynamics measurement, but with no delay between frames. Red line indicates equivalent of the 11 frame time course used in the dynamics measurement. (<bold>B</bold>) Automated tracking used for the dynamics measurement was applied to the bleaching data. Survival curve (blue) shows the fraction of complexes that were successfully tracked through a given number of frames (N = 214). Survival curve for the dynamics experiment (gray) is shown for comparison (<bold>C</bold>) 86% of complexes were traceable for 11 frames. In the dynamics measurement, only 21% of complexes survive the duration of the experiment.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.026">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.026</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig5-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig5s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.027</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Disruption of restart using temperature sensitive DnaC.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) DnaB-YPet imaged at 2 min intervals in strains with and without the <italic>dnaC2</italic> allele at 37°C (non-permissive for the temperature sensitive strain). In the temperature sensitive strain, either a complex is observed in the first frame (e. g. cells 1–3) or the cell generally does not develop complexes during the time course (e. g. cell 4). When a complex is observed, it most commonly disappears before the end of the time course. Once disappearance has occurred (red arrows), no new stable complexes are observed in the majority of cells (85%). In contrast, the wild type strain (e. g. cells 5–6) shows intermittent foci (as observed in the dynamics experiments at 30°C), and complexes may be assembled later in the time series. (<bold>B</bold>) Probability of observing a focus as a function of time in cells where at least one trajectory is observed. DnaC is involved both in initiation of replication at the origin and the rescue of stalled forks. The theoretical ‘Null hypothesis’ curve (red) assumes a continuous 40 min replication cycle imaged for a random 20 min window. However, the probability of observing a focus in the <italic>dnaC2</italic> allele (blue, N = 72) decreases more quickly suggesting that the helicase is disassembled prior to completion of replication. Additionally, in the wild type strain, the probability of observing a focus is roughly independent of time, indicating that both disassembly and re-assembly events are present.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.027">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.027</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig5-figsupp2-v2"/></fig></fig-group><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.028</object-id><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Parameters used in <italic>E. coli</italic> complex lifetime calculation. The parameters summarized above are defined as follows: T is the duration of the experiment, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf19"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of complexes interpreted to disassemble before the end of the experiment, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf20"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of complexes surviving the length of the experiment, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the minimum observable complex lifetime, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf22"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the empirical mean of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf23"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> observable lifetimes, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf24"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the calculated disassembly rate, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf25"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is the calculated mean lifetime (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf26"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>), and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf27"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the calculated number of conflicts per 40 min of replication.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.028">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.028</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top"/><th valign="top"><p>T (min)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf28"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf29"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf30"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (min)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf31"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (min)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf32"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (min<sup>-1</sup>)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf33"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> (min)</p></th><th valign="top"><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf34"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>Wild-Type</p></td><td valign="top"><p>20</p></td><td valign="top"><p>171</p></td><td valign="top"><p>46</p></td><td valign="top"><p>4</p></td><td valign="top"><p>9.1</p></td><td valign="top"><p>0.12</p></td><td valign="top"><p>9.4</p></td><td valign="top"><p>4.2</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>Rif-Treated</p></td><td valign="top"><p>20</p></td><td valign="top"><p>42</p></td><td valign="top"><p>35</p></td><td valign="top"><p>4</p></td><td valign="top"><p>12.3</p></td><td valign="top"><p>0.05</p></td><td valign="top"><p>21.6</p></td><td valign="top"><p>1.8</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>We further show that disruption of the restart process leads to permanent disappearance of the helicase complex. DnaC is required for the loading of the replicative helicase (DnaB), and is recruited to rescue stalled replication forks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sandler, 2000</xref>). Here, we disrupted the restart process using a temperature-sensitive version of the helicase loader protein (<italic>dnaC2</italic> allele) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Reyes-Lamothe et al., 2008</xref>). We visualized DnaB-YPet in the <italic>dnaC2</italic> mutant under non-permissive conditions (37°C) using the same technique as in the dynamics experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2A</xref>). Helicase complexes observed in the first frame disassembled before the end of the time course in 86% of cases. Furthermore, new complexes rarely developed (15% of the time). To further quantitate this data, we calculate the probability of observing a focus as a function of time in cells that have at least one focus. In the strains containing the <italic>dnaC2</italic> allele, this probability decreases throughout the time series, consistent with failure to restart (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2B</xref>). This observed loss of foci is too rapid to be explained by replication termination (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2B</xref>, null hypothesis). In contrast, the probability of observing a focus in the wild type strain (at 37°C) does not depend strongly on time, indicating that the replisome is in steady state due to its ability to restart. These data are consistent with reports suggesting that <italic>dnaCts</italic> alleles are ineffective for synchronization because replication does not proceed to completion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Ferullo et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Maisnier-Patin et al., 2001</xref>). Overall, these findings are consistent with both our observations in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> and our interpretations of the results of the <italic>E. coli</italic> stoichiometry measurements, suggesting that <italic>E. coli</italic> cells also experience pervasive replisome instability due to transcription.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Transcription inhibition increases the rate of replication</title><p>To test the replisome-instability model, we measured replication rates <italic>in vivo</italic> by radioactive thymidine incorporation assays in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, in both wild-type (without DnaC-GFP) and DnaC-GFP strains. It takes roughly 40 min to replicate 4.2 and 4.6 Mb of DNA in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> and <italic>E. coli,</italic> respectively; at the 500 bp/s −1 kb/sec measurements from <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kornberg, 1992</xref>), which assume replisome stability during a replication cycle. However, our observation of frequent conflicts (during which the replisome stalls) predicts that the <italic>in vivo</italic> rates should increase if conflicts are reduced. To test the prediction of our model, we measured the rate of thymidine incorporation with and without rifampicin treatment, as well as in the <italic>rpoB*</italic> strains – two different conditions where we observed the stabilization of the replisome. As predicted, both transcription perturbations (rifampicin and <italic>rpoB*</italic>) increase the replication rate: Thymidine incorporation rates in rifampicin-treated cells are roughly 60–65% higher than that measured for untreated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). The consistency of the incorporation rate in the <italic>rpoB*</italic> strain with rifampicin treatment suggests that the observed increase in rates is probably <italic>not</italic> an artifact of changes in nucleotide uptake in rifampicin-treated cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Wang et al., 2007b</xref>). This interpretation is also supported by the insensitivity of <italic>rpoB*</italic> strains to rifampicin treatment with regards to thymidine incorporation rates. In addition, measurements of the thymidine incorporation rates in DnaC-GFP cells provide further evidence that DnaC-GFP is functional during slow growth: We did not detect any difference in thymidine incorporation rates between the wild-type and the DnaC-GFP strain under these conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). These results provide further evidence that the rate of replication is severely inhibited by transcription in wild-type cells.<fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.029</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Thymidine incorporation assays determine the effect of transcription on replication rate.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) DNA replication rates increase upon transcription-inhibition and in <italic>rpoB*</italic> strains. Thymidine incorporation assays were used to measure the relative rates of DNA replication in WT and DnaC-GFP strains, with (blue bars) and without (gray bars) perturbations to transcription by rifampicin treatment (Rif) or <italic>rpoB*</italic> cells. Note that <italic>rpoB*</italic> strains are resistant to rifampicin and therefore show no additional increase in replication rate after rifampicin treatment. (<bold>B</bold>) DNA replication rates increase in cells grown in minimal arabinose medium, relative to glucose, where transcription of rRNA and other ribosomal protein genes is higher.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.029">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.029</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig6-v2"/></fig></p><p>The observed transcription-induced replication conflicts should be at least partially due to the ribosomal RNA and protein genes. We previously showed that replication restart proteins preferentially associate with these regions during fast growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Merrikh et al., 2011</xref>). Although somewhat counterintuitive, our model predicts that replication rates should be slower during fast growth due to conflicts with transcription. To test this prediction, we measured replication-rates in slow and fast growth conditions. Despite the faster growth rate of <italic>B. subtilis</italic> on minimal glucose versus arabinose medium, we observe significantly higher thymidine incorporation rates in arabinose compared to glucose, where ribosomal RNA and protein genes are much more highly expressed and are a major source of conflicts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Mirouze et al., 2011</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The basic principles underlying the mechanism of genome replication are thought to be well established, especially in bacteria. Yet, a great part of this work has relied on a combination of <italic>in vitro</italic> reconstitution, from which potentially essential cellular factors and/or processes are absent, or <italic>in vivo</italic> ensemble measurements which are sensitive only to ensemble-averaged cellular behavior. Based primarily on these results and the absence of significant evidence to the contrary, DNA replication was thought to be largely a continuous process that initiates at the origin and moves processively to the terminus. However, there is a contradiction to this widely-accepted model: Our laboratory and others have demonstrated that the replication process can be disrupted from a number of concurrent processes including transcription. The resulting replication conflicts have dire consequences in the absence of rapid and efficient replication restart. If transcription is both an obstacle to the replisome and active throughout the cell cycle, how can the replication process be continuous? If conflicts can occur, what is their frequency? And if these events are frequent, what are the consequences for the replication machinery?</p><p>Using <italic>in vivo</italic> single-molecule fluorescence microscopy techniques in combination with a genetic and cell-biology toolkit developed for studying replication conflicts, we measured the stoichiometry and lifetimes of replication complexes in single cells with single-molecule resolution. The results of the <italic>replicative helicase complex stoichiometry</italic> experiments could be explained by a number of models. It is conceivable that the replisome traverses one of the two arms of chromosome much more rapidly than the other, reaching the terminus and disassembling much earlier than the second replisome complex. However, genomic DNA analyses have already demonstrated that in growing cells, the copy number of the two arms are roughly equal, implying that the average rate of replisome movement on the two arms is about the same (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Srivatsan et al., 2010</xref>). Another model for the low observed replisome stoichiometry is the observation of individual forks, as has previously been reported in <italic>E. coli</italic>. But, our own quantitative characterization of replisome localization reveals factory-like (co-localized) replisome positioning for 80% of the cell cycle in both <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, which cannot account for the low observed stoichiometry in our own experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Mangiameli et al., 2017</xref>) or previous work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Reyes-Lamothe et al., 2010</xref>). The data presented here is most consistent with the model that elongating replisomes are frequently disrupted (roughly 50% of the time) and disassembled during a single replication cycle.</p><p>The direct visualization of the replisome with SMFM in two different bacterial species strongly suggests that the replisome is frequently destabilized by transcription. The observation that these inferred disassembly events are transcription-dependent not only suggests that these events correspond to replication-transcription conflicts previously observed via biochemical means, but also that vast majority of replication conflicts are the result of transcription.</p><p>Our findings suggest that replicating cells often possess only a single active replisome complex. Together, the stoichiometry and dynamics of the replicative helicase and polymerase complexes as well as the replication rate measurements suggest that the replisome is subject to pervasive disassembly and reassembly events. These observations provide a potential explanation for the essentiality of replication restart proteins – at least under growth conditions where rDNA and ribosomal protein genes are relatively highly expressed and PriA is essential.</p><p>Due to the low intensity of single fluorescent molecules, both the stoichiometry and dynamics experiments are technically challenging. In addition, the bacteria themselves are potentially subject to photo damage at the intensities required to resolve single molecules, and this photo damage itself affects cellular processes and replication in particular. Therefore, it is essential to consider these measurements in the context of additional corroboratory biochemical and genetic evidence. The essentiality of restart proteins and the measurement of the replication rates provide independent lines of evidence for the pervasive disassembly model.</p><p>We propose that the number of replication-transcription conflicts is significantly greater than previously suggested: far from being rare, we infer from the data presented here that conflicts are <italic>generic</italic> and occur multiple times per cell cycle. If so, then these encounters frequently compromise the integrity of the replisome, leading to discontinuity in the process of DNA replication. These observations therefore present a new model for the canonical states of DNA replication, arguing against the well-accepted model that the process of replication is highly continuous <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Growth curves</title><p>Cell cultures were grown for 16 hours in minimal arabinose (or LB) medium supplemented with threonine and tryptophan until cells reached log phase growth. Cells were then diluted back to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.1 and monitored at 25 min intervals.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Western blots</title><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic> cells harboring the <italic>dnaC-gfp</italic> allele as well as the isogenic wild type were grown to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.3 and then harvested. Total protein was prepared in SDS loading buffer, and the same volume was loaded on each of the lanes shown. Western blots were probed in Odyssey blocking buffer (Li-Cor P/N 927–40100) with either rabbit anti-DnaC polyclonal antibodies (1:5000 dilution), or rabbit anti-GFP polyclonal antibodies (1:7500 dilution). Blots were then probed with Li-Cor secondary anti-rabbit IR800 antibody at 1:15000 dilution. Blots were scanned and quantified on a Li-Cor Odyssey.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Strain list and strain constructions</title><p>All strains used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl5">Table 5</xref>. The strain containing the IPTG-inducible <italic>lacZ</italic> (P<italic><sub>spank(hy)</sub>-lacZ</italic>) construct (HM1316), was built by transformation of the plasmid (pHM149) encoding <italic>thrC</italic>::P<italic><sub>spank(hy)</sub>-lacZ</italic> into strain HM262. The <italic>polC-ypet</italic> strain (HM604) was constructed by transforming pHM93 (3` <italic>polC</italic>-LEGSG-<italic>ypet</italic> A206K) into wild-type JH642 <italic>B. subtilis</italic> cells. <italic>rpoB*</italic> mutants were isolated by plating 3 ml of saturated <italic>B. subtilis</italic> cells harboring <italic>dnaC-gfp</italic>, or <italic>E. coli</italic> cells harboring <italic>dnaB-ypet</italic>, on LB +0.3 µg/ml rifampicin plates. Revertant colonies were isolated and their <italic>rpoB</italic> gene was sequenced. Rifampicin revertant strains having mutations within <italic>rpoB</italic> were considered <italic>rpoB</italic>* strains. We examined mutants harboring the H482Y mutation which is in cluster 1 of the <italic>rpoB</italic> gene. The strains containing this mutation do not display growth defects on LB or LB supplemented with rifampicin, as was also previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Maughan et al., 2004</xref>). HM2475 (PriA CRISPR precursor) was constructed by transforming the plasmid pHM273 into HM262 to incorporate the sgRNA at <italic>amyE</italic>. The full PriA CRISPR resulted from transformation of gDNA from HM1500 into HM2475. Additional control strain HM2387 containing only dcas9 resulted from transformation of gDNA from HM1500 into HM1. The <italic>E. coli</italic> strain containing the <italic>dnaC2</italic> allele was constructed by P1 transduction of <italic>dnaB-ypet</italic> from HM1391 into PAW542.<table-wrap id="tbl5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.030</object-id><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Strains used in this study.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.030">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.030</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top"><p><bold>Strain #</bold></p> </th><th valign="top"><p><bold>Genotype</bold></p> </th><th valign="top"><p><bold>Species</bold></p> </th><th valign="top"><p><bold>Reference</bold></p> </th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>HM1</p></td><td valign="top"><p><italic>trpC2 pheA1</italic>; wild-type</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>Smith et al.</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM262</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaC-gfp-spec</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>Lemon et al.</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM1312</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaC-gfp rpoB</italic> (H482Y)</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>This study</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM1316</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaC-gfp-spec thrC:</italic>:P<italic><sub>spank(hy)</sub>-lacZ::erm</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>This study</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM604</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>polC-ypet-mls</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>This study</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM1275</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>polC-ypet rpoB</italic> (H482Y)</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>This study</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM1500</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>lacA::P<sub>xl</sub>-dcas9-mls</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>Peters et al.</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM2387</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p>HM1 <italic>lacA::P<sub>xl</sub>-dcas9-mls</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>This study</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM2475</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaC-gfp-spec amyE::P<sub>veg</sub>-sgRNA-priA-cat</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>This study</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM2486</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaC-gfp-spec amyE::P<sub>veg</sub>-sgRNA-priA-cat lacA::P<sub>xl</sub>-dcas9-mls</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>B. subtilis</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>This study</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM1318</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p>wild-type (AB1157)</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>E. coli</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>Dewitt et al.</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>HM1319</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaB-ypet-kan</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>E. coli</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>Reyes-Lamothe et al.</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>PAW912</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaX-ypet-kan</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>E. coli</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>Reyes-Lamothe et al.</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>PAW909</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaE-ypet-kan</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>E. coli</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>Reyes-Lamothe et al.</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>PAW542</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaC2 thrA::tn10-tet</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>E. coli</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>Reyes-Lamothe et al.</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><p>PAW1182</p></td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>dnaB-ypet-km dnaC2 thrA::tn10-tet</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p><italic>E. coli</italic></p> </td><td valign="bottom"><p>This study</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Localization of replisome components</title><p>We ensure that fluorescent foci localize near midcell during active replication, consistent with localization to the replication factory. Stationary phase cells harboring replisome fusions do not have foci indicating that replication is required for localization and that the observed foci are not a result of protein aggregates.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Cell preparation for microscopy</title><p>The following protocol was used to prepare cells for microscopy: (i) Cultures were grown overnight in a shaking incubator at 30°C. (ii) <italic>E. coli</italic> was cultured in M9-minimal media (1X M9 salts, 2 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.2% Glycerol, 100 μg/ml each Arginine, Histidine, Leucine, Threonine and Proline and 10 μg/ml Thiamine hydrochloride). (iii) <italic>B. subtilis</italic> was cultured in minimal arabinose media (1x Spitzizen’s salts (3 mM (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 17 mM K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 8 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 1.2 mM Na<sub>3</sub>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>O<sub>7</sub>, 0.16 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>-(7H<sub>2</sub>O), pH 7.0), 1x metals (2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.7 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>,. 05 mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 µM ZnCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 µM FeCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 µg/ml thymine-HCl) 1% arabinose, 0.1% glutamic acid, 0.04 mg/ml phenylalanine, 0.04 mg/ml tryptophan, and as needed 0.12 mg/ml tryptophan.) (iv) Overnight cultures at an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.3–0.9 were diluted back to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.2 and incubated again for about 2 hr until they reached approximately OD<sub>600</sub> 0.4. (v) Cells were then concentrated by a factor of 10 immediately before imaging by centrifugation. (vi) 1 μL of concentrated cell culture was spotted on a thin 2% (by weight) low-melt agarose pad (invitrogen UltraPure LMP Agarose, Cat. no. 16520–050). (vii) The sample was sealed on the slide under a glass cover slip using VaLP (a 1:1:1 Vaseline, lanolin, and paraffin mixture.) (viii) For rifampicin treatment, a final concentration of 100 μg/mL was added to both the agarose pad and the liquid culture immediately prior to imaging. (ix) Cells were imaged at 30°C.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Microscope configuration</title><p>Imaging was performed on a custom-built inverted fluorescence microscope. To avoid light loss at the phase plate, cells were imaged through a Nikon CFI Plan Apo VC 100 × 1.4 NA objective. An external phase plate (Ti-C CLWD Ph3 Annulus Module) was inserted into the beam path during phase-contrast imaging and retracted for fluorescence imaging to avoiding decreased signal due to the neutral density annulus on the phase plate. The microscope focus was controlled by an IR-autofocus system. In short, an infrared beam was reflected off the coverslip-media interface and the back reflection is detected by a position-sensitive detector (PSD). The displacement was then processed using a PID feedback system to control the z-height of the piezo stage.</p><p>Fluorophores were excited by laser illumination. A Coherent Sapphire 50 mW 488 nm or 150 mW 514 nm CW laser is used to excite GFP and YPet, respectively. We expand the beam diameter is expanded to provide even illumination over the field of view. The excitation intensity is controlled via an Acousto-Optic Tunable Filters (AOTF, AA Opto-Electronic AOTFnC-400.650). Images were collected on an iXon Ultra 897 512 × 512 pixel EMCCD camera. The microscope system is controlled by Micro-Manager.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Imaging protocol for bleaching analysis</title><p>A single phase contrast image is followed by a stack of 300 ms fluorescence images (settings summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl6">Table 6</xref>). Fluorescence images are continued until all foci become photobleached (~120 frames). The imaging time is sufficiently fast that photodamage to the cells is not an issue. Because YPet is brighter, and the 514 nm laser tends to excite lower cellular background intensities (see section 1.4 of supplement for calculation of background), we were able to image at lower laser power.<table-wrap id="tbl6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.031</object-id><label>Table 6.</label><caption><p>Microscopy parameters.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.031">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.031</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th><p>Laser power at objective (mW)</p></th><th><p>Exposure time (ms)</p></th><th><p>Med. background 1st frame (electrons/pixel)</p></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><p>Bleaching (GFP)</p></td><td><p>1.3</p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>87</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Bleaching (YPet)</p></td><td><p>0.4</p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>24.1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Lifetime (GFP)</p></td><td><p>1.1</p></td><td><p>600</p></td><td><p>76</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Lifetime (YPet)</p></td><td><p>0.1</p></td><td><p>600</p></td><td><p>4.5</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Bleaching analysis</title><p>The method for determining the <italic>in vivo</italic> stoichiometry of fluorescent-fusion proteins in active replisomes is outlined below. Our protocol is based-upon the method described recently by Reyes-Lamothe et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45"> (Reyes-Lamothe et al., 2010</xref>) with a number of modifications described in detail below.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Segmentation of the cells from the phase-contrast image</title><p>Cells are initially imaged in phase contrast for the purpose of segmentation, the computational process of determining cell boundaries from an image (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2A</xref>). Imaging for bleaching analysis is sufficiently fast (36 s) that the cells do not grow appreciably during the process, allowing only a single phase image to be collected at the beginning of data acquisition. We then used the Wiggins Lab’s custom segmentation tool (<italic>superSegger)</italic> on the phase image to generate <bold>cell masks</bold> for analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kuwada et al., 2013</xref>). The Wiggins Lab's custom image processing software (superSegger) and documentation is available at the following link: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mtshasta.phys.washington.edu/website/SuperSegger.php">http://mtshasta.phys.washington.edu/website/SuperSegger.php</ext-link></p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Location and scoring of foci in the summed image</title><p>Firstly, to remove xy sample drift, all fluorescence images in the stack are aligned against the first. This corrected alignment is retained for the rest of analysis. Analysis of cell fluorescence begins by computing the summed image, which constitutes of summing the intensity values over all frames in the image stack and then applying a one pixel radius Gaussian blur. We then watershed the conjugate of the summed image to generate sub-regions around each intensity maximum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>). Taking the union of these regions with the cell masks excludes regions external to the cells from analysis. These sub-regions will be called intensity regions. The intensity profile in each intensity region is modeled by a Gaussian distribution:<disp-formula id="equ1"><mml:math id="m1"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mover><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>where, the peak amplitude Gaussian intensity is defined by parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf35"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf36"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> defines the background intensity. The focus position is parameterized by <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf37"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> and the focus width by parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf38"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Within each intensity region, a three pixel radius circular region is centered on the position of the maximum-intensity pixel. The Gaussian intensity model is then fit inside the union of each intensity region and the corresponding circular region. The resulting focus position from the fit <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf39"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is then retained throughout the analysis.</p><p>Once the fit has been performed in each region in the cell, these foci are excised from the cell image using a mask radius of 3 pixels. We compute the per-pixel mean and standard deviation of the intensity (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf40"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf41"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>respectively) in the remaining cell area. We define the background-subtracted intensity:<disp-formula id="equ2"><mml:math id="m2"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mo>≡</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>In general, we found that the background-subtracted intensity had better statistical properties than the Gaussian fit parameters.</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Focus scores</title><p>The focus score <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf42"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is a measure of the statistical significance of a focus. The integrated background-subtracted intensity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf43"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>in a region (radius three pixels and area <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf44"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) is computed. We define the score:<disp-formula id="equ3"><mml:math id="m3"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>where the factor of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf45"><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the denominator accounts for extended area <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf46"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> over which the intensity is integrated. The intensity noise at each pixel is assumed to be uncorrelated and therefore the expected standard deviation in the integrated intensity in area <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf47"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf48"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>All foci scoring two or smaller tended to be located randomly throughout the cell, inconsistent with localization to the replication factory. We therefor retain foci with scores greater than two for further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Determination of the focus and background intensities in individual frames</title><p>Returning to the stack of fluorescence images, we compute the raw focus intensity (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf49"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>in each frame by summing the intensity within a disk (radius three pixels) centered on the position of the focus (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf50"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, determined in the previous step). The per-pixel background intensity was again computed by excising each locus (using a mask radius three pixels) and then computing the mean intensity over the remaining cell area (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf51"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We define the focus intensity (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf52"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) as the difference between the raw focus intensity and the total background intensity within the area of the 3-pixel-radius mask (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf53"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="equ4"><mml:math id="m4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>This background subtraction method is illustrated for a focus in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>, Panel B. The intensity, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf54"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is interpreted as the intensity of the fluorophores at the focus for each frame and plotted to form bleaching traces.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Analysis of bleaching traces</title><p>A key step in the determination of the single-molecule protein stoichiometry is the determination of the fluorescence intensity of a single fluorescent molecule, which M. Leake has called the unitary step (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Leake et al., 2006</xref>). Two independent methods were used to determine this fluorescence intensity: (i) The intensity of GFP and YPet molecules were measured <italic>in vitro</italic> and (ii) the fluorophore intensity was inferred for each complex <italic>in vivo</italic> from the analysis of the bleaching curves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Leake et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>In both cases, the intensity must be inferred from a noisy intensity trace. The method for trace analysis of Leake et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Leake et al., 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Reyes-Lamothe et al., 2010</xref>) was:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Compute the smoothed intensity trace <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf55"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p>2. Compute the Pairwise Probability Density Distribution (PPDD) of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf56"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p>Compute the Power Spectrum of the PPDD</p></list-item><list-item><p>4. Infer the unitary intensity step (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf57"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) from the power spectrum</p></list-item><list-item><p>Fit the intensity trace to an exponential to determine the initial intensity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf58"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p>6. The inferred stoichiometry is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf59"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="s4-14"><title>Smoothing the intensity trace</title><p>Because the raw intensity data has too large a variance to directly detect steps by analysis of the pairwise differences, Leake et al. applied an Edge-Preserving Chung-Kennedy (SED) Filter to smooth the intensity data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith, 1998</xref>). Instead, we use a parameter-free change-point (CP) analysis to idealize the bleaching curves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Wiggins, 2015</xref>). The analysis of simulated intensity traces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>) with similar statistical properties to the observed data illustrates our method for calculating stoichiometry, and the performance of our CP idealization compared to the SED filter. We provide a more detailed discussion of the comparison of the CP method to competing methods in the following sections.<fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.032</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Stoichiometry calculation applied to simulated data.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Simulated intensity data. A bleaching experiment was simulated to demonstrate the performance of the CP Algorithm against the SED filter. The noise and trace length were chosen to closely approximate the observed data. (<bold>B</bold>) Idealized intensity traces. The data (blue dots) is identical to Panel a. True simulated mean (Truth) is shown in blue. There is excellent agreement between the truth (blue) and the CP idealization (red). The SED filtered trace is shown in green. (<bold>C</bold>) Pairwise intensity difference probability distribution (PDPD). The black dotted lines represent multiples of the true step-size 1 AU. (<bold>D</bold>) Power spectrum of the PDPD. The largest peak in the power spectrum is selected as the unitary step (red dotted). The true step-size is also shown (black dotted).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.032">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.032</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig7-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.033</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>CP versus SED filters in unity step determination.</title><p>The performance of the CP versus the SED filter is measured by a histogram of the relative size of the unitary step in simulated data. The CP idealization clearly results in a sharper distribution about the true value (unity).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.033">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.033</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig7-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig7s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.034</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Finding the initial intensity.</title><p>We simulated two approaches for determining the initial intensity of the trace: Exponential Fit and Highest-Level. The probability of the estimated intensity is shown relative to the true initial intensity. The Highest Level method is clearly biased from below relative to the Exponential Fit method which is centered around the true value (unity).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.034">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.034</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig7-figsupp2-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig7s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.035</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>CP vs KV filtering algorithm.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Eight typical datasets (black dots) are plotted with the true mean (blue) and idealizations using both the KV (red) and CP (green) algorithms. The simulated data consisted of 10,000 Gaussian processes with unit variance simulated for 120 frames each. The over segmentation generated by the KV algorithm is clearly visible in the (false) transitions shown in the third, fourth, and fifth traces. No false steps were observed in these eight traces using the CP algorithm. (<bold>B</bold>) The total number of states for the 10,000 simulated datasets is shown for the true mean and the CP and KV idealization. All datasets consisted of a single true level. The true number of states (one) was found 95% of the time using the CP algorithm and only 55% of the time using the KV algorithm.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.035">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.035</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig7-figsupp3-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig7s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.036</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Change point detection efficiency.</title><p>The efficiency of change-point detection was measured for fixed-lifetime and variable-lifetime (constant decay rate) steps. In both cases the mean lifetime was equal to the inverse observed decay rate (41 frames). For fixed-lifetime steps (blue), the detection efficiency is essentially unity for relative step-size greater than two. (We define the relative step size as the mean intensity difference divided by the standard deviation: Δµ/σ.) For variable-lifetime steps (red), the detection efficiency is reduced by the existence of a small fraction of short-lived steps.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.036">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.036</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig7-figsupp4-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig7s5" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.037</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 5.</label><caption><title>Performance of CP algorithm on simulated data.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Distribution of estimated stoichiometry for simulated data with true stoichiometries from 4–14 proteins. (Integer stoichiometries between 3 and 15 were simulated. For clarity only the distributions for even stoichiometries are plotted.) (<bold>B</bold>) Mean estimated stoichiometry as a function of true stoichiometry. The estimated stoichiometry slightly overestimates the true stoichiometry (by a fraction of a protein).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.037">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.037</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="postscript" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-fig7-figsupp5-v2"/></fig></fig-group></p></sec><sec id="s4-15"><title>Pairwise distribution</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C</xref> shows the PPDD for the raw simulated data (blue), CP idealization (red) and SED filtered data (green). The black dotted lines are placed at integral multiples of the true step size (1 AU). Note that the peak widths in the CP idealization are computed from the Fisher Information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Wiggins, 2015</xref>). The first peak in the pairwise distribution of the CP idealization is centered around the true value (1 AU), showing excellent agreement between the calculated and the true step sizes.</p></sec><sec id="s4-16"><title>Power spectrum</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7D</xref> shows the Power Spectrum of the PPDD. Again, the CP idealization shows a stronger enrichment in power at the true intensity step-size (1 AU). Note that the power spectrum is not an FFT, but rather a continuous representation of the Fourier transform of discrete data that is commonly applied in this context (e.g. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Little and Jones, 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-17"><title>Determination of the unitary step</title><p>Leake et al. report that they select the first peak (with respect to increasing intensity) in power spectrum that is four standard deviations above the noise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Leake et al., 2006</xref>). Clearly this method is <italic>ad hoc</italic> since lower noise would resolve higher harmonics of the unitary step, as are easily visible in the power spectrum for the CP idealization. Instead, we selected the largest peak in the power spectrum, as illustrated by the dotted red line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7D</xref>). This approach resulted in the reliable determination of the unitary step in simulations. We show a histogram estimating unitary step size (relative to the true step size) in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>. In our simulations, the Leake et al. method (using the SED filter) resulted in a greater number of failures to correctly identify the unitary step. Most worrying of all, the SED filter lead to a fairly frequent identification of the unitary step as roughly twice the true unitary step, leading to anomalous counts of complexes with half the true stoichiometry.</p></sec><sec id="s4-18"><title>Determination of the initial focus intensity</title><p>Because the probability of a fluorescent protein bleaching is proportional to the number of unbleached proteins, we expect the raw intensities follow a decaying exponential profile. To determine the initial focus intensity <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf60"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, we fit the background subtracted raw intensities to a model of the form<disp-formula id="equ5"><mml:math id="m5"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>optimizing both <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf61"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the characteristic bleaching time <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf62"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We found that this method was more reliable than simply taking <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf63"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as the highest level of the filter based on simulated intensity traces (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s2">Figure 7—figure supplement 2</xref>). Although the highest level is less noisy than the exponential fit, we find <italic>highest level</italic> to be biased from below.</p><p>The mechanism for the bias generation for the highest-level method is as follows: The initial decay in intensity is too rapid to resolve all bleaching steps at high stoichiometry and therefore bleaching steps are merged at the beginning of the bleaching process. As a result the highest-level method typically averages over the first few true levels in the bleaching process. We note that, in general, both the highest-level and exponential fitting techniques produced acceptable results.</p></sec><sec id="s4-19"><title>Data selection</title><p>After automatic processing, all traces are refereed by hand. We remove cells where:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>1. There were segmentation errors.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Replisome foci have strong ellipticity (ellipticity &gt;1.2).</p></list-item><list-item><p>3. The unitary intensity step size was not within a factor of 2.5 of the <italic>in vitro</italic> value.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Unitary peaks in the PPDD and its power spectrum not &gt;10% larger than competing peaks.</p></list-item><list-item><p>5. Exponential fit to determine the initial intensity is &gt;30% from the initial intensity measurement.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Focus localization was inconsistent with a replication factory.</p></list-item></list><p>While applying these data-selection rules had no qualitative effect on our results and conclusions, the selection rules did remove data points that were clearly aberrant from the analysis. All datasets were repeated on at least two occasions, with similar results.</p></sec><sec id="s4-20"><title>Analysis of final count distributions</title><p>We divide the initial focus intensity by the unitary step size for a large number of cells, obtaining final count distributions for each strain. Many of these distributions were bi-modal. We fit all count distributions using a two-Gaussian mixture model where the Gaussian widths, means (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf64"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and peak amplitudes were optimized. To avoid binning the data, we use a maximum likelihood process to determine the best-fit parameters. The fractional population of factories in the low and high stoichiometry populations (F<sub>L</sub> and F<sub>H</sub>) is proportional to the area of the model Gaussians peaked near the appropriate values. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref> for maximum likelihood fits to all stoichiometry distributions not shown in the main figures. The fit parameters are represented graphically in main <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5D</xref>, and numerically in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref> for <italic>B. subtilis</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic>, respectively. Note that the error in F<sub>H</sub> and F<sub>L</sub> was calculated by simulating 10,000 stoichiometry distributions with the same statistical properties as the corresponding empirical distribution. The width of the distribution of F<sub>L</sub> (or F<sub>H</sub>) based on the simulated distributions was taken as the error.</p></sec><sec id="s4-21"><title>Kernel density estimates</title><p>For plotting the probability densities for protein stoichiometry, we used a Kernel Density Estimate (KDE) in order to avoid binning the data (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Reyes-Lamothe et al., 2010</xref>]). A Gaussian kernel was used, and the optimal bandwidth was selected by minimization of the asymptotic mean integrated squared error.</p></sec><sec id="s4-22"><title>Discussion of filtering algorithms</title><p>Because the raw intensity data has too large a variance to directly detect steps by analysis of the pairwise differences, Leake et al. applied an Edge-Preserving Chung-Kennedy (SED) Filter to smooth the intensity data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith, 1998</xref>). Although we could also detect intensity steps using the SED filter, this approach appeared to have two important shortcomings: (i) The filter had what we considered poor performance under many scenarios (described below) and (ii) the filter uses two <italic>ad hoc</italic> filtering parameters which must be optimized. In our hands, the results of the SED filter were not particularly robust to parameter choice.</p><p>To eliminate the need to specify <italic>ad hoc</italic> parameters for the data analysis, we attempted to apply an objective parameter-free step-detection algorithm developed by Kalafut and Visscher (KV) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kalafut and Visscher, 2008</xref>). The KV filter uses a Change-Point Algorithm for determining steps in a signal. The KV filter, as described, has two important shortcomings with respect to the current application: (i) The signal is assumed to have constant variance for all states (false) and (ii) the statistical test for step determination uses the Bayes Information Criterion (BIC), which we have recently demonstrated does not result in optimal performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Wiggins, 2015</xref>), resulting in either over or underfitting depending on the application.</p><p>We describe the adaptation of Change-Point Methods to biophysical applications elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Wiggins, 2015</xref>). In short, our CP algorithm is parameter free. The performance of the CP Algorithm and the SED filter applied to simulated intensity data is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref> shows the raw (unfiltered) data. Panel B shows the truth (blue, true mean intensity simulated), the simulated data (blue dots), CP idealization (red) and the SED filter (green). The performance of the CP Algorithm correctly determines the position of all steps except one and is qualitatively superior to the performance of the SED filter.</p><p>Note that in general the step determination at high intensity is imprecise due to the large variance (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf65"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>∝</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). For higher intensities than those shown in the simulation, the CP algorithm cannot reliably determine the steps, although the CP idealization represents an optimal guess (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Wiggins, 2015</xref>). One might worry that these imprecisely-determined high-intensity steps could result in a significant degradation in the pairwise distribution function, but there are two natural mechanisms for the suppression of their contribution: (i) The short duration of these steps in frames and the large std both result in a small Fisher Information. (ii) Furthermore the weighting in the PPDD is proportional to the lifetime of the step. Therefore these short steps have a much weaker role in determining the single-fluorophore intensity than the long-lived and less noisy steps at the end of the bleaching trace (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Wiggins, 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-23"><title>The KV versus CP filter</title><p>We discovered that the KV filter does not apply a statistical test with suitable frequentist statistical performance to evaluate the existence of new intensity levels. To compare the performance of the KV and CP filters, we simulated intensity data with no transitions. For simplicity, we used a Gaussian process with unit variance for 120 frames for 10,000 independent simulated datasets. We then idealized this data using both the KV and CP filters. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s3">Figure 7—figure supplement 3</xref> for the analysis of 10 typical simulated traces and their idealization using both the KV and CP filters. The KV algorithm has a Type I error (finding at least one false transition) 45% of the time! (See the bar plot of algorithm performance in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s3">Figure 7—figure supplement 3B</xref>) This result implies that data analysis is performed with a 55% confidence level in a Neyman-Pearson Hypothesis Test. Such a small confidence level is clearly unacceptable from a canonical frequentist perspective. In contrast, the Type I error rate for the CP filter is 5%, corresponding to a 95% confidence level. (Although the above simulation describes a scenario under which the KV filter leads to significant over-fitting, in other circumstances, the KV filter can result in significant under-fitting and therefore should not be used for quantitative applications.)</p></sec><sec id="s4-24"><title>Simulation: Step detection efficiency using the CP filter as a function of step size</title><p>There are a number of important factors that influence the resolution of the CP filter. The ability of the CP algorithm to resolve steps depends principally on the lifetime of the states and the step size between states. To estimate the resolution of the CP filter in step determination, we first simulated transitions from one to zero flours (the final bleaching step) using a constant lifetime equal to the inverse observed intensity decay rate (t<sub>b</sub> = 41 frames). The Fixed-Lifetime curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s4">Figure 7—figure supplement 4</xref> shows the detection efficiency for the bleaching step as a function of step size. In our experiments, the step-size to the standard deviation ratio (Δµ/σ) is between 2 and 3. Under these conditions, the step detection efficiency is essentially unity. Of course, the last bleaching step has a distribution of lifetimes, rather than a fixed lifetime equal to the mean lifetime. Next we simulated photobleaching events with variable lifetimes (i.e. stochastic lifetimes with a bleaching rate of k = 1/41 frames). The variable-lifetime curve shows the detection efficiency for the bleaching step as a function of step size. Unlike the Fixed-lifetime curve, the variable-lifetime curve never reaches unity due to the existence of a small subset of events that are not long enough to resolve. In spite of the inability to resolve very short-lived states, the detection efficiency is still roughly 90% in the simulation at the observed signal to noise ratio (Δµ/σ ≈ 2.5).</p></sec><sec id="s4-25"><title>Simulation: Data generated by different protein stoichiometries</title><p>To test the overall consistency of the analysis approach, we simulated intensity traces using the observed ratio of step size to standard deviation (Δµ/σ ≈ 2.5 and assuming linear scaling of the variance with intensity) and state lifetime (k = 1/41 frames<sup>−1</sup>) for different stoichiometries between 3 and 15 proteins. The distribution of estimated stoichiometries for selected simulated stoichiometries is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s5">Figure 7—figure supplement 5A</xref>. The mean estimated stoichiometry as a function of the true stoichiometry is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s5">Figure 7—figure supplement 5B</xref>. Our simulated analysis results in a very small (&lt;0.5) bias in the mean estimated stoichiometry and a mono-modal distribution of stoichiometry around the true value. The widths of the distributions are roughly consistent with those observed in experiment.</p></sec><sec id="s4-26"><title>Imaging protocol for replication-complex lifetime</title><p>Cells are imaged at two-minute intervals, taking both a phase and fluorescence image at each time point. For lifetime measurements, where the foci must be tracked over a longer time scale, bleaching is undesirable. In order to minimize both bleaching and possible photodamage to the cells (as indicated by abnormally slowed elongation), we find a longer (600 ms) exposure at lower laser intensity to be optimal. Imaging may continue for about 20 min before focus visibility is significantly impaired by photobleaching, and we note that cells were elongating exponentially regardless of laser use (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="s4-27"><title>Analysis of replisome-complex lifetime</title><p>Replisome foci were observed to undergo step-like transitions between on and off states. We attempted to use the same analysis used for the bleaching experiments. But, this analysis is designed around the assumption that the replisome undergoes minimal motion. Over the 20 min timescale, the replisome can undergo significant movement and therefore we needed to find an alternative approach.</p><p>The phase contrast image for each time point is segmented to determine cell boundaries. For analysis of the fluorescence images, we used a locus-tracking engine that we have described previously to track and quantify loci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kuwada et al., 2013</xref>). In short, foci are detected and fit to a Gaussian point-spread function in each frame. Up to four foci are identified per cell. Each focus is assigned a score (as described in the section titled ‘Focus scores’ above). The larger the score the more confidence the algorithm has identified a true focus (versus a stochastic fluctuation is fluorescence intensity). Trajectories of replication complexes are then constructed by grouping foci based on the following rules: (i) No foci in the trajectory may score lower than 3. (ii) A focus cannot move more than 350 nm between frames. (iii) The mean of all scores in the trajectory must be a minimum of 4. (iv) At least one focus in the trajectory must score five or higher. (v) Trajectories may continue through a single frame with no (or score <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf66"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) focus provided that all of the above conditions are still met. (vi) Trajectories must last more than three frames. (vii) Included foci must show localization consistent with the replisome.</p><p>We have experimented with various rules for grouping foci, but the above best reproduced trajectories qualitatively consistent with the raw images. Foci scoring three or lower appeared randomly throughout the cell, inconsistent with protein bound to the replication factory. Higher cutoffs were found to lead to gaps in the locus trajectories that lasted for a single frame, consistent with stochastic fluctuations in intensity. We have also required that trajectories last a minimum of three frames. Shorter-lived events are consistent with events observed in cells without active replication, and therefore we believe that these events are also predominantly the result of stochastic fluctuations in fluorescence intensity. Note that, regardless of our choice of grouping, trajectories were always longer lived (on average) for rifampicin treatment and the <italic>rpoB*</italic> mutation.</p><p>For a disassembly event, foci must disappear for more than two minutes to be counted as disassembly events. (i.e. we require the off state to last for more than one frame to remove most intensity-fluctuation induced false negative events.) A typical trajectory corresponds to a cell containing a focus track with foci scores 3–7 transitioning to a cell with no foci or low-scoring foci (≤2 appearing in inconsistent locations in the cell from frame to frame, consistent with false positive focus identification due to photon shot noise (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref> for examples of scored trajectories).</p></sec><sec id="s4-28"><title>Controlling for bleaching in replisome-complex lifetime experiments</title><p>To exclude the possibility that disappearance events are due to photobleaching, we image the cells with the same settings as in the replisome-complex lifetime experiment, but remove the delay between frames. Under these conditions the cells will be dosed with the same amount of light, but over the shortened time scale we would expect bleaching to occur before disassembly due to a conflict. The results confirm that minimal bleaching occurs over the time course. The algorithm successfully tracks 92% and 86% of complexes for the duration of the lifetime experiments in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic>, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s4-29"><title>Estimation of conflict number based on replisome complex lifetime</title><p>Modeling replisome disassembly events as a Poisson process, the distribution of focus lifetimes was fit using an exponential distribution. The likelihood for the focus lifetime is:<disp-formula id="equ6"><mml:math id="m6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>|</mml:mtext><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mtext>exp</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>min</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>k</italic> is the disassembly rate, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf67"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>min</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the shortest observable lifetime (in our case, 4 min since we disregard events lasting less than three consecutive frames). Since some foci persist throughout the experiment, duration <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf68"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, we must also compute the survival probability. The survival probability is (one minus the cumulative probability):<disp-formula id="equ7"><mml:math id="m7"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Pr</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>exp</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>min</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The disassembly rate <italic>k</italic> was estimated using <italic>Maximum Likelihood Estimation</italic>. The sum of the log-likelihood for the observed lifetimes is:<disp-formula id="equ8"><mml:math id="m8"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>|</mml:mtext><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mtext>|</mml:mtext><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Note that the sum in the first term is taken only over the observable lifetimes while the second term accounts for long-lived states. Maximizing the likelihood leads to the following expression for the maximum likelihood estimate of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf69"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="equ9"><mml:math id="m9"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf70"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of lifetimes that were at least the duration of the experiment and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf71"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of observed lifetimes and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf72"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>\bar</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>\tau </mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is their empirical mean. A summary of the parameters used in the replisome-complex lifetime is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref> (<italic>B. subtilis</italic>) and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref> (<italic>E. coli</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-30"><title>Protocol for temperature-sensitive DnaC experiment</title><p>Cells were prepared for microscopy as described above, and imaged under non-permissive conditions using an objective heater (Bioptechs). Imaging started roughly 10 min after cells were placed on the heated objective. Trajectories were generated using the algorithm developed to measure complex lifetime, and foci included in these trajectories counted towards the probability of observing a focus as a function of time. The theoretical ‘null-hypothesis’ curve is generated by assuming a random segment of continuous (no disassemblies due to conflicts) 40 min replication cycle is visualized for 10 frames at 2 min intervals. We include all possible outcomes where a focus is visible in the first frame.</p></sec><sec id="s4-31"><title>Protocol for PriA CRISPR experiment</title><p>Due to the leakiness of the CRISPR system, PriA is already depleted three-fold before induction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Peters et al., 2016</xref>), and we note that the strain grew unusually slowly in minimal arabinose (however, the precursor strain without the sgRNA grew normally). The CRISPR system was fully induced by the addition of 1% xylose in liquid culture roughly 2 hr before imaging to allow the remaining PriA to be diluted out. DnaC-GFP foci were then identified from snapshot images (one phase contrast and one fluorescence image at each field of view). The number of cells with foci was quantified using the following rules: (i) the focus must score three or higher, (ii) the elipticity of the focus must be smaller than 1.2, and (iii) the focus localization must be consistent with the replisome. Because of the leakiness of the CRISPR, we compare to the number of foci in the precursor strain (does not contain sgRNA), also with the addition of 1% xylose. Time-lase microscopy was not productive because the PriA CRISPR strain formed few DnaC-GFP foci even without induction.</p></sec><sec id="s4-32"><title>Protein purification</title><p>Purified GFP was gifted to us by the Asbury Lab at the University of Washington. For purification of YPet, DH5α <italic>E. coli</italic> cells were transformed with the plasmid ROD49 carrying an arabinose-inducible his-tagged mYPet with the monomeric A206K mutation. (This plasmid was the gift of R. Reyes-Lamothe.) The expression was induced at an optical density (OD<sub>600</sub>) of 0.1 with 0.2% L-arabinose for 1 hr at 37°C. Cells resuspended in 20 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 0.5 M NaCl, 25 mM imidazole were lysed by sonication. Lysate was cleared by centrifugation for 1 hr at 18,000 x <italic>g</italic>, and proteins were purified by fast protein liquid chromatography (ÄKTA System, GE Healthcare) using a metal-chelating affinity column (HisTrap HP, GE Healthcare). YPet-containing fractions eluted at high imidazole concentrations were identified by absorbance at 280 nm and confirmed using a microplate photometer to verify the correct excitation and emission spectra.</p></sec><sec id="s4-33"><title>Preparation and imaging of surface immobilized protein</title><p>For imaging, we dilute purified protein in PBS to the point where individual molecules are visible during fluorescence microscopy. We fill a 10 µL flow cell (constructed by sticking a KOH cleaned coverslip to a base slide with two strips of two sided tape) with the PBS-fluorescent protein solution and allow it to sit upside down for 10 min, binding the proteins to the coverslip. The channel is then rinsed with 400 µL of PBS to clear any remaining fluorescent protein from the background.</p><p>We image and the isolated protein using the same settings as the <italic>in vivo</italic> bleaching experiments, and analysis proceeds as for live cell bleaching experiments (the only difference being that we do not take a phase contrast image and intensity regions are identified from the fluorescent images alone). See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s5">Figure 1—figure supplement 5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2A</xref> for example isolated protein bleaching traces. We arrive at the unitary intensity step distribution for known single fluorophores. As a consistency check, we confirm that the <italic>in vivo</italic> unitary intensity step distributions for all strains are highly similar to those found <italic>in vitro</italic>. We find agreement of the peak values for <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> distributions to within 19% for GFP and 18% for YPet.</p></sec><sec id="s4-34"><title>Thymidine incorporation assays</title><p>Exponentially growing cells raised in minimal MOPS medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Wang et al., 2007b</xref>) supplemented with either 1% arabinose or glucose, at 30°C, were split at OD 0.2 into equal 1.2 ml cultures. Cells continued to grow until they reached OD 0.3., at which point 30 µg/ml rifampicin was added to one of the cultures for 2 min. Next, 38 µCi <sup>3</sup>H-thymidine (Perkin Elmer 70–90 Ci/mMol) was added to both cultures, and timepoints were taken at 2 min intervals by pipetting 200 µl of cells into 3 ml of ice-cold 10% TCA. Samples were collected on glass microfiber filters (GE Healtthcare #1825–025), and washed 3x with 5% TCA prior to detection on a liquid scintillation counter.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to Seemay Chou for purification of the YPet protein and Patrick Nugent for building of the P<italic><sub>spank(hy)</sub>-lacZ</italic> construct. This work was funded by the National Science Foundation grant MCB1243492.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf1"><p>The authors declare that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>SMM, Conceptualization, Software, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>CNM, Conceptualization, Investigation, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>PAW, Conceptualization, Resources, Software, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>HM, Conceptualization, Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="SD3-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.038</object-id><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Independent fork model.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19848.038">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19848.038</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19848-supp1-v2.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baharoglu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lestini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Duigou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>RNA polymerase mutations that facilitate replication progression in the rep uvrD recF mutant lacking two accessory replicative helicases</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>324</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07208.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20497334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliason</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>The crystal structure of the thermus aquaticus DnaB helicase monomer</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>4728</fpage><lpage>4736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17606462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourse</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>RNA polymerase mutants that destabilize RNA polymerase-promoter complexes alter NTP-sensing by rrn P1 promoters</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.1998.1779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9642041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes-Lamothe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A replisome's journey through the bacterial chromosome</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>562</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26097470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bidnenko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lestini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>The Escherichia coli UvrD helicase is essential for tus removal during recombination-dependent replication restart from ter sites</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05382.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17020578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boubakri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>de Septenville</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Viguera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The helicases DinG, Rep and UvrD cooperate to promote replication across transcription units in vivo</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2009.308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19851282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year><article-title>When polymerases collide: replication and the transcriptional organization of the E. coli chromosome</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(88)90086-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3286014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Farache</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Polard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>DnaB, DnaD and DnaI proteins are components of the Bacillus subtilis replication restart primosome</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02631.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11679082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Velten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sérèna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Polard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Functional interplay between the Bacillus subtilis DnaD and DnaB proteins essential for initiation and re-initiation of DNA replication</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>1138</fpage><lpage>1150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04451.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15686560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreuzer</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherratt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marians</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>The importance of repairing stalled replication forks</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>404</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35003501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10716434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Septenville</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Duigou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boubakri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Replication fork reversal after replication-transcription collision</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e1002622</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22496668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shatalin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Epshtein</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Nudler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Linking RNA polymerase backtracking to genome instability in E. coli</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>146</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2011.07.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21854980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fass</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogden</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Crystal structure of the N-terminal domain of the DnaB hexameric helicase</article-title><source>Structure</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0969-2126(99)80090-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10404598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferullo</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovett</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Cell cycl<italic>e</italic> synchronization of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> using th<italic>e</italic> stringent respons<italic>e</italic>, with fluorescenc<italic>e</italic> labeling assays for DNA content and replication</article-title><source>Methods</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2009.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19245839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabbai</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Marians</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Recruitment to stalled replication forks of the PriA DNA helicase and replisome-loading activities is essential for survival</article-title><source>DNA Repair</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dnarep.2009.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20097140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahdi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwynn</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>van Knippenberg</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillingham</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>McGlynn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Rep provides a second motor at the replisome to promote duplication of protein-bound DNA</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>654</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2009.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19941825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helmstetter</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1968">1968</year><article-title>DNA synthesis during the division cycle of rapidly growing <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-2836(68)90424-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalafut</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>An objective, model-independent method for detection of non-uniform steps in noisy signals</article-title><source>Computer Physics Communications</source><volume>179</volume><fpage>716</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpc.2008.06.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeck</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Single-molecule and bulk approaches to the DnaB replication fork helicase</article-title><source>Frontiers in Bioscience</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2741/4097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koppes</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woldringh</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanninga</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Escherichia coli contains a DNA replication compartment in the cell center</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0300-9084(99)00217-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10572292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><source>DNA Replication</source><publisher-name>W.H. Freeman and Co</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuwada</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheveralls</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Traxler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Mapping the driving forces of chromosome structure and segregation in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>7370</fpage><lpage>7377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23775792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipe</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Søballe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Økstad</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barre</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherratt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Spatial and temporal organization of replicating Escherichia coli chromosomes</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03640.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12864855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leake</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Stoichiometry and turnover in single, functioning membrane protein complexes</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>443</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16971952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemon</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Localization of bacterial DNA polymerase: evidence for a factory model of replication</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>282</volume><fpage>1516</fpage><lpage>1519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.282.5393.1516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9822387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Signal processing for molecular and cellular biological physics: an emerging field</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences</source><volume>371</volume><fpage>20110546</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsta.2011.0546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23277603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lovett</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Filling the gaps in replication restart pathways</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2005.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15780929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maisnier-Patin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordström</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Replication arrests during a single round of replication of the Escherichia coli chromosome in the absence of DnaC activity</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>1371</fpage><lpage>1382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02718.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11886566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mangiameli</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Veit</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>The Replisomes remain spatially proximal throughout the Cell Cycle in Bacteria</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>e1006582</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28114307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Polard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Early steps of Bacillus subtilis primosome assembly</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>276</volume><fpage>45818</fpage><lpage>45825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M101996200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11585815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maughan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Galeano</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Novel rpoB mutations conferring rifampin resistance on Bacillus subtilis: global effects on growth, competence, sporulation, and germination</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>186</volume><fpage>2481</fpage><lpage>2486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.186.8.2481-2486.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15060052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGlynn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Recombinational repair and restart of damaged replication forks</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12415303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>The B. subtilis accessory helicase PcrA facilitates DNA replication through transcription units</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1005289</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26070154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Machón</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grainger</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Soultanas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Co-directional replication-transcription conflicts lead to replication restart</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>470</volume><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21350489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Replication-transcription conflicts in bacteria</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22669220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Million-Weaver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Samadpour</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015a</year><article-title>Replication restart after Replication-Transcription conflicts requires RecA in Bacillus subtilis</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>197</volume><fpage>2374</fpage><lpage>2382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00237-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25939832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Million-Weaver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Samadpour</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno-Habel</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nugent</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brittnacher</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Liachko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrikh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015b</year><article-title>An underlying mechanism for the increased mutagenesis of lagging-strand genes in Bacillus subtilis</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>E1096</fpage><lpage>E1105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1416651112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25713353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirkin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirkin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Mechanisms of transcription-replication collisions in bacteria</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Biology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>888</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.25.3.888-895.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15657418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirkin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirkin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Replication fork stalling at natural impediments</article-title><source>Microbiology and Molecular Biology Reviews</source><volume>71</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00030-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17347517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirouze</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Prepiak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Fluctuations in spo0A transcription control rare developmental transitions in Bacillus subtilis</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e1002048</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21552330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Langston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Principles and concepts of DNA replication in bacteria, archaea, and eukarya</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>a010108</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a010108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23818497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Colavin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Czarny</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiver</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>A comprehensive, CRISPR-based functional analysis of essential genes in bacteria</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>165</volume><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>1506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27238023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Velten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigley</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Restart of DNA replication in Gram-positive bacteria: functional characterisation of the Bacillus subtilis PriA initiator</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>1593</fpage><lpage>1605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.7.1593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11917020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reyes-Lamothe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Possoz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Danilova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherratt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Independent positioning and action of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> replisomes in liv<italic>e</italic> cells</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>133</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.01.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18394992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reyes-Lamothe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherratt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leake</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Stoichiometry and architecture of active DNA replication machinery in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>328</volume><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1185757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20413500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marians</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zavitz</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parent</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>dnaC mutations suppress defects in DNA replication- and recombination-associated functions in priB and priC double mutants in Escherichia coli K-12</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1999.01576.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10540288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marians</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Role of PriA in replication fork reactivation in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>182</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.182.1.9-13.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10613856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Multiple genetic pathways for restarting DNA replication forks in Escherichia coli K-12</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>155</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sensi</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1969">1969</year><article-title>Structure-activity relationships of rifamycin derivatives</article-title><source>Acta tuberculosea et pneumologica Belgica</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5371662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sensi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1983">1983</year><article-title>History of the development of rifampin</article-title><source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>S402</fpage><lpage>S406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/clinids/5.Supplement_3.S402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>A quantitative method for the detection of edges in noisy time-series</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><volume>353</volume><fpage>1969</fpage><lpage>1981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.1998.0348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soultanas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>The replication-transcription conflict</article-title><source>Transcription</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/trns.2.3.15908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21826285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srivatsan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tehranchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>MacAlpine</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Co-orientation of replication and transcription preserves genome integrity</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e1000810</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20090829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ulbrich</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Subunit counting in membrane-bound proteins</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth1024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkmen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007a</year><article-title>Genome-wide coorientation of replication and transcription reduces adverse effects on replication in Bacillus subtilis</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>5608</fpage><lpage>5613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0608999104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17372224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007b</year><article-title>Nutritional control of elongation of DNA replication by (p)ppGpp</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>128</volume><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.12.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17350574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>An information-based approach to change-point analysis with applications to biophysics and cell biology</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2015.05.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26200870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zavitz</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Marians</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>ATPase-deficient mutants of the Escherichia coli DNA replication protein PriA are capable of catalyzing the assembly of active primosomes</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>267</volume><fpage>6933</fpage><lpage>6940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1313026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>The rpoB mutants destabilizing initiation complexes at stringently controlled promoters behave like &quot;stringent&quot; RNA polymerases in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>2908</fpage><lpage>2913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.6.2908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9501189</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="article-commentary" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.039</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>van Oijen</surname><given-names>Antoine M</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff6"><institution>University of Wollongong</institution>, <country>Australia</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;The replisome undergoes multiple rounds of disassembly every cell cycle&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been favorably evaluated by Kevin Struhl as the Senior Editor and three reviewers, one of whom is a member of our Board of Reviewing Editors. The reviewers have opted to remain anonymous.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>Relying on single-molecule fluorescence imaging, the manuscript describes intriguing data suggesting that replisomes are disassembled and reassembled multiple times during each cell cycle in both <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>B. subtilis</italic>. Three main lines of evidence are presented to support this claim: the intensities of replisome foci (which typically contain a pair of sister replisomes) are lower than expected in ~40% of cases, consistent with only a single replisome being active; replication foci are observed to disappear and reappear on the tens-of-minutes timescale; the intensities and dynamics of replisome foci are strongly affected by inhibition of transcription. The claimed observation of frequent collisions between replisomes and transcription complexes would represent a significant advance in the field and should be of interest to a wide community.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>While all reviewers expressed excitement about the observations, a number of serious concerns were raised during the review process that should be addressed in a revised submission, requiring the introduction of new experimental data. In particular, those described in points 1 and 2 are essential in order for a revised submission to be further considered. I feel it is important to note that one reviewer expressed disappointment in the authors not having implemented suggestions and addressed concerns that were brought up during previous review processes at another journal.</p><p>Reviewers' comments:</p><p>1) As the authors note, replication takes ~30-40 minutes. And they are imaging for ~20 minutes. So, if the replisome really collapses 5-6 times per cell cycle, then they should see multiple collapses and reassembly events during a single imaging experiment. But this is not discussed or reported, as near as I can tell. The authors partially address this issue by stating: &quot;Due to the low intensity of single fluorescent molecules, both the stoichiometry and dynamics experiments are technically challenging. In addition, the bacteria themselves are subject to photo damage at the intensities required to resolve single molecules, and this photo damage itself affects cellular processes and replication in particular.&quot; But then the authors state that there is very little bleaching over the twenty-minute time frame currently used (subsection “Replicative helicase complexes are short-lived”, first paragraph. These statements are directly contradictory. More importantly, they highlight the fact that the authors don't adequately discuss or present the effects of photobleaching on their experiments – and they don't convincingly show that they can distinguish between photobleaching and disassembly events or use their set up to rigorously observe multiple disassembly events within a single cell cycle, which is absolutely essential to their primary conclusion that disassembly takes place <italic>multiple</italic> times per cell cycle.</p><p>(I will also note that the quote above from the Discussion was modified slightly from the previous version of the manuscript I reviewed – it used to say &quot;The low stoichiometry of DnaC makes it technically difficult to image the same cells throughout their entire cell cycle without significant photobleaching at the same frame rate.&quot;)</p><p>Here's the bottom line: If the photobleaching really isn't an issue, then the authors must examine cells for longer and document multiple assembly and reassembly events over the course of an individual cell cycle. However, if the photobleaching is a major issue over a 20 min time-course, then I'm not convinced that the authors can really safely distinguish bleaching effects from disassembly events, at least based on the analyses currently presented.</p><p>Related to the points above: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6D</xref> need to make clear (in the figure, not just the legend) that the number of conflicts per cell cycle is being 'predicted' based on some assumptions about the Poisson distribution of events inferred from the behavior of single events being measured. The graph may lead some readers to believe that these values were measured, which they are not.</p><p>2) The authors need some alternative methods to corroborate their conclusion that replication forks collapse multiple times every cell cycle. Relying exclusively on the single-molecule microscopy is a recipe for disaster. The authors clearly agree, as they state in the second to last paragraph of the manuscript: &quot;Due to the low intensity of single fluorescent molecules, both the stoichiometry and dynamics experiments are technically challenging. In addition, the bacteria themselves are subject to photo damage at the intensities required to resolve single molecules, and this photo damage itself affects cellular processes and replication in particular. Therefore, it is essential to consider these measurements in the context of additional corroboratory biochemical and genetic evidence. The essentiality of restart proteins and the measurement of the replication rates provide independent lines of evidence for the pervasive disassembly model.&quot; I agree fully with the authors here that the photobleaching and photodamage that is occurring during their experiments is indeed likely affecting cellular processes and DNA replication, which means that relying on the single-molecule microscopy alone is extremely dangerous. So, the question then is what data help corroborate the microscopy? The authors cite two things: (1) The authors cite the measurements of replication rates in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>. These data are fine, but say nothing about the frequency of replication fork collapse per cell cycle. Slower nucleotide incorporation rates could occur from replication slowing down without the replisome fully disassembling and reassembling. In short, these data are loosely consistent with the authors' favored model, but do not incisively probe the issue. (2) The essentiality of restart proteins like PriA. The Polard et al. 2002 study of <italic>B. subtilis</italic> PriA did indeed show that cells with mutant priA are quite sick, bordering on essential. But it's still not clear whether it's essential because it's required <italic>every</italic> cell cycle multiple times or because it's required once every few cell cycles. Simply examining plating efficiency only says priA mutants are essential, but it doesn't say how often the protein is required. What is needed is a means of rapidly shutting off PriA activity (via a temp. sensitive allele or induced degradation) and then to examine what happens in individual cells. In other words: The fact that Pri proteins are essential in the sense that mutants cannot be readily recovered on plates does <italic>not</italic> imply that these proteins are required multiple times every single cell cycle. That conclusion requires an analysis of single cells, immediately after the factor of interest has been eliminated. This is a very straightforward experiment that could help to bolster the authors' conclusion (or not).</p><p>3) The IPTG-induced expression of a gene oriented to produce a head-on collision is nice, but is lacking a crucial control, namely the same construct should be inserted at the same location but in the opposite and co-directional orientation.</p><p>In a previous round of review the authors indicated that this had been done and there is some effect, which is puzzling. There are many, many native, co-oriented genes, so if just one extra co-oriented gene has a measurable effect, then how does the replisome ever complete replication?</p><p>4) The lifetime calculation and modeling need more details. How do the authors deal with photobleaching and incomplete capture of the replisome lifetime? How is the Maximum likelihood estimation obtained? Is the lifetime for one replisome, i.e. only a single replisome is followed, or are both replisomes compounded together? Are the assembly/disassembly of the two replisome coupled or independent? How do the authors take into account the possibility in the lifetime measurement that one replisome disassembled, and the other one reassembled immediately after that?</p><p>5) The authors assumed the replication time is 40 min based on literature (subsection “Transcription inhibition increases the rate of replication”, first paragraph), and the cell cycle time is close to 65 min. Is the 'number of conflicts per cell cycle' being 5 the number of conflicts per replisome per one 40 min or 65 min? Or is this number the total number of conflict for both replisomes? Is this based on the assumption of that there is only one replication run per cell cycle without multiple rounds of re-initiation? In addition, what's confusing is that the number of conflicts here needs the disappearance of both forks, implying that they are coupled? But the stoichiometry section clearly has many cells with one stable fork, so they are not counted as conflicts in the lifetime measurement? The authors should more clearly address the differences in what's being measured between the lifetime and stoichiometry experiments, and how the numbers add up and any discrepancies here.</p><p>6) The authors monitored replisome dynamics in live cells. Could they provide more information regarding what the off-time of replisome (the time each replisome stays off DNA) is? For example, if the percentage of cells containing only one active replisome is ~ 40-50%, it would translate to an averaged total off time of ~ 20 min for a replication time of 40 min (assuming the probability of a replisome staying off DNA is p at any given moment, then the chance of observing both replisome is p<sup>2</sup>, both replisomes off (1-p)<sup>2</sup>, and only one replisome at any given time is p(1-p) + (1-p)p= 2p(1-p). Therefore, solving 2p(1-p) = 0.5 leads to p = 0.5, hence 20 min per 40 min cycle). How does this translate into the average off-time per replisome given the number of conflicts per replisome cell cycle or replication cycle?</p><p>7) The authors technically cannot measure the stoichiometry of replisomes with two disassembled forks during replication. Is this the fraction of cells (~16%) mentioned in the third paragraph of the subsection “Replicative helicase and DNA polymerase stoichiometries are consistent with a single active complex”? Or does this fraction also include cells before or at the end of replication where both replisomes are disassembled? Is this population (2 disassembled forks) accounted for the calculation of 40-50% of cells having only one replisome?</p><p>8) Thymidine incorporation: although the authors noted that the higher incorporation rate of thymidine in transcription inhibited strains is unlikely due to changes in membrane permeability, there is still a possibility that inhibited transcription may cause changes in membrane permeability through other mechanism such as the lack of expression of proteins involved in safeguarding membrane integrity. Therefore, the enhanced thymidine incorporation could still be due to an indirect effect of transcription inhibition, but not direct effect of transcription-replication conflict. Different growth conditions could have the same indirect effect as well. Could the authors use some dyes that can monitor membrane potentials such as the live/death kit of Invitrogen or something similar to verify this possibility? Also, they could use the lacZ induction strain to examine whether the thymidine incorporation rate in these strains is indeed lower.</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were requested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><p>Thank you for resubmitting your work entitled &quot;The replisome undergoes multiple rounds of disassembly every cell cycle&quot; for further consideration at <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been favorably evaluated by Kevin Struhl as the Senior Editor and three reviewers, one of whom is a member of our Board of Reviewing Editors.</p><p>The addition of new experimental evidence and more detail on the analyses have improved the manuscript, but the reviewers still raise significant concerns about the statement that the replisome collapses multiple times per cell cycle, a conclusion that is not based on direct observation, but rather is inferred.</p><p>Nonetheless, your observations of the replisome collapsing as a consequence of transcriptional collisions is of interest to the readers of <italic>eLife</italic> and we would like to invite the submission of a revised manuscript. For it to be acceptable for publication, a significant revision of the writing is necessary, including change of the title and softening of the major claim that the replisome collapses multiple times per cell cycle.</p><p>Below you will find the reviewers' main points of criticism, with suggestions for additional experiments in case you wish to provide more direct evidence of the original claim. The inclusion of new experimental data may have to be evaluated by the original reviewers, before arriving at a final decision.</p><p>1) If the photobleaching really isn't an issue as the authors strongly claim, there needs to be a better demonstration that there really are 5-6 fork collapses and restarts in a single cell cycle time course. This is still lacking. The authors point to the image strips in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref> as showing two disassemblies, but the WT data are not compelling; it's not clear whether there's a collapse and reassembly event or whether the first &quot;collapse&quot; is really a collapse in the first place as the two frames with an apparently disassembled fork have a focus just as intense as in subsequent panels indicating a &quot;reassembled&quot; fork. Even more importantly: the authors make a strong prediction that forks disassemble and reassemble 5-6 times per cell cycle and there's simply no direct demonstration of this occurring.</p><p>As a side note, the rif-treated cells show longer focus lifetimes, which is certainly consistent with the authors' model, but rif-treatment could be affecting the process and focus stability in all sorts of indirect ways, none of which are considered or ruled out.</p><p>2) There needs to be a clear, independent corroboration that forks collapse multiple times per cell cycle, every cell cycle. The new data using CRISPRi to knockdown priA are a step in the right direction but incomplete and inconclusive right now. The authors can clearly knockdown priA, but the timing of knockdown is not characterized, which is important here. There is a single snapshot analysis done suggesting fewer foci in the priA knockdown, but the images shown in the supplement are very, very difficult to interpret; relatively few cells are shown, the foci in both the experiment and control strain are not nearly as clear as in other parts of the paper and the DnaC-GFP levels overall appear substantially reduced in the priA strain. Moreover, there's no demonstration that the loss of priA leads to an immediate loss in viability, only that the priA CRISPRi strain losses plating viability – but as noted previously, this doesn't distinguish between fork restart being required <italic>every</italic> cell cycle vs. once every few cell cycles, which is the key issue here.</p><p>3) The authors did not really address the request of making the calculation of conflict per replication time clear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B, C</xref>, and D). I had to play with the source data of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> myself, and arrived at a value similar but not the same, number of conflicts (~ 4.4) per 40 min replication time. Nevertheless, please do add a section in the Materials and methods to explain how the survival probability is calculated, report the mean lifetime of replisome of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>, the mean survival rate of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>, and the corresponding fitting functions and parameters. They will be helpful for the community. In addition, the authors should use experimentally measured survival probability, instead of the theoretical value from the exponential fitting in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref> to plot <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>. Similar comments apply to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19848.040</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p><italic>Essential revisions:</italic> </p><p><italic>While all reviewers expressed excitement about the observations, a number of serious concerns were raised during the review process that should be addressed in a revised submission, requiring the introduction of new experimental data. In particular, those described in points 1 and 2 are essential in order for a revised submission to be further considered. I feel it is important to note that one reviewer expressed disappointment in the authors not having implemented suggestions and addressed concerns that were brought up during previous review processes at another journal.</italic> </p><p><italic>Reviewers' comments:</italic> </p><p><italic>1) As the authors note, replication takes ~30-40 minutes. And they are imaging for ~20 minutes. So, if the replisome really collapses 5-6 times per cell cycle, then they should see multiple collapses and reassembly events during a single imaging experiment. But this is not discussed or reported, as near as I can tell. The authors partially address this issue by stating: &quot;Due to the low intensity of single fluorescent molecules, both the stoichiometry and dynamics experiments are technically challenging. In addition, the bacteria themselves are subject to photo damage at the intensities required to resolve single molecules, and this photo damage itself affects cellular processes and replication in particular.&quot; But then the authors state that there is very little bleaching over the twenty-minute time frame currently used (subsection “Replicative helicase complexes are short-lived”, first paragraph. These statements are directly contradictory. More importantly, they highlight the fact that the authors don't adequately discuss or present the effects of photobleaching on their experiments – and they don't convincingly show that they can distinguish between photobleaching and disassembly events or use their set up to rigorously observe multiple disassembly events within a single cell cycle, which is absolutely essential to their primary conclusion that disassembly takes place multiple times per cell cycle.</italic> </p><p><italic>(I will also note that the quote above from the Discussion was modified slightly from the previous version of the manuscript I reviewed – it used to say &quot;The low stoichiometry of DnaC makes it technically difficult to image the same cells throughout their entire cell cycle without significant photobleaching at the same frame rate.&quot;)</italic> </p><p><italic>Here's the bottom line: If the photobleaching really isn't an issue, then the authors must examine cells for longer and document multiple assembly and reassembly events over the course of an individual cell cycle. However, if the photobleaching is a major issue over a 20 min time-course, then I'm not convinced that the authors can really safely distinguish bleaching effects from disassembly events, at least based on the analyses currently presented.</italic> </p><p>We have added new experimental data supporting our ability to distinguish between photobleaching and replisome disassembly during the time courses (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>).</p><p>Additional experiment: To test whether focus loss was due to photobleaching or replisome dynamics, we compared the focus lifetimes with and without a two minute delay between frames. In the no-delay experiment, the foci are expected to be bleached before conflict-induced disassembly, whereas in the two-minute-delay experiments, conflict-induced disassembly is faster than photobleaching. Since the net dosage of excitation light is the same in the two experiments by frame number, conflict-induced disassembly is expected to shorten lifetime (measured in frames) of the foci in the two-minute-delay experiment relative to the no- delay experiment.</p><p>Results: In the no-delay experiment, 8% of GFP-labeled complexes disappeared during the eleven frame time course; whereas, in the two- minute-delay experiment, 80% of foci disappeared, an order of magnitude increase in the rate, strongly rejecting the photobleaching hypothesis.</p><p>Additional evidence: Experimental evidence was already included in the original manuscript which rejects the photobleaching hypothesis. Rif- treated and <italic>rpoB*</italic> cells are imaged under exactly the same conditions as the wild type cells. Focus lifetime are observed to increase under these conditions, which reduce transcription and therefore conflict-induced dynamics. If photobleaching were the dominant mechanism of focus disappearance, the lifetime would be equal in all three experiments (WT, rif, <italic>rpoB*</italic>). Therefore, the transcription dependence of the lifetime also provides strong evidence against the photobleaching hypothesis.</p><p>Given the calculated rates of conflicts, we expect to observe an average of roughly 2.5 disassemblies per time course. This number is consistent with our data, and the example wild type image strips in both organisms show two disassemblies.</p><p><italic>Related to the points above: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6D</xref> need to make clear (in the figure, not just the legend) that the number of conflicts per cell cycle is being 'predicted' based on some assumptions about the Poisson distribution of events inferred from the behavior of single events being measured. The graph may lead some readers to believe that these values were measured, which they are not.</italic></p><p>We agree with the reviewers. We have now included the word “estimated” in the axis label to make this point clearer.</p><p><italic>2) The authors need some alternative methods to corroborate their conclusion that replication forks collapse multiple times every cell cycle. Relying exclusively on the single-molecule microscopy is a recipe for disaster. The authors clearly agree, as they state in the second to last paragraph of the manuscript: &quot;Due to the low intensity of single fluorescent molecules, both the stoichiometry and dynamics experiments are technically challenging. In addition, the bacteria themselves are subject to photo damage at the intensities required to resolve single molecules, and this photo damage itself affects cellular processes and replication in particular. Therefore, it is essential to consider these measurements in the context of additional corroboratory biochemical and genetic evidence. The essentiality of restart proteins and the measurement of the replication rates provide independent lines of evidence for the pervasive disassembly model.&quot; I agree fully with the authors here that the photobleaching and photodamage that is occurring during their experiments is indeed likely affecting cellular processes and DNA replication, which means that relying on the single-molecule microscopy alone is extremely dangerous. So, the question then is what data help corroborate the microscopy? The authors cite two things: (1) The authors cite the measurements of replication rates in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>. These data are fine, but say nothing about the frequency of replication fork collapse per cell cycle. Slower nucleotide incorporation rates could occur from replication slowing down without the replisome fully disassembling and reassembling. In short, these data are loosely consistent with the authors' favored model, but do not incisively probe the issue. (2) The essentiality of restart proteins like PriA. The Polard et al. 2002 study of B. subtilis PriA did indeed show that cells with mutant priA are quite sick, bordering on essential. But it's still not clear whether it's essential because it's required every cell cycle multiple times or because it's required once every few cell cycles. Simply examining plating efficiency only says priA mutants are essential, but it doesn't say how often the protein is required. What is needed is a means of rapidly shutting off PriA activity (via a temp. sensitive allele or induced degradation) and then to examine what happens in individual cells. In other words: The fact that Pri proteins are essential in the sense that mutants cannot be readily recovered on plates does not imply that these proteins are required multiple times every single cell cycle. That conclusion requires an analysis of single cells, immediately after the factor of interest has been eliminated. This is a very straightforward experiment that could help to bolster the authors' conclusion (or not).</italic> </p><p>We agree with the reviewer that it would be nice to show the reported reassembly events are dependent on a well-established biological mechanism. In addition, we also agree that determining whether restart (PriA or the helicase loaders) are required for the observed reassembly events would provide solid evidence that supports our findings. To address these points, we carried out two additional experiments:</p><p>Additional experiment 1: We first perturbed the restart process in <italic>E. coli:</italic> DnaC<sub>Ec</sub> is required for the loading of the replicative helicase DnaB, and is recruited to stalled replication forks through the action of Pri proteins. The loading process can be perturbed using the <italic>E. coli</italic> temperature sensitive helicase loader mutant allele, <italic>dnaC2</italic>. If the reappearance events we observe in the lifetime experiments are indeed due to restart, we would expect that the <italic>dnaC<sub>Ec</sub></italic>mutant would be defective in reassembly of the helicase (DnaB) or reappearance of the foci. We therefore observed the replisome dynamics in the <italic>dnaC2</italic> allele at both the permissive and the non-permissive temperature. (WT was also analyzed at the high temperature to control for potential artifacts of temperature change on lifetimes).</p><p>Results: We observed qualitatively different DnaB-YPet focus dynamics in the <italic>dnaC2</italic> strain at the nonpermissive temperature, as predicted. Foci that disassemble are typically not observed to reassemble. To quantitate this data, we calculate the probability of observing a focus as a function of time in cells that have at least one focus. In strains containing the <italic>dnaC2</italic> allele, this probability decreases throughout the time course consistent with failure to restart. In the wild type strain, the probability is roughly constant indicating that the replisome is in steady state due to its ability to restart. We observed loss of foci in the <italic>dnaC2</italic> allele strain is too rapid to be explained by replication termination.</p><p>Additional experiment 2: We next perturbed the restart process in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> by depleting the PriA protein. We constructed a CRISPR system to inducibly deplete PriA from <italic>B. subtilis</italic> cells. Again, the predicted phenotype is the failure of replisome foci to reassemble after disassembly.</p><p>Results: Consistent with the restart hypothesis, we find that after depletion of PriA through the induction of the CRISPR system, helicase (DnaCBs) foci disappear, with 87% of cells now lacking any visible foci. The foci do not reappear after PriA depletion and the initial disappearance.</p><p>In summary, we targeted two successive steps in the restart process, the <italic>dnaC2<sub>Ec</sub></italic>experiments from <italic>E. coli</italic> and the PriA depletion experiments from <italic>B. subtilis,</italic> and found that both strongly support the proposed model.</p><p><italic>3) The IPTG-induced expression of a gene oriented to produce a head-on collision is nice, but is lacking a crucial control, namely the same construct should be inserted at the same location but in the opposite and co-directional orientation.</italic> </p><p><italic>In a previous round of review the authors indicated that this had been done and there is some effect, which is puzzling. There are many, many native, co-oriented genes, so if just one extra co-oriented gene has a measurable effect, then how does the replisome ever complete replication?</italic> </p><p>These data have been added (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). There is a slight but significant increase in single-helicase population.</p><p>The observation of some small increase in disassembly is expected given our previous findings. Co-oriented genes do result in conflicts when they are transcribed at high levels and the transcription unit is long, as is the case here (<italic>lacZ</italic> is 3 kb in length) [H. Merrikh et al. 2011, Million-Weaver et al. 2015]. In fact, we have previously demonstrated that conflicts occur at this reporter using ChIP-qPCR experiments. See Merrikh et al. (2015). It should be noted that the length of the lacZ gene, combined with the strength of the promoter used here creates conflicts with similar severity to those observed for the rDNA genes, and thus, this reporter is not surprisingly more problematic than most genes transcribed co- directionally on the chromosome.</p><p><italic>4) The lifetime calculation and modeling need more details. How do the authors deal with photobleaching and incomplete capture of the replisome lifetime? How is the Maximum likelihood estimation obtained? Is the lifetime for one replisome, i.e. only a single replisome is followed, or are both replisomes compounded together? Are the assembly/disassembly of the two replisome coupled or independent? How do the authors take into account the possibility in the lifetime measurement that one replisome disassembled, and the other one reassembled immediately after that?</italic> </p><p>We have now included a new mathematical analysis to address the reviewers’ suggestion to analyze a more detailed model where the forks transition independently. We initially avoided introducing this model explicitly since it relies on a number of assumptions that we have not tested and believe to be incorrect. The model also leads to roughly comparable estimates, but with significantly more complex mathematical expressions. However, there is value in such an analysis and thus, we have modeled it and the results of the independent-fork model are now included in a supplementary note.</p><p><italic>5) The authors assumed the replication time is 40 min based on literature (subsection “Transcription inhibition increases the rate of replication”, first paragraph), and the cell cycle time is close to 65 min. Is the 'number of conflicts per cell cycle' being 5 the number of conflicts per replisome per one 40 min or 65 min? Or is this number the total number of conflict for both replisomes?</italic> </p><p>This is an important question. We have now included a brief discussion of the length of the cell cycle in the description of the independent fork model.</p><p><italic>Is this based on the assumption of that there is only one replication run per cell cycle without multiple rounds of re-initiation? In addition, what's confusing is that the number of conflicts here needs the disappearance of both forks, implying that they are coupled? But the stoichiometry section clearly has many cells with one stable fork, so they are not counted as conflicts in the lifetime measurement? The authors should more clearly address the differences in what's being measured between the lifetime and stoichiometry experiments, and how the numbers add up and any discrepancies here.</italic> </p><p>We agree with the reviewers about this point. See the discussion of the independent-fork model.</p><p><italic>6) The authors monitored replisome dynamics in live cells. Could they provide more information regarding what the off-time of replisome (the time each replisome stays off DNA) is?</italic> </p><p>We have included a discussion of the estimated off time in the description of the independent-fork model.</p><p><italic>For example, if the percentage of cells containing only one active replisome is ~ 40-50%, it would translate to an averaged total off time of ~ 20 min for a replication time of 40 min (assuming the probability of a replisome staying off DNA is p at any given moment, then the chance of observing both replisome is p<sup>2</sup>, both replisomes off (1-p)<sup>2</sup>, and only one replisome at any given time is p(1-p) + (1-p)p= 2p(1-p). Therefore, solving 2p(1-p) = 0.5 leads to p = 0.5, hence 20 min per 40 min cycle). How does this translate into the average off-time per replisome given the number of conflicts per replisome cell cycle or replication cycle?</italic> </p><p>See the discussion of the independent-fork model.</p><p><italic>7) The authors technically cannot measure the stoichiometry of replisomes with two disassembled forks during replication. Is this the fraction of cells (~16%) mentioned in the third paragraph of the subsection “Replicative helicase and DNA polymerase stoichiometries are consistent with a single active complex”? Or does this fraction also include cells before or at the end of replication where both replisomes are disassembled? Is this population (2 disassembled forks) accounted for the calculation of 40-50% of cells having only one replisome?</italic> </p><p>While we normally see a single midcell focus representing the both replisomes, occasionally the forks separate enough to be individually resolvable (this is ~16% of the time). We exclude individually resolvable forks since our interpretation of the counting experiments depends on both forks co-localizing to a single diffraction limited spot. We do not report the number of zero focus cells because they can result either from disruption of both forks, or the absence of replication. The 40- 50% refers to the number of cells with a focus that are consistent with having one replisome.</p><p><italic>8) Thymidine incorporation: although the authors noted that the higher incorporation rate of thymidine in transcription inhibited strains is unlikely due to changes in membrane permeability, there is still a possibility that inhibited transcription may cause changes in membrane permeability through other mechanism such as the lack of expression of proteins involved in safeguarding membrane integrity. Therefore, the enhanced thymidine incorporation could still be due to an indirect effect of transcription inhibition, but not direct effect of transcription-replication conflict. Different growth conditions could have the same indirect effect as well. Could the authors use some dyes that can monitor membrane potentials such as the live/death kit of Invitrogen or something similar to verify this possibility? Also, they could use the lacZ induction strain to examine whether the thymidine incorporation rate in these strains is indeed lower.</italic> </p><p>Many independent lines of evidence contradict this proposal: (i) Since the thymidine incorporation experiments are performed over a short time interval (&lt;10 min), protein levels are not expected to change appreciably. (ii) Rif treatment does not increase thymidine incorporation further in the <italic>rpoB</italic>* cells, suggesting that Rif treatment does not change membrane permeability in general. (iii) <italic>rpoB</italic>* cells do not show a significant change in growth rate, which would be expected if membrane integrity was significantly compromised. (iv) The proposed artifact is unlikely to explain the coincident results from three independent experiments: rif, <italic>rpoB</italic>* and changes carbon source. (v) Rif treatment doesn’t appear to significantly compromise membrane integrity since normal cell elongation is observed for more than an hour after rif treatment.</p><p>We have not performed the <italic>lacZ</italic> induction experiment since we are not convinced that the effect would be large enough to detect by thymidine incorporation.</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were requested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><p><italic>The addition of new experimental evidence and more detail on the analyses have improved the manuscript, but the reviewers still raise significant concerns about the statement that the replisome collapses multiple times per cell cycle, a conclusion that is not based on direct observation, but rather is inferred.</italic> </p><p><italic>Nonetheless, your observations of the replisome collapsing as a consequence of transcriptional collisions is of interest to the readers of eLife and we would like to invite the submission of a revised manuscript. For it to be acceptable for publication, a significant revision of the writing is necessary, including change of the title and softening of the major claim that the replisome collapses multiple times per cell cycle.</italic> </p><p>We have changed the manuscript title, and softened the language surrounding our statements about multiple collapse events, making it clear that they were inferred. Please find below our responses to the reviewers’ criticisms. Although no new experimental data have been introduced, we clarify some of the points brought up by the reviewers.</p><p><italic>Below you will find the reviewers' main points of criticism, with suggestions for additional experiments in case you wish to provide more direct evidence of the original claim. The inclusion of new experimental data may have to be evaluated by the original reviewers, before arriving at a final decision.</italic> </p><p><italic>1) If the photobleaching really isn't an issue as the authors strongly claim, there needs to be a better demonstration that there really are 5-6 fork collapses and restarts in a single cell cycle time course. This is still lacking. The authors point to the image strips in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref> as showing two disassemblies, but the WT data are not compelling; it's not clear whether there's a collapse and reassembly event or whether the first &quot;collapse&quot; is really a collapse in the first place as the two frames with an apparently disassembled fork have a focus just as intense as in subsequent panels indicating a &quot;reassembled&quot; fork. Even more importantly: the authors make a strong prediction that forks disassemble and reassemble 5-6 times per cell cycle and there's simply no direct demonstration of this occurring.</italic> </p><p>Although it would be ideal to observe the replisome for entire cell cycles, the components simply aren’t present at high enough stoichiometry for this to be technically possible using the tools we currently have available. The ~20 minute time courses were taken at random places during the cell cycle, and should be representative of the cell cycle as a whole. However, drawing specific conclusions about the number of conflicts during the entire cell cycle from the 20 minute time courses does require a number of assumptions as the reviewers suggests, so we have softened the language, making it clear that the conflict number was calculated and not directly observed.</p><p>We would like to add that the fluorescence intensity is relatively spread out in the region where the first collapse event is interpreted to occur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). The fluorescence in the frame where we interpret re-assembly is much more localized. This can be more easily seen in the (larger) reproduction of this image strip in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>, where we describe the process of identifying foci. Regardless, the same automated tracking was applied to the wild-type, rif-treated, and <italic>rpoB*</italic> mutant cells. We observed that the focus lifetimes were transcription dependent, and have adjusted the language in the manuscript to focus on the destabilization of the replisome due to transcription rather than the specific inferred number of conflicts.</p><p><italic>As a side note, the rif-treated cells show longer focus lifetimes, which is certainly consistent with the authors' model, but rif-treatment could be affecting the process and focus stability in all sorts of indirect ways, none of which are considered or ruled out.</italic> </p><p>To control for potential artifacts caused by rifampicin treatment, we corroborated our results using an <italic>rpoB*</italic> mutant. Using this independent method for ameliorating replication-transcription conflicts, we observe similarly elongated focus lifetimes relative to those observed in the wild type. These data can be found for the focus lifetime measurement in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</p><p><italic>2) There needs to be a clear, independent corroboration that forks collapse multiple times per cell cycle, every cell cycle. The new data using CRISPRi to knockdown priA are a step in the right direction but incomplete and inconclusive right now. The authors can clearly knockdown priA, but the timing of knockdown is not characterized, which is important here. There is a single snapshot analysis done suggesting fewer foci in the priA knockdown, but the images shown in the supplement are very, very difficult to interpret; relatively few cells are shown, the foci in both the experiment and control strain are not nearly as clear as in other parts of the paper and the DnaC-GFP levels overall appear substantially reduced in the priA strain. Moreover, there's no demonstration that the loss of priA leads to an immediate loss in viability, only that the priA CRISPRi strain losses plating viability – but as noted previously, this doesn't distinguish between fork restart being required every cell cycle vs. once every few cell cycles, which is the key issue here.</italic> </p><p>While the priA snap-shot data supports a model where the replisome is disassembled, we understand that they do not provide additional evidence that disassembly occurs every cell cycle, and have softened the language in our manuscript to reflect this. Nonetheless, we would like to point out that we were able to perform the experiment suggested by the reviewer (visualization of the helicase immediately after disruption of restart) in <italic>E. coli</italic>. We showed that disruption of restart via a temperature sensitive version of the helicase loader protein (<italic>dnaC2</italic> allele) lead to loss of the DnaB-YPet focus before the end of the 20 minute time course in 80% percent of cases. We can infer (but are unable to observe directly) a 96% of focus disassembly before the end of a 40 minute replication cycle. Additionally, we note that 40 minutes is an upper limit on how quickly replication can be completed, and provides the most conservative estimate for the number of conflicts per cell cycle. This strongly supports at least one disassembly event per replication cycle.</p><p>We would have liked to have observed the fate of the DnaC-GFP focus in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> immediately after the depletion of PriA. However, due to leaky expression of the CRISPR system, PriA was already depleted threefold prior to induction (Peters, 2016). Because of this, even the uninduced priA CRISPR strain showed substantially reduced numbers of DnaC-GFP foci. After induction, so few foci remained at the start of imaging that time lapse imaging was not productive.</p><p>Other methods for PriA depletion were attempted, but the cells were highly sensitive to any modification to <italic>priA</italic>. Despite substantial effort, we were not able to construct a better system for PriA depletion in a reasonable amount of time.</p><p>Clearer representative images have been included in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s3">Figure 2—figure supplement 3</xref>.</p><p><italic>3) The authors did not really address the request of making the calculation of conflict per replication time clear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B, C</xref>, and D). I had to play with the source data of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> myself, and arrived at a value similar but not the same, number of conflicts (~ 4.4) per 40 min replication time. Nevertheless, please do add a section in the Materials and methods to explain how the survival probability is calculated, report the mean lifetime of replisome of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>, the mean survival rate of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>, and the corresponding fitting functions and parameters. They will be helpful for the community. In addition, the authors should use experimentally measured survival probability, instead of the theoretical value from the exponential fitting in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref> to plot <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>. Similar comments apply to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>.</italic> </p><p>A section entitled “Estimation of conflict number based on replisome complex lifetime” has been added to the manuscript that includes the details suggested by the reviewer. Furthermore, we have now included a summary of the requested parameters in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref> (<italic>B. subtilis</italic>) and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref> (<italic>E. coli</italic>).</p></body></sub-article></article>