<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">eLife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">12040</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A family of photoswitchable NMDA receptors</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-43664"><name><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>Shai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib">†</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-43665"><name><surname>Szobota</surname><given-names>Stephanie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib">†</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa1">‡</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-43666"><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa2">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-47460"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>Elizabeth C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-43667"><name><surname>Kienzler</surname><given-names>Michael A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-43668"><name><surname>Guyon</surname><given-names>Alice</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-19939"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Tong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con7"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-43669"><name><surname>Tauner</surname><given-names>Dirk</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con8"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-43309"><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>Ehud Y</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4775-9359</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con9"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Molecular and Cell Biology</institution>, <institution>University of California, Berkeley</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Berkeley</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Institut de Pharmacologie Moléculaire et Cellulaire</institution>, <institution>Université de Nice Sophia Antipolis</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Nice</named-content></addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Chemistry</institution>, <institution>University of California, Berkeley</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Berkeley</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Chemistry, Center of Integrated Protein Science</institution>, <institution>University of Munich</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Munich</named-content></addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution content-type="dept">Helen Wills Neuroscience Institute</institution>, <institution>University of California, Berkeley</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Berkeley</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution content-type="dept">Physical Bioscience Division</institution>, <institution>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Berkeley</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>Indira M</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff7"><institution>Northwestern University</institution>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><email>ehud@berkeley.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa1"><label>‡</label><p>Otonomy, Inc., San Diego, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa2"><label>§</label><p>Faculty of Biology and Biotechnology, Ruhr University Bochum, Bochum, Germany</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="equal-contrib"><label>†</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e12040</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>01</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016, Berlin et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Berlin et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-12040-v1.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.001</object-id><p>NMDA receptors, which regulate synaptic strength and are implicated in learning and memory, consist of several subtypes with distinct subunit compositions and functional properties. To enable spatiotemporally defined, rapid and reproducible manipulation of function of specific subtypes, we engineered a set of photoswitchable GluN subunits ('LiGluNs'). Photo-agonism of GluN2A or GluN2B elicits an excitatory drive to hippocampal neurons that can be shaped in time to mimic synaptic activation. Photo-agonism of GluN2A at single dendritic spines evokes spine-specific calcium elevation and expansion, the morphological correlate of LTP. Photo-antagonism of GluN2A alone, or in combination with photo-antagonism of GluN1a, reversibly blocks excitatory synaptic currents, prevents the induction of long-term potentiation and prevents spine expansion. In addition, photo-antagonism in vivo disrupts synaptic pruning of developing retino-tectal projections in larval zebrafish. By providing precise and rapidly reversible optical control of NMDA receptor subtypes, LiGluNs should help unravel the contribution of specific NMDA receptors to synaptic transmission, integration and plasticity.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.001">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.001</ext-link></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>Within the nervous system, neurons are organized into extensive networks via connections called synapses. To signal across a synapse, one neuron releases chemical messengers that bind to “receptors” on the surface of the neighboring cell. The ease with which neurons can communicate can change depending on how often a synapse is used. This adaptability is known as synaptic plasticity, and is central to the formation of memories.</p><p>NMDA receptors are one group of receptors that play an important role in synaptic plasticity. There are several types of NMDA receptor, which are made up of different combinations of protein subunits and have different properties. This means that each type contributes to synaptic plasticity in a slightly different way.</p><p>Other receptors found in neurons have been studied using a technique called chemical optogenetics, which allows the activity of modified proteins to be turned on and off by light. Now, Berlin, Szobota et al. have designed a toolbox that enables the activity of four of the NMDA receptor subunits to be controlled with light, which activates or blocks the NMDA receptors that they form (which includes several of the main receptor types). Thus, how these types of NMDA receptor contribute to synaptic plasticity can be investigated.</p><p>The toolbox can be used to control synaptic plasticity under a wide range of conditions. Plasticity can be induced or prevented in either single synaptic connections or large regions containing many thousands of synapses. The approach works in individual neurons grown artificially in the laboratory, in brain slices and in the living brain. Furthermore, synaptic plasticity can be controlled precisely to affect single synaptic events (which occur in milliseconds) or it can be controlled over several days to study whether this affects how neurons develop.</p><p>The next steps will be to expand the toolset so that the activity of all the NMDA receptor subtypes can be controlled using light. Further studies could then incorporate the receptors into the brains of mammals to study how the receptors’ activity affects a range of processes including memory formation and disease.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.002">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.002</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Author Keywords</title><kwd>NMDA receptor</kwd><kwd>photoswitch</kwd><kwd>liGluN</kwd><kwd>gluN2</kwd><kwd>synaptic plasticity</kwd><kwd>synapse</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research Organism</title><kwd>Mouse</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="par-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2PN2EY018241</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>Ehud Y</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>elife-xml-version</meta-name><meta-value>2.5</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Molecular engineering can generate light-sensitive NMDA receptors with specific subunit combinations.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>NMDA receptors are ligand-gated ion channels at excitatory synapses throughout the nervous system. They trigger long-term potentiation (LTP) and long-term depression (LTD) of synaptic strength and are implicated in memory formation, synapse development, circuit refinement, neuropsychiatric disorders, excitotoxicity and neurodegeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Lau and Zukin, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Nabavi et al., 2014</xref>). NMDA receptors are heterotetramers, consisting of two glycine-binding GluN1 subunits paired with two glutamate-binding GluN2 and/or glycine-binding GluN3 subunits, yielding a combinatorial diversity of channel composition and function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Paoletti et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91">Traynelis et al., 2010</xref>). The glutamate-binding GluN2 subunits (GluN2A-D) are encoded by four genes, which appear at specific developmental stages, bind distinct regulatory proteins, and are situated at diverse cellular locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hardingham and Bading, 2010</xref>). The complexity of subunit stoichiometry and receptor localization has made it difficult to unravel the roles of NMDA receptor signaling in circuit function and behavior.</p><p>Much has been learned about the function of NMDA receptors from pharmacological and genetic manipulations that target specific receptor subtypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Foster et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88">Tang et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91">Traynelis et al., 2010</xref>). However, pharmacological agents need to be used at low concentrations to maintain selectivity, resulting in slow onset, and are slow to wash out due to high affinity, are difficult to confine spatially, and generally cannot be targeted to a specific cell. Genetic manipulations, like gene-knockout or RNA-interference, provide subunit-specificity, but are either for the life of the organism or, when conditional, slow to turn on and cannot typically be turned off. These chronic effects can lead to circuit changes and compensation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Nakazawa et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Rossi et al., 2015</xref>). Moreover, the ability to confine these manipulations to specific brain regions and cell types is limited. The problems of spatial and temporal control have been addressed by the advent of caged versions of glutamate, NMDA and the pore blocker MK-801, which can be photo-uncaged in very small volumes at precise times (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Huang et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Kohl et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Matsuzaki et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Palma-Cerda et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Rodríguez-Moreno et al., 2011</xref>). MK-801 can work from inside the cell and, therefore, can be loaded <italic>via</italic> the patch pipet, whereas glutamate and NMDA cannot and so cannot be targeted precisely to a specific cell; furthermore, none of these compounds are selective for receptor subtype. A recent development has been the subunit-specific control of an ion channel with a photo-reactive unnatural amino acid that enables photo-inactivation. So far, this methodology has been applied to a potassium channel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kang et al., 2013</xref>), AMPA receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Klippenstein et al., 2014</xref>) and GluN2B-containing NMDA receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib106">Zhu et al., 2014</xref>). However, photo-inactivation requires intense and prolonged irradiation with UV light and, importantly, is irreversible.</p><p>To overcome the above obstacles, we set out to endow individual GluN subunits with fast and reversible light-switching via the site-directed, on-cell attachment of a Photoswitched Tethered Ligand (PTL). We employed PTLs from the 'MAG' family (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a</xref>), which consist of <underline>M</underline>aleimide (for covalent attachment to a cysteine residue substituted onto the water exposed surface of the ligand binding domain of the GluN subunit), a photo-isomerizable <underline>A</underline>zobenzene linked to a <underline>G</underline>lutamate ligand (for synthesis see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">Volgraf et al., 2006</xref>]). Illumination with near UV light (360–405 nm; violet light) isomerizes MAG into the bent <italic>cis-</italic>configuration, whereas illumination with blue-green light (460–560 nm; green light) isomerizes MAG to the <italic>trans-</italic>configuration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Gorostiza and Isacoff, 2008</xref>). By choosing geometrically favorable positions for introduction of the cysteine attachment site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>) and altering the length of the MAG molecule by varying the linker via additional glycine(s) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a</xref>, dashed brackets; <italic>n</italic>), the glutamate moiety of MAG can be designed to either engage or obstruct the ligand binding pocket in the <italic>cis</italic> configuration, and withdraw from the ligand binding pocket in the <italic>trans</italic> configuration, yielding light-dependent gating (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2a</xref>, but see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Numano et al., 2009</xref>]). PTLs, including MAGs, have been employed to generate light-gated ionotropic kainate receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Janovjak et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Reiner et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Szobota et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">Volgraf et al., 2006</xref>), metabotropic glutamate receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>), nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib90">Tochitsky et al., 2012</xref>), P2X receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Lemoine et al., 2013</xref>) and GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Lin et al., 2014</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.003</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Photo-<italic>agonism</italic> of NMDA receptors in HEK293 cells and hippocampal neurons.</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) MAG photoswitches showing chemical structure and cartoon depiction. MAG0 and MAG1 differ in length (brackets, <italic>n</italic> = 0, 1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gorostiza et al., 2007</xref>), whereas L-MAG and D-MAG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>) differ in stereochemistry (red asterisk). Illumination with 360–405 nm light photoisomerizes MAG from the elongated <italic>trans-</italic> azobenzene (red) configuration to the bent <italic>cis</italic> configuration; illumination at ~460–560 nm returns MAG to the <italic>trans</italic> isomer, as does slow thermal relaxation in the dark. The maleimide group (cyan) allows attachment to an engineered cysteine. (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) Space filled, crystal structure of GluN2A’s Ligand Binding Domain (LBD, PDB-2A5S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Furukawa et al., 2005</xref>)) showing the site of glutamate binding (blue sticks) as well as the nearby V713 position (green spheres), which was mutated to a cysteine to which maleimide tethers and yields photo-agonism. (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) Cartoon depiction of a photo-agonized NMDA receptor showing, for simplicity, only one of the two LiGluN1a-<italic>wt</italic> subunits (purple) co-assembling with one of the two engineered LiGluN2A subunits (pink). The MAG photoswitch (color-coded sticks; as shown in <bold>a</bold>) is covalently attached to the LBD (cyan dot) to endow the channel with light-sensitivity. The <italic>cis</italic> configuration allows docking of the glutamate headgroup (orange triangle) into the binding pocket (middle cartoon), inducing LBD closure and channel opening (rightward cartoon). For simplicity the ligand of the GluN1 subunit (glycine) is not shown. Light- and glutamate/NMDA-induced currents in (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>) HEK293 cells or (<bold><bold>e</bold></bold>) hippocampal neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats) expressing GluN1a-<italic>wt</italic> and GluN2A(V713C) labeled with L-MAG1. Photo-current is elicited by 380 nm light (~3 mW/mm<sup>2</sup>) (violet bar) and turned off by 500 nm light (~3 mW/mm<sup>2</sup>) (green bar). Full activation is induced by application of 1 mM glutamate or NMDA (black bar). (<bold><bold>f</bold></bold>) Representative trace (averaged from 4 consecutives sweeps) for fast MAG photoisomerization by an intense 375 nm light pulse (2 ms at ~20 W/mm<sup>2</sup>) leading to rapid activation and opening of GluN2A(V713C) (red trace is a monoexponential fit, τ indicated). (<bold><bold>g</bold>-<bold>h</bold></bold>) Representative traces (2 cells) for tuning the off kinetics of the photo-current by applying high intensity (~12 mW/mm<sup>2</sup>, average of 8 consecutive sweeps) for fast deactivation (<bold><bold>g</bold></bold>) or low green light intensity (~1.5 mW/mm<sup>2</sup>, average trace from 4 consecutives sweeps) for slow deactivation (<bold><bold>h</bold></bold>). (<bold><bold>i</bold></bold>) Representative image (left, scale bar 10 µm) and trace (right) showing the bistability of the photoswitch in a cultured hippocampal neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats) transfected with GluN2A(V713C)-only. The <italic>cis</italic> state of MAG is photo-stable, so that following illumination (targeted line-scanning) by a brief 405 nm laser pulse (2 s) over a large region of the dendritic tree (dashed violet box) induces an inward current (black trace, ON) that persists in the dark without visible decay for tens of seconds (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>). Likewise, following closure of the channel (black trace- OFF) with brief green light (488 nm) illumination (2 sec), the channel remains shut and no current is observed unless triggered anew by violet light. Spontaneous EPSCs are observed during the opening and closing of the channel.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.003">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.003</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Screen of GluN2A cysteine positions and MAG variants.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Amino acids near the glutamate binding site of GluN2A were individually replaced with cysteine by site-directed mutagenesis, co-transfected with wild-type GluN1a into HEK293 cells, and tested with several MAG variants: L-MAG0, L-MAG1, L-MAG2 and D-MAG1, previously used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">Volgraf et al., 2006</xref>). Photo-responses were detected by calcium-imaging with Fura2-AM and characterized as agonist or antagonist by photo-switching in the absence and presence of 1 mM glutamate, respectively. Most photo-responses, albeit small, were detected during illumination with 380 nm light (violet), one during illumination at 500 nm (green), and several exhibited no photo-response (grey). The colors in the first column correspond to the sites group-colored in the structure of GluN2A’s LBD on the left (PDB-2A5S [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Furukawa et al., 2005</xref>]). The largest agonistic and antagonistic photo-responses yielded by violet light illumination (emphasized by solid boxes and colored fonts) were GluN2A(V713C) conjugated to L-MAG1 and GluN2A(G712C) conjugated to L-MAG0, respectively, and were subsequently scrutinized using patch clamping techniques (examples shown in <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> and see main figures). (<bold><bold>b</bold>-<bold>c</bold></bold>) Repeatable manipulation of photo-switching speed. Near-UV and green light illumination was switched at varying frequencies to mimic different modes of transmissions and or experimental paradigms. Representative traces from cultured hippocampal neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats) showing the versatility of the photo-switching technique and responses in neurons. Illumination at 405 nm (violet bars) is used to open the channels (downward inflection of the current), whereas 488 nm (green bars, upward inflection of the current) to close them. This could be done repeatedly at low (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) or high switching frequency (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.004">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.004</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig1-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.005</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Pharmacological characterization of GluN2A(V713C), GluN2A(G712C), GluN2B(V714C) and GluN1a(E406C).</title><p>Wild-type (<italic>wt</italic>) and engineered GluNRs were expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes and ligand-induced currents were recorded by two-electrode voltage-clamp (V<sub>m</sub> = −60 mV, 0 Mg<sup>2+</sup>). (<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) GluN1a-<italic>wt</italic> and GluN2A (<italic>wt</italic>, V713C or 712C) currents (normalized) in response to increasing glutamate concentrations alone (black, red, blue, respectively), summarized in (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>). (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) GluN1a-<italic>wt</italic> and GluN2B (<italic>wt</italic> or V714C) currents (normalized) in response to increasing glutamate concentrations alone (black, green respectively), summarized in (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>). (<bold>e</bold>) GluN1a (<italic>wt</italic> or E406C) and GluN2B-<italic>wt</italic> currents (normalized) in response to increasing glycine concentrations alone (black, purple, respectively), summarized in (<bold><bold>f</bold></bold>). (<bold><bold>g</bold>-<bold>h</bold></bold>) Activation kinetics of GluNRs containing the LiGluNx subunits. Activation kinetics were assessed by fast uncaging of 500 µM MNI-glutamate over the entire HEK293 cells (pink bar- 1 ms pulse, 375 nm, ~50 W/mm<sup>2</sup>) of (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Matsuzaki et al., 2001</xref>) during whole cell voltage-clamp recording. The uncaging elicited rapid activation of <italic>wt</italic> and engineered GluN2A (V713C or G712C) subunits (<bold><bold>g</bold></bold>) or <italic>wt</italic> and engineered GluN2B(V714C) subunits (<bold><bold>h</bold></bold>) co-expressed with GluN1a-<italic>wt</italic> in HEK293 cells. In <bold>g,</bold> bar graphs show mean ± SD, n.s., not significant, one way ANOVA, Dunnet <italic>post hoc</italic> test or <bold>h</bold>; two-tailed, unpaired t-test, <italic>n</italic> shown within bars. Non parametric Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Test.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.005">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.005</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig1-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.006</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Lack of perturbation of neurons by MAG or LiGluN2A(G712C).</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) MAG-exposure does not cause cell death or damage membrane integrity of cultured hippocampal neurons. Representative images of neurons (15 DIV) from <italic>wt</italic> animals following incubation for 45 min with either L-MAG1, 0.3% DMSO (in NMDG buffer) or NMDG buffer alone (see Materials and methods) showed no reduction in cell viability (green labeling) or membrane integrity (red labeling, neurites) compared to untreated cells (no treatment prior labeling) and Summary (right) (N coverslips= no treatment (no treatm.)- 2, +NMDG- 2, +DMSO- 5, +L-MAG1- 9). Values are mean ± SEM (n.s., not significant, one way ANOVA, <italic>post hoc</italic> Tukey test, all pairwise comparison). (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) Expression of GluN2A(G712C) combined with exposure to L-MAG0 does not perturb electrophysiological properties of neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats) in comparison to non-transfected neurons that were also exposed to MAG. No change in resting potential (left) or resting membrane resistance (right) was observed between non-transfected (black bars) and GFP-NR2A(G712V)-transfected (cyan bars) neurons. (<bold><bold>c</bold>-<bold>d</bold></bold>) No effect of MAG on native receptors or channels. (Left) Representative trace showing a non-transfected hippocampal neuron, though treated with L-MAG1, that does not display any light-responses to either 380 nm light (violet bar) or 500 nm light (green bar); before or during application (and washout) of 1 mM NMDA. Summary of the effect of light on the current in individual non-transfected neurons (exposed to L-MAG1, middle panel) and box plot representation with median and outliers (filled circles, right panel) displayed. (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>) Transfection of GFP-GluN2A(G712C) (orange bar) did alter GluNR-expression compared to GFP only -transfected neurons (green bar), as no change in total current amplitude induced by 1 mM NMDA was observed. To note, these observations are in line with earlier reports demonstrating that MAG (and related PTLs) do not have non-specific action or adverse effect on neuronal physiology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Caporale et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Lemoine et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Li et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Szobota et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib90">Tochitsky et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">Volgraf et al., 2006</xref>). (<bold><bold>e</bold></bold>) Representative trace showing the bistability of the photoswitch. The <italic>cis</italic> state of MAG is photo-stable, so that following activation by a brief 380 nm light pulse the current persists in the dark without visible decay for 60 s (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1i</xref> and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Reiner and Isacoff, 2014</xref>]). Statistics in panels (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) and (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>) are shown as mean ± SEM, tested with two-tailed, unpaired t-test; n.s.- not-significant, <italic>n</italic>, shown within bars.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.006">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.006</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig1-figsupp3-v1"/></fig></fig-group><fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.007</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Rapid development of light-agonized LiGluN2B subunit, based on LiGluN2A.</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) Partial sequence alignment (left) and overlaid crystal structures (ribbon) of the LBDs of GluN2A (blue, PDB-2A5S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Furukawa et al., 2005</xref>)) and GluN2B (grey, PDB- 4PE5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Karakas and Furukawa, 2014</xref>]) showing the high degree of similarity between the two LBDs and the corresponding mutation in GluN2B(V714) to that of LiGluN2A(V713) (dashed circle, Valine; color-coded spheres). (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) Representative trace of photo-agonism of LiGluN2B(V714C). A HEK293 cell transfected with GluN1a and LiGluN2B(V714C), and labeled with L-MAG1, when illuminated with 380 nm light (violet bars) produces an inward photo-current that can be turned off by 510 nm light (green bars). Note the small increase in current during glutamate perfusion, suggesting that L-MAG1 may act as a stronger agonist than glutamate. (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) LiGluN2B(V714C) photocurrents are of similar size, but slower to turn off than those of LiGluN2A(V713C). Hippocampal neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats), transfected with either LiGluN2A (top black trace) or -2B (bottom grey trace) exhibit similar inward photo-currents, during which barrages of spontaneous EPSCs emerge (violet bars), demonstrating that photo-activation of LiGluNs receptors causes action potential firing of presynaptic neurons (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> and Figure 4 supplements). LiGluN2B photocurrents deactivate ~3 times slower than those of LiGluN2A (insets), as well as display consistently longer enduring observable EPSCs, summarized in <bold>d-f</bold>. (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>) Box plot representation of median, outliers (filled circles) and individual data points (filled squares) are displayed. Red trace in (<bold><bold>f</bold></bold>) is a monoexponential fit, τ indicated. Statistics in panels are shown as Box plots of the data (not normally distributed, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>), showing median, outliers (filled circles) and individual data points (filled squares in <bold><bold>d</bold></bold>). Significance was tested using a nonparametric Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Test (see Materials and methods), ***p&lt;0.001, n.s.- not-significant, <italic>n</italic> shown next to plots.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.007">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.007</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.008</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Photo-activation of LiGluN2A and -2B drives action potential firing in hippocampal neurons.</title><p>(<bold>a-b</bold>) Representative traces (current clamp) of neurons transfected with LiGluN2A(V713C) (<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>, black trace) or LiGluN2B(V714C) (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>, grey); labeled with L-MAG1 and illuminated with 380 nm (violet bars) or 510 nm (green bars) light. Neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats), held at -45 to -50 mV, during green light illumination display very little activity (i.e. action potentials, AP). When switching to violet light and photo-activation of LiGluN2A or -2B, neurons display a significant increase in firing frequency (F<sub>AP</sub>, frequency plots shown below traces), summarized for LiGluN2A(V713C) or -2B(V714C) in panels (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) and (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>), respectively. The lag from the appearance of violet light to initiation of an action potential (time to excitation, top insets) and lag to cessation of firing after toggling back to green light (time to de-excitation, bottom insets) are shown and summarized in panels (<bold><bold>f</bold></bold>) and (<bold><bold>g</bold></bold>) respectively. (<bold><bold>e</bold></bold>) No difference in firing frequency was observed between neurons transfected with LiGluN2A(V713C) or -2B(V714C). Statistics in panels are shown as mean ± SEM, tested with two-tailed, unpaired t-test; *p&lt;0.05, ***p&lt;0.001, n.s.- not-significant, <italic>n</italic> shown within bars.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.008">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.008</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig2-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.009</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Summary of nonparametric statistics for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</title><p>Results from Normality and nonparametric Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Tests are displayed for results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2d–f</xref>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.009">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.009</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig2-figsupp2-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>We now report a novel family of four <underline>Li</underline>ght-gated GluN subunits, or LiGluNs: 1) a light-activated GluN2A, 2) a light-activated GluN2B, 3) a light-antagonized GluN2A and 4) a light-antagonized GluN1, isoform 1a, (GluN1a). The first three LiGluN subunits enable selective manipulation of GluN2A- or GluN2B-containing receptors, whereas the fourth operates as a general controller of <underline>all</underline> plasma membrane NMDA receptors, owing to the obligatory occurrence of GluN1 in all NMDA receptors. We show that LiGluN-containing NMDA receptors function normally, incorporate into synapses, and that their expression does not alter NMDA receptor expression levels. Photoswitching can be sculpted to generate NMDA receptor currents that mimic the fast (GluN2A-like) or slow (GluN2B-like) deactivation kinetics of native excitatory postsynaptic currents (EPSCs). Widefield illumination and photo-activation of LiGluN2A or LiGluN2B-containing receptors in primary hippocampal neurons robustly drives activity, whereas photo-antagonism of LiGluN2A and LiGluN1a reversibly block excitatory synaptic currents. Spatially-targeted photo-activation of LiGluN2A-containing receptors on single dendritic spines can be used to trigger a spine-specific increase in calcium and the spine expansion that is associated with LTP. Complementarily to this, photo-antagonism of LiGluN2A-containing receptors can block LTP-induction via Schaffer collateral stimulation or prevent spine expansion. LiGluNs fulfill a major promise of chemical optogenetic photo-pharmacology by providing the kind of spatio-temporally precise control that is obtained with heterologous microbial opsins, that over-ride normal cellular signals, but in this case to control the native neuronal signaling proteins of the synapse that play central roles in synaptic plasticity, learning and memory. Together, these tools may open the door to advanced studies of receptor biophysics, and their function in synapses and neural circuits.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Development of photo-agonized LiGluN subunits</title><p>We, and others, have previously generated light-controlled receptors and channels to manipulate cellular excitability (e.g. see reviews [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Kramer et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">Szobota and Isacoff, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib92">Tye and Deisseroth, 2012</xref>]) by photo-regulating the flux of ions across the cell membrane. Here, we asked whether light-activated NMDA receptors could be engineered, which would traffic to synapses and function normally and thereby engage the cellular mechanisms of neuronal plasticity. Our previous success with light-gated glutamate receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Szobota et al., 2007</xref>) along with other reports demonstrating that exogenously expressed GluN2 subunits efficiently co-assemble with endogenous GluN1 subunits and traffic properly to synapses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Barria and Malinow, 2002</xref>), suggested to us that this could be achieved by designing GluN subunits that contain a single cysteine attachment site for anchoring the MAG PTL.</p><p>We therefore systematically introduced single cysteine point mutations at different locations on the GluN2A ligand-binding domain (LBD) with proximity and accessibility to the glutamate binding site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1a</xref>), and following conjugation to different MAG variants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a</xref>), assessed the effects of photoswitching in HEK293 cells, first using calcium-imaging and then following with voltage-clamp recordings of the most promising candidates, as shown below. We found several attachment positions that yielded light-responses, however focused on variants that when conjugated to L-MAG0 or L-MAG1, yielded the largest light-responses.</p><p>We initially focused on photo-agonism of the light-gated GluN2A subunits with the cysteine attachment site introduced at residue 713 (LiGluN2A(V713C)). When LiGluN2A(V713C) was co-expressed with wildtype (<italic>wt</italic>) GluN1a, photoisomerization of L-MAG1 to its <italic>cis</italic> configuration by illumination with 380 nm light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a,c</xref>) generated an inward current (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1d,e</xref>- violet bars) in both HEK293 cells (37.3 ± 2.2% of the total current induced by 1 mM glutamate, n = 5, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1d</xref>) and in primary cultured hippocampal neurons (30.8 ± 5.9% of the total current induced by 1 mM NMDA, n = 6, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1e</xref>). This photocurrent could then be completely turned off by photoisomerization of L-MAG1 to <italic>trans</italic> by illumination at 488 nm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1d,e</xref>- green bars). Since the isomerization of the azobenzene is fast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1f</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Reiner and Isacoff, 2014</xref>) and fully reversible, opening and closing of the channels could be accomplished by toggling between near-UV and green-light illumination, at various frequencies and repeatedly, to mimic various physiological patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1b,c</xref>). No inhibition of the current was observed during photo-agonism in the presence of saturating glutamate or NMDA, suggesting that when MAG in its <italic>cis</italic> form competes with free glutamate in LiGluN2A, and is as good an agonist as glutamate.</p><p>Dose-response profiling of NMDA receptors containing LiGluN2A(V713C) (as well as other variants, see below) shows preservation of the glutamate potency (EC50) as seen in <italic>wt</italic> receptors that contain the GluN2A-<italic>wt</italic> subunit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2a,b</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anson et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Chen et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Hedegaard et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Paoletti et al., 2013</xref>). Moreover, LiGluN2A(V713C)-containing receptors have <italic>wt</italic> activation kinetics, as assessed by fast MNI-glutamate uncaging that was designed to mimic the brief rise of glutamate that occurs in synapses due to vesicle release (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2g</xref>).</p><p>Importantly, MAG labeling had no effect on the health, resting membrane potential or membrane resistance of cultured hippocampal neurons and yielded no photo-responses in neurons that did not express the cysteine-modified GluN2 subunit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3a–c</xref>), indicating a lack of action on native glutamate receptors or other channels. Moreover, expression of the LiGluN2A subunit did not significantly change the amplitude of NMDA-induced current in hippocampal neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3d</xref>), suggesting that it competes with native LiGluN2 subunits for assembly with the native GluN1, so that the total number of synaptic NMDA receptors is preserved, but now subject to photo-control. Together, these results show that NMDA receptors containing the LiGluN subunits should support normal synaptic transmission and plasticity, while providing specific photo-control over these processes.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Temporal control of LiGluN2A(V713C)-containing receptors</title><p>MAG photoswitching provides two advantageous properties for the remote control of NMDA receptors. First, since the speed of MAG photoswitching depends on light intensity so that switching can be achieved either with short high intensity pulses or longer low intensity pulses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gorostiza et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Reiner and Isacoff, 2014</xref>), it should be possible to sculpt the photocurrent to resemble NMDA receptor excitatory postsynaptic currents (EPSC<sub>NMDA</sub>). Using LiGluN2A(V713C) conjugated to L-MAG1, a 2 ms pulse of 375 nm light could be used to trigger substantial receptor activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1f</xref>), with the fast rise kinetics comparable to those of EPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> kinetics observed for GluN2A-containing synaptic NMDA receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bidoret et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Erreger and Traynelis, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib93">Vicini et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib100">Yuan et al., 2009</xref>). Then, off-photoswiching could be triggered over tens of milliseconds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1g</xref>), as typical of GluN2A, or more slowly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1h</xref>) to mimic the slower GluN2B deactivation kinetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Erreger and Traynelis, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib94">Vicini et al., 1998</xref>). Triggering these EPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> waveforms by only regulating light intensity avoids the need for piezo-driven fast perfusion systems and a cocktail of inhibitors typically used to isolate EPSCs<sub>NMDA</sub>. Since variations in the off-kinetics leads to variation in the intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-concentration, this kind of control could be employed to study the role of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and specific NMDA receptor subtypes in the induction of LTP and LTD, as it is still debated how the magnitude, temporal pattern and NMDA receptor subunit type contribute to plasticity changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Cummings et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Köhr et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Pawlak et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">Shipton and Paulsen, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib105">Zhou et al., 2005</xref>). A second advantageous property is the bistability of MAG photoswitches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gorostiza et al., 2007</xref>). After switching with a brief 380 nm light pulse, photo-agonism (or photo-antagonism, as described below) is sustained in the dark for extended periods of time, until it is reversed by a brief 500 nm light pulse, as illustrated in both hippocampal neurons, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1i</xref>) and HEK293 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3e</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Design of a photo-agonistic LiGluN2B subunit</title><p>Our scan to identify effective cysteine attachment sites for MAGs in LiGluN2A provided a guide for the development of a LiGluN2B based on the homology of its LBD with that of GluN2A. Hence, we introduced a cysteine at position 714 of GluN2B, corresponding to the 713 position that yielded the photo-agonism in GluN2A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2a</xref>). Indeed, conjugation of L-MAG1 to LiGluN2B(V714C) that was coexpressed with GluN1a in HEK293 cells yielded GluN2B-containing NMDA receptors which were activated by light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2b</xref>). Unlike with LiGluN2A(V713C), photo-activation of LiGluN2B(V714C) in the presence of saturating glutamate yielded a small increase in current (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2b</xref>), suggesting that L-MAG1 is a more potent agonist than glutamate. Importantly, LiGluN2B(V714C)-containing receptors displayed the same glutamate affinity and activation kinetics as <italic>wt</italic> GluN2B receptors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2c, d and h</xref>), indicating that, as with LiGluN2A(V713C), the orthogonal light control is obtained over receptors that otherwise function normally.</p><p>Light-agonistic LiGluN2A and LiGluN2B subunits were examined side-by-side in hippocampal neurons. We expressed either LiGluN2A or LiGluN2B alone, relying on them to co-assemble with the endogenous pool of GluN1a subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Barria and Malinow, 2002</xref>). Following labeling with L-MAG1, each of these variants gave rise to photocurrents in neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2c</xref>). The LiGluN2A and LiGluN2B photocurrents were similar in amplitude and activation kinetics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2d and e</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>), but the LiGluN2B photocurrent turned off ~3 times more slowly under identical light conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2c</xref>, inset and f and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>), reminiscent of the slower deactivation kinetics of GluN2B- than GluN2A-containing receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bidoret et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib94">Vicini et al., 1998</xref>). Widefield photoactivation at 380 nm of both LiGluN2A and LiGluN2B triggered an increase in EPSC frequency and this was reversed—more slowly in LiGluN2B—by illumination at 510 nm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2c</xref>), suggesting that photoactivation of NMDA receptors containing either LiGluN2A or LiGluN2B triggered action potential firing in presynaptic neurons. Indeed, in current clamp recording, photoactivation (violet bars) and photodeactivation (green bars) reliably and reproducibly elicited bouts of firing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1a–e</xref>). Photoactivation of LiGluN2A elicited a faster rise of excitation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1a–b</xref>, top insets, and f) and photodeactivation of LiGluN2A elicited a faster (~three fold) de-excitation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1a–b</xref>, bottom insets, and g) than neurons expressing LiGluN2B.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Development of photo-antagonized LiGluN subunits</title><p>Our initial screen also identified several LBD anchoring positions where light blocked the glutamate-induced current (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1a</xref>), suggesting that, instead of docking correctly in the glutamate binding pocket, the ligand end of MAG could obstruct access of free glutamate to the binding pocket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3a</xref>). The largest photo-antagonism was generated by L-MAG0 anchored at G712C of the GluN2A subunit when expressed in hippocampal neurons (56.4 ± 2.9% inhibition of the total current induced by 1 mM NMDA, n = 7) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3b, c and f</xref>), similar to the block observed in HEK293 cells (65.8 ± 4.3% inhibition of the total current induced by 1 mM glutamate in HEK cells, n = 9). This photo-antagonism is on par with the antagonism of GluN2A by NVP-AAM077, when applied at concentrations that maintain subunit selectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Monaghan et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Neyton and Paoletti, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Paoletti and Neyton, 2007</xref>), and so, although incomplete (likely due to labeling efficiency, see below and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>), would be predicted to have utility. Whereas the specific photo-antagonism of GluN2A enables fast, reversible inhibition of GluN2A-containing NMDA receptors <italic>only</italic>, we also sought to develop a general tool for photo-antagonizing <italic>all</italic> NMDA receptor-subtypes within a given neuron, by creating a photo-antagonized GluN1. The GluN1 subunit is activated by glycine or D-serine, but not glutamate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3b</xref>). In fact, GluN1 antagonists resemble MAG in that they consist of an α-amino acid attached to a larger structure that prevents closure of the LBD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Inanobe et al., 2005</xref>). We therefore reasoned that MAG tethered near the GluN1 ligand binding pocket would prevent normal agonist binding when photo-docked and would thereby function as a photo-antagonist. Indeed, a screen of cysteine mutants around the glycine-binding pocket identified a labeling site, E406C, where L-MAG0 functioned as photo-antagonist (30.7 ± 1.7% inhibition of the total current neurons, n = 6) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3b, d and f</xref>), without affecting the glycine potency of the subunit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2e,f</xref>). When the photo-antagonizable GluN1a(E406C) and GluN2A(G712C) subunits were co-expressed in dissociated hippocampal neurons and incubated with L-MAG0, their combined effect resulted in 73.8 ± 5.2% (n = 4) photo-inhibition of the total NMDA-induced current in neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3e,f</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.010</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Photo-<italic>antagonism</italic> of NMDA receptors in hippocampal neurons.</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) Photo-antagonism with L-MAG0 attached to LiGluN2A(G712C), where the <italic>cis</italic>-configuration is thought to place the glutamate end of MAG near the binding pocket, where it impedes LBD closure or entry of free glutamate (blue triangles, rightmost cartoon), leaving the channel closed. (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) Space filled, crystal structures of GluN1a (light grey) and GluN2A (dark grey) LBDs (PDB-2A5S, 2A5T(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Furukawa et al., 2005</xref>), respectively) showing the sites of glycine and glutamate binding (green and blue sticks, respectively) as well as the nearby E406 and G712 positions (red spheres) which, when tethered to L-MAG0, yield photo-antagonism. (<bold><bold>c-e</bold></bold>) Representative traces of photo-antagonism by 380 nm light (violet bars) of NMDA currents induced by 1 mM NMDA (black bars) in neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats) labeled with L-MAG0 that express either: <bold>b-</bold> GluN1a-<italic>wt</italic> and GluN2A(G712C) to photo-block the glutamate binding pocket of the GluN2A subunit; <bold>c-</bold> GluN1a(E406C) to photo-block the glycine binding site of GluN1a subunit; <bold>d-</bold> GluN1a(E406C) and GluN2A(G712C) to photo-block both classes of binding sites. (<bold><bold>f</bold></bold>) Summary of the average (± SEM) photo-antagonism (red bars) and photo-agonism (green bars) observed in neurons. <italic>n</italic> shown within bars.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.010">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.010</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.011</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Moderate correlation between total current size and photo-current.</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) Representative traces of photo-antagonism (left) and photo-agonism (right), displaying the relative sizes of the total NMDA-induced current and the photo-responses (inhibition/activation), plotted in <bold><bold>b</bold>.</bold> (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) A modest correlation (Spearman, R = 0.709, R<sup>2 </sup>= 0.502), albeit significant (p&lt;0.001), was obtained for the relationship between both types of currents, suggesting that the variation in the photo-current size cannot be fully (~50%) explained by a simple increase in the content of NMDA receptors at the plasma membrane (assuming consistent MAG-labeling efficiency). Variability in photo-current size is likely due to variability in labeling efficiency.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.011">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.011</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig3-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Cultured hippocampal neurons from <italic>wt</italic> rats (C57BL) transfected with the photo-antagonizing GluN2A(G712C) subunit in combination with photo-antagonizing GluN1a(E406C), labeled with L-MAG0 and under green light illumination, exhibited typical action potential activity under current clamp recordings. Photo-antagonism with 370 nm light hyperpolarized cells and suppressed firing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4a,b</xref>), as seen with conventional NMDA receptor blockers. No such photo-effect was seen in non-transfected cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4c,d</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>). Reversal of photo-antagonism by 510 nm light elicited a gradual repolarization, reminiscent of physiological recovery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4b</xref>). In voltage clamp, neurons transfected with the photo-antagonizing GluN2A(G712C) subunit alone, or in combination with the photo-antagonizing GluN1a(E406C), displayed typical barrages of spontaneous EPSC<sub>NMDA</sub>events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Groc et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Ivenshitz and Segal, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Kirson and Yaari, 1996</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1a</xref>). During green light illumination, action currents were detected in some cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1a</xref>, arrow and inset) and illumination with violet light decreased the inward current, the frequency of action currents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1a</xref>, inset), and of spontaneous EPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1a</xref>, and summary in d), with no effect of violet light on non-transfected neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1b</xref>, right panel, summary in c and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.012</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Photo-inhibition of neuronal activity with LiGluN1a and LiGluN2A.</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) Representative trace showing a long recording (current clamp) of a neuron (from <italic>wt</italic> rats) transfected with LiGluN1a(E406C) and LiGluN2A(G712C), labeled with L-MAG0, and illuminated with 380 nm (violet bars) or 510 nm (green bars) light (held at −40 mV, Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free, 20 µM CNQX). During green light illumination, the neuron displayed strong action potential activity that could be faithfully inhibited by near-UV light (i.e. block is ON), as the photo-antagonism hyperpolarized the cell to suppress action potential firing, (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>), as typically seen with soluble GluNRs blockers. (<bold><bold>c-d</bold></bold>) Summary of photo-antagonism on membrane potential on individual transfected- and non-transfected neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats) (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>), and summary of the effect on membrane potential (ΔVm) is shown in (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>). (<bold><bold>e</bold></bold>) Summary for the reduction in firing frequency following violet light illumination of individual cells (circles) and averages ± SEM (color-coded filled squares). Statistics in panel <bold>d</bold> are shown as Box plots of the data (not normally distributed, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>), showing median and outliers (filled circles) followed by a nonparametric Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Test (see methods), ***p&lt;0.001, **p&lt;0.01, n.s.- not-significant, <italic>n</italic> shown next to plots. Statistics in panel <bold>e</bold> are shown as mean ± SEM, tested with two-tailed, paired t-test; **p&lt;0.01.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.012">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.012</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig4-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.013</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Photo-<italic>antagonism</italic> of NMDA receptors in hippocampal neurons inhibits the development of EPSCs.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Representative trace (voltage clamp, −60 mV) of a hippocampal neuron (from <italic>wt</italic> rats) transfected with LiGluN1a(E406C) and LiGluN2A(G712C), labeled with L-MAG0. During green light illumination (i.e. no block), spontaneous EPSC can be seen (F<sub>EPSC</sub>- frequency shown in plot below trace), as well as occasional current potentials (arrow and asterisks in inset). During violet light (i.e. during receptor block), the baseline current is reduced as well as the frequency of EPSCs (shown in plot below trace) and current potentials completely disappear. Note that the current potentials were cut in trace to ease the view of the much smaller EPSCs (inset). (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) Light-induced photo-antagonism reduces the current in individual transfected-, but not in non-transfected (non-trans.), neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats). (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) Average ( ± SEM) of the extent of current reduction in transfected and non-transfected neurons. (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>) Reduction in the frequency of EPSCs. During 370 nm illumination (violet bar) individual neurons display a consistent decrease in the frequency of spontaneous EPSCs (filled squares, mean ± SEM). Statistics in panel <bold>c</bold> are shown as Box plots of the data (not normally distributed, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref>), showing median and outliers (filled circles) followed by a nonparametric Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Test (see methods), ***p&lt;0.001. Statistics in panel d are shown as mean ± SEM (filled color-coded squares) and individual cells are displayed (circles). <italic>n</italic>, when displayed, appears next to bars. Hippocampal neurons obtained from <italic>wt</italic> rats.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.013">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.013</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig4-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig4s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.014</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Summary of nonparametric statistics for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>.</title><p>Results from Normality and nonparametric Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Tests are displayed for results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4c–e</xref> and for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1b–d</xref>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.014">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.014</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig4-figsupp2-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>LiGluNs operate at synapses to provide optical control over NMDA receptor synaptic current</title><p>The fundamental power of the highly selective photo-pharmacology that is utilized in chemical optogenetics is the ability to orthogonally and spatially control native signaling proteins in their physiological location in the cell- in the synapse for NMDA receptors. To test whether LiGluN2 subunits are incorporated into synapses, as shown earlier for <italic>wt</italic> GluN2A or GluN2B subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Cummings et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Prybylowski et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib89">Thomas et al., 2006</xref>), we turned to autaptic connections, in which hippocampal neurons from <italic>wt</italic> rats are grown at low density (see Materials and methods) that neurons synapse onto themselves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5a</xref>), thereby serving as both the presynaptic cell which can be stimulated electrically as well as the postsynaptic cell, from which we can record synaptic currents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bekkers and Stevens, 1991</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.015</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Photo-block of synaptic transmission by LiGluNs in hippocampal autapses.</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) (left) Representative images of hippocampal neurons (from <italic>wt</italic> rats) grown in low density forming autapses. (right) Schematics of hippocampal autapse used to measure the effect on the NMDA receptors EPSC (blue trace, evoked NMDA EPSC- eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub>) of turning ON (violet bar) and OFF (green bar) the photo-antagonsim of LiGluN. (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) No significant difference in eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> amplitude (left) or deactivation times (bi-exponential weighted τ<sub>deact</sub>) (right) in autaptic neurons expressing GluN2A(G712C) alone (cyan) or GluN2A(G712C) and GluN1a(E406C) (red) compared to non-transfected control neurons (black) (from <italic>wt</italic> rats). Inset shows superimposed eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> for the three conditions. (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) Autaptic NMDA receptor’s EPSCs in neurons transfected with GluN2A(G712C) and GluN1a(E406C) before photo-antagonism (1, under 510 nm light). Individual EPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> (grey) are superimposed with average of 5 consecutive EPSCs (green for 510 nm light; violet for 370 nm light). Photo-antagonism 370 nm light reversibly reduces the amplitude of the eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub>. (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>) Time series of NMDA receptors EPSC amplitudes for cell shown in (<bold>c</bold>) reveals repeated reversibility of photo-block of eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub>, despite the typical rundown of the responses (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Goda and Stevens, 1998</xref>]). (<bold><bold>e</bold></bold>) Non-transfected cell exposed to L-MAG0 does not exhibit light-dependent modulation of eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> amplitude. (<bold><bold>f</bold></bold>) Summary of photo-block (as % inhibition) of autaptic NMDA receptors EPSCs in transfected and non-transfected neurons (color scheme as in <bold><bold>b</bold></bold>). 4 cells were excluded (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>). Statistics in panels <bold>b</bold> and <bold>c</bold> are shown as Box plots displaying medians, outliers (filled circles) and individual data points (filled, color-coded squares), followed by a nonparametric ANOVA on ranks (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>), n.s., not significant. Statistics for panel <bold>f</bold> are shown as mean ± SEM, tested with one way ANOVA, ***p&lt;0.001, **p&lt;0.01, all pairwise Tukey <italic>post hoc</italic> test, <italic>n</italic> shown in parentheses atop bars.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.015">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.015</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig5-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.016</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Summary of nonparametric and parametric statistics for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>.</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) Results from Normality tests and nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis One Way Analysis of Variance (ANOVA on ranks) are displayed for panels shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5b</xref> and One Way ANOVA for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5f</xref>. (<bold>b</bold>) No correlation (Spearman, R = 0.543, R<sup>2 </sup>= 0.295, p = 0.297) was obtained for the relationship between the effect of light (i.e. photo-block of the EPSC<sub>NMDA</sub>;% inhibition) and the total size of the synaptic NMDA-current (EPSC<sub>NMDA</sub>) pooled for both LiGluN2 and LiGluN1+2 groups. This suggests that the variation in the effect of light (i.e. relative size of the block) has no relationship with the total size of the synaptic current, in line with the observations displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>. Dashed region- 4 non responding cells transfected with either LiGluN2A-only or with LiGluN2A and LiGluN1a are shown for: 1- comparison with responsive cells and 2- showing variability in labeling efficiency. Non-responding cells (i.e. transfected neurons and exposed to MAG, but that exhibited less than 5% inhibition) were excluded from the average shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5f</xref>. This criterion was defined to differentiate between real photo-inhibition from variability in transmission rundown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Goda and Stevens, 1998</xref>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.016">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.016</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig5-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Transfected neurons that formed autapses displayed eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> events that were similar in amplitude and kinetics to those seen in non-transfected cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1a</xref>), indicating that LiGluN expression makes synaptic NMDA receptors sensitive to light without significantly changing their number, consistent with evidence presented above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3d</xref>) and with earlier reports which expressed wildtype subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Prybylowski et al., 2002</xref>). In neurons that were transfected with the photo-antagonizing LiGluN2A(G712C) and labeled with L-MAG0, the amplitude of the eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> was inhibited by illumination at 370 nm and this photo-antagonism was relieved by illumination at 510 nm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5c, d and f</xref>). The photo-antagonism could be toggled on and off repeatedly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5c,d</xref>), whereas non-transfected neurons showed no change in their eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub>'s amplitude as the wavelength of illumination was switched between 510 nm and 370 nm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5e,f</xref>). The magnitude of the light-dependent inhibition of the synaptic eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> was not correlated with eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> amplitude, suggesting that the degree of inhibition varies primarily with labeling efficiency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1b</xref>; % inhibition ranges from ~20-50%), but also see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>). Thus, LiGluN subunits incorporate into synaptic NMDA receptors and function normally in response to synaptically released glutamate, while providing for optical control over the synaptic transmission that is mediated by that specific receptor subtype.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Photo-antagonism blocks LTP-induction in hippocampal slice</title><p>An attractive application of optical control over the function of specific NMDA receptors is to probe their function in synaptic plasticity in specific neural circuits. To determine whether such control is possible, we initially turned to the prototypical form of NMDA receptor-dependent plasticity, where tetanic stimulation of hippocampal CA3 Schaffer collateral axons evokes LTP at CA1 pyramidal cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bliss and Collingridge, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Lüscher and Malenka, 2012</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6a</xref>). Organotypic slices from GluN2A-knockout neonate mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Sakimura et al., 1995</xref>) were biolistically transfected with GluN1a(E406C), GluN2A(G712C) and tdTomato (typically 1–3 transfected CA1 neurons per slice, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6b</xref>). Following incubation with L-MAG0, neurons were illuminated with green light (497 nm for 2 s) to place the majority of L-MAG0 in its inactive <italic>trans</italic> state. Then, Schaffer collaterals were stimulated at 0.03 Hz and evoked EPSCs were recorded from CA1 neurons for a 8-minute baseline period. Illumination was then applied for 2 s at either 390 nm (photo-antagonism ON; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6c</xref>, violet) or 497 nm (photo-antagonism OFF; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6c</xref>, green). Because of the bistability of MAG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1i</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3e</xref>), LiGluNs remain blocked (following violet light) or unblocked (following green light) in the dark for many minutes. Following the brief illumination protocol, we immediately applied a tetanic stimulation with a pair of 1 s long 100 Hz bursts in the dark. Stimulation was then returned to 0.03 Hz for an extended period to measure changes in synaptic strength (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6c</xref>). Slices, in which L-MAG0 was maintained in <italic>trans</italic> (photo-antagonism off) by green light, exhibited robust LTP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6c</xref>, black circles; EPSC amplitude increased to 185 <underline>+</underline> 31% (n = 10) of baseline, averaged over 20–30 min. post-tetanus; summary in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6d</xref>), whereas slices in which L-MAG0 was switched to <italic>cis</italic> (photo-antagonism on) by violet light did not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6c</xref>, open circles; EPSC amplitude dropped to 67 <underline>+</underline> 28% (n = 10) of baseline, averaged over 20–30 min. post-tetanus; summary in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6d</xref>). Slices to which L-MAG0 was not added, but which were illuminated at 390 nm, exhibited the same level of LTP as those labeled with L-MAG0 and illuminated with 497 nm light (174 <underline>+</underline> 31.74%, n = 4), demonstrating that the light protocol did not interfere with the generation of LTP and that the block of LTP-induction is a specific outcome of photo-antagonism. Thus, photo-antagonism of post-synaptic NMDA receptors can be used to gate the induction of LTP that is induced by presynaptic bursts of action potentials.<fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.017</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>LTP induction blocked by photo-<italic>antagonism</italic> of LiGluN1a(E406C) and LiGluN2A(G712C) in organotypic hippocampal slice from GluN2A-knockout neonate mice.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Schematic of the hippocampus with stimulating electrode on Schaffer collaterals CA3 pyramidal axons that innervate pyramidal neurons of CA1 and recording pipette on a transfected CA1 neuron from Glu2A-KO mice. (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) Transfected neuron in an organotypic hippocampal slice identified by tdTomato fluorescence after biolistic co-transfection of LiGluN1a(E406C), LiGluN2A(G712C) and tdTomato. (<bold>c</bold>) Following exposure of the slices to L-MAG0, Schaffer Collaterals were electrically stimulated once every 30 s to obtain a baseline EPSC amplitude (ranging from −8 to 0 min), followed by two high frequency trains (tetanic stimulation: 1-s long trains at 100 Hz, separated by 20 s), followed by a return for 30 min to a one stimulus every 30 s. Normalized mean ± SEM of evoked EPSC amplitudes once every 30 s are shown (ranging from 0 to 35 min). When the tetanic stimulation was preceded by illumination at 497 nm (photo-antagonism OFF; green bar, filled symbols, n = 10) EPSC amplitude approximately doubled, as common for CA3-CA1 LTP. However, illumination at 390 nm (photo-antagonism ON; violet bar, open symbols, n = 10) prevented the generation of LTP. Inset shows representative average EPSCs before (black traces) and after (at t= 20–30 min) the tetanic stimulation (green and violet traces). (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>) Summary of the results shown in (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>), averaged between <italic>t</italic> = 20–30 min. Statistics in panels are shown as mean ± SEM, tested with two-tailed, unpaired t-test, p as indicated, <italic>n</italic> shown within bars.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.017">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.017</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig6-v1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Single spine GluN2A photo-agonism induces structural plasticity in hippocampal slice</title><p>Having shown that precisely timed light pulses can be used to control the activity of synaptic LiGluN containing NMDA receptors, we turned to a second major attraction of light, the ability to focus in small regions of interest, and attempted to control NMDA receptor function at single synapses. Dendritic spine expansion is a structural correlate of LTP, which can be induced at the level of single dendritic spines by the local photo-uncaging of glutamate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Matsuzaki et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Matsuzaki et al., 2004</xref>). We asked whether highly local, subunit-specific photo-agonism of GluN2A can induce such structural changes at single spines. As with the experiments, above, which demonstrated the ability to block LTP induction by photo-antagonism of LiGluN2A-containing NMDA receptors, these experiments were performed in organotypic slices obtained from GluN2A-knockout neonate mice (see Materials and methods).</p><p>Since calcium entry through NMDA receptors is critical for synaptic plasticity, first we examined the ability of photo-agonized GluN2A(V713C) labeled with L-MAG1 to elicit spine-specific rises in Ca<sup>2+</sup> in slices co-transfected with the soluble calcium reporter R-GECO1.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib104">Zhao et al., 2011</xref>). Illumination of a single spine head at 405 nm (100 µW for 100 µs/pixel) elicited a rise in R-GECO fluorescence in the illuminated spine, with little or no response in nearby spines or in the dendritic shaft, consistent with spine head Ca<sup>2+</sup>-signaling compartmentalization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7b,c</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib101">Yuste, 2013</xref>). We next asked whether photo-activation of GluN2A(V713C) can trigger spine expansion. Slices expressing GluN2A(V713C), along with tdTomato as a reporter of spine size (see Materials and methods and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Holtmaat et al., 2005</xref>]), were labeled with L-MAG1 and imaged in a Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free, high Ca<sup>2+</sup> solution containing TTX. Spine head illumination with 405 nm (100 µW/µm<sup>2</sup> for 600 μs per pixel, ~200 ms per spine) triggered an increase in spine head volume that peaked in ~5 min (<italic>F<sub>t</sub>/F<sub>i </sub></italic>= 1.67 ± 0.15 of baseline, n = 26, p&lt;0.001, two-tailed, paired t-test) and then declined to an elevated plateau that persisted for at least 45 min (<italic>F<sub>t</sub>/F<sub>i</sub></italic> = 1.31 ± 0.06 of baseline, n = 26, p&lt;0.001, two-tailed, paired t-test) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7d and e</xref>, red symbols). Non-illuminated nearby spines did not change volume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7e</xref>, black symbols), nor did illuminated spines in slices that were not labeled with L-MAG1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7d and e</xref>, blue symbols). These experiments show that: i) LiGluN2A(V713C) traffics to synapses, as shown above for LiGluN2A(G712C), ii) photo-agonism of GluN2A(V713C) can be used to induce a spine-specific elevation in internal calcium, and iii) activation of post-synaptic GluN2A-containing receptors is sufficient to induce the morphological correlate of LTP.<fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.018</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>GluN2A(V713C) photo-<italic>agonism</italic> triggers calcium increase and expansion in single dendritic spines of organotypic hippocampal slice from GluN2A-knockout neonate mice.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Schematic of photo-agonism with L-MAG1 conjugated to the LiGluN2A(V713C) subunit. (<bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold>) Single-spine calcium rise induced by photo-agonism. (<bold>b</bold>) CA1 neurons co-expressing LiGluN2A(V713C) fused to R-GECO1.0 [LiGluN2A(V713C)-R-GECO1.0] and soluble R-GECO1.0 (red) as well as GFP (green) in merged low power image showing cluster of transfected neurons (top) and high-magnification image of dendritic shaft with several spines, showing the green, red and merged channels (bottom). Photo-agonism with 405 nm illumination focuses on spine #1 (red dashed circle), while R-GECO1.0 imaging measures calcium in spines # 1–4 and the dendritic shaft (dashed green rectangle). (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) Illumination of spine #1 in (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) at 405 nm (violet bar, with additional excitations at 488 and 561 nm to image eGFP (green bar) and R-GECO1.0 (orange bar), respectively, elicits an increase in R-GECO1.0 fluorescence within the head of spine #1 (red trace), while other spines (black traces) and the dendritic shaft (green trace) display little or no increase in fluorescence. (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>) Single spine expansion by photo-agonism of LiGluN2A. Spines from CA1 pyramidal neuron co-expressing GluN2A(V713C) and tdTomato and treated with L-MAG1 were stimulated with repetitive 405 nm laser scanning at the tip of the spine head, at ~1 Hz for a total amount of 1–2 min. (Top) Time lapse of a representative spine undergoing expansion after on-spine stimulation with 405 nm light (violet bar on top of inset, dashed red circle). Non-illuminated, nearby spines (white arrowheads) do not exhibit any change in volume. (Bottom) Representative spine from a slice without L-MAG1 treatment showing no response to 405 nm light (blue dashed circle). Numbers above images indicate time in min relative to photo-stimulation at <italic>t</italic> = 0. (<bold><bold>e</bold></bold>) Summary of results. Statistics in panel (<bold><bold>e</bold></bold>) are shown as mean ± SEM, ***p&lt;0.001, two-tailed, paired t-test compared to baseline, Δt= -10–0 mi. <italic>n,</italic> from series of experiments as in (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>), is shown in parentheses.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.018">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.018</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig7-v1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Single spine photo-antagonism gates structural plasticity in hippocampal slice</title><p>We next asked whether photo-antagonism of GluN2A and GluN1a could be used to prevent glutamate-induced spine expansion at single dendritic spines in organotypic slices obtained from GluN2A-knockout neonate mice. Caged-glutamate (MNI-glu) was added to a Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free bathing solution for 1–2 min followed by photo-uncaging with 405 nm light at a spot of the same lateral size as the spine head, but located 0.5 µm away (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1a</xref>). The 405 nm illumination was well-confined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1a</xref>) and reliably induced spine expansion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1b</xref>) when LiGluN2A was transfected, as shown earlier for GluN2A-<italic>wt</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Lee et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Matsuzaki et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Matsuzaki et al., 2004</xref>), but stable expansion did not occur in slices that were not transfected with LiGluN2A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1c</xref>). To determine if the spine expansion that is triggered by glutamate uncaging could be prevented by photo-antagonism of LiGluN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8a</xref>), we co-expressed LiGluN2A(G712C) and LiGluN1a(406C) with tdTomato and labeled the slices with L-MAG0. Individual spines received two successive bouts of near-spine glutamate photo-uncaging, the first following induction of LiGluN photo-antagonism by 405 nm on the spine head (100 µW/µm<sup>2</sup> for 600 µs per pixel), and the second following reversal of the photo-antagonism by 488 nm light (100 µW/µm<sup>2</sup> for 150 µs per pixel) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8b,c</xref>). In this experimental design, the second bout of uncaging was crucial to determining that a spine that did not respond to the first bout of uncaging was nevertheless competent to expand, asmany spines are not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Lynch et al., 2013</xref>). The first uncaging bout, during GluN1a/GluN2A photo-antagonism, induced only a small, transient increase in spine head volume, which peaked in 1 min (<italic>F<sub>t</sub>/F<sub>i</sub></italic> = 1.18 ± 0.07 of baseline, n = 12, p&gt;0.1, two tailed, paired t-test) and shrank back to near baseline (<italic>F<sub>t</sub>/F<sub>i</sub></italic> F = 1.05 ± 0.05 of baseline, n = 12, p&gt;0.1, two tailed, paired t-test) within 5 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8c</xref>, red symbols), indicating a lack of the long-lasting expansion that is associated with LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99">Yang et al., 2008</xref>). After turning off the GluN1a/GluN2A photo-antagonism with green light, the second bout of near-spine glutamate uncaging induced a large persistent expansion (<italic>F<sub>t</sub>/F<sub>i </sub></italic>= 1.47 ± 0.13 compared to new moderately elevated baseline between t = 3 min and 15 min, n = 12, p&lt;0.01, two tailed, paired t-test) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8c</xref>, red symbols). Nearby, non-illuminated spines did not respond (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8b and c</xref>, black symbols). These experiments show that photo-antagonism of GluN1a/GluN2A can block the induction of spine expansion and that this block is reversible, enabling a morphological correlate of LTP to be gated temporally at single synapses.<fig-group><fig id="fig8" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.019</object-id><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>Photo-<italic>antagonism</italic> prevents glutamate-induced expansion in single dendritic spines of organotypic hippocampal slice from GluN2A-knockout neonate mice.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Schematic of a photo-<italic>antagonized</italic> NMDA receptors containing LiGluN1a(E406C) and LiGluN2A(G712C) conjugated to L-MAG0. (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) CA1 pyramidal neuron co-expressing LiGluN1a(E406C), LiGluN2A(G712C) and tdTomato following treatment with L-MAG0. (Top) Single spine receiving two bouts of near-spine glutamate-uncaging at 405 nm (magenta spots, insets), the first after photo-antagonism was induced by 405 nm on-spine illumination (violet dashed circle, left inset), the second following removal of the photo-antagonism by 488 nm on-spine illumination (green dashed circle, right inset). Photo-block (and relief of block) of the receptors was done by stimulating the tip of the spine head with repetitive 405 nm (or 488) laser scanning, at ~1 Hz for a total amount of 1 min. MNI-glutamate uncaging was performed slightly away from the spine head (~2 µm) to avoid further stimulation of the receptors found on the spine head. The spine undergoes a small expansion in response to the first glutamate-uncaging (p=0.06, compared to baseline at t= -8 – 0 min), and a large expansion following removal of the photo-antagonism. (Bottom) A nearby non-illuminated spine (arrowhead) does not change size. Numbers above images indicate time in min relative to photo-stimulation at <italic>t</italic> = 0. (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) Summary of results from a series of experiments as in (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) (mean ± SEM, **p&lt; 0.01, two-tailed, paired t-test compared to baseline at t= 9–15 min, <italic>n</italic> shown in parentheses).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.019">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.019</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig8-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig8s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.020</object-id><label>Figure 8—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Single spine spatial precision of photocontrol in organotypic hippocampal slice from GluN2A-knockout neonate mice.</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) Photo-bleaching indicates spatial precision of &quot;on-spine&quot; photo-stimulation. High intensity illumination at 405 nm (magenta arrow) rastered over a single 1 µm diameter spine for 1 s (white dashed circle in images, black symbols in graph) leads to &gt;70% confined bleaching of GFP in that spine (white arrowhead in right image taken 3.5 s following the bleaching) and only marginal bleaching (&lt;10%) of the neighboring dendritic shaft (red dashed circle in images, red symbols in graph) or nearby spine (green dashed circle in images, green symbols in graph). Numbers above images indicate time in seconds (0 before bleaching, 3.5 s after bleaching). (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) (Top) Uncaging of MNI-glutamate (2.5 mM in nominally Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free solution, see Materials and methods) near a single spine (magenta spot in left image at time 0 or magenta arrow shown in plot) of a CA1 pyramidal neuron from a cultured GluN2A-KO mice organotypic slice, biolistically-transfected with GluN1a(E406C), GluN2A(G712C) and tdTomato, but not treated with L-MAG0, triggers expansion of targeted spine (magenta dashed circle), but not of nearby spines (white arrowheads). Numbers above images indicate time in minutes (0 before uncaging, 10 and 20 min after uncaging). (Bottom) Summary of results from series of experiments as in (Top). Slices, biolistically-transfected with GluN2A(G712C) but unexposed to MAG, following 1–2 min incubation with 2.5 mM MNI-glutamate exhibit long-lasting expansion, demonstrating the sufficiency of this time window to deliver the compound to spines and rescue of long lasting expansion. (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) Spines, of CA1 neurons from a cultured GluN2A-KO mice organotypic slice, biolistically transfected with td-tomato only and unexposed to MAG, do not maintain increased volume following MNI-glu uncaging (magenta arrow), reminiscent of earlier findings showing reduced hippocampal LTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Sakimura et al., 1995</xref>). Statistics in panels are shown as mean ± SEM, tested with two-tailed, paired t-test; ***p&lt;0.001, <italic>n</italic> displayed in plots.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.020">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.020</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig8-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>LiGluN2A photo-antagonism disrupts pruning of zebrafish retinal ganglion cell axonal arbor in vivo</title><p>Having seen that LiGluNs provide optical control over NMDA receptor dependent transmission and plasticity in dissociated neurons and in brain slice, we turned to test their utility in vivo in larval zebrafish, <italic>Danio rerio.</italic> As a model of NMDA receptor-dependent plasticity, we examined the synaptic pruning that takes place in the developing visual system. NMDA receptors play an important role in the formation of sensory topographic maps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bliss and Collingridge, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Lüscher and Malenka, 2012</xref>). In many vertebrates, including zebrafish, exposure to soluble NMDA receptor antagonists during a critical period in development of retinotectal projections can disrupt the convergence of retinal ganglion cell axons, thus disrupting retinotopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cline and Constantine-Paton, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Ruthazer et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Schmidt, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102">Zhang et al., 1998</xref>). In zebrafish larvae, one such critical period occurs between 5 and 7 days post fertilization (dpf), coincident with the onset of behaviors that require visual acuity, such as prey capture. Larvae exposed to soluble NMDA receptor antagonists during this critical period exhibit enlarged RGC axonal arbors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Schmidt et al., 2000</xref>).</p><p>We asked whether photo-antagonism of LiGluNR2A(G712C) during the 5–7 dpf critical period would affect retinal ganglion cell axon growth. We generated a transgenic line of zebrafish expressing GluN2A(G712C) under the control the gal4-UAS expression system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Scott et al., 2007</xref>). Double transgenic Tg[<italic>s1101t-gal4;UAS-GluN2A</italic>(<italic>G712C</italic>)] fish were incrossed to produce embryos with GluN2A(G712C) expressed throughout the nervous system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9b</xref>), including the retina and optic tectum. To visualize individual retinal ganglion cells, embryos were injected with DNA for GFP expression (see methods) to sparsely mark a subset of retinal ganglion cells projecting to the optic tectum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9b</xref>, right panels) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib98">Xiao and Baier, 2007</xref>). At 5 dpf, healthy larvae expressing LiGluN2A(G712C) pan-neuronally, with sparse expression of GFP in retinal ganglion cells, were divided into three treatment groups: (1) L-MAG0, (2) vehicle (DMSO only), or (3) MK-801. All larvae were mounted in agarose to image baseline axon arbor morphology, and then freed and transferred to a 48-well plate imaging chamber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>). Between 5 and 7 dpf, freely swimming larvae were exposed to a 10 s flash of 405 nm light once every 30 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9a</xref>). Because MAG is bistable (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>), we reasoned that brief bouts of isomerization into the photo-antagonizing state would be sufficient to provide long-term antagonism, while allowing the larvae to develop under predominantly natural visual stimuli. At 7 dpf, larvae were imaged a second time to assess the growth of each axon arbor.<fig-group><fig id="fig9" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.021</object-id><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><title>GluN2A(G712C) photo-antagonism disrupts refinement of retinal ganglion cell axon arbors in larval zebrafish in vivo.</title><p>(<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) Cartoons depicting GluN2A(G712C) photo-antagonism (top left), development of retinal ganglion cell projection (top, right) and timeline of the photo-antagonism assay (bottom). (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) (Left) Dorsal view of 5 dpf larva showing pan-neuronal expression pattern driven by <italic>s1101t-gal4</italic> visualized by expression of <italic>UAS-GCaMP3</italic>. Transverse (right, top) and dorsal (right, bottom) tectal projection of a retinal ganglion cell axon arbor labeled by mosaic expression of <italic>pou4f3:mGFP</italic> at 7 dpf. (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) Axon arbors were traced and arbor radius measured by a 3-dimensional Sholl analysis counting the number of intersections encountered by concentric spheres centered on the first branch point. Arrows indicate arbor radius (R) at 5 dpf and 7 dpf. (<bold><bold>d</bold></bold>) Prior to antagonism, Tg[<italic>s1101t-gal4; UAS:GluN2A(G712C)]</italic> animals have a comparable distribution of arbor radii at 5 dpf as non-expressing animals (without UAS, but mix of s1101t +/-) (n.s., p &gt;0.6, Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Test, n = 19, GluN2A(G712C)-expressing axons and 10 non-expressing axons). Box plot whiskers indicate 5% and 95% percentiles. Dots above whiskers represent outliers. (<bold><bold>e</bold></bold>) Representative selection of retinal ganglion cell axon arbors in transgenic animals at 5 dpf (green) and 7 dpf (magenta). Larvae were treated at 5 dpf with either 150 µM L-MAG0 in 0.3% DMSO, 0.3% DMSO alone, or 25 µM MK-801, and subjected to 10 s flashes of 405 nm light at 30 min intervals from 128–168 hpf. (<bold><bold>f</bold></bold>) In animals where GluN2A(G712C) was photo-antagonized by MAG, retinal ganglion cell axon arbors grew significantly more compared to DMSO-treated control groups (left-to-right: ΔR = 6.9%, <italic>n</italic> = 10 axons, ΔR = 1.2%, <italic>n</italic> = 9 axons; ΔR = 16.4%, <italic>n</italic> = 12 axons). This overgrowth was comparable to the change in arbor radius observed in animals treated with MK-801 (ΔR = 13.8%, <italic>n</italic> = 10 axons). For statistical analysis of the relative change in arbor radius (ΔR = (R<sub>7dpf</sub>-R<sub>5dpf</sub>)/R<sub>5dfp</sub>), we initially compared untreated –<italic>wt</italic> animals and untreated transgenic animals (two left bars) and observed no statistical difference (mean ± SEM, n.s. not significant, two-tailed, unpaired t-test). This enabled the comparison between the animals from the same transgenic background (second to fourth bar) for the effect of photo-inhibition on radius (mean ± SEM, n.s. not significant, **p&lt;0.01, *p&lt;0.05, tested with one way ANOVA, all pairwise Tukey <italic>post hoc</italic> test (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s1">Figure 9—figure supplement 1c</xref>). Individual data points are shown for <bold>f</bold> (open circles).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.021">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.021</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig9-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig9s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.022</object-id><label>Figure 9—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>MAG treatment of zebrafish larvae in the absence of LiGluN2A expression does not affect behavior.</title><p>Wildtype larvae were treated at 5 dpf with either 150 µM MAG0 in 0.3% DMSO (n = 48) or 0.3% DMSO alone (n = 48) for 40 min, rinsed thoroughly in fresh fish water, and allowed to develop as two separate groups without further treatment in large common dishes of E3. (<bold><bold>a</bold></bold>) MAG treatment in the absence of LiGluN2A expression does not affect innate escape reflex or the habituation of this reflex. Zebrafish at 7dpf were subjected to an acousto-vibrational stimulus protocol (top) designed to assay (i) sensitivity, (ii) responsiveness, (iii) habituation in response to repeated stimuli, and (iv) spontaneous dishabitutation (n = 48 animals). Movies were scored for response within 60 ms of the stimulus. Escape probabilities were calculated as the mean number of responders per group (mean ± SEM). No significant difference was seen between the MAG-treated (blue) and DMSO-treated groups (green) in any phase of the assay. (<bold><bold>b</bold></bold>) At 7 dpf, individual fish were transferred to single wells of 48-well plates and spontaneous swimming was filmed at 10 fps. Fish were tracked in each well (blue = MAG-treated; green = DMSO-treated) by detecting changes in pixel intensity between movie frames using Matlab (see Materials and methods). Empty wells represent fish that were excluded from statistical analysis if the automated tracking algorithm failed for more than 15% of the 10 min imaging session (manual inspection revealed that the automated tracking failed when fish spent extended time near a partially obscured well edge; in total, 10% were excluded). (bottom) Summary shows that MAG and DMSO treated animals showed no significant difference in cumulative distance traveled during spontaneous swim bouts, swim bout frequency or duration, or average speed, or time spent resting. (n=41 for MAG0, n=43 for DMSO-treated animals, n.s., not significant, two-tailed, unpaired t-test). Values mean ± SEM. (<bold><bold>c</bold></bold>) Statistical results of a one way ANOVA (all pairwise Tukey <italic>post hoc</italic> test), performed for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9f.</xref></p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12040.022">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12040.022</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife-12040-fig9-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>The size of a retinal ganglion cell axon arbor was determined by a 3-dimensional Sholl analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9c</xref>), which compared z-stacks obtained at 5 dpf and 7 dpf. At 5.25 dpf (126 ± 2 hr post fertilization), the size distribution of retinal ganglion cell axon arbors from Tg[<italic>s1101t-gal4;UAS-GluN2A(G712C)</italic>] larvae was indistinguishable that of siblings lacking the <italic>UAS-GluN2A(G712C)</italic> transgene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9d</xref>) (p&gt;0.7, two- two-tailed, unpaired t-test, n = 19 Tg[<italic>s1101t-gal4;UAS-GluN2A(G712C)</italic>] and n = 10 control axons), indicating that gal4-driven expression of UAS-GluN2A(G712C) does not alter the initial development of the retinotectal projection. However, by 7 dpf, axon arbors in Tg[<italic>s1101t-gal4;UAS-GluN2A(G712C)</italic>] larvae that were illuminated episodically to induce photo-antagonism showed a significant increase in arbor radius (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9f</xref>, ΔR = 16.4 ± 1.7%, n = 12 axons), compared to illuminated vehicle-treated (ΔR = 1.2 ± 3.4%, n = 9 axons) or wild-type siblings (ΔR = 6.9% ± 2.6%, n = 10 axons) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s1">Figure 9—figure supplement 1a</xref>). Tg[<italic>s1101t-gal4;UAS-GluN2A(G712C)</italic>] larvae that were not treated with MAG, but were instead reared in 25 µM MK-801, under the same conditions from 5–7 dpf, showed a comparable increase in arbor radius (ΔR = 13.8 ± 3.7%, n = 10 axons), indicating that the efficacy of photo-antagonism was on par with a relatively strong dose of a soluble NMDA receptor blocker. MAG treatment alone had no effect on development compared to vehicle-treated siblings, based on an assessment of spontaneous swim behavior, escape behavior and habituation of escape behavior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s1">Figure 9—figure supplement 1b</xref> and Materials and methods). These results demonstrate that extended photo-antagonism of LiGluN2A(G712C) mimics the effect of in vivo chronic systemic exposure to a soluble NMDAR antagonist, producing a block of activity-dependent remodeling of retinotectal projections.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We have used chemical optogenetics to engineer light-controlled NMDA receptors that can be used to study the mechanisms of NMDA receptor function and of synaptic transmission and plasticity. We generated a family of four light-gated NMDA receptor-subunits that provide reversible spatiotemporal control of receptor activity and synaptic plasticity <italic>via</italic> a photochemical switch that either activates or antagonizes specific 'LiGluN' subunits: LiGluN1a, LiGluN2A and LiGluN2B. The photo-agonized subunits can be photoactivated to yield persistent currents or be sculpted in time to mimic synaptic activation of the receptors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). Photo-antagonism blocks the effects of perfused ligands (glutamate/NMDA) and of synaptically released glutamate, thus controlling NMDA receptor mediated EPSCs and LTP. Spatial confinement of photo-antagonism to a single dendritic spine blocks the spine expansion that is associated with LTP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8</xref>). As a complement to this, single-spine photo-agonism evokes spine-specific Ca<sup>2+</sup>-transients and spine expansion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>).</p><p>We also report a transgenic zebrafish line that expresses the light-antagonized version of GluN2A, which enables chronic antagonism over days of larval development after a single application of MAG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>). We take advantage of the bistability of MAG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1i</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1e</xref>) to produce chronic photo-antagonism with short pulses of light at long intervals over a period of 40 hr in freely swimming fish, thereby minimizing visual stimulation and avoiding photo-toxicity. We find that the photo-antagonism is as potent as MK-801 in interfering with the normal NMDA receptor dependent pruning process, producing an overgrowth of retinal ganglion cell axons in the optic tectum. Conveniently, in the zebrafish system, MAG can simply be added to the water to be taken up systemically, as shown earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Janovjak et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Szobota et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib97">Wyart et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>For photo-controlled NMDA receptors to work under physiological expression conditions, one would want LiGluN subunits to replace native subunits, rather than increasing the pool of NMDA receptors. Fortunately, in some preparations, GluN2A overexpression does not appear to increase synaptic content of NMDA receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Barria and Malinow, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Prybylowski et al., 2002</xref>), most likely because of the limiting supply of the native obligatory partner GluN1 subunit. We find that expression of LiGluN2A makes NMDA receptors sensitive to light without altering whole cell NMDA-induced current or NMDA receptor EPSCs evoked by action potential-driven glutamate release at autaptic synapses. The degree of photo-block of NMDA receptor EPSCs in autapses from neurons from <italic>wt</italic> rats (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>) is small on average (mean 25–35%, range ~20–50% without inclusion of non-responding cells, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>), but shows that functional light-controlled receptors can be obtained in a wild-type background where the LiGluN subunits compete with <italic>wt</italic> subunits to assemble into receptors that are properly trafficked to the plasma membrane of the synapses. It should be noted that, the expression of the photoswitchable subunits in a wild-type background where the native subunit is expressed yielded variable effects, ranging from very strong block to no block at all (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1b</xref>). This may result from a combination of factors, including variation in expression level that results in variable incorporation into GluN2-containing receptors. Nevertheless, in responding cells, regardless of the magnitude of fractional optical control, the control is reproducible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1b</xref>). The degree of photo-block in other preparations, such as organotypic slices from the GluN2A-KO mice, where we demonstrated block of LTP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>) and either induction or block of spine expansion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figures 7</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8</xref>), is likely greater because of absence of the native GluN2A subunit.</p><p>The chemical optogenetic approach is selective for the subunit that bears the cysteine anchoring site for the MAG photoswitch. Thus, our toolset allows for the direct and specific optical manipulation of GluN2A or GluN2B receptors and should make it possible to address the roles of these subunits in synaptic plasticity, circuit function and memory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Foster et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Kohl et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Liu et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Massey et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Sakimura et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib96">Weitlauf et al., 2005</xref>). In addition, owing to the ability to localize and shape light, it should also be possible to determine how synaptic transmission and circuit function are shaped by receptor type at various subcellular locations and within single dendritic spines.</p><p>Chemical labeling and azobenzene isomerization have limitations that need to be considered. While neurons in culture and slice are easily incubated with MAG, and MAG can be readily delivered systemically in zebrafish when added to the swimming media (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Janovjak et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Szobota et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib97">Wyart et al., 2009</xref>), we do not know the efficiency of this process and incomplete conjugation (i.e. partial occupancy) may contribute to the incomplete photo-agonism and photo-antagonism that we observe. In addition, a small fraction of MAG remains in <italic>trans</italic> during 380 nm illumination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gorostiza et al., 2007</xref>), and there may be differences in occupancy in the <italic>cis</italic> state of MAG molecules that are bound to the cysteine at the two possible stereochemistries of attachment to the maleimide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Numano et al., 2009</xref>). We have recently solved two of these challenges for photoswitching a metabotropic glutamate receptor by replacing the maleimide-cysteine conjugation with the bio-orthogonal and very efficient conjugation of a benzylguanine photoswitch to a SNAP tag fused to the N-terminal of the LBD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Broichhagen et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>Because the cysteine-reactive maleimide of MAG hydrolyzes, receptor conjugation will occur in the first hours after addition of MAG. Only those receptors that are on the plasma membrane during this time window will be labeled and become photo-controllable. As a result, the time frame of an experiment is limited by receptor-turnover, and for in vivo experiments extending several days, MAG may need to be reapplied. It also means that for studies of development, cells born after MAG application will not be under light control. This will mean that the tools do not work for some applications, or require an extra step (i.e. MAG reapplication). In some cases it could actually provide an advantage to selectively antagonize or agonize based on receptor 'birthdate'.</p><p>Recent advances in the design of azobenzene-based photo-switches have yielded new classes of MAG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Kienzler et al., 2013</xref>) that exhibit favorable two-photon absorption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carroll et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Gascón-Moya et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Izquierdo-Serra et al., 2014</xref>). This is particularly advantageous for light confinement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Emiliani et al., 2015</xref>), especially for small subcellular compartments, and for deeper tissue penetration, for in vivo applications. Fortunately, in preparations such as <italic>C.elegans</italic>, <italic>Drosophila</italic> and zebrafish, where precise genetic targeting can be readily achieved (i.e. of the photoswitch-ready subunit) and where the nervous system is accessible to light and less scattering, it is already possible with conventional 1-photon illumination to accomplish MAG photo-control of glutamate receptors, as previously shown in zebrafish sensory neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Szobota et al., 2007</xref>), the central pattern generator circuit for swimming (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Janovjak et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib97">Wyart et al., 2009</xref>), pan-neuronally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>), and as shown here in transgenic zebrafish expressing the LiGluN2A(G712C) subunit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, we have engineered a palette of light-controlled NMDA receptor subunits, which enable the fast and reversible remote control of specific receptor subtypes, in specific cells and thereby with presynaptic versus postsynaptic selectivity. These properties should enable a new level of study of the molecular mechanism of function of NMDA receptors and how specific NMDA receptors participate in synaptic transmission, integration and plasticity.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Site-directed mutagenesis</title><p>Cysteine point mutations were introduced near, but outside of the glutamate-binding site of GluN2A, GluN2B and GluN1a using site-directed mutagenesis and verified by full sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Cell culture and transfection</title><p>HEK293 or HEK293T cells were maintained in DMEM with 5% FBS on poly-L-lysine-coated glass coverslips at ~3 x 10<sup>6</sup> cells per milliliter and transiently co-transfected with GluN1a and GluN2A plasmids at a DNA ratio of 1:2 using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen/Life technologies, Carlsbad, CA). Calcium imaging or patch clamping was performed 12–48 hr after transfection. Dissociated postnatal hippocampal neurons (P0-P5) were prepared from Sprague Dawley rats (Charles River) at high density (80 K cells/coverslip) and transfected as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Berlin et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Szobota et al., 2007</xref>), using 1 µg of cDNA encoding the NMDA receptor subunit(s) and 0.2 µg of GFP. For autaptic recordings, cells were plated at a lower density (20 K cell/coverslip) with the extracellular medium enriched with 15 mM KCl, to promote the formation of autaptic connections. As an additional precaution, we transfected these neurons at very low efficiency so that very few neurons in a dish expressed LiGluN. We took this additional provision so that the illumination would only affect the population of LiGluN receptors located on the recorded cell, without affecting the activity of other cells in the vicinity (of which the majority are non-transfected even under normal transfection methods nonetheless), as is the case of other soluble blockers. For <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocyte mRNA injection, we have cloned GluNRs and LiGluNRs into pGEM-HJ, synthesized mRNA in vitro and injected into defolliculated oocytes; as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Berlin et al., 2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Organotypic hippocampal slice culture preparation and biolistic transfection</title><p>All experiments on hippocampal slices (physiological experiments on LTP induction and single spine expansion experiments) were in cultured (organotypic) slices from GluN2A-knockout mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Sakimura et al., 1995</xref>). Briefly, slices (400 µm thick) were prepared at postnatal days 6–8 as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Fuller and Dailey, 2007</xref>). Slices were cut in ice-cold, oxygenated dissection solution (95% O<sub>2</sub>/5% CO<sub>2</sub>) containing (in mM) 1 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 dextrose, 4 KCl, 5 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 26 NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 233 sucrose, 0.0005% phenol red, and grown on cell culture inserts (Millipore, EMD) in culture medium consisting of neurobasal medium (no L-glutamine, GIBCO), horse serum (Hyclone), insulin (Sigma), ascorbic acid (Sigma), Glutamax (GIBCO), penicillin-streptomycin (GIBCO) and HEPES (pH 7.4) at 34°C. Medium was supplemented with 4 µM cytosine β-D-arabinofuranoside hydrochloride (AraC, Sigma) the day after. Slices were biolistically transfected with gold particles (1 µm, Bio-Rad) covered with the appropriate DNA combination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">O'Brien and Lummis, 2006</xref>). AraC was withdrawn from the media prior to transfection and 10 µM MK-801 (Tocris) was added at that time. The MK-801 was removed on the day of experiment.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Calcium-imaging in HEK293 cells</title><p>HEK293 cells were loaded in recording solution with 5 μM Fura2-AM (Molecular Probes) for 30 min at 37°C, 5% CO2. The recording solution contained (in mM): 150 NaCl, 5 KCl, 0.2 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 D-glucose, 10 D-sucrose, 10 HEPES, 0.01 EDTA, 0.05 glycine, pH 7.4. Cells were labeled with 50–100 µM MAG in glycine-free recording solution. Changes in intracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] in individual cells were measured from Fura2-AM fluorescence intensity by brief (&lt;1 s, ~1.5 µW/mm<sup>2</sup>) excitation at 350 nm and 380 nm at 5 s intervals and by detecting emission at 510 nm.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Electrophysiology</title><p>Patch clamp recordings used an Axopatch 200 A amplifier in the whole cell mode. Recordings were carried out 12 to 48 hr after transfection in HEK cells and after 15 DIV for hippocampal neurons. Cells were pre-treated with 1 mM DTT for 5 min, rinsed for 10 min, and incubated with 50–100 µM MAG (and for GluN2A(G712C), 500 µM AP5) for 30 min at 37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. The labeling solution contained (in mM): 150 NMDG-HCl, 3 KCl, 0.5 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 HEPES, 5 D- glucose, pH 7.4. Cells were voltage-clamped at -60 mV. Pipettes had resistances of 2–8 MΩ and were filled with a solution containing, for HEK cells (in mM): 110 D-gluconic acid, 30 CsCl, 4 NaCl, 5 HEPES, 5 BAPTA, 0.5 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, pH 7.3, and for neurons (in mM): 136.5 K-gluconate, 17.5 KCl, 9 NaCl, 1 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 HEPES, 0.2 EGTA, pH 7.3. The extracellular recording solution for HEK cells was as described above for calcium-imaging experiments. For dissociated rat hippocampal neurons, when assessing the relative photo-current (or block) compared to the total NMDA- induced current the extracellular recording solution, nominally Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free and with high external Ca<sup>2+</sup>, contained (in mM): 138 NaCl, 1.5 KCl, 10 D-glucose, 3.7 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 HEPES, pH 7.4 and 0.05 glycine. All other experiments with cultured neurons were performed with 2.5 mM external Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Illumination was applied using a Polychrome monochromator (TILL Photonics) (also see below) coupled to the back port of an Olympus IX70 inverted microscope. Light intensity measured at the 40x objective was ~3 mW/mm<sup>2</sup>.</p><p>Recording of autapses was performed using a standard protocol as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>). Briefly, cells we held at −70 and depolarized to +20 or 40 mV for 3–5 ms, then returned to −70 mV. For recording NMDA-dependent spontaneous or evoked EPSC (sEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> and eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub>, respectively), cells were incubated with 20 µM CNQX, in nominally Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free extracellular recording solution and with 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. To note, during autaptic recordings we consistently observed the gradual reduction in eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> amplitude (transfected and non-transfected neurons), consistent with previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Goda and Stevens, 1998</xref>).</p><p>Hippocampal slices were obtained from GluN2A-knockout neonate mice and electrophysiological recordings to measure LTP induction were done on at 6–8 d in vitro. Just before recording, slices were incubated at room temperature (~25°C) with 100 µM TCEP for 1 min, rinsed for 2 min, and incubated for 45 min with 250 μM MAG and 500 µM AP5 diluted in the NMDG-labeling solution (see above). Slices were rinsed twice in labeling solution before recording. Whole-cell patch-clamp recordings were performed on an upright Zeiss AxioExaminer using an Axopatch 200B amplifier (Molecular Devices). A bipolar stimulating electrode was placed along the Schaffer collateral pathway and post-synaptic currents were recorded in whole-cell mode from transfected CA1 pyramidal neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>). The internal solution contained (in mM): 142 CsCl, 2 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 EGTA, 10 HEPES, 0.4 Na3GTP, 4.4Na2ATP, 5 QX314, pH 7.4. Slices were perfused with a medium containing (in mM): 118.9 NaCl, 2.5 KCl, 2 NaH2PO4, 26.2 NaHCO3, 11 D-Glucose, 2.5 CaCl2, 1.3 MgCl2 and 0.01 glycine, pH 7.4 when saturated with 95% O<sub>2</sub> / 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. The light used for photoswitching was from a DG-4 (Sutter Instruments) coupled to the microscope and projected onto the sample through a 40× objective. Light intensity measured at the sample was approximately 43 mW/mm<sup>2</sup> at 390 nm and 51 mW/mm<sup>2</sup> at 497 nm. EPSCs were recorded in voltage-clamp mode and the tetanus (consisting of two 1 s trains of 100 Hz separated by 20 s) was delivered in current-clamp mode.</p><p>Two-electrode voltage clamp experiments were performed in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocytes injected with 50 nl mRNA of the different GluN subunits at 1–1.5 ng/oocyte. GluN2A (<italic>wt</italic>, G712C, V713C) and GluN2B (<italic>wt</italic>, V714C) were injected with GluN1a-<italic>wt</italic> at a ratio of 1:1. GluN1a (E406C) was injected with GluN2B-<italic>wt</italic>. Cells were then incubated in ND-96 (96 mM NaCl, 2 mM KCl, 1.8 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 mg/ml gentamicin, 2.5 mM Na-pyruvate and 5 mM HEPES, pH 7.6) at 18°C for 24 hr. For measuring glutamate efficacy, cells were clamped at −60 mV and perfused with Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free extracellular solution containing (mM): 100 NaCl, 0.3 BaCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 HEPES (adjusted with KOH to 7.3), 100 µM Glycine and 10 µM DTPA (zinc chelator- added before the experiment). Glutamate concentrations ranged from 0.1 to 100 µM. For Glycine efficacy of GluN1a (<italic>wt</italic>, E406C), extracellular solution contained 10 µM glutamate and glycine concentrations ranged from 0.1 to 10 µM. Recordings were performed with the use of a Dagan CA-1 amplifier (Dagan Corporation), controlled by the Digidata-1440 board and pClamp10 software package (Axon Instruments).</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Illumination, fast MAG photoswitching and fast glutamate uncaging</title><p>Most electrophysiological experiments were performed with illumination that was applied to the entire field of view using a Polychrome V monochromator (TILL photonics) through 20 or 40x objectives. For organotypic slice recordings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>) illumination was applied using a Lambda DG4 high speed wavelength switcher (Sutter instruments), with a 380 nm and a 500 nm filters through a 20x objective. Fast, millisecond photoswitching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1f–h</xref>) and fast photouncaging (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2g,h</xref>) was achieved with a laser spot illumination system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Reiner and Isacoff, 2014</xref>). In brief, the output of a 375/488 nm dual diode laser module (Omicron LDM: 375 nm 200 mW multi-mode, 488 nm 80 mW single-mode) was coupled into a UV/VIS multi-mode fiber (OZ Optics, 10 μm, NA 0.1), the divergence of the exiting light reduced by threefold magnification of the fiber end, and the collimated beam directed to the objective. The laser output was controlled with TTL pulses and analog power modulation. Single spine illumination was performed on a confocal microscope (Zeiss 780-upright confocal) equipped with a 405 nm laser (100 μW at the objective). To note, we consistently used near-UV illumination (365–405 nm) for photoactivation, as nucleotides, DNA and proteins do not efficiently absorb in this region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Forné et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Schmid, 2001</xref>), making these wavelengths and technique undamaging and compatible with biological preparations.</p><p>Targeted illumination with simultaneous electrophysiological recordings were performed on a Zeiss 780-upright confocal microscope (e.g. Figure 1i, dashed box and Figure 1—figure supplement 1b, c) .</p><p>For sculpting the photo-activation and deactivation profile of light-agonized GluN2A(V713C) the 488 nm light intensity was modulated. Typically 4–8 traces were averaged and the apparent activation and photo-deactivation kinetics were fitted with single exponential functions. For photouncaging experiments, 4-methoxy-7-nitroindolinyl-caged-L-glutamate (MNI-glutamate, Tocris) was added to the bath (0.5 mM) and uncaged with a short 375 nm laser pulse centered at the cell (~50 W/mm<sup>2</sup>, ~ 15 μm spot diameters). Uncaging pulses of 0.5 ms, 1 ms and 2 ms yielded identical activation kinetics, demonstrating that these reflected the intrinsic receptor activation kinetics rather than concentration-dependent second order binding. Deactivation due to diffusion of glutamate out of the uncaging site occurred on the timescale of seconds and became slower, as more glutamate was uncaged with longer pulse lengths. Rise times (10–90%) were used to describe the speed of activation and were compared to <italic>wt</italic>-receptors using two-tailed, unpaired t-tests.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Cell viability assay</title><p>Hippocampal cells (15 DIV) were assayed for cellular and membrane viability following different treatments: 1) incubation with 300 µM L-MAG1 in NMDG-labeling solution (see above), 2) with 0.3% DMSO, 3) with NMDG-labeling solution or 4) untreated. Cells were labeled using the Neurite outgrowth kit (Molecular Probes) and red and green fluorescence was acquired using a Zeiss 780-upright confocal microscope. Assessment was done by comparing multiple coverslips (N= 2–9) at same cellular density. Confocal images of red (neurite content) and green (cell viability) fluorescence were taken under identical imaging settings and identical region sizes (as described by the manufacturer). Data is presented as mean ± SEM and compared using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with a <italic>post hoc</italic> Tukey test, all-pairwise analysis (n.s.; not significant).</p></sec><sec id="s4-8"><title>Single spine imaging of calcium and structural plasticity</title><p>Single spine imaging experiments were performed in organotypic slices obtained from GluN2A-knockout neonate mice at room temperature (~25°C) in Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free and high-Ca<sup>2+</sup>ACSF containing (in mM): 118.9 NaCl, 2.5 KCl, 1 NaH2PO4, 26.2 NaHCO3, 11 glucose, 4–5 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.001 TTX and 2.5 MNI-glutamate, oxygenated with 95% O2 and 5% CO2, as typically described elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Matsuzaki et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Okamoto et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Harvey and Svoboda, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Harvey et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Makino and Malinow, 2009</xref>). TTX and glycine were added and MK-801 removed at least 25 min before start of the imaging experiments. Images were taken using a laser scanning microscope; Zeiss 780-upright confocal microscope. Photo-uncaging of MNI-glutamate and photo-activation of MAG (300 µM) for either photo-<italic>agonism</italic> or photo-<italic>antagonism</italic> was triggered by illumination with a 405 nm laser at ~1 Hz for a total of 1–2 min, as previously described for MNI-uncaging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Matsuzaki et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Nishiyama and Yasuda, 2015</xref>).</p><p>To test the ability of photo-agonism to induce a rise in calcium in single spines, we expressed a fusion of the calcium indicator R-GECO1.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib104">Zhao et al., 2011</xref>) to the C-terminus of GluN2A(V713C) (GluN2A(V713C)-R-GECO) and co-transfected with additional soluble R-GECO, to improve the calcium signal detection within the entire spine head, under excitation at 561 nm, and eGFP, to enable simultaneous imaging of spine size under excitation at 488 nm. In the photo-agonized (100 µW for 100 µs/pixel) spine, the R-GECO signal decayed over tens of seconds, even though the photo-agonized GluN2A containing NMDAR remains open without decay for tens of seconds, due to bleach induced by 3 different illuminating lasers (405, 488 and 561 nm). We applied this unique combination of laser-illumination, to bypass the known artifacts of R-GECO, which undergoes unique reversible bleaching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">Shaner et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Spine morphological changes were assessed by time-lapse Z-stack images of single spines collected using a 20x/NA=1.0 water immersion objective (digital zoom: 10–13) by imaging space-filling cytosolic tdTomato with a 561 nm laser. 3-dimensional projection images (of 512x512 or 1024x1024 pixels) were exported (Zen 2011 software, Zeiss) for analysis with a custom MATLAB program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Peled and Isacoff, 2011</xref>). We measured the fluorescence of the spine (as shown in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103">Zhang et al., 2008</xref>]), which is proportional to spine-head volume (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Holtmaat et al., 2005</xref>), and normalized it to the fluorescence of the shaft to correct for any changes that may have occurred to fluorescence; resulting from bleach or movement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Nimchinsky et al., 2004</xref>). Nearby spines typically consisted of spines located on the same dendrite (&lt;10 µm from photo-stimulated spine) found in the same field of view as the photostimulated spine or atop dendrites that ran across the field of view, nearby the photostimulated region.</p><p>To determine whether the ability to induce spine expansion was restored to CA1 neuronal spines, in slices prepared from GluN2A-knockout mice, neurons were transfected with the GluN2A(V713C) subunit and single spines were assessed for expansion by uncaging MNI-glutamate. MNI-glutamate (2.5 mM final concentration) was allowed to diffuse into the slice during 1–2 min of superfusion with Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free bathing solution, in the presence of 2 µM TTX, before photo-uncaging. Photo-uncaging with 405 nm light (100 µW for 100 µs/pixel) at a spot of the same lateral size as the spine head, but located 0.5 µm away (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1b</xref>). This illumination reliably induced expansion of the spine below the spot of illumination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8s1">Figure 8—figure supplement 1b</xref>, dashed circle) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hardingham and Bading, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Lee et al., 2009</xref>), indicating rescue of structural plasticity by expression of the cysteine-bearing subunits.</p></sec><sec id="s4-9"><title>Generation of GluN2A(G712C) transgenic zebrafish</title><p>To generate a stable transgenic line of LiGluN2A zebrafish, we inserted the rat-GluN2A(G712C) gene with a N-terminal GFP tag under control of a 10X-UAS sequence into a pT2KXIG-delta-IN vector containing Tol2 transposon recognition sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Suster et al., 2009</xref>) using <italic>EcoR</italic>I and <italic>Not</italic>I restriction sites. The resulting pT2-LiGluN2A(G712C) construct was diluted to 50 ng/μL with 0.25 ng Tol2 transposase and 0.05% Phenol Red (Sigma). Injected embryos were raised to sexual maturity and outcrossed to identify founder (F0) fish. F1 fish were genotyped for GluN2A(G712C) using primers 5’-TGCA GAG AAT CGG ACC CAC T-3’ and 5’-TCG ATC ACT GCC CTC ACT GT-3’. F1 <italic>Tg[UAS:GluN2A(G712C)]</italic> fish were outcrossed to a pan-neuronal transgenic Gal4 line, <italic>Tg(s1101t-gal4)</italic>. Double transgenic <italic>Tg[s1101t- gal4;UAS-GluN2A(G712C)]</italic>; fish grew to sexual maturity with no obvious phenotypes.</p><p>To determine whether exposure to MAG affected the health or development of zebrafish larvae, we assayed basic spontaneous and evoked behaviors of freely swimming animals for up to 2 days post-treatment. 5 dpf wildtype larvae were bathed in either with 150 µM MAG or vehicle only under the same conditions as used in the LiGluN2A experiments. Fish were transferred to 48-well plates (1 fish per well with 800 µL fresh E3) and placed in an imaging arena (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Levitz et al., 2013</xref>). After a 10 min acclimation period, spontaneous behavior was filmed for 10 min. Movies were analyzed, using custom made Matlab programs, to determine population statistics for metrics representative of spontaneous motor behaviors: distance traveled, time spent resting, place preference, and the frequency and duration of spontaneous swim bouts. MAG-treated animals exhibited no significant difference in any measure compared with DMSO-treated controls.</p></sec><sec id="s4-10"><title>Time lapse imaging of retinal ganglion cell axonal arbor development</title><p>For visualization of individual retinal ganglion cells, embryos from incrosses of <italic>Tg[s1101t-gal4;; UAS-GluN2A(G712C)]</italic> fish were injected with <italic>pou4f3-gal4:UAS-mGFP</italic> DNA (mGFP; monomeric membrane-bound due to palmitoylation sequence from gap43). Injected embryos were reared in E3 containing 0.005% 1-phenyl 2-thiourea (PTU) and screened based on GFP expression at 48 hpf. Typically, injected embryos had 1–3 non-overlapping labeled axons. At 120 hpf, <italic>pou4f3- gal4:UAS-mGFP</italic> positive fish were assessed for spontaneous swimming and inflated swim bladder as markers for normal development. Healthy animals were divided into two groups to receive treatment in either 150 µM MAG-0 in E3 with 0.3% DMSO or in E3 with 0.3% DMSO for 40 min at 28.6°C. All fish then were rinsed twice in fresh E3 and allowed to recover for 2 hr at 28.6°C.</p><p>Fish were then embedded in 1.4% low-melting agarose in E3 for an initial imaging session to measure baseline morphology of the RGC projections. Following the baseline imaging session, each animal was freed from agarose and transferred to fresh E3 containing 0.005% PTU to recover from anesthesia. Fish typically recovered spontaneous swimming within 1 hr. Between 128 hpf and 168 hpf, fish were subjected to a photo-antagonism protocol described below. Each fish was then remounted in agarose for a second imaging session to assess RGC growth. Following the second imaging session, fish were euthanized in 0.4% tricaine. Genomic DNA was then extracted from individual whole animals in 60 µl volume (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Meeker et al., 2007</xref>) and genotyped for the <italic>UAS-GluN2A(G712C)</italic> transgene using the PCR primers described above.</p><p>At 128 hpf, each fish was transferred to a 48 well plate in 800 µl E3 with 0.005% PTU and placed in a custom imaging chamber equipped with an array of 405 nm LEDs centered under each well. The LED array was controlled by a DAQ (National Instruments) programmed to produce 10 s flashes every 30 min. The imaging chamber maintained ambient lighting on a 14 hr light/10 hr dark cycle with an ambient temperature of ~26°C.</p><p>Twenty minutes prior to each imaging session, each fish was mounted dorsal-side up in a glass-bottom dish in 1.4% low-melting-point agarose dissolved in E3, and anesthetized with 0.02% tricaine. Z-stacks with 0.35–0.5 µm steps were obtained using a 2-photon Zeiss LSM710 microscope equipped with a 3 W Ti-Sapphire laser (Coherent, Chameleon Ultra) tuned to 920 nm. Minimal laser intensity was used (&lt;20 mW measured at the front of the objective). A long working distance water-dipping 40X/1.0 NA objective was used to acquire all images. In each 3- dimensional image, RGC axon arbors were traced using the Simple Neurite Tracer plug-in for ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Longair et al., 2011</xref>). Sholl analysis was performed on each isolated 3-dimension arbor, where spheres were centered on the first branch point remaining at 7 dpf (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9c</xref>, inset).</p></sec><sec id="s4-11"><title>Availability of MAG</title><p>MAG photo-switches are now available commercially from Aspira​ Scientific: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aspirasci.com/neuroscience-probes">http://www.aspirasci.com/neuroscience-probes</ext-link></p></sec><sec id="s4-12"><title>Animal usage</title><p>All animal experiments were done under oversight by the University of California institutional review board (Animal Care and Use committee). This study was performed in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. All of the animals were handled according to approved institutional animal care and use committee (IACUC) protocols (AUP-2015-04-7437) of the University of California. Every effort was made to minimize suffering.</p></sec><sec id="s4-13"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Results are shown as mean ± SEM. Data sets of &gt;3 points of data were tested for Normality (normal distribution), followed by a multiple group comparison, using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with a <italic>post hoc</italic> Tukey test. Data sets which failed the normality test were followed by ANOVA on ranks (Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Test). All-pairwise analysis and two group comparisons were done using two-tailed, T-test or paired T-test, when applicable (SigmaPlot<sup>TM</sup>, 2011, Systat Software Inc., San Jose, CA). Rank Sum test was applied whenever normality failed for two group comparison. Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences as follows: *p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01; ***p&lt;0.001, n.s., not significant. Box plots display medians, 10<sup>th</sup> and 90<sup>th</sup> percentiles and outliers (filled circles). Individual data points, when displayed, are found to the right of the box plot as filled squares.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Noam Ziv for NMDA receptor cDNAs, Masayoshi Mishina and David Lovinger for GluN2A-knockout mice, Holly Aaron for help with microscopy, Marta Soden for guidance on hippocampal slice culture and Zhu Fu and Matthew Truong for help with molecular biology and cell culture. We also thank Mu-Ming Poo, Richard Kramer, Dan Feldman, Doris Fortin and Matthew Volgraf for helpful discussion. We thank Joshua Levitz for helpful discussion and help with autapse recordings. Support was provided by the National Institutes of Health Nanomedicine Development Center for the Optical Control of Biological Function (NIH 2PN2EY018241) (DT and EYI) and U01 NS090527 (EYI), National Science Foundation (NSF-1041078) (EYI), HFSP (RGP0013/2010) (EYI), ERC Advanced Grant (DT), National Science Foundation predoctoral fellowship (SS), German Research Foundation postdoctoral fellowship (DFG RE 3101/1-1) (AR), and CNRS (INSB) (AG).</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf1"><p>The authors declare that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>SB, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>SS, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>AR, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>ECC, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>MAK, Drafting or revising the article, Contributed unpublished essential data or reagents</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>AG, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con7"><p>TX, Conception and design, Analysis and interpretation of data</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con8"><p>DT, Conception and design, Contributed unpublished essential data or reagents</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con9"><p>EYI, Conception and design, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Animal experimentation: This study was performed in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. All of the animals were handled according to approved institutional animal care and use committee (IACUC) protocols (AUP-2015-04-7437) of the University of California. Every effort was made to minimize suffering.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anson</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyllie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoepfer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Identification of amino acid residues of the NR2A subunit that control glutamate potency in recombinant NR1/NR2A NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>589</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malinow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Subunit-specific NMDA receptor trafficking to synapses</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(02)00776-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bekkers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Excitatory and inhibitory autaptic currents in isolated hippocampal neurons maintained in cell culture</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>7834</fpage><lpage>7838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.88.17.7834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Photoactivatable genetically encoded calcium indicators for targeted neuronal imaging</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>852</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Keren-Raifman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Castel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dessauer</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dascal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>G alpha(i) and g betagamma jointly regulate the conformations of a g betagamma effector, the neuronal g protein-activated k+ channel (gIRK)</article-title><source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>285</volume><fpage>6179</fpage><lpage>6185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.085944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bidoret</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Casado</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Presynaptic NR2A-containing NMDA receptors implement a high-pass filter synaptic plasticity rule</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>14126</fpage><lpage>14131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0904284106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Collingridge</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year><article-title>A synaptic model of memory: long-term potentiation in the hippocampus</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>361</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/361031a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broichhagen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Damijonaitis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Leippe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Konrad</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Orthogonal optical control of a g protein-coupled receptor with a SNAP-tethered photochromic ligand</article-title><source>ACS Central Science</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscentsci.5b00260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caporale</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolstad</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tochitsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalkara</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Flannery</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>LiGluR restores visual responses in rodent models of inherited blindness</article-title><source>Molecular Therapy : The Journal of the American Society of Gene Therapy</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>1212</fpage><lpage>1219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mt.2011.103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kienzler</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Two-photon brightness of azobenzene photoswitches designed for glutamate receptor optogenetics</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>112</volume><elocation-id>E776</elocation-id><lpage>E785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1416942112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Geballe</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Stansfeld</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyllie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Structural features of the glutamate binding site in recombinant NR1/NR2A n-methyl-d-aspartate receptors determined by site-directed mutagenesis and molecular modeling</article-title><source>Molecular Pharmacology</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>1470</fpage><lpage>1484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.104.008185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantine-Paton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1989">1989</year><article-title>NMDA receptor antagonists disrupt the retinotectal topographic map</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0896-6273(89)90201-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulkey</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicoll</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Malenka</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Ca2+ signaling requirements for long-term depression in the hippocampus</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80102-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emiliani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Deisseroth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Häusser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>All-optical interrogation of neural circuits</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>13917</fpage><lpage>13926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2916-15.2015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erreger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Allosteric interaction between zinc and glutamate binding domains on NR2A causes desensitization of NMDA receptors</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>569</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2005.095497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forné</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwigsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Imhof</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller-Planitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Probing the conformation of the ISWI ATPase domain with genetically encoded photoreactive crosslinkers and mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>M111 012088</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M111.012088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Edbauer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantine-Paton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Distinct roles of NR2A and NR2B cytoplasmic tails in long-term potentiation</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>2676</fpage><lpage>2685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4022-09.2010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dailey</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Preparation of rodent hippocampal slice cultures</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Protocols</source><volume>2007</volume><fpage>pdb.prot4848</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/pdb.prot4848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancusso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouaux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Subunit arrangement and function in NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>438</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gascón-Moya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pejoan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Izquierdo-Serra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittolo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabré</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernando</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alibés</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorostiza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Busqué</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>An optimized glutamate receptor photoswitch with sensitized azobenzene isomerization</article-title><source>The Journal of Organic Chemistry</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>9915</fpage><lpage>9925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.joc.5b01402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Readily releasable pool size changes associated with long term depression</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>1283</fpage><lpage>1288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.3.1283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorostiza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Optical switches for remote and noninvasive control of cell signaling</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>322</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1166022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorostiza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Volgraf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Numano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Szobota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Mechanisms of photoswitch conjugation and light activation of an ionotropic glutamate receptor</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>10865</fpage><lpage>10870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0701274104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groc</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Spontaneous unitary synaptic activity in CA1 pyramidal neurons during early postnatal development: constant contribution of AMPA and NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>5552</fpage><lpage>5562</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardingham</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bading</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Synaptic versus extrasynaptic NMDA receptor signalling: implications for neurodegenerative disorders</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Neuroscience</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Locally dynamic synaptic learning rules in pyramidal neuron dendrites</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>450</volume><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>The Spread of Ras Activity Triggered by Activation of a Single Dendritic Spine</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>321</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1159675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedegaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bräuner-Osborne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Molecular pharmacology of human NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Neurochemistry International</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2011.11.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holtmaat</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Trachtenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilbrecht</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Knott</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Transient and persistent dendritic spines in the neocortex in vivo</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2005.01.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedoryak</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis-Davies</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergles</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of 4-methoxy-7-nitroindolinyl-d-aspartate, a caged compound for selective activation of glutamate transporters and n-methyl-d-aspartate receptors in brain tissue</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>3316</fpage><lpage>3326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi048051m</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inanobe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouaux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Mechanism of partial agonist action at the NR1 subunit of NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2005.05.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivenshitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Neuronal density determines network connectivity and spontaneous activity in cultured hippocampus</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>1052</fpage><lpage>1060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00914.2009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izquierdo-Serra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascón-Moya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirtz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittolo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Poskanzer</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>È</given-names></name><name><surname>Alibés</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Busqué</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuste</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernando</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorostiza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Two-photon neuronal and astrocytic stimulation with azobenzene-based photoswitches</article-title><source>Journal of the American Chemical Society</source><volume>136</volume><fpage>8693</fpage><lpage>8701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja5026326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janovjak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Szobota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>A light-gated, potassium-selective glutamate receptor for the optical inhibition of neuronal firing</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Coin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Leary</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Slesinger</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>In vivo expression of a light-activatable potassium channel using unnatural amino acids</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2013.08.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karakas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Crystal structure of a heterotetrameric NMDA receptor ion channel</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>344</volume><fpage>992</fpage><lpage>997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1251915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kienzler</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>A red-shifted, fast-relaxing azobenzene photoswitch for visible light control of an ionotropic glutamate receptor</article-title><source>Journal of the American Chemical Society</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>17683</fpage><lpage>17686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja408104w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirson</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaari</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Synaptic NMDA receptors in developing mouse hippocampal neurones: functional properties and sensitivity to ifenprodil</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>497 (Pt 2)</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>455</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klippenstein</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghisi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wietstruk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Plested</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Photoinactivation of glutamate receptors by genetically encoded unnatural amino acids</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3725-13.2014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shipton</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Deacon</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawlins</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Deisseroth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Hemisphere-specific optogenetic stimulation reveals left-right asymmetry of hippocampal plasticity</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mourot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Adesnik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Optogenetic pharmacology for control of native neuronal signaling proteins</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Köhr</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Koester</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihaljevic</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Utvik</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kvello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottersen</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeburg</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprengel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hvalby</surname><given-names>Ø</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Intracellular domains of NMDA receptor subtypes are determinants for long-term potentiation induction</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>10791</fpage><lpage>10799</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zukin</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>NMDA receptor trafficking in synaptic plasticity and neuropsychiatric disorders</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Neuroscience</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Escobedo-Lozoya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Szatmari</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Activation of CaMKII in single dendritic spines during long-term potentiation</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>458</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Habermacher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mery</surname><given-names>P-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouquier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Diverchy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Taly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rassendren</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Specht</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grutter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Optical control of an ion channel gate</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>20813</fpage><lpage>20818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1318715110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantoja</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaub</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Janovjak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoagland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoppik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stawski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schier</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Optical control of metabotropic glutamate receptors</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hérault</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Oheim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ropert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Optogenetic activation of LiGluR-expressing astrocytes evokes anion channel-mediated glutamate release</article-title><source>The Journal of Physiology</source><volume>590</volume><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>873</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2011.219345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mourot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vytla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Engineering a light-regulated G<sub>A</sub>B<sub>A<sub>a</sub></sub> receptor for optical control of neural inhibition</article-title><source>ACS Chemical Biology</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>1414</fpage><lpage>1419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cb500167u</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozza</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lingenhoehl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Auberson</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Role of NMDA receptor subtypes in governing the direction of hippocampal synaptic plasticity</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>304</volume><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1096615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Longair</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Simple neurite tracer: open source software for reconstruction, visualization and analysis of neuronal processes</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>2453</fpage><lpage>2454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramár</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Babayan</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rumbaugh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Differences between synaptic plasticity thresholds result in new timing rules for maximizing long-term potentiation</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2012.07.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lüscher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Malenka</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>NMDA receptor-dependent long-term potentiation and long-term depression (lTP/LTD)</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><volume>4</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a005710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Malinow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>AMPA Receptor Incorporation into Synapses during LTP: The Role of Lateral Movement and Exocytosis</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2009.08.035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massey</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moult</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Auberson</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Molnar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Collingridge</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bashir</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Differential roles of NR2A and NR2B-containing NMDA receptors in cortical long-term potentiation and long-term depression</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>7821</fpage><lpage>7828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1697-04.2004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis-Davies</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Dendritic spine geometry is critical for AMPA receptor expression in hippocampal CA1 pyramidal neurons</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>1086</fpage><lpage>1092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Honkura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis-Davies</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Structural basis of long-term potentiation in single dendritic spines</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>429</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meeker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Trede</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Method for isolation of PCR-ready genomic DNA from zebrafish tissues</article-title><source>BioTechniques</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2144/000112619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jane</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Pharmacological modulation of NMDA receptor activity and the advent of negative and positive allosteric modulators</article-title><source>Neurochemistry International</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2012.01.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nabavi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Proulx</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Malinow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Engineering a memory with LTD and LTP</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>511</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonegawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>NMDA receptors, place cells and hippocampal spatial memory</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Neuroscience</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn1385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neyton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Relating NMDA receptor function to receptor subunit composition: limitations of the pharmacological approach</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>1331</fpage><lpage>1333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5242-05.2006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nimchinsky</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oertner</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>The number of glutamate receptors opened by synaptic stimulation in single hippocampal spines</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>2054</fpage><lpage>2064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5066-03.2004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Biochemical computation for spine structural plasticity</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.05.043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Numano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Szobota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorostiza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Volgraf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Nanosculpting reversed wavelength sensitivity into a photoswitchable iGluR</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>6814</fpage><lpage>6819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0811899106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lummis</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Biolistic transfection of neuronal cultures using a hand-held gene gun</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2006.145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>K-I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyawaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Rapid and persistent modulation of actin dynamics regulates postsynaptic reorganization underlying bidirectional plasticity</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>1104</fpage><lpage>1112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn1311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palma-Cerda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowell</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Swift</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cais</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyklicky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Corrie</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>New caged neurotransmitter analogs selective for glutamate receptor sub-types based on methoxynitroindoline and nitrophenylethoxycarbonyl caging groups</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2012.05.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>NMDA receptor subunit diversity: impact on receptor properties, synaptic plasticity and disease</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Neuroscience</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn3504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Neyton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>NMDA receptor subunits: function and pharmacology</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Pharmacology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coph.2006.08.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pawlak</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Schupp</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kvello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hvalby</surname><given-names>Ø</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeburg</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Köhr</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Frequency-dependent impairment of hippocampal LTP from NMDA receptors with reduced calcium permeability</article-title><source>The European Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2005.04226.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peled</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Optical quantal analysis of synaptic transmission in wild-type and rab3-mutant drosophila motor axons</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prybylowski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Losi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenthold</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Relationship between availability of NMDA receptor subunits and their expression at the synapse</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>8902</fpage><lpage>8910</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Tethered ligands reveal glutamate receptor desensitization depends on subunit occupancy</article-title><source>Nature Chemical Biology</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.1458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Controlling ionotropic and metabotropic glutamate receptors with light: principles and potential</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Pharmacology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coph.2014.12.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodríguez-Moreno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeve</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Presynaptic induction and expression of timing-dependent long-term depression demonstrated by compartment-specific photorelease of a use-dependent NMDA receptor antagonist</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>8564</fpage><lpage>8569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0274-11.2011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kontarakis</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hölper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krüger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stainier</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Genetic compensation induced by deleterious mutations but not gene knockdowns</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>524</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruthazer</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Akerman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Control of axon branch dynamics by correlated activity in vivo</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>301</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1082545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutsuwada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Manabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushiya</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Reduced hippocampal LTP and spatial learning in mice lacking NMDA receptor epsilon 1 subunit</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>373</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/373151a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>F-X</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><chapter-title>Biological Macromolecules: UV-visible Spectrophotometry</chapter-title><source>Encyclopedia of Life Sciences</source><publisher-loc>Chichester, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npg.els.0003142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Buzzard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Borress</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhillon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>MK801 increases retinotectal arbor size in developing zebrafish without affecting kinetics of branch elimination and addition</article-title><source>Journal of Neurobiology</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4695(20000215)42:3&lt;303::AID-NEU2&gt;3.0.CO;2-A</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Long-term potentiation during the activity-dependent sharpening of the retinotopic map in goldfish</article-title><source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</source><volume>627</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.1991.tb25910.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrenberg</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziv</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosse</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Targeting neural circuitry in zebrafish using GAL4 enhancer trapping</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth1033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaner</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>McKeown</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbach</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazelwood</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Improving the photostability of bright monomeric orange and red fluorescent proteins</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shipton</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>GluN2A and GluN2B subunit-containing NMDA receptors in hippocampal plasticity</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological Sciences</source><volume>369</volume><fpage>20130163</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2013.0163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suster</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikuta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Urasaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Transgenesis in zebrafish with the tol2 transposon system</article-title><source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source><volume>561</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-60327-019-9_3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szobota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorostiza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Bene</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolstad</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tulyathan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Volgraf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Numano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aaron</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Flannery</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Remote control of neuronal activity with a light-gated glutamate receptor</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2007.05.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szobota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Optical control of neuronal activity</article-title><source>Annual Review of Biophysics</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biophys.093008.131400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rampon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerchner</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Genetic enhancement of learning and memory in mice</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>401</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/43432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Synaptic and extrasynaptic NMDA receptor NR2 subunits in cultured hippocampal neurons</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>1727</fpage><lpage>1734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00771.2005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tochitsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Banghart</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mourot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaub</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Optochemical control of genetically engineered neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors</article-title><source>Nature Chemistry</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchem.1234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traynelis</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollmuth</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>McBain</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Menniti</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dingledine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Glutamate receptor ion channels: structure, regulation, and function</article-title><source>Pharmacological Reviews</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/pr.109.002451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tye</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Deisseroth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Optogenetic investigation of neural circuits underlying brain disease in animal models</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Neuroscience</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn3171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vicini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Prybylowski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kralic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Homanics</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>GABA(A) receptor alpha1 subunit deletion prevents developmental changes of inhibitory synaptic currents in cerebellar neurons</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>3009</fpage><lpage>3016</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vicini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Grayson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Functional and pharmacological differences between recombinant n-methyl-d-aspartate receptors</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>566</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volgraf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorostiza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Numano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Allosteric control of an ionotropic glutamate receptor with an optical switch</article-title><source>Nature Chemical Biology</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib96"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weitlauf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Honse</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Auberson</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovinger</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Winder</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Activation of NR2A-containing NMDA receptors is not obligatory for NMDA receptor-dependent long-term potentiation</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>8386</fpage><lpage>8390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2388-05.2005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib97"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Bene</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Warp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Optogenetic dissection of a behavioural module in the vertebrate spinal cord</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>461</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib98"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Lamina-specific axonal projections in the zebrafish tectum require the type IV collagen dragnet</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1529</fpage><lpage>1537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn2002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib99"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name><name><surname>Frerking</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Spine expansion and stabilization associated with long-term potentiation</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>5740</fpage><lpage>5751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3998-07.2008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib100"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynelis</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Control of NMDA receptor function by the NR2 subunit amino-terminal domain</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>12045</fpage><lpage>12058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1365-09.2009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib101"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuste</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Electrical compartmentalization in dendritic spines</article-title><source>Annual Review of Neuroscience</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-neuro-062111-150455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib102"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Poo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>A critical window for cooperation and competition among developing retinotectal synapses</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>395</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/25665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib103"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Holbro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Oertner</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Optical induction of plasticity at single synapses reveals input-specific accumulation of CaMKII</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>12039</fpage><lpage>12044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0802940105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib104"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Teramoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdelfattah</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>An expanded palette of genetically encoded ca(2)(+) indicators</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>333</volume><fpage>1888</fpage><lpage>1891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1208592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib105"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y-D</given-names></name><name><surname>Acker</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Netoff</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Increasing Ca2+ transients by broadening postsynaptic action potentials enhances timing-dependent synaptic depression</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>19121</fpage><lpage>19125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0509856103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib106"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Riou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bensaude</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Genetically encoding a light switch in an ionotropic glutamate receptor reveals subunit-specific interfaces</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>6081</fpage><lpage>6086</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1318808111</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="article-commentary" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.023</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>Indira M</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff8"><institution>Northwestern University</institution>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your work entitled &quot;A family of photoswitchable NMDA receptors&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by two peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Gary Westbrook as the Senior Editor.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>The reviewers were favorably impressed with the main achievement of the study, i.e., the development of NMDA receptor subunits with photoswitchable tethered ligands, whose introduction into cells allows NMDA receptors of specific compositions to be turned on and off by light. These optically gated subunits set the stage for a wide range of studies of NMDA receptor contributions to a variety of neural processes. (The Reviewers' specific comments are included in &quot;General Assessment&quot; below.)</p><p>Essential Revisions:</p><p>The reviewers brought up several points for revision. Since the primary contribution of the work is to generate a tool, its experimental utility must be more explicitly demonstrated, and its shortcomings and/or limitations must be clearly explained. As one reviewer said in the discussion, &quot;At the moment, the excellent data are slightly diminished by glossing over important details.&quot; The points to address therefore center on showing and/or clarifying how broadly applicable the technique in its current form actually is. They are summarized here, and more details are given in the in &quot;Essential Revisions&quot; of the Reviewers' comments below.</p><p>1) Please provide better quantification of the effect of the photoswitchable receptors, especially regarding how the effect of photostimulation varies with efficiency of labeling and the ratio of modified to wild-type receptors. Comparison of existing results (in wild-type autapses and KO slices) to data from knockout autapses and/or with overexpression in wild-type slices would be helpful.</p><p>2) Because the main power of the technique will likely come from applications in preparations that are more intact than autapses and organotypic slices from neonates (e.g., acute slices and/or more intact preparations), as well as from subcellular control of receptors, please show or assess how feasible it will be to (de)activate these receptors with a technique like 2-photon absorption.</p><p>3) Since use of these receptors depends on application of the MAG ligands, please provide an indication of or instructions regarding their availability.</p><p>4) Some of the experiments appear statistically underpowered. Please reassess the statistical methods and revise accordingly (either by obtaining additional measures or modifying the analysis and/or conclusions).</p><p>5) In general, please ensure that the claims of the manuscript are commensurate with the data.</p><p>Reviewers' Comments:</p><p>General assessment comments:</p><p>This paper is an example of the mature stage of the authors' fascinating project of photo pharmacology with MAG and related compounds that started about 10 years ago. The molecular engineering and characterisation of the derivatized receptors is very impressive. It's satisfying that the authors seem to be able to bend the receptors to their will. The scope of the work is broad and it fits well to <italic>eLife</italic>.</p><p>This exceptional study describes the development of NMDAR subunits that can be modified with light to allow spatiotemporal control over NMDAR signaling. The authors employ a previously developed strategy to render different NMDAR subunits sensitive to light, by incorporating cysteines in key locations in the glutamate binding pocket of GluN subunits, allowing attachment of photoswitch-tethered ligands (a maleimide and a photoisomerizable azobenzine-glutamate) that when exposed to UV light enable activation or inactivation. The authors performed a detailed analysis of photo-antagonism and photo-agonism of these constructs in HEK cells, cultured neurons and in brain slices, demonstrating their ability to modulate NMDAR signaling at synapses to control excitation and plasticity with unprecedented precision. One major advantage of this approach is that the alteration of receptors is reversible, as the ligands can be switched from inactive trans to active cis states by different wavelengths of light. Remarkably, overexpression of these modified receptors does not appear to alter normal synaptic function (e.g. lead to enhanced NMDARs at synapses or alter the ability of endogenous glutamate to activate these receptors) and activation of photoswitches appears affected primarily NMDARs, despite the many accessible cysteines found in other proteins. Thus, it is likely that these tools will be very useful in defining the roles of distinct NMDAR subunits in synaptic function and plasticity, and provide a new optogenetic approach for eliciting cellular excitation.</p><p>Essential Revisions (expanded version):</p><p>1) The experiments in slices, which potentially provide the real excitement here, are somewhat patchy. Some are spectacular, e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref> is very strong. In other aspects, the approach is piecemeal. Effects on spine size are of exceptional interest, but what does photo-antagonism of synaptic currents look like on a KO? Is the effect limited by labelling in slice? Or by the ratio of wt:mut subunits? It's possible that long stimulation overcomes this problem for the photo-agonism experiments. No matter the results on LTP and spines, which are strong, the labelling/efficiency question is very important. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>, the effect is small and not much of much practical use. What happens on a KO background? Is the effect small because of limited labelling, or because of limited expression, or both or is it something else? This paper primarily introduces a tool. If the authors want their tool to be widely accepted, this kind of information is essential. The simplest way to address this is – to what extent are synaptic currents inhibited on KO background? If this experiment can't or won't be done, then there must be an explanation of this caveat in the paper. I would not include the latter (albeit impressive) effects on spines as a justification that the effect of light is all or nothing. We don't know how much NMDA current is needed for the effects on spines.</p><p>2) The authors have demonstrated the efficiency of modification using visible light. However, in intact preparations it is often desirable to manipulate signaling in subcellular domains. Although visible light is useful for dissociated cells and cells near the surface of cultured slices, scattering limits the utility of this approach when cells are deeper in tissue. It would significantly enhance the study if the authors were to provide an evaluation of the ability of these photoswitches to be modified by two photon absorbance.</p><p>3) The primary impact of the study lies in the ability of these variants and this strategy to be employed in a variety of contexts. In this regard, it is important to recognize that the manipulations require L-MAG0 and L-MAG1, in addition to the modified receptors. Thus, the authors should provide some information in the paper about the availability of the photoswitch ligands.</p><p>4) For statistical analyses, t-tests or one-way ANOVA with posthoc Tukey tests were performed. These tests require that the data are normally distributed. However, the authors do not indicate whether tests of normality were performed, and in places where individual datapoints are provided (e.g. Figure.4B-D), they do not appear to be normally distributed. There is some concern that for experiments such as those shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref> that the analysis is underpowered. If variance is high and multiple samples are compared, it is relatively easy to find no significance difference between groups. If the authors were to address these issues, it would increase confidence in the comparisons.</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were requested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><p>Thank you for resubmitting your work entitled &quot;A family of photoswitchable NMDA receptors&quot; for further consideration at <italic>eLife</italic>. Your revised article has been favorably evaluated by Gary Westbrook (Senior editor), a Reviewing editor, and two reviewers. The manuscript has been greatly improved. There are a few remaining issues that must be addressed before acceptance, as outlined below:</p><p>The reviewers appreciated the extent and quality of the revisions. The main question that arose had to do with the reporting of results relating to the efficiency of the manipulations in a manner that would be most useful the readers who might wish to implement the technique. A specific issue was the separation of responding and non-responding wild-type cells after transfection. The basis for this separation was not clearly stated in the manuscript, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref> came across as ambiguous, since the 4 non-responding cells of 10 tested were neither reported nor illustrated in the main text. Because the strength of this manuscript lies in the development of tools, the reviewers agree that a clear statement here and throughout the manuscript of n values and fraction of cells responding is crucial for others to evaluate the usefulness of the technique. A related point is that in our discussion of the reviews, the reviewers raised the possibility that the fraction of non-responders could result either from efficiency of labeling (as stated in the text) or from expression of the target (not stated in the text), which you may wish to comment upon. The full reviews are included below.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1:</italic> </p><p>The authors have made a comprehensive response that largely answers all the previously raised points of difficulty.</p><p>However, the analysis that has been added to answer concerns about the fundamental mechanisms underlying partial effects is itself possibly problematic.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref> indicates 4 non-responding cells. My interpretation is that these cells were transfected, exposed to MAG but did not get inhibited. Otherwise, they would be controls of some description. 6 further cells were used (in each case pooled across 2 conditions) and are shown in the main figure. The non-responders are not included in the average effect. They did have typical synaptic currents, in 3 out of 4 cases. The statistical analysis for inhibition included in the supplementary figure seems distinct from that for the tau and epsc size. Overall, for whatever reason, be it weak/variable expression of the target subunits, or poor labelling with the optically active element, the impression I have here is that 6/10 experiments gave inhibition, but 4/10 did not. Thus, the range cited in the third paragraph of the Discussion is misleading. If the authors want to exclude these cells for an objective reason, they should state in the main figure, and where they cite the range, that 4 cells were excluded.</p><p>Likewise, there are quite a few cells in the supplement to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> that might be thought of as non-responders.</p><p>These results are described by the authors in their response and in the discussion as &quot;satisfyingly reliable&quot;. If I have understood correctly, these data indicate that, on a wild-type background, the method is not that reliable. There is a stark contrast here with the very reproducible and important effects when rescuing GluN2A expression on a knockout background, and the new results in zebrafish which are also convincing.</p><p>There is no sense in which this limitation with wild-type backgrounds detracts from the overall study and its groundbreaking nature. The weak and variable effects are not surprising and can be circumvented with standard methods (genetically-targeted animals). But at the moment, I have the impression that authors are not accurately reporting the work on wild-type backgrounds.</p><p>Further, are there any other panels where non-responding cells are excluded and, if so, on what basis?</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1 (Additional data files and statistical comments):</italic> </p><p>The statistical analysis for inhibition included in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref> seems distinct from that for the tau and epsc size. Why?</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2:</italic> </p><p>The authors have done a nice job of responding to the previous concerns, in particular by extending the statistical analyses, providing additional experimental details, softening some of their earlier conclusions, and providing additional discussion. They have also included additional results showing that GluN2 photoantagonism in vivo in zebrafish induces axonal refinement deficits that are comparable to systemic MK801 exposure, providing another demonstration of utility. The authors have not provided data regarding the efficiency with which these photoswitches can be induced using two photon absorption, but they indicate that new MAG photoswitches will be developed based on strategies already shown to work with kainate and metabotropic receptors. It would have been nice to include data on the existing molecules to guide other investigators with their use, but I don't see this as an essential revision.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12040.024</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p><italic>Essential Revisions:</italic> </p><p> <italic>1) Please provide better quantification of the effect of the photoswitchable receptors, especially regarding how the effect of photostimulation varies with efficiency of labeling and the ratio of modified to wild-type receptors. Comparison of existing results (in wild-type autapses and KO slices) to data from knockout autapses and/or with overexpression in wild-type slices would be helpful.</italic> </p><p>We have addressed the two possible sources of variability between experiments: A) expression level of the cysteine-substituted (photoswitch-ready) LiGluN subunit and B) level of labeling with the MAG photoswitch. In addition, to put the degree of efficacy and variability in context of conventional pharmacology, we have added C) a new experiment that compares MAG photoswitching of LiGluN-containing NMDA receptors in transgenic animals to conventional pharmacological manipulation of native NMDA receptors in control animals.</p><p>We cannot compare between KO data and autaptic data because they were obtained from different species: autaptic currents and all other cultured cell data were from C57BL-<italic>wt</italic> rats, whereas the KO data is was from GluN2A-KO mice (Sakimura, Kutsuwada et al. 1995).</p><p>A) To assess expression levels of the LiGluN subunits we further investigated the relationship between the size of the photo-response (in the case of photo-agonism the amplitude of the photo-current; in the case of photo-antagonism the amplitude of the current reduction by light) and the total current induced by agonist or synaptic glutamate release, now shown in two new panels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>). We observe a moderate correlation between the photo-responses and total NMDA-induced current (R=0.709, P&lt;0.0001, n=22; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>) and no correlation for the autaptic recordings (R= 0.543, P=0.297, n=6; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>). This is consistent with our initial conclusion that expression of the engineered subunits does not induce a substantial overexpression of NMDA receptors (as assessed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>).</p><p>B) We have no direct way of measuring MAG conjugation efficiency (MAG is not fluorescent), but given (A), above, and the general experience in the field of variable penetration of small organic molecules of the size of MAG (such as fluorescent dyes) into synapses in dissociated primary neuron cultures and in brain slice, we conjecture that variability in photoswitch efficacy is primarily due to variability in MAG conjugation efficiency.</p><p>In accordance with the reviewer request, we now provide data from individual recordings to key figure panels to show the experiment-to-experiment variability (see revised <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D-F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2—figure supplement 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). The raw data for individual autapses was already provided in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref> (open circles), but are now also included in a new panel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>) with additional non responding cells as comparison, for easy assessment of the variability in the experiment.</p><p>C) We have also added a new section (including two Figures) to compare the variability of our optogenetic photo-pharmacological block of NMDA receptors using LiGluN with the variability seen with conventional pharmacology for blocking NMDA receptors. We did this in the challenging biological context of the intact zebrafish brain in vivo. We compared the effect of photo-antagonism of NMDA receptors with LiGluN2A(G712C) versus the activity-dependent pore blocker MK-801 on the activity-dependent development of retinal ganglion cell axonal arbors in the optic tectum. We find that the manipulations have both a similar magnitude of effect and a strikingly similar degree of variability (new <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref> and its supplement).</p><p><italic>2) Because the main power of the technique will likely come from applications in preparations that are more intact than autapses and organotypic slices from neonates (e.g., acute slices and/or more intact preparations), as well as from subcellular control of receptors, please show or assess how feasible it will be to (de)activate these receptors with a technique like 2-photon absorption.</italic> </p><p>We agree that 2-photon photoswitching would be very valuable to achieve good 3D light confinement and better tissue penetration in acute brain slice and in vivo. We and others have recently designed three new classes of MAGs (Kienzler, Reiner et al. 2013; Gascon-Moya, Pejoan et al. 2015) that we, and others, show to work well with 2-photon (2P) photoactivation of a related iGluR (kainate receptor) and an mGluR (Izquierdo-Serra, Gascon-Moya et al. 2014; Carroll, Berlin et al. 2015; Gascon-Moya, Pejoan et al. 2015). This approach will be adapted to LiGluNs as well. This is now mentioned in the text (Discussion, seventh paragraph).</p><p>In preparations such as <italic>C. elegans, Drosophila</italic> and zebrafish, in which precise genetic targeting can be readily achieved (i.e. of the photoswitch-ready subunit) and where the nervous system is accessible to light and much less scattering (especially in the zebrafish), it is already possible to accomplish MAG photo-control of glutamate receptors with conventional 1-photon (1P) illumination, as we showed previously in zebrafish sensory neurons (Szobota, Gorostiza et al. 2007), in the central pattern generator circuit for swimming (Wyart, Del Bene et al. 2009; Janovjak, Szobota et al. 2010) and pan-neuronally (Levitz, Pantoja et al. 2013). We now add a new section to the paper (final section of Results) that demonstrates effective optical control with 1P light in vivoin transgenic zebrafish expressing the LiGluN2A(G712C) subunit (new <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s1">Figure 9—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p> <italic>3) Since use of these receptors depends on application of the MAG ligands, please provide an indication of or instructions regarding their availability.</italic> </p><p>MAG photo-switches are now available commercially from Aspira Scientific: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aspirasci.com/neuroscience-probes">http://www.aspirasci.com/neuroscience-probes</ext-link> (noted in subsection “Availability of MAG”).</p><p> <italic>4) Some of the experiments appear statistically underpowered. Please reassess the statistical methods and revise accordingly (either by obtaining additional measures or modifying the analysis and/or conclusions).</italic> </p><p>We reassessed our statistical analysis and figure presentations and now show the complete data sets and statistical analysis. We replotted panels where the data did not distribute normally as Box plots and included results for normality tests and ANOVA on ranks that we performed on the data (SigmaPlot 2011; V11.0 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3C</xref>, right panel, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D-F</xref> and corresponding supplement 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4D and supplement 1C</xref> with their corresponding supplement 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref> and corresponding supplement 1, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref> and corresponding supplement 1C). We have also expanded our description of the statistical analysis in Methods (subsection “Statistical analysis”). Importantly, our interpretation of the results did not change based on these new statistical tests. We have, however, moderated our description in the Discussion, as suggested by the reviewers.</p><p><italic>5) In general, please ensure that the claims of the manuscript are commensurate with the data.</italic> </p><p>We have followed this suggestion, as documented below.</p><p> <italic>Essential Revisions (expanded version):</italic></p><p> <italic>1) The experiments in slices, which potentially provide the real excitement here, are somewhat patchy. Some are spectacular, e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref> is very strong. In other aspects, the approach is piecemeal. Effects on spine size are of exceptional interest, but what does photo-antagonism of synaptic currents look like on a KO? Is the effect limited by labelling in slice? Or by the ratio of wt:mut subunits? It's possible that long stimulation overcomes this problem for the photo-agonism experiments. No matter the results on LTP and spines, which are strong, the labelling/efficiency question is very important. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>, the effect is small and not much of much practical use. What happens on a KO background? Is the effect small because of limited labelling, or because of limited expression, or both or is it something else? This paper primarily introduces a tool. If the authors want their tool to be widely accepted, this kind of information is essential. The simplest way to address this is</italic> –</p><p><italic>to what extent are synaptic currents inhibited on KO background? If this experiment can't or won't be done, then there must be an explanation of this caveat in the paper. I would not include the latter (albeit impressive) effects on spines as a justification that the effect of light is all or nothing. We don't know how much NMDA current is needed for the effects on spines.</italic> </p><p>As described in the response to the Essential Revisions Summary point 1, the degree of photo-activation or block is influenced by: i) the fraction of cysteine-substituted (&quot;photoswitch ready&quot;) subunits that are incorporated into the GluN2 &quot;slot&quot; of NMDA receptors and ii) the efficiency of labeling those subunits with the photoswitch. In the case of the KO, (i) is optimized due to absence of the native GluN2A. However, even in neurons isolated from WT animals expressing the WT GluN2A (as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C-E</xref> and summary in F, and in new <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>), photo-antagonism can be remarkably potent (&gt;50%; i.e. equivalent to the efficacy obtained with classical blockers, such as the GluN2A antagonist NVP-AAM077, when applied at concentrations that ensure selectivity for GluN2A-containing receptors).</p><p>The degree of photo-block of NMDA receptor EPSCs in the autapses from WT rat neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref>) is indeed small on average (mean 25-35%, range ~20-50%). We elected to test this in the WT context because this represents the strongest test of the efficiency of the approach for generating NMDARs that are light-controlled in a background where the LiGluN subunit competes with WT subunits to assemble into receptors that are properly trafficked into synapses. Despite the smaller fractional optical control, it is satisfying that the control is reliable. We have added into the Results, Methods and Figure Legends an explicit mention for each experiment of whether it was performed in the GluN2A-KO or in WT (e.g.” Cultured hippocampal neurons from wt rats (C57BL) transfected with the photo-antagonizing 261 GluN2A(G712C) subunit in combination with photo-antagonizing GluN1a(E406C),”; in <italic>all</italic> relevant figure legends and Methods, subsections “Cell culture and transfection” and “Organotypic hippocampal slice culture preparation and biolistic transfection”). We provide a caveat that explains that the degree of photo-block in organotypic slices from the GluN2A-KO that were used for the LTP and spine expansion experiments is likely significantly greater than the small degree of photo-block seen in WT autapses where only a fraction of the NMDA receptors are under optical control (in the Discussion, third paragraph).</p><p>We have added several additional panels to show the variability of photoswitching in several different preparations and experimental paradigms to the figures that did not already include such data (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D-F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9F</xref>).</p><p>In NR2A-KO cells, where we could block the remaining NR2B-containing receptors using ifenprodil for example, we would still be limited by variability in MAG labeling, much like the results obtained from HEK-cell recordings, that lack native NMDA receptors and so necessarily contain two subunits of LiGluN2A in each and every receptor found at their membrane but which, nevertheless show the same variability in photo-current amplitude compared to agonist-evoked current.</p><p>We do not know how much NMDA receptor current is needed to induce spine expansion, but this uncertainty applies as well to the “classical” method of studying spine morphological dynamics of photo-uncaging of caged glutamate (MNI-glutamate). In fact, most uncaging experiments are performed in high external Ca<sup>2+</sup> (i.e. &gt;2.5 mM)(e.g. (Matsuzaki, Honkura et al. 2004; Okamoto, Nagai et al. 2004; Harvey and Svoboda 2007; Harvey, Yasuda et al. 2008; Makino and Malinow 2009); as described in the first paragraph of the subsection “Single spine imaging of calcium and structural plasticity“, taking into consideration the variability in the number of responsive spines and threshold for activation (Lynch, Kramar et al. 2013), the fact that synaptic transmission nor uncaging saturates synaptic NMDA receptors (Mainen, Malinow et al. 1999) and because the number of receptors per spine is highly variable.</p><p>Our ability to induce or block spine expansion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figures 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8</xref>) represents a fundamental practical success since this cellular change is thought to be key to LTP (Matsuzaki, Ellis-Davies et al. 2001; Matsuzaki, Honkura et al. 2004; Zhang, Holbro et al. 2008), which we rephrased in the text (subsection “Single spine imaging of calcium and structural plasticity”). The proof of the relevance of this to the study of the mechanism of long-term synaptic plasticity and its role in circuit function is obtained by using an electrophysiological assay to confirm that photo-antagonism blocks LTP induction as measured electrophysiologically via changes in EPSC amplitude (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>).</p><p><italic>2) The authors have demonstrated the efficiency of modification using visible light. However, in intact preparations it is often desirable to manipulate signaling in subcellular domains. Although visible light is useful for dissociated cells and cells near the surface of cultured slices, scattering limits the utility of this approach when cells are deeper in tissue. It would significantly enhance the study if the authors were to provide an evaluation of the ability of these photoswitches to be modified by two photon absorbance.</italic> </p><p>As described in the response to the Essential Revisions Summary point 2, we and others have generated three new variant versions of MAG (Kienzler et al., 2013; Gascon-Moya, Pejoan et al. 2015) that work well with 2-photon (2P) photoactivation of a related iGluR (kainate receptor) and an mGluR (Carroll, Berlin et al. 2015; Gascon-Moya, Pejoan et al. 2015). This approach can next be adapted to LiGluNs. This is now mentioned in the text (Discussion, seventh paragraph).</p><p>In addition, in preparations such as <italic>C. elegans, Drosophila</italic> and zebrafish, where precise genetic targeting can be readily achieved (i.e. of the photoswitch-ready subunit) and where the nervous system is accessible to light and (especially in the zebrafish) much less scattering, it is already possible with conventional 1-photon (1P) illumination to accomplish MAG photo-control of glutamate receptors, as we showed previously in zebrafish sensory neurons (Szobota et al., 2007), the spinal central pattern generator circuit for swimming (Wyart et al., 2009; Janovjak et al., 2010) and pan-neuronally (Levitz et al., 2013).</p><p>We have added a new section to the paper (LiGluN2A photo-antagonism disrupts pruning […] in vivo) that demonstrates effective optical control with 1P light in vivo in transgenic zebrafish expressing the LiGluN2A(G712C) subunit (new <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9s1">Figure 9—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p><italic>3) The primary impact of the study lies in the ability of these variants and this strategy to be employed in a variety of contexts. In this regard, it is important to recognize that the manipulations require L-MAG0 and L-MAG1, in addition to the modified receptors. Thus, the authors should provide some information in the paper about the availability of the photoswitch ligands.</italic> </p><p>MAG photoswitches are now available commercially from Aspira​ Scientific: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aspirasci.com/neuroscience-probes">http://www.aspirasci.com/neuroscience-probes</ext-link>, now mentioned in Methods (subsection “Availability of MAG”).</p><p><italic>4) For statistical analyses, t-tests or one-way ANOVA with posthoc Tukey tests were performed. These tests require that the data are normally distributed. However, the authors do not indicate whether tests of normality were performed, and in places where individual datapoints are provided (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B-D</xref>), they do not appear to be normally distributed. There is some concern that for experiments such as those shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref> that the analysis is underpowered. If variance is high and multiple samples are compared, it is relatively easy to find no significance difference between groups. If the authors were to address these issues, it would increase confidence in the comparisons.</italic></p><p>As described in the response to the Essential Revisions Summary point 4, we reassessed our statistical analysis and figure presentations and now show complete data sets and analysis. This includes normality tests and ANOVA on ranks for data that do not normally distribute. Accordingly, we replotted panels to better describe the data. Importantly, our interpretation of the results did not change based on these new statistical tests. This is also noted in Methods; statistics section (subsection “Statistical analysis”) and in additional panels and supplementary figures.</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were requested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><p><italic>The reviewers appreciated the extent and quality of the revisions. The main question that arose had to do with the reporting of results relating to the efficiency of the manipulations in a manner that would be most useful the readers who might wish to implement the technique. A specific issue was the separation of responding and non-responding wild-type cells after transfection. The basis for this separation was not clearly stated in the manuscript, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5F</xref> came across as ambiguous, since the 4 non-responding cells of 10 tested were neither reported nor illustrated in the main text. Because the strength of this manuscript lies in the development of tools, the reviewers agree that a clear statement here and throughout the manuscript of n values and fraction of cells responding is crucial for others to evaluate the usefulness of the technique. A related point is that in our discussion of the reviews, the reviewers raised the possibility that the fraction of non-responders could result either from efficiency of labeling (as stated in the text) or from expression of the target (not stated in the text), which you may wish to comment upon. The full reviews are included below. Reviewer #1: The authors have made a comprehensive response that largely answers all the previously raised points of difficulty. However, the analysis that has been added to answer concerns about the fundamental mechanisms underlying partial effects is itself possibly problematic. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref> indicates 4 non-responding cells. My interpretation is that these cells were transfected, exposed to MAG but did not get inhibited. Otherwise, they would be controls of some description. 6 further cells were used (in each case pooled across 2 conditions) and are shown in the main figure. The non-responders are not included in the average effect. They did have typical synaptic currents, in 3 out of 4 cases. The statistical analysis for inhibition included in the supplementary figure seems distinct from that for the tau and epsc size. Overall, for whatever reason, be it weak/variable expression of the target subunits, or poor labelling with the optically active element, the impression I have here is that 6/10 experiments gave inhibition, but 4/10 did not. Thus, the range cited in the third paragraph of the Discussion is misleading. If the authors want to exclude these cells for an objective reason, they should state in the main figure, and where they cite the range, that 4 cells were excluded.</italic> </p><p>Though the 4 excluded cells were initially mentioned in the legend of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>, we now added mention to the main text (Discussion, third paragraph), and we added a description of the criteria for exclusion in the legend. We note that non-responding cells were excluded from the averages shown in the main figure in both legends (main <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>) because of the very small degree of block (&lt;10%). These small effects (though likely real) are hard to discern from the naturally occurring rundown that results from the depletion of the ready-releasable pool of vesicles, as shown by Goda and Stevens (Goda &amp; Stevens, 1998) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref> legend). Therefore, we applied this rigorous exclusion criteria to prevent inclusion of rundown-dependent decreases in EPSC amplitude.</p><p>We retested all of the statistics and find the statistical tests to be appropriate. eEPSC<sub>NMDA</sub> size and τ<sub>deac</sub> are not normally distributed for the entire data set (although 2/3 of the subgroups did have a normal distribution). As a result, these were further analyzed using Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA on Ranks. The Normality test for “% inhibition” did pass for the entire data set so that it could be tested by ANOVA for significance (Sigmaplot 10.0).</p><p><italic>Likewise, there are quite a few cells in the supplement to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> that might be thought of as non-responders.</italic> </p><p>Non-transfected cells do not exhibit any observable response to light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1C</xref>), thus all photo-agonistic induction of current and all photo-block of NMDA-evoked current are due to photoswitching of the LiGluNs. While some of the responses are small, they are all non-zero and thereby included (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1B</xref>).</p><p><italic>These results are described by the authors in their response and in the discussion as &quot;satisfyingly reliable&quot;. If I have understood correctly, these data indicate that, on a wild-type background, the method is not that reliable. There is a stark contrast here with the very reproducible and important effects when rescuing GluN2A expression on a knockout background, and the new results in zebrafish which are also convincing. There is no sense in which this limitation with wild-type backgrounds detracts from the overall study and its groundbreaking nature. The weak and variable effects are not surprising and can be circumvented with standard methods (genetically-targeted animals). But at the moment, I have the impression that authors are not accurately reporting the work on wild-type backgrounds.</italic> We have rephrased our conclusions to clarify this issue. We note that the expression of the light-gated variants in a wild-type background yielded variable effects, ranging from very strong block to no block at all (Discussion, third paragraph). These observations may result from a combination of factors, among which the variable replacement of the endogenous receptors likely plays a major role. However, in responding cells, despite the small fractional optical control, the control is reproducible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1B</xref>).</p><p><italic>Further, are there any other panels where non-responding cells are excluded and, if so, on what basis?</italic> </p><p>No.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2: The authors have done a nice job of responding to the previous concerns, in particular by extending the statistical analyses, providing additional experimental details, softening some of their earlier conclusions, and providing additional discussion. They have also included additional results showing that GluN2 photoantagonism</italic> in vivo <italic>in zebrafish induces axonal refinement deficits that are comparable to systemic MK801 exposure, providing another demonstration of utility. The authors have not provided data regarding the efficiency with which these photoswitches can be induced using two photon absorption, but they indicate that new MAG photoswitches will be developed based on strategies already shown to work with kainate and metabotropic receptors. It would have been nice to include data on the existing molecules to guide other investigators with their use, but I don't see this as an essential revision.</italic></p><p>In the text, we mention that 2-photon (2P) activation of LiGluN should be possible based on recent advances by our lab that demonstrated 2P photo-agonism in the kainite-type ionotropic GluR, iGluR6 (GluK2) (aka “LiGluR”), using one MAG variant, as well as in a metabotropic GluR, mGluR3 (aka “LimGluR3”), using another MAG variant (Carroll et al., 2015), as well as other MAG variants for LiGluR, based on a distinct photoswitch design; made by the Gorostiza lab (Izquierdo-Serra et al., 2014; Gascon-Moya et al., 2015). We have not yet generated MAG variants of these 2P types for LiGluNs.</p></body></sub-article></article>