<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">37024</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Developmental Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Stem Cells and Regenerative Medicine</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Altered bone growth dynamics prefigure craniosynostosis in a zebrafish model of Saethre-Chotzen syndrome</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-105818"><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>Camilla S</given-names></name><email>cteng@usc.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-109622"><name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>Man-chun</given-names></name><email>manchunt@usc.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-119898"><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>D'Juan T</given-names></name><email>djuanfar@usc.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-120184"><name><surname>Brockop</surname><given-names>Mia</given-names></name><email>brockoms@faculty.laccd.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-109623"><name><surname>Maxson</surname><given-names>Robert E</given-names></name><email>maxson@usc.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-16285"><name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>J Gage</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3209-0026</contrib-id><email>gcrump@usc.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund4"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con6"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Stem Cell Biology and Regenerative Medicine</institution><institution>University of Southern California</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Los Angeles</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Biochemistry, Keck School of Medicine</institution><institution>University of Southern California</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Los Angeles</named-content></addr-line><country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>Richard M</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Bronner</surname><given-names>Marianne E</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>California Institute of Technology</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date date-type="publication" publication-format="electronic"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e37024</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-03-27"><day>27</day><month>03</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-10-14"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018, Teng et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Teng et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-37024-v1.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.001</object-id><p>Cranial sutures separate the skull bones and house stem cells for bone growth and repair. In Saethre-Chotzen syndrome, mutations in <italic>TCF12</italic> or <italic>TWIST1</italic> ablate a specific suture, the coronal. This suture forms at a neural-crest/mesoderm interface in mammals and a mesoderm/mesoderm interface in zebrafish. Despite this difference, we show that combinatorial loss of <italic>TCF12</italic> and <italic>TWIST1</italic> homologs in zebrafish also results in specific loss of the coronal suture. Sequential bone staining reveals an initial, directional acceleration of bone production in the mutant skull, with subsequent localized stalling of bone growth prefiguring coronal suture loss. Mouse genetics further reveal requirements for <italic>Twist1</italic> and <italic>Tcf12</italic> in both the frontal and parietal bones for suture patency, and to maintain putative progenitors in the coronal region. These findings reveal conservation of coronal suture formation despite evolutionary shifts in embryonic origins, and suggest that the coronal suture might be especially susceptible to imbalances in progenitor maintenance and osteoblast differentiation.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>Some of the most common birth defects involve improper development of the head and face. One such birth defect is called craniosynostosis. Normally, an infant’s skull bones are not fully fused together. Instead, they are held together by soft tissue that allows the baby’s skull to more easily pass through the birth canal. This tissue also houses specialized cells called stem cells that allow the brain and skull to grow with the child. But in craniosynostosis these stem cells behave abnormally, which fuses the skull bones together and prevents the skull and brain from growing properly during childhood.</p><p>One form of craniosynostosis called Saethre-Chotzen syndrome is caused by mutations in one of two genes that ensure the proper separation of two bones in the roof of the skull. Mice with mutations in the mouse versions of these genes develop the same problem and are used to study this condition. Mouse studies have looked mostly at what happens after birth. Studies looking at what happens in embryos with these mutations could help scientists learn more. One way to do so would be to genetically engineer zebrafish with the equivalent mutations. This is because zebrafish embryos are transparent and grow outside their mother’s body, making it easier for scientists to watch them develop.</p><p>Now, Teng et al. have grown zebrafish with mutations in the zebrafish versions of the genes that cause Saethre-Chotzen syndrome. In the experiments, imaging tools were used to observe the live fish as they developed. This showed that the stem cells in their skulls become abnormal much earlier than previous studies had suggested. Teng et al. also showed that similar stem cells are responsible for growth of the skull in zebrafish and mice.</p><p>Babies with craniosynostosis often need multiple, risky surgeries to separate their skull bones and allow their brain and head to grow. Unfortunately, these bones often fuse again because they have abnormal stem cells. Teng et al. provide new information on what goes wrong in these stem cells. Hopefully, this new information will help scientists to one day correct the defective stem cells in babies with craniosynostosis, thus reducing the number of surgeries needed to correct the problem.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>Saethre-Chotzen Syndrome</kwd><kwd>Twist1</kwd><kwd>Tcf12</kwd><kwd>coronal suture</kwd><kwd>craniosynostosis</kwd><kwd>skull bones</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>Mouse</kwd><kwd>Zebrafish</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000072</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>F31DE024031</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>Camilla S</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000072</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>T90DE021982</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>Camilla S</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100005237</institution-id><institution>Helen Hay Whitney Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>D'Juan T</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund4"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000072</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R01DE026339</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Maxson</surname><given-names>Robert E</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>J Gage</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund5"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000072</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R35DE027550</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>J Gage</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Sequential live imaging of abnormal skull bone fusion in zebrafish reveals a deeply conserved role of two transcription factors, Twist1 and Tcf12, in regulating stem cell activity during growth of the skull.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Craniofacial anomalies are among the most common congenital defects, encompassing cleft lip and palate, facial malformations, and abnormalities in the flat bones forming the top of the skull. Craniosynostosis involves the premature fusion of the skull bones at sutures, fibrous structures that join the bones. During normal development, cranial sutures hold bones of the skull in place while providing malleability required during childbirth. Cranial sutures also contain stem cells that allow for continued skull bone growth as the brain and head structure expands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Zhao et al., 2015</xref>). While human skull bones eventually fuse later in life, precocious bone fusion in craniosynostosis correlates with region-specific defects in bone growth that often negatively impact growth of the underlying brain. Genetic causes of craniosynostosis include mutations in genes that participate in developmental signaling pathways, including <italic>FGFR</italic>s <italic>1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, and <italic>3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Hajihosseini, 2008</xref>), <italic>TGFBR</italic>s <italic>1</italic> and <italic>2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Loeys et al., 2005</xref>), and the Notch ligand <italic>JAGGED1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kamath et al., 2002</xref>). A central unanswered question is the extent to which defects in these pathways result in a failure to maintain postnatal stem cells once the sutures have formed, or whether these pathways have roles in the specification and maintenance of bone progenitors during earlier phases of bone growth preceding suture formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Flaherty et al., 2016</xref>). Most studies have focused on the maintenance of postnatal sutural stem cells, as these stem cells have only been recently marked with a variety of reporters in mice, for example based on <italic>Gli1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Zhao et al., 2015</xref>), <italic>Axin2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Maruyama et al., 2016</xref>), and <italic>Prrx1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wilk et al., 2017</xref>). Less is known, however, about how potential defects in the embryonic progenitors that grow the skull bones may prefigure suture loss, although a few reports describe altered bone formation during embryonic stages in craniosynostosis mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Merrill et al., 2006</xref>). The ex utero development and transparency of zebrafish provide a unique opportunity to track the progenitors that form the skull bones, and to better understand how defects in the dynamics of bone growth relate to a later ability to form and maintain sutures once the bones come together (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Quarto and Longaker, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Laue et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kague et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Topczewska et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>A striking feature of many forms of craniosynostosis is that only particular sutures are affected. For example, in Saethre-Chotzen syndrome, the second most common form of craniosynostosis, the coronal suture is selectively lost. The majority of Saethre-Chotzen patients harbor heterozygous loss-of-function mutations in <italic>TWIST1</italic> or <italic>TCF12</italic>, which encode basic helix-loop-helix transcription factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">el Ghouzzi et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Howard et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Sharma et al., 2013</xref>). Similarly, mice lacking one copy of <italic>Twist1</italic>, or compound heterozygous for <italic>Twist1</italic> and <italic>Tcf12</italic>, display loss of just the coronal suture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Sharma et al., 2013</xref>). Analysis of mouse models has led to an appreciation of proper cell migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Yoshida et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Ting et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Roybal et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Deckelbaum et al., 2012</xref>), segregation of osteogenic and non-osteogenic cells at the sutural boundary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Merrill et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Ting et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Yen et al., 2010</xref>), and maintenance of postnatal stem cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Zhao et al., 2015</xref>) in suture patency. However, it remains unknown the extent to which defects in early progenitors versus postnatal stem cells account for suture loss. As fish are amenable to repeated live imaging of calvarial bone growth and suture development outside the mother, this model provides an opportunity to correlate early defects in osteoprogenitors and bone growth with later suture loss in individual mutants, particularly in cases where the synostosis phenotype is variably penetrant. However, a potential complication is that the coronal suture of zebrafish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kague et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Mongera et al., 2013</xref>), as well as those of some amphibians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Piekarski et al., 2014</xref>) and birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Matsuoka et al., 2005</xref>), forms at a mesoderm/mesoderm boundary, contrasting with the mammalian coronal suture that forms at a unique interface between the neural-crest-derived frontal bone and the mesoderm-derived parietal bone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Ishii et al., 2015</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). Mammalian sutures may therefore not be considered evolutionarily homologous to the sutures of these other vertebrates, at least from a strict embryological perspective. Should the neural-crest/mesoderm boundary be a factor in coronal sensitivity, non-mammalian coronal sutures might not be susceptible to the same genetic perturbations that cause coronal-specific synostosis in mammals.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.003</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Coronal suture loss in <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutant zebrafish.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Diagrams of zebrafish, mouse, and human skulls, with neural crest contributions in turquoise and mesoderm contributions in gold. The coronal suture is at a mesoderm-mesoderm boundary in zebrafish and a neural-crest-mesoderm boundary in mouse and human. Instead of a suture, an epiphyseal bar cartilage (eb) is present at the neural-crest-mesoderm boundary in zebrafish. ms, metopic suture; ss, sagittal suture. (<bold>B</bold>) Dissected skullcaps of adult fish stained with Alizarin Red show loss of the coronal suture (asterisks) in <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> double mutants but not single mutants. Scale bar, 1 mm. (<bold>C</bold>) Micro-CT scans of adult fish heads show unilateral (left) and bilateral (right) coronal suture loss in <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> mutants. Shading indicates bone derived from neural crest (turquoise) and mesoderm (gold). Panels below are digital sections through the coronal sutures indicated by the dotted lines above. Arrowhead indicates the wild-type suture. (<bold>D</bold>) Hematoxylin and eosin-stained sections show loss of the coronal suture mesenchyme (arrowhead) in <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> mutants. Scale bar, 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Zebrafish TALEN mutants.</title><p>The sites of nucleotide changes induced by TALEN cleavage are shown for each mutant allele. Schematics show the predicted protein truncations caused by the frame-shift mutations, relative to the DNA-binding basic helix-loop-helix domain (HLH, purple).</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig1-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.005</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Patent sutures in <italic>tcf12</italic> single mutants.</title><p>Skull bones of an adult <italic>tcf12</italic><sup>-/-</sup> fish were stained with Alizarin Red. Scale bar, 1 mm. Sections of the coronal suture (cs) and sagittal suture (ss) were stained with hematoxylin and eosin to show presence of suture mesenchyme. Scale bar, 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig1-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.006</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Zebrafish skull phenotypes in different mutant combinations.</title><p>Dorsal views of adult zebrafish skull bones stained with Alizarin Red. We observed coronal suture loss (asterisks) in <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> mutants of any <italic>twist1a</italic> genotype (<bold>D–F</bold>). Animals lacking both Twist1 homologs occasionally develop ectopic sutures (arrows) in the anterior frontal bone region (B,C, enlarged in F). We also occasionally observed gaps (arrowhead, (<bold>D</bold>) and ectopic sutures (arrows, enlarged in G) in the posterior region of the parietal bone. Scale bars, 1 mm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig1-figsupp3-v1"/></fig></fig-group><p>We report in this study the generation of a zebrafish model of Saethre-Chotzen syndrome that faithfully recapitulates the craniosynostosis phenotype seen in mice and humans with heterozygous mutations in <italic>TCF12</italic> and <italic>TWIST1</italic>. The similarity in the genetic interaction between Twist1 and Tcf12 in mice, humans, and fish, despite differences in the cell lineages that give rise to the bones, suggests that the underlying processes of coronal suture development and craniosynostosis are deeply conserved. We demonstrate that in <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutant fish, the frontal and parietal bones grow abnormally. In mutants, skull bones initiate normally, yet early bone growth is accelerated across the skull. However, subsequent bone growth selectively stalls at the future coronal suture that is destined to fuse. Moreover, sequential live imaging of individual mutant fish shows that the degree of later bone stalling predicts which animals will lose the coronal suture. We observe a similar misregulation of bone growth in <italic>Tcf12<sup>+/-</sup>; Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mutant mice, with tissue-specific removal of <italic>Twist1</italic> resulting in selective overgrowth of the frontal or parietal bones. Further, <italic>Twist1</italic> function must be perturbed within both neural crest- and mesoderm-derived bones, and not just the mesoderm-derived postnatal sutural mesenchyme, to prevent suture formation. At least in mice, we find that these altered bone growth dynamics may be due to changes in osteoblast proliferation and eventual depletion of Gli1<sup>+</sup> and Gremlin1<sup>+</sup> putative bone progenitors prior to the fusion of the bones. These findings demonstrate that Tcf12 and Twist1 have a conserved early function during skull bone growth to regulate the sustained production of osteoblasts, possibly through maintenance of osteoprogenitors, and that the coronal suture is particularly sensitive to defects in this process.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Specific loss of the coronal suture in <italic>tcf12</italic>; <italic>twist1b</italic> mutant zebrafish</title><p>In order to investigate requirements for Tcf12 and Twist1 homologs in zebrafish suture formation, we designed TALE nucleases to generate mutant alleles for <italic>tcf12</italic> and both zebrafish Twist1 homologs, <italic>twist1a</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic>. The <italic>tcf12<sup>el548</sup></italic>, <italic>twist1a<sup>el570</sup></italic>, and <italic>twist1b<sup>el571</sup></italic> alleles result in premature truncations before the helix-loop-helix domains required for DNA-binding and dimerization, thus likely abrogating all protein function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>). Whereas individual homozygous mutants displayed no gross defects as embryos or adults and had patent sutures across the head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>), 38% of <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> double mutant adults developed unilateral or bilateral coronal synostosis, as revealed by Alizarin Red staining of bone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). We confirmed loss of the coronal suture by micro-computed tomography scans and histology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C,D</xref>). As in mice and humans, coronal suture loss correlated with reduced anterior-posterior growth of the frontal and parietal bones, and in cases where the suture was lost unilaterally we consistently observed reduced anterior-posterior growth on that side of the skull (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). In contrast, we did not detect a requirement for <italic>twist1a</italic> in suture development; sutures formed normally in <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1a<sup>-/-</sup></italic> mutants, and loss of <italic>twist1a</italic> alleles did not increase the severity or penetrance of suture defects in <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Loss of <italic>tcf12</italic> appears essential for synostosis, as rare adult viable <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> fish had normal sutures. While we only detected fusions of the coronal suture in <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> fish, we did observe other abnormalities in skull bones in different mutant combinations, including ectopic sutures and small gaps between the parietal bones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s3">Figure 1—figure supplement 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>). Our results demonstrate that, as in humans and mice with reduced <italic>TCF12</italic> and/or <italic>TWIST1</italic> dosage, mutations in the homologous genes in zebrafish primarily result in loss of the coronal suture, although other calvarial defects are also rarely observed.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Loss of <italic>tcf12</italic> partially suppresses the embryonic defects and lethality of Twist1 deficiency</title><p>Given the synergistic effect of <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> loss on coronal suture formation, we examined whether <italic>tcf12</italic> also interacts genetically with Twist1 genes in earlier craniofacial development. Similar to previous reports of zebrafish with antisense morpholino reduction of <italic>twist1a</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Das and Crump, 2012</xref>), and mice with neural-crest-specific deletion of <italic>Twist1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bildsoe et al., 2009</xref>), <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> zebrafish embryos displayed defects in the specification of skeletogenic ectomesenchyme from the neural crest. In wild-type embryos, neural crest expression of <italic>sox10</italic> is down-regulated by 20 hr post-fertilization (hpf) as ectomesenchyme neural crest cells populate the pharyngeal arches. In <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> embryos, we observed persistent <italic>sox10</italic> expression in arch ectomesenchyme and reductions in facial cartilage and bone at 5 days post-fertilization (dpf) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A,B</xref>). Dorsal facial cartilages (e.g. palatoquadrate and hyosymplectic) were most affected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata1">Figure 2—source data 1</xref>), potentially reflecting the greater sensitivity of these elements to general neural crest defects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Cox et al., 2012</xref>) and/or post-migratory roles of Twist1 genes in branchial arch development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Askary et al., 2017</xref>). Interestingly, loss of <italic>tcf12</italic> suppressed rather than enhanced the severity of facial skeletal defects in <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> larvae, with partial suppression seen with loss of just one <italic>tcf12</italic> allele (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B,D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata2">Figure 2—source data 2</xref>). The suppression did not appear to be due to a rescue of ectomesenchyme specification, as similarly persistent <italic>sox10</italic> was evident in <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> embryos with or without <italic>tcf12</italic> loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). We also observed that loss of at least one copy of <italic>tcf12</italic> enhanced adult viability of <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata3">Figure 2—source data 3</xref>). These findings indicate temporally distinct genetic interactions between Twist1 and Tcf12, with Tcf12 acting antagonistically to Twist1 during arch development and synergistically during later skull bone growth and suture formation.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.007</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Loss of <italic>tcf12</italic> partially rescues <italic>twist1a; twist1b</italic> jaw cartilage defects and viability.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) In situ hybridizations at 20 hpf show abnormal persistence of <italic>sox10</italic> expression in arch ectomesenchyme (boxed region) in <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> and <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> mutants. Arrowheads indicate persistent <italic>sox10</italic> expression in arches. (<bold>B</bold>) Unilateral dissections of the first and second arch skeletons stained with Alcian Blue (cartilage) and Alizarin Red (bone) at 5 dpf. Compared to the reductions of the upper facial skeleton in <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> mutants, <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> triple mutants display less severe defects. Scale bars, 250 µm. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantitation of wild-type and <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> jaw cartilage areas show specific reductions in more dorsal cartilages, the palatoquadrate (Pq) and hyosympletic (Hs). M, Meckel’s cartilage; Ch, ceratohyal. (<bold>D</bold>) Qualitative scoring of facial skeletal defects from Grade 0 (unaffected) to Grade 4 (most affected). Loss of one or two copies of <italic>tcf12</italic> improved the facial skeletal morphology of <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> mutants. Wild type (wt, <italic>n</italic> = 20), <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> (<italic>12<sup>+/+</sup></italic>, <italic>1a<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 25), <italic>tcf12<sup>+/-</sup>; twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> (<italic>12<sup>+/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1a<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 32), <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> (<italic>12<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1a<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 22). Using a Fisher’s Exact Test, p=0.0032 for <italic>12<sup>+/+</sup></italic>, <italic>1a<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> versus <italic>12<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1a<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> and p=0.001 for <italic>12<sup>+/+</sup></italic>, <italic>1a<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> versus <italic>12<sup>+/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1a<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, <italic>1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic>. (<bold>E</bold>) Reduction of <italic>tcf12</italic> dosage improves adult viability of <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> mutants. From an incross of <italic>tcf12<sup>+/-</sup>; twist1a<sup>+/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>+/- </sup></italic>fish, we obtained <italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b</italic><sup>-/-</sup> mutants and assessed their viability to 3 months of age. After genotyping for <italic>tcf12</italic>, we observed a 4:36:12 ratio of <italic>tcf12<sup>+/+</sup></italic>: <italic>tcf12<sup>+/-</sup></italic>: <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup></italic>, compared to the predicted 13:26:13 ratio, which was significantly skewed as determined by a Chi-squared test (p=0.0062).</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.008</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Cartilage size in <italic>twist1a</italic>;<italic>twist1b </italic>mutants.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig2-data1-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.009</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Severity of cartilage defects in combinatorial Twist1 and Tcf12 mutants.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig2-data2-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig2sdata3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.010</object-id><label>Figure 2—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Adult viability of combinatorial Twist1 and Tcf12 mutants.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig2-data3-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig2-v1"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Expression of <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> at multiple sutures in zebrafish</title><p>Given the selective loss of the coronal suture in mutants, we examined whether <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> genes might be selectively expressed in this suture. However, at a stage when sutures have just formed (14 mm standard length), we observed expression of <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> within the mesenchyme of not only the coronal but also the metopic and sagittal sutures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). Whereas <italic>twist1b</italic> expression was largely restricted to the suture mesenchyme, <italic>tcf12</italic> expression was observed more broadly in the suture mesenchyme and cells surrounding the skull bones. Expression of <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> at multiple sutures in fish is consistent with similarly broad suture expression of <italic>Twist1</italic> in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Rice et al., 2000</xref>) and argues against genetic sensitivity of the coronal suture being due to selective expression of <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> at this suture.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.011</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Expression of <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> in multiple sutures of zebrafish.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic of the zebrafish skull depicting positions of sections (dotted lines) used for RNAscope in situ hybridizations. cs, coronal suture; ms, metopic suture; ss, sagittal suture; fb, frontal bone; pb, parietal bone. (<bold>B–D</bold>) In situ hybridizations on sections taken from zebrafish at 14 mm standard length. Red puncta indicate positive expression. <italic>DapB</italic> (<bold>B</bold>) was included as a negative control, with suture mesenchyme outlined in a dashed white line for reference. Expression of <italic>tcf12</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) and <italic>twist1b</italic> (<bold>D</bold>) was detected in the metopic, coronal and sagittal suture mesenchyme, with <italic>tcf12</italic> also expressed broadly outside the sutures. <italic>n</italic> = 3 for each experiment. Scale bar, 50 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig3-v1"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Altered calvarial bone growth prefigures coronal suture loss in <italic>tcf12</italic>; <italic>twist1b</italic> mutant fish</title><p>We next investigated whether suture defects in <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants might result from an earlier misregulation of skull bone growth, to which the coronal suture might be particularly sensitive. In wild-type zebrafish, the anlage of the frontal and parietal bones can first be seen at 6 mm standard length, with the coronal suture forming at the interface of these bones in a lateral to medial progression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kague et al., 2016</xref>). Live mineralization stains revealed that initiation of the frontal and parietal bones was unaffected in mutants, yet accelerated growth of these bones became detectable in mutants by 8 mm, and more so by 9 mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Staining with the mineralization dye Calcein Green revealed accelerated frontal bone fronts by 10.25 ± 0.25 mm in mutants, with no difference in the degree of increased bone between sides that developed synostosis and those that did not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B,C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata1">Figure 4—source data 1</xref>). Although the overall area of the mutant parietal bone was comparable to that of wild types at 10.25 ± 0.25 mm, both the mutant frontal and parietal bones were aberrantly shaped. In particular, both the frontal and parietal bones exhibited enhanced growth along an axis diagonal to the anterior-posterior and medial-lateral axes, which themselves exhibit little to no changes in directional growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata2">Figure 4—source data 2</xref>). Such enhanced diagonal growth would be expected to bring the frontal and parietal bones closer together at the forming coronal suture, particularly in the medial region most commonly affected in mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). Likewise, the lack of enhanced medial-lateral growth of the parietal bones correlates with the sagittal suture being unaffected in mutants.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.012</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Altered bone growth dynamics precede craniosynostosis in mutant zebrafish.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Dorsal views of the developing skull bones in the same wild-type and mutant individuals across four developmental stages. Live fish were stained with Calcein Green at 6, 7, and 8 mm and Alizarin Red at 9 mm. For the right sides, arrows show initiation of the frontal bone at 6 mm and dashed lines show the frontal (left) and parietal (right) fronts at successive later stages. (<bold>B</bold>) Individual wild-type and <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutant fish were stained with Calcein Green at 10.25 ± 0.25 mm, recovered, and then stained again with Alizarin Red and imaged at 14 ± 0.5 mm. These same fish were then grown to 20 mm, at which stage they were fixed and stained again with Alizarin Red to assess suture patency. White dotted lines indicate bone generated by 10.25 mm. Arrowheads indicate missing coronal suture. Scale bars, 1 mm. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of calvarial bone growth. Bone produced by 10.25 ± 0.25 mm was calculated based on the area (µm) stained with Calcein Green (white outlines in B). At 10.25 mm, compared to control frontal bones (<italic>n</italic> = 12), <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutant frontal bones that developed synostosis later (<italic>n</italic> = 11) and those that did not (<italic>n</italic> = 11) showed similar increases in bone formation. Bone shape was assessed by overlaying tracings of posterior frontal bones and parietal bones for wild types and mutants. Specific growth directionality in the anterior-posterior, medial-lateral, and diagonal axes were measured and quantified (green arrows). (<bold>D</bold>) Bone growth from 10.25 ± 0.25 mm to 14 ± 0.5 mm was analyzed in respect to prospective suture zones. Growth in the metopic (yellow) and sagittal (blue) zones did not differ significantly in controls versus <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants, which correlated with no defects in these sutures in mutants. In contrast, growth in the coronal zone was reduced in <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants, with a more pronounced decrease in mutant sides that later developed synostosis. p values were determined by Student’s t-tests; error bars represent standard error of the mean.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.013</object-id><label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Quantification of skull bone area in mutants by 10.25 mm.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig4-data1-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.014</object-id><label>Figure 4—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Directionality of bone growth in mutants.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig4-data2-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.015</object-id><label>Figure 4—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Quantification of growth in coronal area.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig4-data3-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.016</object-id><label>Figure 4—source data 4.</label><caption><title>Quantification of growth in metopic area.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig4-data4-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig4sdata5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.017</object-id><label>Figure 4—source data 5.</label><caption><title>Quantification of growth in sagittal area.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig4-data5-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig4-v1"/></fig><p>Subsequent sequential staining with Alizarin Red unveiled a marked decrease in bone growth in mutants from 10.25 ± 0.25 to 14 ± 0.5 mm at the future coronal but not the metopic or sagittal sutures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata3">Figure 4—source data 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata4">Figure 4—source data 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig4sdata5">Figure 4—source data 5</xref>). We further took advantage of the variable penetrance of suture defects to correlate the degree of bone stalling with later suture loss in individual <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants. Consistently, synostotic sides exhibited greater reductions in earlier bone growth compared to mutant sides that had patent sutures. Thus, the degree to which the growth of the mutant parietal and frontal bones slows in the coronal zone predicts later loss of this suture. Reciprocally, the absence of bone stalling at the future metopic and sagittal zones is consistent with these sutures being unaffected in mutants.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Altered dynamics of bone front cells in <italic>tcf12</italic>; <italic>twist1b</italic> mutant fish</title><p>We next examined the cellular mechanisms underlying altered bone growth in mutants. Analysis of an <italic>sp7:EGFP</italic> transgenic line, which labels Sp7<sup>+</sup> osteoblasts, revealed accelerated frontal and parietal bone fronts along the diagonal axis in <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants versus sibling controls at 10 mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>), consistent with our analysis using mineralization dyes. We then used BrdU incorporation in combination with anti-Sp7 antibody staining to assess the numbers of proliferative cells at the growing fronts of the frontal and parietal bones at an earlier 9 mm stage. Analysis of Sp7<sup>+</sup> osteoblasts revealed acceleration of frontal and parietal bone growth, with the leading edges of the bones appearing uneven (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>; additional examples in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2</xref>). After digitally extracting the bone fronts to avoid signals from the highly proliferative skin, we quantified the numbers of proliferative cells at the fronts. Along both the mutant frontal and parietal bone fronts, we observed an increase in the percentage of Sp7<sup>+</sup> osteoblasts undergoing proliferation, and a trend toward increased numbers of proliferative Sp7<sup>-</sup> cells just ahead of the bone fronts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B,C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata1">Figure 5—source data 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig5sdata2">Figure 5—source data 2</xref>). These results suggest that increased proliferation of early osteoblasts, and potentially also osteoprogenitors, contribute to the initial acceleration of bone growth across the mutant skull.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.018</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Altered proliferation and osteoblast production at mutant zebrafish bone fronts.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Dissected skullcaps were stained for BrdU (magenta) and Sp7 protein (green) at 9 mm. Top panels show maximum intensity projections of whole skull volumes, and middle panels are the same volumes but processed to extract the bone fronts (note that much of the BrdU staining in the center of the top images is in the skin). Bottom panels show enlarged regions of the osteogenic fronts (dotted rectangles). White arrows show proliferative osteoblasts (BrdU<sup>+</sup>/Sp7<sup>+</sup>) and magenta arrows show adjacent proliferative Sp7<sup>-</sup> cells. fb, frontal bone; pb, parietal bone. Scale bars, 300 µm for whole skull view, 100 µm for enlarged view. (<bold>B, C</bold>) Based on the extracted osteogenic fronts (middle panels in A), we quantified the percentage of Sp7<sup>+</sup> osteoblasts that were BrdU<sup>+</sup> (<bold>B</bold>) and the number of adjacent BrdU<sup>+</sup>/Sp7<sup>-</sup> cells per area (<bold>C</bold>). Wild-type controls, <italic>n</italic> = 20; <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants, <italic>n</italic> = 28. p values were determined by a Student’s t-test; error bars represent standard error of the mean.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.021</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Quantification of proliferative sp7+ osteoblasts in mutant zebrafish.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig5-data1-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig5sdata2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.022</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Quantification of proliferative sp7- cells in mutant zebrafish.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig5-data2-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig5-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.019</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Accelerated bone fronts in <italic>tcf12</italic>; <italic>twist1b</italic> mutants transgenic for <italic>sp7:EGFP</italic>.</title><p>Live imaging of <italic>sp7:EGFP</italic> was performed on wild-type sibling controls (<italic>n</italic> = 11) and <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants (<italic>n</italic> = 7) at 10 mm standard length. Dorsal views of the skull bones showed accelerated and dysmorphic bone fronts in all mutants examined. To the right, bone fronts of individual fish were traced and overlaid according to genotype. Scale bar, 250 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig5-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig5s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.020</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Additional examples of BrdU and Sp7 staining in <italic>tcf12</italic>; <italic>twist1b</italic> mutant zebrafish.</title><p>Dorsal views of 9 mm zebrafish skullcaps stained with Sp7 antibody (green) and BrdU (magenta) show an array of altered bone shapes in mutants compared to wild type. fb, frontal bone; pb, parietal bone.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig5-figsupp2-v1"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Altered calvarial bone growth precedes coronal suture loss in <italic>Tcf12<sup>+/-</sup></italic>; <italic>Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mice</title><p>Given the similarity of coronal suture defects in <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> fish and <italic>Tcf12<sup>+/-</sup>; Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mice, we investigated whether earlier alterations in calvarial bone growth might also prefigure suture loss in mice. At embryonic day (E) 13.5, when skull bone rudiments are first apparent, alkaline phosphatase staining revealed accelerated frontal and parietal bones that were in closer apposition in <italic>Tcf12<sup>+/-</sup>; Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mutants versus wild-type sibling controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). At birth, mutant frontal and parietal bones were more closely apposed than in controls and had abnormal shapes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>). Next, we assessed proliferation rates and osteoblast density at the forming coronal suture (E14.5) and sagittal suture (E16.5) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>, outlined regions of bottom panels). In mutants, we observed thicker bone fronts, as marked by Sp7<sup>+</sup> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig6s1sdata1">Figure 6-figure supplement 1-Source Data 1</xref>), as well as a marked increase in the number of Sp7<sup>+</sup> osteoblasts at the bones fronts predestined for the coronal and sagittal sutures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig6sdata1">Figure 6—source data 1</xref>). We also observed an increase in the number of proliferative Sp7<sup>-</sup> cells immediately adjacent to osteoblasts at the bone fronts, with this increase more evident at the forming coronal versus sagittal suture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig6sdata2">Figure 6—source data 2</xref>). In contrast to fish, we noted a decrease in the number of proliferative osteoblasts at the forming coronal suture, and no change at the forming sagittal suture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6F</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig6sdata3">Figure 6—source data 3</xref>). These findings largely support a conserved role for Tcf12 and Twist1 in negatively regulating the number of proliferative cells at the growing bone fronts in fish and mice.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.023</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Altered bone growth dynamics in <italic>Tcf12<sup>+/-</sup>; Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mice.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Lateral views of E13.5 mouse heads show Alkaline phosphatase staining of developing frontal and parietal bones. Dotted lines indicate the bone fronts that will form the coronal suture. Compared to wild types (<italic>n</italic> = 5), the fronts were accelerated in all <italic>Tcf12<sup>+/-</sup>; Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mutants (<italic>n</italic> = 12). Scale bar, 1 mm. (<bold>B</bold>) Dorsal views of skull bones stained with Alizarin Red at birth (P0). Compared to wild types (<italic>n</italic> = 5), the fronts were closer together in all <italic>Tcf12<sup>+/-</sup>; Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mutants (<italic>n</italic> = 11). Scale bar, 1 mm. (<bold>C</bold>) Sections of E14.5 coronal sutures and E16.5 sagittal sutures stained for BrdU (magenta), Sp7 protein (green), and DAPI (blue, nuclei). Boxed regions are magnified in lower panels, with yellow dotted lines indicating the regions of interest (ROI) used for quantification. fb, frontal bone; pb, parietal bone. Scale bar, 100 µm. (<bold>D–F</bold>) Quantification of Sp7<sup>+</sup> osteoblasts per ROI (<bold>D</bold>), BrdU<sup>+</sup>Sp7<sup>-</sup> bone front cells per ROI (<bold>E</bold>), and the percentage of Sp7<sup>+</sup> osteoblasts that are BrdU<sup>+</sup> in the ROI (<bold>F</bold>). Cell counts were performed at the developing coronal sutures (cs, four wild types, three mutants) and sagittal sutures (ss, six wild types, six mutants). p values were determined by Student’s t-tests; error bars represent standard error of the mean.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.026</object-id><label>Figure 6—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Quantification of Sp7+ osteoblast number in mutant mice.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig6-data1-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6sdata2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.027</object-id><label>Figure 6—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Quantification of proliferative Sp7- cells in mutant mice.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig6-data2-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6sdata3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.028</object-id><label>Figure 6—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Quantification of proliferative Sp7+ osteoblasts in mutant mice.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig6-data3-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig6-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.024</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Increased calvarial bone front thickness in mutants.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Sections of mouse E14.5 coronal sutures and E16.5 sagittal sutures stained for Sp7 protein (green) and DAPI (blue, nuclei) were used to assess bone thickness. Yellow lines indicate thickness measurements used for quantification. fb, frontal bone; pb, parietal bone. Scale bar, 100 µm. (<bold>B</bold>) Bone front thickness of the coronal (four wild types, three mutants) and sagittal sutures (six wild types, six mutants) were quantified. p values were determined by Student’s t-tests; error bars represent standard error of the mean.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig6s1sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.025</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Quantification of calvarial bone front thickness in mutant mice.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig6-figsupp1-data1-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig6-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Selective reduction of the osteoprogenitor pool at the mutant coronal suture</title><p>We next investigated whether the lack of continued bone growth at the mutant coronal fronts might reflect an exhaustion of osteoprogenitor cells. In mouse, sutural stem cells express <italic>Prrx1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wilk et al., 2017</xref>) and <italic>Gli1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Zhao et al., 2015</xref>). <italic>Grem1</italic> also marks skeletal stem cells throughout the animal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Worthley et al., 2015</xref>), yet a role in the skull and sutures has not been previously examined. Using RNAscope in situ hybridization technology in zebrafish, we find that <italic>prrx1a</italic> is broadly expressed at the parietal and frontal bone fronts destined for the coronal and sagittal sutures, as well as the periosteum, at 10 mm, and in the sutures and periosteum at adult stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A,B</xref>). The expression of <italic>gli1</italic> and <italic>grem1a</italic> appears more restricted to the growing bone fronts and suture mesenchyme, although we also see more general periosteal expression at earlier stages. In <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants, we still observe cells expressing <italic>gli1</italic>, <italic>grem1a</italic>, and <italic>prrx1a</italic> at the forming coronal and sagittal sutures, as well as within the periosetum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A,B</xref>), with quantitation revealing similar levels of each gene on a per cell basis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig7s1sdata1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1—source data 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig7s1sdata2">Figure 7—figure supplement 1—source data 2</xref>). At the coronal suture, we observed that the mutant frontal and parietal bones were more closely apposed than in stage-matched wild-type siblings, which could possibly be a consequence of depleted progenitors at the bone fronts. In adult mutants with fused coronal sutures, we failed to detect <italic>gli1</italic><sup>+</sup>, <italic>grem1a</italic><sup>+</sup>, or <italic>prrx1a</italic><sup>+</sup> cells in the coronal suture region, whereas <italic>prrx1a</italic> was still expressed in the periosteum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). Normal expression of all three markers was observed at the patent sagittal suture. We also examined Fgf signaling in zebrafish mutants, as the expression of <italic>Fgfr2</italic> has been reported to be altered in mouse <italic>Twist1</italic> heterozygous animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Rice et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Connerney et al., 2006</xref>). As with <italic>gli1</italic>, <italic>grem1a</italic>, and <italic>prrx1a</italic>, we still observed cells expressing <italic>fgfr2</italic> and the Fgf target gene <italic>dusp6</italic> at the mutant coronal suture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig7s1sdata3">Figure 7—figure supplement 1—source data 3</xref>), arguing against the calvarial phenotypes being due to wholesale loss of Fgfr2 signaling at the bone fronts.</p><fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.029</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Reduced osteoprogenitor pool at the mutant coronal suture.</title><p>(<bold>A, B</bold>) Sections of forming coronal and sagittal sutures of 10 mm fish and fully formed sutures of adult fish were assessed for <italic>gli1</italic>, <italic>grem1a</italic>, and <italic>prrx1a</italic> mRNA expression (white) by RNAscope in situ hybridization. Orange dotted lines indicate bones, and the boxed regions of the coronal suture regions are magnified below. For adult sutures, yellow arrowheads show expression in the suture mesenchyme, yellow arrows show expression of <italic>prrx1a</italic> in the periosteum, and grew arrows show lack of expression of <italic>gli1</italic> and <italic>grem1a</italic> in the periosteum. Scale bar at 10 mm stage, 20 µm; scale bar at adult stage, 50 µm. (<bold>C, D</bold>) Sections of E14.5 coronal sutures and E16.5 forming sagittal sutures of mice stained for Gli1/Grem1 (magenta) and Sp7 protein (green). Yellow arrowheads indicate progenitor regions in forming coronal sutures. Boxed regions of parietal bone fronts in the forming sagittal sutures are magnified in lower panels. Nuclei are stained blue by DAPI in all images. Scale bars, 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig7-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.030</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Quantification of progenitor marker and Fgf pathway transcripts in <italic>tcf12</italic>; <italic>twist1b</italic> mutants.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The number of <italic>gli1</italic>, <italic>grem1a</italic>, and <italic>prrx1a</italic> transcripts at the forming coronal and sagittal suture regions were quantified per region area (between the bone fronts in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). Although the progenitor regions expressing these genes were reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>), no significant difference in transcript levels were observed in equivalent areas of remaining progenitors between wild types (<italic>n</italic> = 4) and <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants (<italic>n</italic> = 4, with the exception of <italic>n</italic> = 2 mutants for <italic>prrx1a</italic> transcripts). p values were determined by Student’s t-tests; error bars represent standard error of the mean. (<bold>B</bold>) RNAscope in situ hybridizations show <italic>fgfr2</italic> and <italic>dusp6</italic> transcripts (white dots) relative to all nuclei (DAPI, blue) at the forming coronal sutures of 10 mm standard length fish. Orange dotted lines indicate bones and magenta dotted lines the forming suture region in which <italic>fgfr2</italic> and <italic>dusp6</italic> transcripts were quantified. Although coronal progenitor regions expressing <italic>fgfr2</italic> and <italic>dusp6</italic> were reduced, these genes were expressed at similar levels per area of progenitor regions in wild types (<italic>n</italic> = 5) and <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutants (<italic>n</italic> = 5). p values were determined by Student’s t-tests; error bars represent standard error of the mean. Scale bar, 20 µm.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7s1sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.031</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Quantification of <italic>gli1</italic>,<italic>grem1a</italic>, and <italic>prrx1a </italic>transcripts in coronal suture region of mutant fish.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig7-figsupp1-data1-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7s1sdata2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.032</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Quantification of <italic>gli1</italic>,<italic>grem1a</italic>, and <italic>prrx1a </italic>transcripts in sagittal suture region of mutant fish.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig7-figsupp1-data2-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="fig7s1sdata3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.033</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Quantification of <italic>fgfr2 </italic>and <italic>dusp6 </italic>transcripts in coronal suture region of mutant fish.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig7-figsupp1-data3-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig7-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group><p>Given the difficulty in quantitating the numbers of osteoprogenitors at the forming coronal suture zone of mutant zebrafish, owing in part to the small sizes of these bone fronts, we also examined putative progenitors in mutant mice. As in zebrafish, we observed cells expressing Gli1 and Grem1 protein at and around the fronts of the embryonic frontal and parietal bones. In <italic>Tcf12<sup>+/-</sup>; Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mice, we observed a marked reduction in the number of Gli1<sup>+</sup> and Grem1<sup>+</sup> putative progenitors at and around the developing coronal but not the sagittal bone fronts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7C,D</xref>). These findings highlight a conserved molecular signature of putative osteoprogenitors and sutural stem cells of zebrafish and mice and suggest, at least in mice, a selective exhaustion of osteoprogenitors at the developing coronal suture.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Tissue-specific roles for Twist1 in calvarial bone growth and suture patency</title><p>To investigate whether Twist1 functions tissue-intrinsically for proper skull bone growth, we took advantage of the unique germ-layer origins of the mammalian frontal and parietal bones to remove one copy of <italic>Twist1</italic> in each tissue. At postnatal day (P) 21, we found that reduced dosage of <italic>Twist1</italic> in the neural-crest-derived precursors of the frontal bone, in <italic>Wnt1-Cre;</italic> Twist1<italic><sup>flox/+</sup></italic> mice, resulted in the overgrowth of the frontal bone relative to the parietal bone, which we quantified by measuring the ratio of the sagittal to metopic suture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig8sdata1">Figure 8—source data 1</xref>). Reciprocally, removing one copy of <italic>Twist1</italic> from the mesoderm-derived parietal bone, in <italic>Mesp1-Cre;</italic> Twist1<italic><sup>flox/+</sup></italic> mice, resulted in its overgrowth relative to the frontal bone. Reduced dosage of <italic>Twist1</italic> in both the neural crest and mesoderm, in <italic>Wnt1-Cre; Mesp1-Cre; Twist1<sup>flox/+</sup></italic> mice, normalized the relative sizes of the frontal and parietal bones and resulted in loss of the coronal suture, a phenotype not seen upon deletion of <italic>Twist1</italic> in neural crest or mesoderm alone. We conclude that Twist1 negatively regulates bone growth in both the neural-crest- and mesoderm-derived portions of the skull, and that <italic>Twist1</italic> must be mutated in not only the mesoderm-derived parietal bone and suture mesenchyme, but also the neural-crest-derived frontal bone, to impact coronal suture formation.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.034</object-id><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>Tissue-autonomous bone overgrowth in <italic>Twist1</italic> conditional mutants.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Dorsal views of Alizarin-stained skulls of three-week-old mice. In the accompanying diagrams, turquoise indicates the neural-crest-derived frontal bones and gold the mesoderm-derived parietal bones. The relative lengths of the metopic suture (ms) and sagittal suture (ss) serve as a proxy for bone size. Compared to wild type (<italic>n =</italic> 0/10), <italic>Wnt1-Cre; Twist1<sup>flox/+</sup></italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 0/8), and <italic>Mesp1-Cre; Twist1<sup>flox/+</sup></italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 0/4); <italic>Wnt1-Cre; Mesp1-Cre; Twist1<sup>flox/+</sup></italic> mice (<italic>n</italic> = 2/3) displayed coronal synostosis (arrowhead, average craniosynostosis index of 2.33). Scale bar, 1 mm. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of the relative length of the sagittal over the metopic suture. p values were determined by a one-way ANOVA with post-hoc Tukey-Kramer HSD test; error bars represent standard error of the mean.</p><p><supplementary-material id="fig8sdata1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.035</object-id><label>Figure 8—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Ratio of the sagittal to metopic suture length in mutant mice.</title></caption><media mime-subtype="plain" mimetype="text" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig8-data1-v1.txt"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-37024-fig8-v1"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Discovery of a selective requirement for <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> in coronal suture formation in zebrafish has allowed us to gain a better understanding of the developmental basis of suture loss in Saethre-Chotzen syndrome. The similarity of coronal suture defects from humans to mice to zebrafish is striking, although each species displays unique dosage sensitivities to loss of <italic>TWIST1</italic> and <italic>TCF1</italic>2. In humans, haploinsufficiency of <italic>TWIST1</italic> or <italic>TCF12</italic> can lead to suture loss. In mice, haploinsufficiency of <italic>Twist1</italic> also results in coronal suture loss, yet haploinsufficiency of <italic>Tcf12</italic> does not, despite enhancing the penetrance of suture defects in <italic>Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Sharma et al., 2013</xref>). In zebrafish, only loss of one of two Twist1 homologs (<italic>twist1b</italic>) along with loss of <italic>tcf12</italic> results in suture loss. It remains unclear why humans are more sensitive to Twist1 and Tcf12 dosage than mice and zebrafish, although a similar phenomenon has been observed with other synostosis genes (e.g. <italic>JAG1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Teng et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Repeated live imaging of individual mutant fish revealed a strong correlation between the extent of altered bone growth and later suture loss. Whereas the initiation of the frontal and parietal bones was largely unaffected in mutants, we observed increased proliferation and osteoblast production at the mutant bone fronts in both fish and mice. There were some subtle differences between fish and mice, with larger increases in proliferative osteoblasts in mutant fish than mice, which might reflect species-specific or staging differences. Nonetheless, mutants in both species displayed accelerated growth of both the frontal and parietal bones, which often resulted in abnormal shapes likely due to growth variations along individual bone fronts. In particular, we found that increased diagonal growth in mutants brought the parietal and frontal bones together at the prospective medial regions of the coronal suture much earlier than in wild type animals, which correlates with the medial region of the coronal suture being most commonly fused in mutants. This altered directional growth might be one reason why the coronal suture is preferentially affected in both zebrafish and mouse Twist1/Tcf12 mutants, despite the different origins of the coronal suture in these species.</p><p>Another prominent finding was a lack of continued bone growth at the future coronal but not other sutures in mutants, with the degree of bone stalling predicting synostosis in individuals. We identified <italic>Gli1/gli1</italic> and <italic>Grem1/grem1a</italic> as conserved markers of putative osteoprogenitors in both the growing bone fronts and mature sutures of mice and zebrafish, although both genes display broader expression at early stages of calvarial bone development, including in some periosteal cells. Future lineage tracing experiments should help reveal the extent to which <italic>gli1</italic> in fish and <italic>Grem1/grem1a</italic> in both species mark similar populations of embryonic osteoprogenitors and postnatal sutural stem cells. A previous study had observed reduced expression of <italic>Gli1</italic> in the sutures of adult <italic>Twist1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Zhao et al., 2015</xref>). Here, we extend this finding to embryonic stages when the coronal suture is forming, and uncover the existence of Grem1+ cells in and around the bone fronts of the nascent coronal suture that become depleted in mutant mice. Whether similar osteoprogenitors become exhausted at the developing coronal suture of zebrafish remains to be determined, as it was difficult to precisely quantify the numbers of these progenitors by RNA expression alone. One possibility is that reduced Twist1 and Tcf12 function alters the balance between long-term sutural stem cells (i.e. those marked by <italic>Gli1</italic>) and proliferative osteoblasts and their immediate progenitors. In such a model, the early increase in osteoblast production would come at the expense of long-term progenitors, thus leading to a later failure of continued bone growth and a loss of the sutural stem cells that would normally separate the skull bones. In addition to further verifying this model, an important next step will be to determine why the fronts of the parietal and frontal bones abutting the future coronal suture are most sensitive to progenitor exhaustion in mutants. We did not observe preferential expression of <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> at the coronal suture in fish, consistent with similarly broad sutural expression of <italic>Twist1</italic> in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Rice et al., 2000</xref>). Instead, osteoprogenitors in the coronal zone could be fewer in number at initial stages and/or more sensitive to loss of Tcf12 and Twist1, for example due to compensation by related genes at other sutures.</p><p>Further support for suture defects arising from much earlier changes in bone growth come from our conditional <italic>Twist1</italic> deletion experiments in mouse. Whereas the frontal bone arises from neural crest and the parietal bone from mesoderm, the mesenchyme within the postnatal coronal suture is largely mesoderm-derived (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Yen et al., 2010</xref>). However, suture loss was only observed upon conditional deletion of one allele of <italic>Twist1</italic> from both the embryonic mesoderm and neural crest. This finding is inconsistent with Twist1 functioning solely in the mesoderm-derived postnatal suture mesenchyme for suture patency, instead suggesting that misregulated growth of both the frontal and parietal bones is required to later disrupt the coronal suture in <italic>Twist1</italic> mutants.</p><p>Our study highlights a selective role for Tcf12 in the later growth of the skull bones and patency of the coronal suture. In contrast to animals lacking Twist1 homologs, zebrafish lacking <italic>tcf12</italic> do not display embryonic lethality or defects in ectomesenchyme and facial cartilage formation. Instead, loss of <italic>tcf12</italic> partially suppresses the facial cartilage defects and lethality of <italic>twist1a; twist1b</italic> mutants. Suppression of embryonic defects could be due to loss of competition of Tcf12 with other Twist binding partners, such as Hand2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Firulli et al., 2005</xref>). In this scenario, maternal Twist1a/b and/or other Twist family members (e.g. <italic>twist2</italic> and <italic>twist3</italic>) could compensate for lack of zygotic Twist1a/b. Loss of <italic>tcf12</italic> would then allow remaining Twist proteins to more effectively form homodimers or alternate heterodimers important for embryogenesis. Whereas a previous report indicates that Tcf12 and Twist1 can form heterodimers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Connerney et al., 2006</xref>), it is also possible that Tcf12 has Twist1-independent functions that antagonize Twist1 during embryogenesis. Future efforts to directly visualize Tcf12-Twist1 complexes will help to resolve how Tcf12 promotes Twist1 function during skull bone growth while counteracting it during embryonic neural crest development.</p><p>Development of homologous structures often employs ancestrally conserved gene regulatory networks. For example, a requirement for Pax6 genes in eye development in a wide range of animals has been used to argue for deep homology of eye structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Gehring and Ikeo, 1999</xref>). Here, we show remarkably specific loss of a single anatomical structure, the coronal suture, in zebrafish and mice lacking Tcf12 and Twist1, despite this suture occurring at a mesoderm/mesoderm interface in zebrafish and a neural-crest/mesoderm interface in mice. Hence, sensitivity of the coronal suture in Saethre-Chotzen syndrome is unlikely to be due to its location at a unique neural-crest/mesoderm interface. In addition, there are several other sutures occurring at a neural-crest/mesoderm interface in mice and fish that are not affected by loss of Tcf12 and Twist1. There has been on-going debate, given these distinct tissue boundaries, as to whether coronal sutures are truly homologous across vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Maddin et al., 2016</xref>). Our data indicate that the conserved genetic dependence of the coronal suture in fish and mammals likely reflects a similar sensitivity to early bone growth changes, perhaps owing to similar developmental and anatomical constraints irrespective of the embryonic origins of the bones flanking this suture.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Key resources table</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Reagent type <break/>(species) <break/>or resource</th><th>Designation</th><th>Source or reference</th><th>Identifiers</th><th>Additional information</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td><italic>sp7:EGFP</italic></td><td>PMID: 20506187</td><td><break/><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zfin.org/ZDB-GENO-100402-2">RRID: ZFIN_ZDB-GENO-100402-2</ext-link></td><td>Zebrafish International <break/>Resource Center</td></tr><tr><td> genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td><italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup></italic></td><td>this paper</td><td/><td>allele <italic>el548</italic>; see <break/><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td><italic>twist1a<sup>-/-</sup></italic></td><td>this paper</td><td/><td>allele <italic>el571</italic>; see <break/><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>)</td><td><italic>twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic></td><td>this paper</td><td/><td>allele <italic>el570</italic>; see <break/><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>M. musculus</italic>)</td><td><italic>Tcf12<sup>-/-</sup></italic></td><td>PMID: 23354436</td><td/><td>Dr. Robert Maxson <break/>(University of Southern <break/>California)</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>M. musculus</italic>)</td><td><italic>Twist1<sup>-/-</sup></italic></td><td>PMID: 7729687</td><td><break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/IMSR_JAX:002221">IMSR_JAX:002221</ext-link></td><td>Dr. Richard Behringer <break/>(University of Texas, M. D. <break/>Anderson Cancer Center)</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>M. musculus</italic>)</td><td><italic>Twist1<sup>flox</sup></italic></td><td>PMID: 19414008</td><td><break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/MMRRC_016842-UNC">MMRRC_016842-UNC</ext-link></td><td>Dr. Patrick Tam (Children's <break/>Medical Research Institute, <break/>The University of Sydney)</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>M. musculus</italic>)</td><td><italic>Wnt1-Cre</italic></td><td>PMID: 9843687</td><td><break/>RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/IMSR_JAX:003829">IMSR_JAX:003829</ext-link></td><td>Dr. Henry Sucov <break/>(University of Southern <break/>California)</td></tr><tr><td>Genetic reagent <break/>(<italic>M. musculus</italic>)</td><td><italic>Mesp1-Cre</italic></td><td>PMID: 10393122</td><td/><td>Dr. Sachicko Iseki <break/>(Tokyo Medical and <break/>Dental University)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>rabbit anti-Osx/Sp7</td><td>Santa Cruz <break/>Biotechnology</td><td>cat.#: sc-22536-r; <break/>RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_831618">AB_831618</ext-link></td><td>(1:300)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>rat anti-BrdU</td><td>Bio-Rad Laboratories</td><td>cat.#: MCA2060 GA; <break/>RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_10545551">AB_10545551</ext-link></td><td>(1:100–150)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>goat anti-Grem1</td><td>Thermo Fisher <break/>Scientific</td><td>cat.#: PA5-47973; <break/>RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2610125">AB_2610125</ext-link></td><td>(1:40)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>goat anti-Gli1</td><td>R and D Systems</td><td>cat.#: AF3455; <break/>RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2247710">AB_2247710</ext-link></td><td>(1:40)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>goat anti-rat FITC</td><td>Santa Cruz <break/>Biotechnology</td><td>cat.#: sc-2011; <break/>RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_631753">AB_631753</ext-link></td><td>(1:200)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>goat anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor 568</td><td>Thermo Fisher <break/>Scientific</td><td>cat.#: A-11011; <break/>RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_143157">AB_143157</ext-link></td><td>(1:200–500)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>donkey anti-goat Alexa Fluor 488</td><td>Abcam</td><td>cat.#: ab150129; <break/>RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2687506">AB_2687506</ext-link></td><td>(1:200)</td></tr><tr><td>Antibody</td><td>goat anti-rat Alexa Fluor 633</td><td>Thermo Fisher <break/>Scientific</td><td>cat.#: A21094; <break/>RRID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/AB_2535749">AB_2535749</ext-link></td><td>(1:500)</td></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>RNAscope Probe - Dr-tcf12-C2</td><td>Advanced Cell <break/>Diagnostics</td><td>cat.#: 517031-C2</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>RNAscope Probe - Dr-twist1b</td><td>Advanced Cell <break/>Diagnostics</td><td>cat.#: 413121</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>RNAscope Probe - Dr-gli1-C3</td><td>Advanced Cell <break/>Diagnostics</td><td>(not yet in catalog)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>RNAscope Probe - Dr-grem1a</td><td>Advanced Cell <break/>Diagnostics</td><td>cat.#: 535291</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>RNAscope Probe - Dr-prrx1a</td><td>Advanced Cell <break/>Diagnostics</td><td>cat.#: 535321</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>RNAscope Probe - Dr-fgfr2</td><td>Advanced Cell <break/>Diagnostics</td><td>cat.#: 420961</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Sequence-based <break/>reagent</td><td>RNAscope Probe - Dr-dusp6-C3</td><td>Advanced Cell <break/>Diagnostics</td><td>cat.#: 515021-C3</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay <break/>or kit</td><td>RNAscope 2.5 HD Assay – RED</td><td>Advanced Cell <break/>Diagnostics</td><td>cat.#: 322350</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Commercial assay <break/>or kit</td><td>RNAscope Multiplex Fluorescent Kit v2</td><td>Advanced Cell <break/>Diagnostics</td><td>cat.#: 323110</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, <break/>drug</td><td>Alizarin Red S</td><td>Amresco</td><td>cat.#: 9436–25G</td><td>live staining: 1 mg / 30 mL</td></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, <break/>drug</td><td>Calcein</td><td>Thermo Fisher <break/>Scientific</td><td>cat.#: C481</td><td>live staining: 1 mg / 10 mL</td></tr><tr><td>Chemical compound, <break/>drug</td><td>Alcian Blue</td><td>Anatech LTD</td><td>cat.#: 862</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s4-1"><title>Experimental model and subject details</title><sec id="s4-1-1"><title>Animals</title><p>The University of Southern California Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee approved all animal experiments, and all methods were performed in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations. Zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) embryos were raised in Embryo Medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Westerfield, 2007</xref>) at 28.5°C. Juvenile and adult fish were housed in groups of 10–15. Mutant lines were maintained on a mixed Tubingen wild-type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Haffter et al., 1996</xref>), <italic>casper</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">White et al., 2008</xref>), and <italic>sp7:EGFP</italic> background. Three targeted mutant lines (<italic>tcf12<sup>el548</sup></italic>, <italic>twist1a<sup>el571</sup></italic>, and <italic>twist1b<sup>el570</sup></italic>) were generated for this study (see below). Lines were propagated by genotyping fin biopsies. As we found that <italic>twist1a</italic> loss did not effect the penetrance or expressivity of suture loss in <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> fish (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>), we pooled <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> fish with any <italic>twist1a</italic> genotype for the experiments. Mice (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>) were housed in cages with no more than five adults or three adults with one litter per cage. The <italic>Tcf12</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Wojciechowski et al., 2007</xref>)<italic>, Twist1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Chen and Behringer, 1995</xref>), conditional <italic>Twist1</italic>-flox (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bildsoe et al., 2009</xref>), <italic>Wnt1-cre</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Danielian et al., 1998</xref>), and <italic>Mesp1-cre</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Saga et al., 1999</xref>) alleles were genotyped as described.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Method details</title><sec id="s4-2-1"><title>Generation of zebrafish mutant lines</title><p>Zebrafish mutant for <italic>tcf12</italic>, <italic>twist1a</italic>, or <italic>twist1b</italic> were generated with TALEN-based targeted mutagenesis. TALEN constructs were generated using the PCR-based platform (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Sanjana et al., 2012</xref>) and digested with StuI (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA). RNAs were synthesized from linearized constructs using the mMessage mMachine T7 Ultra kit (Ambion/Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA). TALEN RNAs were injected at 100 ng/μl into 1<bold>-</bold>cell-stage embryos, and we identified mosaic germline founders by sequencing their progeny. The <italic>tcf12<sup>el548</sup></italic> allele includes base pair changes and insertions that disrupt a common exon shared in all protein-coding transcript variants. The <italic>twist1a<sup>el571</sup></italic> and <italic>twist1b<sup>el570</sup></italic> alleles are deletions that interrupt the coding sequence close to the translation start site. All three alleles are frame-shift mutations that result in premature stop codons upstream of the helix-loop-helix DNA-binding domains. Detailed sequences of TALEN targets and genotyping primers are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp2">Supplementary file 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-2"><title>Skull preparations</title><p>Adult zebrafish were fixed overnight at 4°C with 4% paraformaldehyde, washed with 0.5% KOH for at least half an hour, cleared with 3% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in 0.5% KOH for several hours until pigmentation was removed, washed with 35% NaBO<sub>4</sub> for at least half an hour, incubated with 1% trypsin in 35% NaBO<sub>4</sub> for several hours until tissue was reasonably cleared, washed with 10% glycerol in 0.5% KOH for at least one hour, stained with 0.02% Alizarin Red S (Amresco 9436) pH 7.5 in 10% glycerol and 0.5% KOH overnight, washed with 50% glycerol/0.5% KOH until residual stain was removed, and stored in 100% glycerol. Skullcaps were dissected and imaged using a Leica S8 APO stereomicroscope.</p><p>The heads of newborn mice were skinned and cleared with 1% KOH for 1 to 2 days, stained with 2% Alizarin Red S in 1% KOH until mineralized bone was red, and stored in 100% glycerol. Mouse skulls were imaged using a Leica MZ125 stereomicroscope.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-3"><title>Micro-computed tomography</title><p>Data was collected on a Nikon Metrology Xt S 225 ST with the following parameters: energy at 120kV; current at 26 uA; 3141 projections at two frames/sec and averaging two frames; no filter; and at 6 μm resolution. Two-dimensional slices were rendered into three-dimensional reconstructions using Arivis (Phoenix, AZ).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-4"><title>Paraffin embedding, sectioning, and tissue histology</title><p>Whole zebrafish were embedded into paraffin according to standard protocol. Briefly, fish heads were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde at 4°C or 10% neutral buffered formalin at room temperature overnight, washed with PBS for half an hour each time, and then separated into heads and trunks. Heads were decalcified with 20% EDTA pH 8.0 for 10 days at room temperature, washed with DEPC-treated water, dehydrated through a series of sequentially increasing ethanol to DEPC water ratios, treated through a series of sequentially increasing Hemo-De (xylene substitute) to ethanol ratios, washed in 50% paraffin in Hemo-De at 65°C for one hour, incubated at 65°C in 100% paraffin overnight, embedded in paraffin in molds, and allowed to solidify at room temperature. Paraffin blocks were cut into 5 μm sections using a Shandon Finesse Me + microtome (cat no. 77500102) and collected on superfrost plus slides (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</p><p>For tissue histology, hematoxylin and eosin staining was performed according to standard protocol. Briefly, sections were deparaffinized in xylene and ethanol, rinsed in water, stained with hematoxylin, rinsed in 4% glacial acetic acid, rinsed with water, washed with blueing solution, rinsed with water, dried with ethanol, stained with eosin, washed with ethanol and Hemo-De, and mounted with cytoseal.</p><p>For whole-mount alkaline phosphatase staining, E13.5 mouse heads were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS, bisected mid-sagitally after fixation, and stained with NBT and BCIP. Sections were imaged on a Leica DM2500 compound microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-5"><title>In situ hybridization</title><p>Colorimetric <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization using a <italic>sox10</italic> digoxigenin-labeled riboprobe was performed on 20 hpf zebrafish embryos as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Cox et al., 2012</xref>). Briefly, embryos were fixed, dehydrated with an increasing methanol series, and stored in 100% methanol at −20°C until use. Embryos were then rehydrated with a decreasing methanol series, treated with 1 μg/ml Proteinase K for 6.6 min, post-fixed with 4% PFA, incubated with hybridization buffer (50% formamide, 5X SSC, 100 μg/ml yeast RNA, 50 μg/ml heparin, 0.125% Tween-20, citric acid to pH 6), hybridized with probe, washed with solution series with decreasing formamide and SSC, incubated in blocking solution (5 mg/ml BSA, 5% sheep serum), treated with sheep digoxigenin-AP at 1:10,000, stained with NBT and BCIP (Roche), and color was allowed to develop for two and a half hours. Stained embryos were imaged on a Leica DM2500 compound microscope. RNAscope in situ hybridization was performed with the RNAscope 2.5 HD Assay – RED (Advanced Cell Diagnostics, Newark, CA) or the RNAscope Multiplex Fluorescent Kit v2 (Advanced Cell Diagnostics, Newark, CA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol for formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded sections. Probes include <italic>twist1b</italic> (C1), <italic>tcf12</italic> (C2), <italic>prrx1a</italic> (C1), <italic>grem1a</italic> (C1), <italic>gli1</italic> (C3), <italic>fgfr2</italic> (C1), and <italic>dusp6</italic> (C3).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-6"><title>Zebrafish larvae skeletal staining</title><p>Alcian Blue (cartilage) and Alizarin Red S (bone) staining was performed on 5 dpf zebrafish larvae as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Walker and Kimmel, 2007</xref>). Briefly, larvae were fixed for one hour in 2% paraformaldehyde, rinsed in 100 mM Tris pH 7.5 in 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, incubated overnight in Alcian Blue solution (0.04% Alcian Blue, 80% ethanol, 100 mM Tris pH 7.5, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>), rehydrated through a sequentially decreasing series of ethanol to 100 mM Tris pH 7.5 and 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> ratio, bleached with 3% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in 0.5% KOH under a lamp, washed with 25% glycerol in 0.1% KOH, stained with Alizarin Red S (0.01% Alizarin Red, 25% glycerol, 100 mM Tris pH 7.5), and de-stained with 50% glycerol in 0.1% KOH. Dissected jaw cartilages were mounted in 50% glycerol on a slide and imaged with a Leica DM2500 compound microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-7"><title>Sequential live staining and imaging</title><p>Fish were anesthetized, measured for body length, and recovered in Calcein Green stain (3 mg/30 ml, Molecular Probes C481) overnight in the dark. The following day, fish were washed in fish system water at least twice for one hour each time before imaging with a Zeiss AxioZoom microscope and returned to tanks on system. This process was repeated at a later time point with Alizarin Red S (1 mg/30 ml).</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-8"><title>BrdU treatments and immunohistochemistry</title><p>Anesthetized fish were measured for body length and incubated in 4.5 mg/ml BrdU solution (B5002, Sigma Aldrich) for two hours in the dark. Fish were then transferred to fish system water or embryo medium for 15 min before euthanasia. Heads were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde overnight before skullcaps were dissected and stored in PBS at 4°C. For mouse embryos at E14.5 and E16.5, BrdU was injected into the pregnant female (200 μg/g body weight) 2 hr prior to dissection. Heads of embryos were embedded in OCT medium (Histoprep, Fisher Scientific) before sectioning. Frozen sections were cut at 10 μm. Immunohistochemistry was performed using rat anti-BrdU (MCA2060 GA, Bio-Rad), rabbit anti-Osx/Sp7 (sc-22536-r, Santa Cruz), goat anti-Grem1 (PA5-47973, Thermo Fisher), or goat anti-Gli1 (AF3455, R and D Systems) diluted in 1% BSA/PBS and incubated overnight at 4°C. Detection of primary antibodies was performed by incubating goat anti-rat FITC (sc-2011, Santa Cruz), goat anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor 568 (A-11011, Thermo Fisher Scientific), or donkey anti-goat Alexa Fluor 488 (ab150129, Abcam) for 1 hr at room temperature followed by DAPI counterstaining.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2-9"><title>Quantitation and statistical analyses</title><p>Severity of coronal synostosis was quantified using a coronal synostosis scoring index that was adapted from Oram and Gridley’s craniosynostosis index (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Oram and Gridley, 2005</xref>). Left and right sutures were given scores of 0 (no fusion), 1 (&lt;50% fused), 2 (≥50% fused), or 3 (completely fused). A composite score for each animal was calculated by adding the sum of both suture scores. The index value was determined by the sum of composite scores in each genotype group divided by the number of animals in the group.</p><p>The degree of jaw cartilage defect was determined by the number of cartilage elements affected, with more affected equating to a higher grade of severity. Flat-mounted cartilages were measured for area using Fiji.</p><p>Directional bone growth was quantified using Fiji. For bone produced by 10.25 mm and subsequent growth by 14 mm, bone regions were drawn freehand and measured for area. For assessment of BrdU<sup>+</sup> and Sp7<sup>+</sup> cells, tiled z-stacks were captured of stained zebrafish skulls caps using a Zeiss LSM 800. The bone fronts were then digitally extracted using a 30-pt. brush in Amira software, and cells were manually counted in a 3D view on Imaris software. In mouse coronal suture sections, the region of interest was determined by a defined length across the bone fronts and suture. In mouse sagittal suture sections, defined lengths included several cell diameters medial from the last Sp7<sup>+</sup> cell at the bone fronts and accounted for bone curvature. Five sections per animal were quantified and averaged. For bone thickness quantifications, a perpendicular measurement across the broadest point of Sp7+ cells was measured for each section. All measurements and counting were completed in Fiji. For the quantification of RNAscope experiments, regions of interests were defined by the edge of the calvarial bones (imaged by DIC microscopy) in Fiji. The coronal progenitor region was defined as the space between the neighboring frontal and parietal bones, and the sagittal progenitor region was defined as an approximately three-cell layer length region ahead of the parietal bone. RNAscope signal was quantified across a Z-stack projection using the 3D Object Counter tool, and measurements above a pre-defined unit of one transcript were adjusted to account for closely packed transcripts. The final transcript count was normalized to the area of the region of interest. Three sections per animal were averaged for each probe. Unpaired t-tests were performed for all statistical analyses, and all samples were scored blindly.</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Megan Matsutani and Jennifer DeKoeyer Crump for fish care; Seth Ruffins, Director of the Microscopy Core Facility of USC Stem Cell, for assistance in rendering micro-CT reconstructions; and members of the Maxson, Crump, and Yang Chai labs for insightful discussions. This work was supported by NIH grant R01DE026339 to REM and JGC, NIH grant R35DE027550 to JGC, NIH training fellowships F31DE024031 and T90DE021982 to CST, and the Helen Hay Whitney Postdoctoral fellowship to DTF.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Formal analysis, Investigation</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con5"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing—original draft, Writing—review and editing</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con6"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing—original draft, Project administration, Writing—review and editing</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Animal experimentation: This study was performed in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. The University of Southern California Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) approved all animal experiments (protocol #20552), and all methods were performed in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.036</object-id><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Summary of phenotypes observed in combinatorial zebrafish mutants</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-37024-supp1-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.037</object-id><label>Supplementary file 2.</label><caption><title>TALEN targeting and mutant genotyping</title></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-37024-supp2-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.038</object-id><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-37024-transrepform-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material><sec id="s7" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in the manuscript and supporting files.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Askary</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Barske</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bay</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bump</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Balczerski</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonaguidi</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crump</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of facial skeletal regionalization in zebrafish</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>144</volume><fpage>2994</fpage><lpage>3005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.151712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28705894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bildsoe</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Loebel</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Behringer</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Requirement for Twist1 in frontonasal and skull vault development in the mouse embryo</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>331</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2009.04.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19414008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name><surname>Behringer</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>twist is required in head mesenchyme for cranial neural tube morphogenesis</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.9.6.686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7729687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connerney</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreeva</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Leshem</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Muentener</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercado</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Spicer</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Twist1 dimer selection regulates cranial suture patterning and fusion</article-title><source>Developmental Dynamics</source><volume>235</volume><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.20717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16502419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnett</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Medeiros</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Crump</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>An essential role of variant histone H3.3 for ectomesenchyme potential of the cranial neural crest</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e1002938</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23028350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danielian</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Muccino</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowitch</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Modification of gene activity in mouse embryos in utero by a tamoxifen-inducible form of Cre recombinase</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>S2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(07)00562-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crump</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Bmps and id2a act upstream of Twist1 to restrict ectomesenchyme potential of the cranial neural crest</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e1002710</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22589745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deckelbaum</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Basilico</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Loomis</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Regulation of cranial morphogenesis and cell fate at the neural crest-mesoderm boundary by engrailed 1</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>139</volume><fpage>1346</fpage><lpage>1358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.076729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22395741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>el Ghouzzi</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Merrer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin-Schmitt</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lajeunie</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Benit</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Renier</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourgeois</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolcato-Bellemin</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Munnich</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonaventure</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Mutations of the TWIST gene in the Saethre-Chotzen syndrome</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0197-42</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8988167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Firulli</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Krawchuk</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Centonze</surname> <given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargesson</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Virshup</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cserjesi</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Laufer</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Firulli</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Altered Twist1 and Hand2 dimerization is associated with Saethre-Chotzen syndrome and limb abnormalities</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15735646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flaherty</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Richtsmeier</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Understanding craniosynostosis as a growth disorder</article-title><source>Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Developmental Biology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wdev.227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27002187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gehring</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeo</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>Pax 6: mastering eye morphogenesis and eye evolution</article-title><source>Trends in Genetics</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9525(99)01776-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10461206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haffter</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Granato</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullins</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammerschmidt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kane</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Odenthal</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Eeden</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname> <given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Heisenberg</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelsh</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Furutani-Seiki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelsang</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Beuchle</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schach</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabian</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nüsslein-Volhard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>The identification of genes with unique and essential functions in the development of the zebrafish, Danio rerio</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>123</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9007226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hajihosseini</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Fibroblast growth factor signaling in cranial suture development and pathogenesis</article-title><source>Frontiers of Oral Biology</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000115037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18391500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howard</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Paznekas</surname> <given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname> <given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz de Luna</surname> <given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia Delgado</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Ramos</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kline</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabs</surname> <given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Mutations in TWIST, a basic helix-loop-helix transcription factor, in Saethre-Chotzen syndrome</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0197-36</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8988166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishii</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ting</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>The development of the calvarial bones and sutures and the pathophysiology of craniosynostosis</article-title><source>Current Topics in Developmental Biology</source><volume>115</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.ctdb.2015.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26589924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kague</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Franz-Odendaal</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Skeletogenic fate of zebrafish cranial and trunk neural crest</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e47394</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23155370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kague</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Asselin</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonet</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Albertson</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Osterix/Sp7 limits cranial bone initiation sites and is required for formation of sutures</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>413</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2016.03.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26992365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamath</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolle</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bason</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Colliton</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Piccoli</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinner</surname> <given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Krantz</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Craniosynostosis in Alagille syndrome</article-title><source>American Journal of Medical Genetics</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.10608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12244552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laue</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pogoda</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname> <given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>van Haeringen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alanay</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>von Ameln</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachwalski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Breuning</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawyer</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherland-Smith</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikkels</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubisch</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloch</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollnik</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammerschmidt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Craniosynostosis and multiple skeletal anomalies in humans and zebrafish result from a defect in the localized degradation of retinoic acid</article-title><source>The American Journal of Human Genetics</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2011.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22019272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loeys</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Neptune</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Judge</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Podowski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leitch</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsanis</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharifi</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Spevak</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>De Backer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellemans</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Coucke</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rifkin</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>De Paepe</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietz</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>A syndrome of altered cardiovascular, craniofacial, neurocognitive and skeletal development caused by mutations in TGFBR1 or TGFBR2</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15731757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maddin</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Piekarski</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sefton</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanken</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Homology of the cranial vault in birds: new insights based on embryonic fate-mapping and character analysis</article-title><source>Royal Society Open Science</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>160356</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.160356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27853617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maruyama</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheu</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Stem cells of the suture mesenchyme in craniofacial bone development, repair and regeneration</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>10526</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms10526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26830436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlberg</surname> <given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessaris</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Iannarelli</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennehy</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Koentges</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Neural crest origins of the neck and shoulder</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>436</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16034409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merrill</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bochukova</surname> <given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugger</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilz</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkie</surname> <given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Cell mixing at a neural crest-mesoderm boundary and deficient ephrin-Eph signaling in the pathogenesis of craniosynostosis</article-title><source>Human Molecular Genetics</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>1319</fpage><lpage>1328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddl052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16540516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mongera</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Levesque</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Konstantinidis</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nüsslein-Volhard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Genetic lineage labeling in zebrafish uncovers novel neural crest contributions to the head, including gill pillar cells</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>140</volume><fpage>916</fpage><lpage>925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.091066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23362350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oram</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gridley</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Mutations in snail family genes enhance craniosynostosis of Twist1 haplo-insufficient mice: implications for Saethre-Chotzen Syndrome</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>170</volume><fpage>971</fpage><lpage>974</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.105.041277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15802514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piekarski</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanken</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Evolutionary innovation and conservation in the embryonic derivation of the vertebrate skull</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>5661</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms6661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25434971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quarto</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Longaker</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>The zebrafish (Danio rerio): a model system for cranial suture patterning</article-title><source>Cells Tissues Organs</source><volume>181</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000091100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16534205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Aberg</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kettunen</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakarinen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Thesleff</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Integration of FGF and TWIST in calvarial bone and suture development</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>1845</fpage><lpage>1855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10751173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roybal</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ting</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafer</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Inactivation of Msx1 and Msx2 in neural crest reveals an unexpected role in suppressing heterotopic bone formation in the head</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>343</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2010.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20398647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saga</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyagawa-Tomita</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitajima</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year><article-title>MesP1 is expressed in the heart precursor cells and required for the formation of a single heart tube</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>3437</fpage><lpage>3447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10393122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanjana</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cong</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunniff</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>A transcription activator-like effector toolbox for genome engineering</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2011.431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22222791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname> <given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenwick</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockop</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>McGowan</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goos</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogeboom</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeelani</surname> <given-names>NO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulliken</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Phipps</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomkins</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornall</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Broxholme</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanapin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Spek</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathijssen</surname> <given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Twigg</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkie</surname> <given-names>AO</given-names></name><collab>500 Whole-Genome Sequences (WGS500) Consortium</collab></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Mutations in TCF12, encoding a basic helix-loop-helix partner of TWIST1, are a frequent cause of coronal craniosynostosis</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23354436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teng</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Barske</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Llamas</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Segil</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Go</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Lara</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Crump</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Requirement for Jagged1-Notch2 signaling in patterning the bones of the mouse and human middle ear</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>2497</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-02574-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28566723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ting</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roybal</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>EphA4 as an effector of Twist1 in the guidance of osteogenic precursor cells during calvarial bone growth and in craniosynostosis</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>136</volume><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.028605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19201948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Topczewska</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoela</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomaszewski</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirmira</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosain</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>The Morphogenesis of Cranial Sutures in Zebrafish</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e0165775</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0165775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27829009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimmel</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>A two-color acid-free cartilage and bone stain for zebrafish larvae</article-title><source>Biotechnic &amp; Histochemistry</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10520290701333558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17510811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westerfield</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><source>THE ZEBRAFISH BOOK: A Guide for the Laboratory Use of zebrafish(Danio Rerio)</source><publisher-loc>Eugene, OR</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Oregon Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBlanc</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceol</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourque</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dovey</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goessling</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zon</surname> <given-names>LI</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Transparent adult zebrafish as a tool for in vivo transplantation analysis</article-title><source>Cell Stem Cell</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2007.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18371439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilk</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortensen</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghaffarigarakani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardo</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassir</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldawood</surname> <given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Intini</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Postnatal Calvarial Skeletal Stem Cells Expressing PRX1 Reside Exclusively in the Calvarial Sutures and Are Required for Bone Regeneration</article-title><source>Stem Cell Reports</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>933</fpage><lpage>946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stemcr.2017.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wojciechowski</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>E2A and HEB are required to block thymocyte proliferation prior to pre-TCR expression</article-title><source>The Journal of Immunology</source><volume>178</volume><fpage>5717</fpage><lpage>5726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.178.9.5717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17442955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worthley</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Compton</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tailor</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Si</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Uygur</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Renz</surname> <given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Setlik</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nizami</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldwell</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Asfaha</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Westphalen</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagar</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kheirbek</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolhe</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaire</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Renders</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Manieri</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Muthupalani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichert</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraud</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwabe</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pradere</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakash</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumucio</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rustgi</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Stappenbeck</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershon</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sims</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grikscheit</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>FY</given-names></name><name><surname>Karsenty</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Gremlin 1 identifies a skeletal stem cell with bone, cartilage, and reticular stromal potential</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>160</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.11.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25594183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yen</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ting</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxson</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Jagged1 functions downstream of Twist1 in the specification of the coronal suture and the formation of a boundary between osteogenic and non-osteogenic cells</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>347</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2010.08.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20727876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivatbutsiri</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Morriss-Kay</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Saga</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iseki</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Cell lineage in mammalian craniofacial mesenchyme</article-title><source>Mechanisms of Development</source><volume>125</volume><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mod.2008.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18617001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname> <given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimes</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Urata</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>The suture provides a niche for mesenchymal stem cells of craniofacial bones</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>386</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb3139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25799059</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.040</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>Richard M</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</institution><country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for sending your article entitled &quot;Altered progenitor dynamics prefigure craniosynostosis in a zebrafish model of Saethre-Chotzen syndrome&quot; for peer review at <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article is being evaluated by three peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Marianne Bronner as the Senior Editor. The reviewers have opted to remain anonymous.</p><p>We have included the detailed reviews below. All three of the reviewers commend the basic finding that Twist1/Tcf12 is involved in synostosis, and that the zebrafish is therefore a useful model for studying this syndrome. However, at the same time there is a major concern about a lack of a mechanistic explanation for why Tcf12 leads to the defects you have observed. After discussing this with each of the reviewers, our general feeling is that for us to consider proceeding at <italic>eLife</italic>, there would need to be a more compelling mechanistic explanation for the observed effects.</p><p>Based on these serious concerns, I would like to inquire as to whether you have additional mechanistic data that you think would address this.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1:</italic> </p><p>This manuscript from Teng et al. describes the effect of loss of Twist1 and Tcf12 on cranial bone growth and progenitor proliferation in the zebrafish and mouse models. It has been known for some time that heterozygous mutations in <italic>Twist1</italic> result in coronal synostosis in Saethre-Chotzen syndrome in humans and mice, and more recently, has been demonstrated that Tcf12 is a Twist1 binding partner that is also involved in coronal synostosis in humans and mice. Here, the authors demonstrate that as in mice, Twist1 and Tcf12 interact in zebrafish such that <italic>tcf12<sup>-/-</sup>; twist1b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> exhibit coronal synostosis. Using successive bone staining in zebrafish the authors characterize bone growth in these mutants and find that though bone growth is slightly elevated in the earliest phase of formation of the development of the calvarial bones, bone growth is diminished later; these changes correlate with the incidence of synostosis. The number of proliferative osteoprogenitors and osteoblasts is increased in zebrafish, but in mouse only osteoprogenitors have an increased proliferation, though the total number of osteoblasts increases. Finally the authors demonstrate that the craniosynostosis phenotype requires loss of Twist1 from both the parietal and frontal bone. Together, these careful analyses make a compelling case that Twist1 and Tcf12 control bone progenitor cell dynamics to regulate normal growth of the calvaria and prevent craniosynostosis. The zebrafish work suggests that there is nothing unique about the neural crest/mesoderm boundary, but rather suggests that there may be directionality in the way that Twist1/Tcf12 regulate bone growth, though this possibility is not explored and the question of why the coronal suture is specifically synostosed remains uncertain. Nevertheless, these findings advance our understanding of the developmental function of Twist1 and Tcf12 in craniosynostosis in zebrafish and mice and will be of broad interest to the craniofacial development and disease communities. Additionally, these studies validate the zebrafish as a powerful model system for the study of the developmental mechanisms underlying craniosynostosis.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2:</italic> </p><p>The manuscript 'Altered progenitor dynamics prefigure craniosynostosis in a zebrafish model of Saethre-Chotzen syndrome' by Teng et al. presents interesting new findings concerning animal models of coronal suture fusion from <italic>TWIST1</italic> and <italic>TCF12</italic> mutations in the zebrafish and the mouse. This paper is significant as it demonstrates conservation of mechanisms underlying coronal suture fusion and presentation of Twist1/Tcf12 phenotypes in the zebrafish. The authors show independence of these suture pathologies to embryological tissue origin, suggesting that the common/ancestral developmental specification of suture formation may have different causes. The authors highlight changes in growth of the calvaria parallel/presage adult pathologies suggesting that changes in growth rate and potential may underlie observed pathologies. To support these observations the authors detail changes in the number of proliferative cells in the osteogenic fronts suggesting the defect in rate maybe attributable to lack of maintenance of progenitors/stem cells. The implications of their findings are first and foremost the conservation of mechanisms of craniosynostosis between zebrafish and mouse. This matter has been of much debate in the field with little data to support either opinion. The discussion of the similarities between the models and the independence to embryological tissue of origin (mesoderm/neural crest) is well done and important for the presentation of this work to the field. Second, the developmental analysis clearly pointed to early growth events as being primary to the changes in suture phenotypes in the models. This is in stark contrast to the center of much of the work in the field centering on suture mesenchyme and late maintenance of patency. The causes of the early shifts in proliferative capacity may be diverse, but the change in growth may be a shared phenotype underlying suture pathologies associated with synostosis.</p><p>Although these are strong points, the mechanistic data to support the changes in growth as underlying suture pathology is thin. My comments fall to two general areas:</p><p>1) Of general concern is the lack of sufficient experimental evidence to support conclusions of changes in postnatal stem cells as key finding of their mechanism. The authors look to BrdU and Sp7 expression to argue for changes in progenitor populations and proliferative potential. This measure is nicely tied to changes in osteogenic progression (surface). This is a measure of proliferation and not stem cells per se; the decrease in numbers could be in fact due to altered production of mitogens such as Fgf signaling factors that have been associated with altered suture fusion. Notably, Twist function is tied to <italic>Fgfr2</italic>. Further, without label retention studies, lineage tracing, or use of different progenitor markers such as <italic>gli1</italic> and <italic>prrx1</italic>, it is not appropriate to conclude that this is due to altered maintenance of postembryonic stem cell populations. There is little evidence for the effect being due to alteration in stem cells and supporting their discussion of this as the mechanism for the differential growth rate.</p><p>As one of the strengths of this work is the commonalities between mouse and zebrafish providing dual models to approach mechanism, it is imperative that more of the mechanisms be ironed out, lest the impact of the findings here highlighted above will be lessened.</p><p>2) The detailing of the growth dynamics as an early causative mechanism for how suture defects arise is interesting and potentially transformative for the field. However, the descriptions presented in this manuscript are quite descriptive and do not attempt to integrate how expression of key CS associated gene such as Fgfs are varied in their mutants, nor how alteration in Twist1/Tcf12 may affect their expression.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #3:</italic> </p><p>Cranial sutures are thought to contain stem cells and this proposal has driven a lot of recent research into craniosynostosis. The suggestion that embryonic and postnatal stem cell populations are distinct is intriguing.</p><p>This study is limited to closure of the coronal suture in a specific model for craniosynostosis. Although the coronal suture is the suture that is most frequently closed prematurely, other sutures, especially of the facial skeleton have been shown to close prematurely in humans with craniosynostosis syndromes and in Fgfr-related mouse models for craniosynostosis. Have the authors looked carefully at other sutures, facial or vault? Would they expect/not expect suture closure in other sutures? Is the proposal of stem cell mechanism specific to the coronal suture? To cranial vault sutures? Or would you expect to see them in facial sutures too? Why or why not? The fact that you report other skull bone abnormalities local to the vault sutures makes me wonder if we have the whole story here. To focus only on the coronal suture limits the impact of these findings and makes it unclear why the coronal suture is targeted (given there is no mesoderm-nc boundary at this suture in fish).</p><p>The question of whether sutures are homologous across vertebrates is an interesting question. It has been proposed that the mechanism underlying the demonstrated reduction in number of bones of the modern vertebrate skull relative to the skull of pre-synapsid mammals may be similar to mechanisms underlying premature suture closure in modern humans. [True evolutionary homology of sutures would be difficult but not impossible to demonstrate across vertebrates. I am <italic>not</italic> asking that you do this.]</p><p>The live imaging of the sutures is a great tool providing important information.</p><p>The result that Tcf12 and Twist1 have a &quot;conserved&quot; early function during skull bone growth to regulate the balance of progenitors and osteoblasts – is only demonstrated for fish here, but it is a beginning to show conservation across vertebrates.</p><p>The Discussion is overly long and does not provide a solid explanation of what was observed. If there truly are no other fusions in the skulls of these fish, why does the coronal suture respond specifically to these mutations?</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were requested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><p>Thank you for resubmitting your work entitled &quot;Altered progenitor dynamics prefigure craniosynostosis in a zebrafish model of Saethre-Chotzen syndrome&quot; for further consideration at <italic>eLife</italic>. Your revised article has been favorably evaluated by Marianne Bronner as the Senior Editor, a Reviewing Editor, and the 3 original reviewers.</p><p>The manuscript has been improved but there are remaining issues that need to be dealt with. Overall, the reviewers appreciated the effort involved in generating the data in Figure 7 to strengthen the argument that this is due to loss of progenitors. However, all three reviewers had significant concerns about the quantification of this data and whether it truly does reflect loss of the progenitors. This is deemed very important since your proposed mechanism relies on this quantification. A sampling of their concerns includes:</p><p>a) &quot;It is hard to see what the metrics of their quantitation are as I cannot see how &quot;area&quot; of expression can be garnered from those sections – especially when there are 4-6 foci within a section to demarcate regions. Statements of new markers for suture progenitors seems a bit overstated as the expression is generally across the bones – showing lack of expression in non-suture locations, or whole mounts might be more convincing. &quot;</p><p>b) &quot;I found it very hard to see the orange and magenta lines in Figure 7A and once I blew it up big enough to be able to see it, I was unconvinced by the description offered in the figure legend. According to the authors, <italic>prxx1a</italic> is broadly expressed at the bone fronts and in the sutures and perisosteum at 10mm and in the sutures and periosteum at adult stages. I felt more data, or better figures were required to support their overall conclusion that their findings indicate a selective exhaustion of osteoprogenitors at the developing coronal suture – as opposed to more generally across skull bones. &quot;</p><p>c) &quot;I still don't prefer this sentence, beginning: &quot;As in mice and humans, coronal suture loss correlated with reduced anterior-posterior growth of the frontal and parietal bones, resulting in asymmetrically shaped heads when the suture was lost unilaterally.&quot; As written, the authors still ascribe causality of head asymmetry to suture loss, whereas both head asymmetry and unilateral suture loss may be consequences of asymmetrically reduced growth. &quot;</p><p>Based on these concerns, we request that you either:</p><p>1) Provide more convincing quantification to ascribe this to progenitor loss.</p><p>2) If you feel that this cannot be done, then a rewording of the title and discuss to indicate that the study centers on the role of Twist1/Tcf12 in a zebrafish model of CS, and then discuss the possibility that this could be due to progenitor loss although not proven.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.37024.041</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #2:</p><p>[…]</p><p>1) Of general concern is the lack of sufficient experimental evidence to support conclusions of changes in postnatal stem cells as key finding of their mechanism. The authors look to BrdU and Sp7 expression to argue for changes in progenitor populations and proliferative potential. This measure is nicely tied to changes in osteogenic progression (surface). This is a measure of proliferation and not stem cells per se; the decrease in numbers could be in fact be due to altered production of mitogens such as Fgf signaling factors that have been associated with altered suture fusion. Notably, Twist function is tied to Fgfr2. Further, without label retention studies, lineage tracing, or use of different progenitor markers such as gli1 and prrx1, it is not appropriate to conclude that this is due to altered maintenance of postembryonic stem cell populations. There is little evidence for the effect being due to alteration in stem cells and supporting their discussion of this as the mechanism for the differential growth rate.</p><p>As one of the strengths of this work is the commonalities between mouse and zebrafish providing dual models to approach mechanism, it is imperative that more of the mechanisms be ironed out, lest the impact of the findings here highlighted above will be lessened.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree that our original experiments had only inferred stem cell populations in the mutant calvarial bones and sutures through analysis of proliferation and osteoblast production. In a new Figure 7, we now directly examine progenitor populations in zebrafish using three markers (<italic>gli1, grem1a, prrx1a</italic>), both at a stage when the calvarial bones are still growing and at a later stage when the sutures have formed. Consistent with our original model, we find that suture progenitor cells marked by these genes are reduced in number at the developing coronal but not the sagittal suture. We also now show a similar depletion of Gli1<sup>+</sup> and Grem1<sup>+</sup> progenitors at the mouse coronal but not the sagittal suture at embryonic stages. As described in a new Results subsection (“Selective reduction of the osteoprogenitor pool at the mutant coronal suture”), these new experiments show molecular homology between zebrafish and mouse sutural stem cells, reveal <italic>Grem1</italic> as a potential new sutural stem cell marker in both species, and confirm selective exhaustion of osteoprogenitors at the coronal versus the sagittal suture.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>2) The detailing of the growth dynamics as an early causative mechanism for how suture defects arise is interesting and potentially transformative for the field. However, the descriptions presented in this manuscript are quite descriptive and do not attempt to integrate how expression of key CS associated gene such as Fgfs are varied in their mutants, nor how alteration in Twist1/Tcf12 may affect their expression.</p></disp-quote><p>In a new Figure 7—figure supplement 1, we identify expression of <italic>Fgfr2</italic> and the Fgf target gene <italic>dusp6</italic> at the developing coronal suture of zebrafish. In mutants, we find that the domain of osteoprogenitors expressing <italic>fgfr2</italic> and <italic>dusp6</italic> is reduced, yet the remaining bone front cells express similar levels of both genes.</p><p>Subsection “Selective reduction of the osteoprogenitor pool at the mutant coronal suture”: “Thus, the calvarial phenotypes observed are unlikely to be due to whole-scale loss of Fgfr2 signaling at the bone fronts.”</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Reviewer #3:</p><p>Cranial sutures are thought to contain stem cells and this proposal has driven a lot of recent research into craniosynostosis. The suggestion that embryonic and postnatal stem cell populations are distinct is intriguing.</p><p>This study is limited to closure of the coronal suture in a specific model for craniosynostosis. Although the coronal suture is the suture that is most frequently closed prematurely, other sutures, especially of the facial skeleton have been shown to close prematurely in humans with craniosynostosis syndromes and in Fgfr-related mouse models for craniosynostosis. Have the authors looked carefully at other sutures, facial or vault? Would they expect/not expect suture closure in other sutures? Is the proposal of stem cell mechanism specific to the coronal suture? To cranial vault sutures? Or would you expect to see them in facial sutures too? Why or why not? The fact that you report other skull bone abnormalities local to the vault sutures makes me wonder if we have the whole story here. To focus only on the coronal suture limits the impact of these findings and makes it unclear why the coronal suture is targeted (given there is no mesoderm-nc boundary at this suture in fish).</p><p><italic>The question of whether sutures are homologous across vertebrates is an interesting question. It has been proposed that the mechanism underlying the demonstrated reduction in number of bones of the modern vertebrate skull relative to the skull of pre-synapsid mammals may be similar to mechanisms underlying premature suture closure in modern humans. [True evolutionary homology of sutures would be difficult but not impossible to demonstrate across vertebrates. I am</italic> not asking that you do this.]</p><p>The live imaging of the sutures is a great tool providing important information.</p><p>The result that Tcfl2 and Twist1 have a &quot;conserved&quot; early function during skull bone growth to regulate the balance of progenitors and osteoblasts – is only demonstrated for fish here, but it is a beginning to show conservation across vertebrates.</p><p>The Discussion is overly long and does not provide a solid explanation of what was observed. If there truly are no other fusions in the skulls of these fish, why does the coronal suture respond specifically to these mutations?</p></disp-quote><p>We have developed a zebrafish model for a particular form of craniosynostosis, Saethre-Chotzen Syndrome, which almost exclusively affects the coronal suture in mice and humans. A significant and unexpected finding from our study is that the coronal suture is likewise most sensitive to loss of Twist1 and Tcf12, despite this forming at a mesoderm-mesoderm boundary in fish and a neural crest-mesoderm boundary in mammals. While we have not detected loss of other sutures in our fish mutants, we do observe occasional ectopic sutures and other skull anomalies in different mutant combinations, which we describe in detail in Figure 1—figure supplement 3.</p><p>Subsection “Specific loss of the coronal suture in <italic>tcf12; twist1b</italic> mutant zebrafish”: “Nonetheless, our results demonstrate that, as in humans and mice with reduced <italic>TCF12</italic> and/or <italic>TWIST1</italic> dosage, mutations in the homologous genes in zebrafish result primarily in loss of the coronal suture, although other calvarial defects are also rarely observed.”</p><p>In response to Reviewer #2(see new Figure 7), we have also examined several progenitor markers (<italic>prrx1a, grem1a, gli1</italic>) in mutant fish and mice, which reveal selective exhaustion of parietal and frontal bone progenitor pools. We also now show altered directional growth of the parietal and frontal bones in mutants, which brings these bones together earlier than normal at the prospective coronal suture zone. Accordingly, we have extensively revised the Discussion to incorporate these new findings and their implications while condensing other sections to make it more focused.</p><p>Discussion, second paragraph: “In particular, we found that increased diagonal growth in mutants brought the parietal and frontal bones together at the prospective medial regions of the coronal suture much earlier than in wild type animals, which correlates with the medial region of the coronal suture being most commonly fused in mutants. This altered directional growth might be one reason why the coronal suture is preferentially affected in both zebrafish and mouse Twist1/Tcf12 mutants, despite the different origins of the coronal suture in these species.”</p><p>Discussion, third paragraph: “We did not observe preferential expression of <italic>tcf12</italic> and <italic>twist1b</italic> at the coronal suture in fish, consistent with similarly broad sutural expression of <italic>Twist1</italic> in mice (Rice et al., 2000). Instead, osteoprogenitors in the coronal zone might be fewer in number at initial stages and/or more sensitive to loss of Tcf12 and Twist1, for example due to compensation by related genes at other sutures.”</p><p>[Editors' note: further revisions were requested prior to acceptance, as described below.]</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>The manuscript has been improved but there are remaining issues that need to be dealt with. Overall, the reviewers appreciated the effort involved in generating the data in Figure 7 to strengthen the argument that this is due to loss of progenitors. However, all three reviewers had significant concerns about the quantification of this data and whether it truly does reflect loss of the progenitors. This is deemed very important since your proposed mechanism relies on this quantification. A sampling of their concerns includes:</p><p>a) &quot;It is hard to see what the metrics of their quantitation are as I cannot see how &quot;area&quot; of expression can be garnered from those sections – especially when there are 4-6 foci within a section to demarcate regions. Statements of new markers for suture progenitors seems a bit overstated as the expression is generally across the bones – showing lack of expression in non-suture locations, or whole mounts might be more convincing. &quot;</p></disp-quote><p>We agree that quantification was difficult in zebrafish mutants given the small numbers of cells and low RNA signal. We have therefore removed the quantification from Figure 7, as well as the accompanying statement claiming loss of progenitors at the developing coronal suture of zebrafish.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>b) &quot;I found it very hard to see the orange and magenta lines in Figure 7A and once I blew it up big enough to be able to see it, I was unconvinced by the description offered in the figure legend. According to the authors, prxx1a is broadly expressed at the bone fronts and in the sutures and perisosteum at 10mm and in the sutures and periosteum at adult stages. I felt more data, or better figures were required to support their overall conclusion that their findings indicate a selective exhaustion of osteoprogenitors at the developing coronal suture – as opposed to more generally across skull bones. &quot;</p></disp-quote><p>We now provide magnified images in Figure 7A to better visualize the developing coronal sutures in zebrafish. We also added arrows showing the periosteal expression of <italic>prrx1a</italic> but not <italic>grem1a</italic> and <italic>gli1</italic> within the periosteum, and arrows showing suture expression. As stated below, we no longer claim exhaustion of osteoprogenitors in zebrafish at the 10 mm stage, instead only referring to the more convincing mouse data in Figure 7C.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>c) &quot;I still don't prefer this sentence, beginning: &quot;As in mice and humans, coronal suture loss correlated with reduced anterior-posterior growth of the frontal and parietal bones, resulting in asymmetrically shaped heads when the suture was lost unilaterally.&quot; As written, the authors still ascribe causality of head asymmetry to suture loss, whereas both head asymmetry and unilateral suture loss may be consequences of asymmetrically reduced growth. &quot;</p></disp-quote><p>We agree that “resulting in” still implied causality. We therefore changed the sentence to better reflect our findings and avoid claims of causality: “…in cases where the suture was lost unilaterally we consistently observed reduced anterior-posterior growth of that side of the skull”.</p><disp-quote content-type="editor-comment"><p>Based on these concerns, we request that you either:</p><p>1) Provide more convincing quantification to ascribe this to progenitor loss.</p><p>2) If you feel that this cannot be done, then a rewording of the title and discuss to indicate that the study centers on the role of Twist1/Tcf12 in a zebrafish model of CS, and then discuss the possibility that this could be due to progenitor loss although not proven.</p></disp-quote><p>We agree that the quantification of the progenitor loss in zebrafish sutures was difficult due to the small numbers of cells and low level of expression of the genes examined. This made it hard to conclusively count “progenitors”, especially in mutants where the bones are abnormally shaped and more closely apposed. We have therefore chosen option (2) and revised the title and Discussion accordingly.</p><p>The title is changed from “<italic>Altered progenitor dynamics</italic> prefigure…” to “<italic>Altered bone growth</italic> dynamics prefigure craniosynostosis in a zebrafish model of Saethre-Chotzen syndrome”. We feel that this better reflects our in vivo imaging data in zebrafish revealing that the extent of altered bone growth predicts which mutants will develop coronal suture defects. The title also reflects our conceptual advance of developing the first genetic model of CS in zebrafish.</p><p>We have removed the quantification of “progenitor domains” at the zebrafish sutures (originally Figure 7B), and no longer refer to progenitor exhaustion at mutant zebrafish sutures. For example, in the Discussion: “Whether similar osteoprogenitors become exhausted at the developing coronal suture of zebrafish remains to be determined, as it was difficult to precisely quantify the numbers of these progenitors by RNA expression alone.”</p><p>When referring to reduced progenitors at the mutant coronal suture, we now only refer to the mouse data in Figure 7C which we feel is convincing – the reviewers only expressed concern with the zebrafish data in Figure 7A. For example, in the Discussion: “These findings … suggest, at least in mice, a selective exhaustion of osteoprogenitors at the developing coronal suture”.</p><p>Rather than stating that our results prove progenitor exhaustion as the mechanism underlying coronal suture loss, we have altered the language throughout to present progenitor exhaustion as one plausible model consistent with our data. For example, in the Abstract: “These findings … suggest that the coronal suture might be especially susceptible to imbalances in progenitor maintenance and osteoblast differentiation.”</p><p>We have also added new language that Gli1, Grem1, and Prrx1 label “putative” progenitors in the developing sutures, given that lineage tracing studies at these stages would still be needed to confirm this.</p></body></sub-article></article>