<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">eLife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">12850</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Short Report</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Developmental Biology and Stem Cells</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Wnt, Ptk7, and FGFRL expression gradients control trunk positional identity in planarian regeneration</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-45759"><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-7989"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>Christian P</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7552-6865</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-3"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-4"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-5"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Molecular Biosciences</institution>, <institution>Northwestern University</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Evanston</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Robert Lurie Comprehensive Cancer Center</institution>, <institution>Northwestern University</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Evanston</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Sánchez Alvarado</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff3"><institution>Stowers Institute for Medical Research</institution>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><email>christian-p-petersen@northwestern.edu</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><p>Competing interests statement:</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>13</day><month>04</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e12850</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>04</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016, Lander et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lander et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-12850-v2.pdf"/><related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="ra1" related-article-type="article-reference" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12845"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.001</object-id><p>Mechanisms enabling positional identity re-establishment are likely critical for tissue regeneration. Planarians use Wnt/beta-catenin signaling to polarize the termini of their anteroposterior axis, but little is known about how regeneration signaling restores regionalization along body or organ axes. We identify three genes expressed constitutively in overlapping body-wide transcriptional gradients that control trunk-tail positional identity in regeneration. <italic>ptk7</italic> encodes a trunk-expressed kinase-dead Wnt co-receptor, <italic>wntP-2</italic> encodes a posterior-expressed Wnt ligand, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> encodes an anterior-expressed homolog of conserved FGFRL/<italic>nou-darake</italic> decoy receptors. <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> maintain and allow appropriate regeneration of trunk tissue position independently of canonical Wnt signaling and with suppression of <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression in the posterior. These results suggest that restoration of regional identity in regeneration involves the interpretation and re-establishment of axis-wide transcriptional gradients of signaling molecules.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.001">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.001</ext-link></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>Some animals can regrow tissues that have been amputated. A group of flatworms called planarians are often used as a model to study the regeneration process because they are able to restore any lost tissue or even an entire animal from even tiny pieces of the body. For regeneration to be successful, it is critical to identify which tissues or regions of the body need to be replaced.</p><p>The planarian body is divided into three main parts: head, trunk and tail. Several genes involved in specifying what tissues regenerate are very active (or “highly expressed”) in muscle cells in different regions of the planarian body. Some of the genes are involved in mechanisms that allow cells to communicate with each other, such as the Wnt and FGF signaling pathways. These genes could form a coordinated system to control regeneration, but their precise roles remain poorly understood.</p><p>Two groups of researchers have now independently identified genes that provide cells with information about their location in the flatworm body. Lander and Petersen identified three genes that are expressed in an overlapping manner along the body of uninjured animals. One of the genes – known as <italic>ptk7</italic> – is mainly produced in the trunk region, while the second gene (<italic>wntP-2)</italic> is produced from the tail and the third (<italic>ndl-3)</italic> is produced from the head region. The <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> encode components of the Wnt signaling pathway, while <italic>ndl-3</italic> encodes a protein involved in FGF signaling.</p><p>Lander and Petersen used a technique called RNAi to lower the activity of the three genes individually or in pairs, and then examined whether this affected the ability of the worms to regenerate. Inhibition of any of the three genes resulted in an expansion of the trunk tissues into the tail region, indicating that the normal role for these genes is to stop cells adopting the trunk “identity”.</p><p>Another study by Scimone, Cote et al. found that two separate sets of genes – including <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3 –</italic> are needed to correctly position tissues in the head and trunk of planarians. Together these findings suggest that the Wnt and FGFRL pathways act in a body-wide system that co-ordinates where and which new tissues form during regeneration. A future challenge will be to decipher the complete network of genes that provides the positional information needed for regeneration.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.002">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.002</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Author Keywords</title><kwd>planaria</kwd><kwd>regeneration</kwd><kwd>pattern control</kwd><kwd>axis</kwd><kwd>Wnt</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research Organism</title><kwd>S. mediterranea</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="par-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000054</institution-id><institution>National Cancer Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Training grant T32-CA080621-09</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NRSA F32GM108395-01A1</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000863</institution-id><institution>Ellison Medical Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>New Scholar in Aging Research Award AG-NS-0835-11</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-4"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000048</institution-id><institution>American Cancer Society</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Institutional Research Grant ACS-IRG 93-037-15</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-5"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NIH Director's New Innovator Award 1DP2DE024365-01</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>elife-xml-version</meta-name><meta-value>2.5</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Signaling molecules expressed in overlapping body-wide transcriptional gradients determine central axis positional identity in whole-body regeneration.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Robust pattern control is a central but poorly understood feature of regenerative abilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Wolpert, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">French et al., 1976</xref>). Animals cannot anticipate how a given injury will alter tissue composition, so regeneration likely depends critically on the re-establishment of missing tissue identity. Planarians use pluripotent stem cells to regenerate from nearly any amputation to restore a complete set of regionalized tissues, including cephalic ganglia in the anterior and a pharynx and mouth in the trunk, and are a model of positional restoration after amputation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Reddien, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Adler and Sánchez Alvarado, 2015</xref>). Canonical Wnt signaling controls anterior-versus-posterior pole identity in planarian regeneration, with principal upstream determinants <italic>wnt1</italic> expressed at the posterior pole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Petersen and Reddien, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gurley et al., 2010</xref>) and the secreted Wnt inhibitor <italic>notum</italic> expressed at the anterior pole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Petersen and Reddien, 2011</xref>), both activated transcriptionally early after wounding. Inhibition of Wnt signaling components β<italic>-catenin-1</italic>, <italic>wnt1, Evi/wntless, Dvl-1/2</italic> and <italic>teashirt</italic> causes regeneration of ectopic heads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gurley et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Iglesias et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Petersen and Reddien, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Owen et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Reuter et al., 2015</xref>); conversely, inhibition of <italic>APC</italic> or <italic>notum</italic> can cause regeneration of ectopic tails (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gurley et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Petersen and Reddien, 2011</xref>). Other pathways participate in head or tail regeneration, with Hedgehog signaling influencing injury-induced <italic>wnt1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Rink et al., 2009</xref>), several transcription factors required for head formation (<italic>prep, foxD, zic-1/zicA, pbx, egr-4)</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Felix and Aboobaker, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Blassberg et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Chen et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fraguas et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Scimone et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Vásquez-Doorman and Petersen, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Vogg et al., 2014</xref>) and/or tail formation (<italic>junli-1, pitx, pbx</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Blassberg et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Chen et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Currie and Pearson, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Marz et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Tejada-Romero et al., 2015</xref>), and influenced by gap junction and calcium signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Oviedo et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Zhang et al., 2011</xref>). However, comparatively little is known about the restoration of positional information along the head-to-tail body axis through regeneration. Expression profiling and homology searching have identified a cohort of factors related to Wnt, Hox, and FGF signaling expressed regionally in domains along the anteroposterior (A-P) axis in planarians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Cebrià et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Reddien, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Owen et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Reuter et al., 2015</xref>). These factors could in principle form a molecular coordinate system that re-specifies axis identity in regeneration and have been termed 'positional control genes' (PCGs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Witchley et al., 2013</xref>). However, few phenotypes of positional displacement have been reported from perturbation of PCGs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Cebrià et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Kobayashi et al., 2007</xref>), so it remains unclear how the majority of these genes participate in regeneration.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>To uncover programs responsible for patterning along the body axis, we examined PCGs as defined by prior homology and expression profiling studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Reddien, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Witchley et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Owen et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Reuter et al., 2015</xref>) and found a unique expression pattern for a planarian homolog of <italic>ptk7</italic>, expressed in an animal-wide graded fashion maximally in the trunk, and also the CNS and pharynx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1</xref>). Ptk7 proteins encode cell-surface Wnt co-receptors with a predicted intracellular pseudokinase domain that participate in noncanonical, β-catenin-independent Wnt signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lu et al., 2004</xref>), and can either weakly suppress or activate canonical β-catenin-dependent Wnt signaling in a context-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Peradziryi et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Puppo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hayes et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bin-Nun et al., 2014</xref>). Like other described PCGs, planarian <italic>ptk7</italic> was expressed in <italic>collagen+</italic> cells of the body-wall musculature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Witchley et al., 2013</xref>) and aspects of its expression domain could become re-established after amputation even in irradiated animals lacking neoblasts and the ability to form new tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A–C</xref>). In <italic>ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals amputated to remove both head and tail, regeneration produced a normal head and tail (35/35) but caused formation of an ectopic posterior mouth at a high penetrance (83%, n=35) and, more rarely, formation of an ectopic posterior pharynx with broadly normal orientation with respect to the primary body axis (14%, n=35) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D–E</xref>). Thus, <italic>ptk7</italic> limits trunk identity in planarian regeneration.<fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.003</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title><italic>ptk7</italic> is a positional control gene that suppresses trunk identity in regenerating planarians.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Left panel, Double FISH to detect coexpression of <italic>ptk7</italic> within <italic>collagen+</italic> cells of the body-wall musculature in a trunk-centered gradient (116/125 <italic>collagen+</italic> cells were <italic>ptk7+</italic> and 113/125 <italic>ptk7+</italic> cells were <italic>collagen+</italic>, scored in ventral prepharyngeal subepidermal region). Right panels, higher magnification of <italic>collagen+ptk7+</italic> cells. (<bold>B</bold>, upper panels) Freshly amputated head fragments have <italic>ptk7</italic> expression in the CNS but minimal levels in subepidermal cells but by 48–96 hr expression appears at a region within the new anterior of the fragment (arrows, anterior extent of <italic>ptk7</italic> expression). (<bold>B</bold>, lower panels) Animals treated with lethal doses of gamma irradiation (6000 Rads) three days prior to amputation undergo a similar re-establishment of a <italic>ptk7</italic> expression domain along the A-P axis. Images represent at least 3/3 animals probed. (<bold>C</bold>) Irradiation controls showing elimination of <italic>smedwi-1-</italic>expressing neoblasts in animals from the same cohort as (<bold>B</bold>). (<bold>D</bold>) Animals were injected with control or <italic>ptk7</italic> dsRNA three times over three days, amputated to remove heads and tails, allowed to regenerate, fixed at 14 days and stained with a <italic>laminin</italic> riboprobe detecting both the mouth and pharynx (left panels, dotted line indicates amputation plane, red box shows enlarged region of <italic>ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals) or stained with Hoechst dye to label nuclei and visualize the pharynx (right). <italic>ptk7</italic> RNAi caused formation of an ectopic posterior mouth in regenerating trunk fragments (28/35 animals), but not in regenerating head or tail fragments (35/35 animals each). (<bold>D</bold>, right) More rarely, <italic>ptk7</italic> inhibition caused formation of an ectopic posterior pharynx. (<bold>E</bold>) Control or <italic>ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals stained with a fluorescent lectin Concanavalin A to visualize the epidermis and the pre-existing or ectopic mouth (red arrow). Bars, 25 (<bold>A</bold>), or 200 (<bold>B</bold>), or 400 microns (<bold>D–E</bold>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.003">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.003</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Sequence alignment of <italic>Smed-ptk7</italic>.</title><p>Alignment of predicted protein sequence of <italic>Smed-ptk7</italic> with human (HsPtk7, NP_002812.2), mouse (MmPtk7, AAH76578.1), <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> (XlPtk7, NP_001083315.1), zebrafish (DrPtk7, AGT63300.1) and <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (otk, AAF58596.1) Ptk7 proteins. SMED-PTK7 is predicted to have 7 extracellular Ig-family domains and an intracellular tyrosine kinase domain (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de">http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de</ext-link>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.004">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.004</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig1-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig1s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.005</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>RNAi enhancement screen identifies modulators of <italic>ptk7</italic> activity involved in trunk patterning.</title><p>(Upper) Plot of ectopic posterior pharynx phenotype penetrance after administration of dsRNA targeting <italic>ptk7</italic> and each of 22 previously identified positional control genes or Wnt-related factors expressed regionally along the body axis (<italic>wnt11-1, wnt11-2, wnt11-4, wntP-2, wnt2-1</italic>, and <italic>wnt5</italic>), general intracellular components of Wnt signaling (frizzled receptors expressed in the posterior: <italic>fzd4-1/fzd4, fzd4-2</italic>, and <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic>; Disheveled proteins: <italic>Dvl-1</italic> and <italic>Dvl-2</italic>), downstream components of Wnt signaling that act positively (<italic>teashirt)</italic> or negatively (<italic>axin-B)</italic> to influence <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> signaling, secreted Wnt inhibitors (<italic>sFRP-1, sFRP-2, sFRP-3, notum</italic>), Wnt-PCP pathways (<italic>DAAM1, ROCK, vangl2)</italic>, and FGFR-like/<italic>nou-darake</italic> family factors (<italic>ndl-3, ndl-</italic>4). At least 5 animals were examined in each condition except for <italic>wntP-2, DAAM1, ROCK, vangl2</italic> RNAi treatments in which at least 24 animals were examined. Asterisks indicate p &lt; 0.05 from Fisher’s exact test versus control + <italic>ptk7</italic> dsRNA treatment after Benjamini-Hochberg correction for false discovery. Inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> along with either <italic>wntP-2</italic> (p=5.16E-14)<italic>, ndl-3 (</italic>p<italic>=</italic>1.24E-05), <italic>fzd-1/2/7</italic> (p=0.046), or <italic>Dvl-2</italic> (p=4.18E-06) caused the strongest occurrence of the ectopic pharynx phenotype. (Lower) in situ hybridizations showing regionalized expression of selected genes from the screen.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.005">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.005</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig1-figsupp2-v2"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>We next used RNAi and a phenotypic enhancement assay to identify other PCGs that participate with <italic>ptk7</italic> in trunk identity regulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>). Co-inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> with either <italic>wntP-2/wnt11-5/wnt4b</italic> (hereafter referred to as <italic>wntP-2), ndl-3, Dvl-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Almuedo-Castillo et al., 2011</xref>), or <italic>fzd-1/2/7</italic> caused the strongest enhancement of the ectopic pharynx phenotype, resulting in 100% of animals affected, whereas co-inhibition with other PCGs affected this phenotype more weakly and below statistical significance under these conditions. <italic>wntP-2</italic> encodes a Wnt gene expressed in a graded fashion from the posterior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>) and based on phylogenetic analyses has been proposed to be either a Wnt11 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gurley et al., 2010</xref>) or Wnt4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Riddiford and Olson, 2011</xref>) family member. Planarian <italic>ndl-3</italic> is expressed in a graded fashion from the anterior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Rink et al., 2009</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>), and encodes a member of the conserved FGFRL/<italic>nou-darake</italic> class of cell-surface molecules that possess an FGF-receptor-like extracellular domain but lacks a tyrosine kinase intracellular domain and are thus proposed to function as FGF signaling inhibitors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Cebrià et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Gerber et al., 2009</xref>). <italic>fzd-1/2/7</italic> encodes a predicted Wnt receptor expressed broadly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>). Individual inhibition of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2,</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> caused formation of ectopic posterior mouths (30/35 <italic>ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals, 22/33 <italic>wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals, 14/23 <italic>ndl-3(RNAi)</italic> animals), and ectopic posterior pharynges (5/35 <italic>ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals, 8/33 <italic>wntP-</italic>2(RNAi) animals, 2/23 <italic>ndl-3(RNAi)</italic> animals) in amputated animals regenerating both their heads and tails compared to controls (0/46 animals) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). We verified knockdown of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2,</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> using in situ hybridizations and qPCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1A–B</xref>). Inhibition of any pairwise combinations of the three genes enhanced the trunk expansion phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A–B</xref>) (animals with ectopic pharynges: 45/55 <italic>wntP-2(RNAi);ptk7(RNAi)</italic>, 29/32 <italic>ptk7(RNAi);ndl-3(RNAi)</italic>, 24/40 <italic>wntP-2(RNAi);ndl-3(RNAi)</italic>), with double-RNAi animals also frequently forming two ectopic pharynges (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>) and co-inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> producing highest penetrance and expressivity of trunk duplication phenotypes. The orientation of ectopic pharynges was generally oblique, and sometimes inverted, but the majority in all conditions pointed toward the posterior rather than anterior direction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). Live animals with ectopic pharynges were observed during feeding, and the duplicated pharynx could obtain food (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>, <xref ref-type="other" rid="media1">Video 1</xref>), suggesting normal functionality of this organ. Taken together, <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> form a core group of regionally expressed PCGs that jointly suppress trunk identity during posterior regeneration.<fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.006</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title><italic>ptk7</italic> acts with <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> to suppress trunk identity in a context-dependent manner.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> dsRNAs were fed to animals individually or in pair-wise combinations prior to amputation to remove heads and tails, fixation 25 days later, staining with a <italic>laminin</italic> riboprobe and Hoechst dye. (<bold>B</bold>) Scoring information for pharynx and mouth duplication phenotypes. Animals were scored for presence of ectopic mouth (defined as a superficial circle of <italic>laminin+</italic> cells which was always present posterior to the original mouth, arrow), and ectopic pharynx (defined as having pharynx morphology by <italic>laminin+</italic> and Hoechst+ staining, double arrows) and its orientation with respect to the A-P body axis. Animals with an ectopic mouth but not a fully formed ectopic pharynx often had varying degrees of internal <italic>laminin</italic> expression suggestive of a growing pharynx primordium and were scored as having an ectopic mouth only. Co-inhibition of any pairwise combination of the three genes enhanced the penetrance and expressivity of the ectopic pharynx phenotypes. Note that combined pairwise inhibition of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> enhanced the trunk duplication phenotype and that dual inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> produced the strongest effects. (<bold>C</bold>) Analysis of ectopic pharynx orientation, measured at the proximal end of the ectopic pharynx. In many cases, the ectopic pharynx was oriented at an oblique angle with respect to the body axis, perhaps as a result of ectopic mouth placement nearby the original mouth, and ectopic pharynges were observed with fully inverted polarity. In all animals that formed 2 ectopic pharynges (derived from pairwise combinations of dsRNAs), both structures were oriented toward a common ectopic mouth located along the posterior midline. (<bold>D</bold>) Images of live animals showing the ectopic pharynx in <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals (red arrow) can be functional for feeding. (<bold>E</bold>) Prolonged inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> in uninjured animals for at least 36 days (64 days shown) caused formation of an ectopic pharynx (6/8 animals) and multiple posterior mouths (8/8 animals). (<bold>F</bold>) Inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> or <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> caused head and tail fragments to regenerate only a single pharynx like control animals. Therefore, the effects of <italic>ptk7, ndl-3</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> in body patterning are context dependent. Anterior, left. Bars, 300 (<bold>A</bold>,<bold>E</bold>) or 500 (<bold>F</bold>) microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.006">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.006</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig2-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.007</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Verification of RNAi knockdown for <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3.</italic></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) In situ hybridizations verifying that dsRNA to <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> individually reduced the expression of each gene after 12 days of RNAi in the absence of injury (<italic>ptk7</italic>) or 20 days regeneration after head and tail amputation (<italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic>) of RNAi. Images represent 100% of animals stained, n &gt; 4. Bars, 500 microns. (<bold>B</bold>) qPCR showing knockdown of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> mRNA. Asterisks indicate p&lt;0.05 by a 2-tailed t-test.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.007">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.007</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig2-figsupp1-v2"/></fig></fig-group><media content-type="glencoe play-in-place height-250 width-310" id="media1" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-12850-media1.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.008</object-id><label>Video 1.</label><caption><title>Ectopic pharynges in <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi</italic>) animals can be functional for feeding, related to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</title><p>Movie of a live <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animal showing both the original and ectopic pharynges in a 21 day regenerating trunk fragment feeding on liver paste.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.008">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.008</ext-link></p></caption></media></p><p><italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> were expressed regionally in the absence of injury, so we examined whether they act only in regeneration or constitutively to regulate trunk regionalization. Prolonged co-inhibition of <italic>wntP-</italic>2 and <italic>ptk7</italic> produced animals with an ectopic pharynx, indicating that these genes together restrict trunk identity homeostatically in the absence of injury (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>). Furthermore, the fact that such animals ultimately formed multiple ectopic mouths extending toward the posterior suggests that graded activities of <italic>wntP-</italic>2 and/or <italic>ptk7</italic>, rather than their control of a binary switch in developmental outcomes, could pattern the tail and trunk regions.</p><p>We next examined whether trunk suppression mediated by <italic>wntP-2, ptk7</italic>, and <italic>ndl-</italic>3 was operational in all regeneration contexts, as is the case for several characterized patterning genes in planarians. By contrast, under RNAi conditions that produced an 80–100% penetrant pharynx duplication in regenerating trunk fragments, head and tail fragments from <italic>wntP-2(RNAi);ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals or <italic>ndl-3(RNAi);ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals formed only a single <italic>laminin+</italic> pharynx as did control animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>). Eventually, after prolonged dsRNA feeding after regeneration, such animals could form ectopic pharynges (76 days of RNAi, n=3 of 12 animals examined), consistent with homeostatic functioning of the three genes. However, these results indicate that <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> suppress trunk expansion in a context-dependent manner and suggest they may provide information about trunk absence or presence during regeneration.</p><p>We investigated the anatomy of <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> and <italic>ptk7(RNAi);ndl-3(RNAi)</italic> regenerating trunk fragments to determine the extent of the axis under control of the three genes. We first examined the influence of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2,</italic> or <italic>ndl-3</italic> inhibition on expression of PCGs and tissue-specific genes marking A-P axial identity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A–B</xref>). Such <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> or <italic>ptk7(RNAi);ndl-3(RNAi)</italic> regenerating animals had normal anterior pole and brain regions (marked by <italic>notum, ndk</italic>) and a normal pre-pharyngeal region anterior to the original pharynx (marked by <italic>wnt2</italic> and novel gene <italic>SMU15014980</italic>), expansion of trunk-related peripharyngeal cells (expressing <italic>mmp1, FoxA</italic>, and SMU15007112), a reduced domain of PCGs expressed in the posterior (<italic>wnt11-1, fzd-4-1</italic> and <italic>Abd-Ba</italic>), and normal expression of <italic>wnt1</italic> at the posterior pole. We performed additional examinations of the brain (marked by <italic>chat</italic> and <italic>cintillo)</italic> and far posterior (marked by <italic>wnt11-2</italic>) in <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals and found no apparent differences compared to control animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1A–B</xref>). Thus, <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> normally promote anterior tail identity at the expense of the trunk and do not strongly affect head or tail formation. Both the pre-existing and ectopic pharynx were capable of regeneration after amputation by sodium azide treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adler et al., 2014</xref>), suggesting that <italic>wntP-2/ptk7</italic> signaling acts in part to limit the size of the trunk region within the posterior rather than only functioning to position the anterior extent of newly made trunk tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). We next inhibited <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> in a regenerating sexual strain of <italic>S. mediterranea</italic> that forms reproductive organs posterior to the pharynx upon attainment of appropriate size. Such animals formed both an ectopic pharynx and ectopic reproductive organs marked by <italic>laminin</italic> and <italic>dmd-1</italic> expression respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Chong et al., 2013</xref>), indicating <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> regulate trunk regionalization beyond only control of pharynx and mouth formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1C</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.009</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title><italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> control tail-versus-trunk identity.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) In situ hybridizations to detect A-P tissue regionalization in control and <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> and <italic>ptk7(RNAi);ndl-3(RNAi)</italic> regenerating trunk fragments fixed 21 days after head and tail amputation, marking the anterior and head region (<italic>ndk, wnt2</italic>), prepharyngeal region (novel gene SMU15014980), trunk (novel gene SMU15007112, <italic>mmp1, foxA</italic>), posterior (<italic>wnt11-1, fzd4-1, Abd-Ba</italic>), and the anterior and posterior poles (<italic>wnt1, notum</italic>). All panels represent 100% of at least 6 animals stained. Arrow, ectopic trunk gene expression. Brackets, decrease in size of tail domain. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantitation of domain size changes from experiments described in (<bold>A</bold>), measured as length of domain normalized to body length. <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> and <italic>ptk7(RNAi);ndl-3(RNAi)</italic> regenerating trunk fragments had increased sizes of trunk domains marked by expression of <italic>mmp1,</italic> foxA and SMU15007112, and decreased sizes of tail domains marked by expression of <italic>wnt11-1</italic> and <italic>fzd4-1</italic> with little to no change to other domains. Asterisks, p&lt;0.05 by 2-tailed t-test. (<bold>C</bold>) Both the pre-existing and ectopic pharynx in <italic>wntP-2(RNAi);ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals regenerated (4/4 animals) after amputation with brief sodium azide treatment, using FISH to mark the gut (<italic>porcupine</italic>, green) and mouth and pharynx (<italic>laminin</italic>, red). Asterisk, pre-existing pharynx; arrows, ectopic pharynx, arrowhead, ectopic mouth. (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals form ectopic <italic>FoxA+</italic> cells by day 7 of regeneration. Bars, 100 (<bold>D</bold>), 200 (<bold>A</bold>), or 300 (<bold>C</bold>) microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.009">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.009</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig3-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.010</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Additional histological analysis of <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> and animals.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) In situ hybridizations as in 2A showing normal expression of <italic>chat, mag-1</italic>, and <italic>wntl11-2</italic>, but reduced expression domain of <italic>fzd-4-1</italic> in <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals 18 days after head and tail amputation. (<bold>B</bold>, left) Co-inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> did not affect numbers of <italic>cintillo+</italic> neurons of the lateral brain region in day 21 regenerating head fragments or trunk fragments, (B, right) with quantifications of cell number normalized to animal area. Anterior, top. (<bold>C</bold>) Control sexual strain animals regenerate to have a single pharynx (asterisk, <italic>laminin</italic> expression) and a penis papilla (double arrow, <italic>dmd-1</italic> expression) within the trunk (8/8 animals), whereas <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals regenerated to form an ectopic <italic>laminin+</italic> pharynx (arrow, 7/7 animals) and ectopic <italic>dmd-1</italic>-expressing tissues (3/7 animals). Bars, 400 microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.010">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.010</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig3-figsupp1-v2"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>The pharynx is formed from <italic>FoxA+</italic> precursors derived from <italic>smedwi-1+</italic> neoblasts. Because inhibition of trunk identity genes produced an ectopic pharynx, we reasoned this structure likely arose from <italic>FoxA+</italic> progenitor cells. Indeed, <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals regenerating an ectopic pharynx produced an ectopic domain of <italic>FoxA+</italic> cells at a time (7 days of regeneration) prior to appearance of a fully formed ectopic pharynx (14 days of regeneration) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). Expression domains of <italic>ptk7</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>) and <italic>wntP-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Petersen and Reddien, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gurley et al., 2010</xref>) can be altered by amputation independently of neoblasts, so we suggest these genes likely function to regulate axis organization upstream of controlling neoblast fates.</p><p>The unidirectional nature of these axis patterning phenotypes as expansion of trunk at the expense of tail identity prompted us to determine more precisely the nature of the regionalized expression of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> mRNAs. Visual inspection of colorimetric in situ hybridizations suggested that <italic>ndl-3, ptk7,</italic> and <italic>wntP-</italic>2 are expressed in overlapping domains along the anteroposterior axis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). We verified this interpretation by quantifying the staining intensity of colorimetric in situ hybridizations along a lateral region running from head to tail (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). <italic>ndl-3</italic> staining intensity was maximal in the anterior in a region of graded <italic>ptk7</italic> staining. <italic>ptk7</italic> staining was maximal in the trunk region in which <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> staining form opposing gradients. <italic>wntP-2</italic> staining was maximal in the posterior tail in a region of relatively less <italic>ptk7</italic> expression. The graded expression detected in this manner could arise from regional differences in the abundance of cells that uniquely express each factor or in regulation of cells that express combinations of the three genes. To test these models, we performed triple FISH to simultaneously detect expression of all three genes in eight domains along the head-tail axis, which broadly confirmed the regionalized expression behavior of anterior/pre-pharyngeal maximal <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression, trunk maximal <italic>ptk7</italic> expression, and tail maximal <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). We sought to verify this trend quantitatively and segmented the images to examine cells expressing any of the three genes (see Materials and Methods) then determined the mean FISH intensity for each gene per cell. This demonstrated that regions of maximal expression of <italic>ndl-3, ptk7,</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> are comprised of cells with high expression of these genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). We next examined pairwise comparisons of expression of each gene across the body axis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>). This approach identified cells that co-express <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> (in particular in head-to trunk proximal regions R3-R5, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>), <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> (head-to-trunk regions R2-R4), and <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> (trunk-to-tail regions R5-R7). We explored whether this approach could identify the spatial distribution of discrete states of cells expressing all combinations of the three genes. We pooled the cell-based expression data across all regions to determine an approximate threshold to define higher versus lower expression for each gene, then assigned each measured cell into one of eight expression classes representing each combination of high versus low expression of each <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> and determined their distribution across the head-tail axis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement1A–C</xref>). This approach identified domains enriched for each expression state, finding a cohort with high <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression and low <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression in the far posterior, a cohort co-expressing <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> in the anterior tail and trunk regions, a cohort only expressing <italic>ptk7</italic> and not <italic>wntP-2</italic> or <italic>ndl-3</italic> centered in the trunk, cohorts of triple-positive cells and <italic>ptk7+ndl-</italic>3+ cells in the pre-pharyngeal region, and cohort of <italic>ndl-3+</italic> cells in the anterior. These results suggest that a complexity of PCG cell expression states populate regions of the body axis and that a region of high <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> expression exists in the anterior tail at a location where these two genes act together to suppress trunk identity.<fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.011</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title><italic>ndl-3, ptk7</italic>, and <italic>wntP-2</italic> are expressed in a graded fashion in domains along the anteroposterior axis.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) In situ hybridizations showing body-wide graded expression of <italic>ptk7</italic> centered in the trunk, <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression in a gradient from the posterior and <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression in a graded fashion from the anterior. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantitation of colorimetric in situ hybridization staining across the body axis. 4–6 planarians stained as in (<bold>A</bold>) were imaged on a dissecting microscope, the images were inverted and then analyzed for position-specific staining intensity along a lateral domain depicted in the diagram (dotted line with arrow showing directionality). To compare animals of different lengths, position was normalized to length of this domain and signal intensity was normalized such that the minimum and maximum values across each animal were 0 and 1, respectively, and average intensity at each region was determined for animals stained with each probe treatment computed followed by obtaining average intensity, with bars showing standard deviations. (<bold>C</bold>) Triple FISH showing expression of <italic>ndl-3</italic> (red)<italic>, ptk7</italic> (blue), and <italic>wntP-2</italic> (green) mRNA. Panels are maximum projections from a stack of seven 1-micron thick confocal images taken at 40x along the body axis at the regions represented in the cartoon, then adjusted for brightness and contrast uniformly for each channel across the image series. m, mouth. Bars, 100 microns. (<bold>D–E</bold>) Quantification of FISH signal intensity for cells identified in images shown in (<bold>C</bold>). 3-color images were segmented by merging all three channels to define a set of cells in each region with <italic>wntP-2, ndl-</italic>3 and/or <italic>ptk7</italic> expression and this mask used to measure mean FISH signal intensity for each cell. (<bold>D</bold>) Scatter and box plots showing expression of <italic>ndl-3</italic> highest in the anterior, expression of <italic>ptk7</italic> highest in the trunk and tail, and highest <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression in the posterior. (<bold>E</bold>) Plots comparing pairwise FISH signal intensity between the indicated genes across eight body axis regions (R1-R8) as in (<bold>C</bold>). Note the existence of cells expressing both <italic>ndl-3</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> (R3-R5), <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> (R3-R4), and <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> (R5-R7). Bars, 100 (<bold>C</bold>) or 200 (<bold>A</bold>) microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.011">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.011</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig4-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.012</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Distribution of ptk7, wntP-2 and ndl-3 expression states across the body axis.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Mean fluorescence intensity of cells from all regions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref> were combined and density histograms plotted to determine a cutoff (dotted line=55 in arbitrary units) for higher versus lower expression of <italic>ptk7, wntP-</italic>2, and <italic>ndl-3.</italic> Cells within each region shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref> were assigned membership in one of eight classes defined by high ('hi') or low (unstated) expression of each of the three genes (1: <italic>wntP-2</italic><sup>hi</sup> only, 2: <italic>ptk7</italic><sup>hi</sup><italic>wntP-2</italic><sup>hi</sup>, 3: <italic>ptk7<sup>hi</sup></italic> only, 4: <italic>ptk7<sup>hi</sup>wntP-2<sup>hi</sup>ndl-3<sup>hi</sup></italic>, 5: <italic>ptk7<sup>hi</sup>ndl-3<sup>hi</sup></italic>, 6: <italic>wntP-2<sup>hi</sup>ndl-3<sup>hi</sup></italic>, 7: <italic>ndl-3<sup>hi</sup></italic>, 8: all 3 genes low). Class membership was plotted as a fraction of all cells measured in each region (<bold>B</bold>) and as a scatterplot of all cells examined (<bold>C</bold>). By these criteria, several classes of cells expressing combinations of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> exist and are distributed in domains along the body axis. The tail tip has the highest frequency of <italic>wntP-2+</italic> only cells, whereas anterior tail and trunk regions have a comparatively greater fraction of <italic>wntP-2+ptk7+</italic> cells. The above analysis was repeated for a range of high/low expression cutoffs between 30 and 75, resulting in similar the same trends, with lower thresholds resulting in fewer cells assigned as <italic>ptk7<sup>lo</sup>wntP-2<sup>lo</sup>ndl3<sup>lo</sup></italic>and more cells as <italic>ptk7<sup>hi</sup>wntP-2<sup>hi</sup>ndl-3<sup>hi</sup></italic>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.012">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.012</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig4-figsupp1-v2"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>We examined the involvement of canonical Wnt signaling on expression of these factors, as this pathway has multiple functions in patterning the primary body axis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Petersen and Reddien, 2009</xref>). <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> inhibition in uninjured animals severely reduced the expression of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>), consistent with prior analyses of their expression requirements in regeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Owen et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Reuter et al., 2015</xref>). We additionally inhibited <italic>APC</italic>, encoding an intracellular negative regulator of beta-catenin stability and examined regenerating animals for expression of the three trunk regulatory genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>). Such animals regenerated anterior tails that expressed <italic>wntP-2</italic> throughout, that expressed <italic>ptk7</italic> strongly in a region near the amputation plane and away from the terminus, and that lacked <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression. These results suggest that beta-catenin upregulation can be sufficient for tail axis formation in conjunction with <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> expression. Taken together, normal levels of beta-catenin signaling are important for the normal expression of <italic>pkt7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic>.<fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.013</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Trunk control genes likely signal independently of <italic>β-catenin-1</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) In situ hybridizations show reduced expression of <italic>ptk7</italic> (11/11 animals), <italic>wntP-2</italic> (6/6 animals), and <italic>ndl-3</italic> (6/6 animals) after 8 days (<italic>wntP-2, ndl-3</italic>) or 19 days (<italic>ptk7</italic>) of <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> RNAi in uninjured animals. (<bold>B</bold>) In situ hybridizations showing reduction of <italic>axin-B</italic> expression after 11 days of <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> RNAi (14/14 animals) but not after inhibition of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> (14/14 animals) or <italic>ndl-3</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> (14/14 animals). Bars, 400 microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.013">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.013</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig5-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.014</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Examining the effect of <italic>APC</italic> RNAi on expression of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic>.</title><p><italic>APC(RNAi)</italic> regenerating animals formed a domain of ectopic <italic>ptk7</italic> (8/8 animals) and <italic>wntP-2</italic> (9/9 animals) expression in the anterior tail. The ectopic tail appears to have a domain expressing <italic>wntP-2</italic> and not <italic>ptk7</italic> at the terminus and a domain expressing both <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> near the amputation site. Such animals form an ectopic anterior pharynx likely as the consequence of tail formation, and this expressed <italic>ndl-3, ptk7,</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic>. Bars, 400 microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.014">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.014</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig5-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig5s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.015</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title><italic>fzd1/2/7</italic> and <italic>dvl-2</italic> inhibition causes ectopic pharynx and mouth formation in the posterior.</title><p>The indicated dsRNA was delivered to animals by injection prior to amputation, 23 days of regeneration and staining for <italic>laminin</italic> expression to detect pharyngeal tissues. <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic> inhibition (4/6 animals) caused formation of an ectopic pharynx similar to <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and/or <italic>ndl-3</italic> inhibition. <italic>dvl-2</italic> dsRNA enhanced the <italic>ptk7</italic> ectopic pharynx phenotype (9/9 animals). Bars, 300 microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.015">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.015</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig5-figsupp2-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig5s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.016</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Testing planar cell polarity genes for involvement in trunk patterning.</title><p>Regenerating trunk fragments undergoing RNAi as indicated and stained by FISH with a <italic>laminin</italic> riboprobe to detect the pharynx and mouth. Inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> along with <italic>vangl1</italic> (8/8 animals), <italic>vangl2</italic> (4/4 animals), <italic>DAAM1</italic> (6/6 animals) and <italic>ROCK</italic> (6/6 animals) did not suppress or enhance defects due to <italic>ptk7</italic> inhibition alone. Bars, 300 microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.016">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.016</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig5-figsupp3-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig5s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.017</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title><italic>ptk7, wntP-2,</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> inhibition do not influence <italic>axin-B</italic> expression and are not modified by <italic>APC</italic> inhibition.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) qPCR detecting expression of <italic>axin-B</italic> normalized to <italic>ubiquilin</italic> on RNA purified from day 10 regenerating animals after the indicated dsRNA treatments. <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> inhibition reduced relative <italic>axin-B</italic> mRNA abundance, but <italic>ptk7+wntP-2</italic> dsRNA and <italic>ptk7</italic> + <italic>ndl-3</italic> dsRNA had no effect. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>ptk7</italic>+ <italic>wntP-2</italic> RNAi did not alter expression of the <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> target gene <italic>teashirt</italic> in animals 18 days after head and tail amputation (3/3 animals). (<bold>C</bold>) APC inhibition did not detectably affect the frequency of ectopic pharynx formation due to <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> RNAi (p=1.000, Fisher’s exact test) (animals that regenerated an ectopic pharynx: 0/10 control fragments, 0/10 <italic>APC(RNAi)</italic> fragments, 7/9 <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi);control(RNAi)</italic> fragments and 7/10 <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi);APC(RNAi)</italic> fragments). Bars, 200 microns. Anterior, top.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.017">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.017</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig5-figsupp4-v2"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>We next examined candidates for signaling that could occur downstream of <italic>wntP-</italic>2, <italic>ptk7</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3.</italic> Ptk7 proteins can signal through several pathways, including as a coreceptor for Wnt/Frizzled signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Lhoumeau et al., 2011</xref>). The results of our <italic>ptk7</italic> RNAi enhancement screen suggested a candidate molecular pathway in which <italic>wntP-2</italic> signals through <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic> to suppress trunk identity. We verified that RNAi of <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic> alone resulted in ectopic mouth and pharynx formation similar to <italic>ptk7</italic> and/or <italic>wntP-2</italic> inhibition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2A</xref>). Similarly, we verified that <italic>Dvl-2</italic> but not <italic>Dvl-1</italic> could interact with <italic>ptk7</italic> genetically, suggesting the involvement of <italic>Dvl-2</italic> in trunk suppression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2B</xref>). Ptk7 proteins can act in planar cell polarization so we tested for possible functional interactions between <italic>ptk7</italic> and components of the Planar Cell Polarity pathway <italic>vangl1, vangl2, DAAM1</italic> and <italic>ROCK</italic> but inhibition of these genes did not increase or decrease the occurrence of ectopic mouth or pharynx phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s3">Figure 5—figure supplement 3</xref>). We additionally tested whether a downstream step in trunk suppression could be promotion or inhibition of beta-catenin activity. However, co-inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> or <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> had no detectable effect on expression of beta-catenin-dependent transcripts <italic>axin-B</italic> and <italic>teashirt</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s4">Figure 5—figure supplement 4A–B</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Owen et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Reuter et al., 2015</xref>). <italic>β-catenin-1(RNAi)</italic> animals lose trunk regional identity and their pharynx while becoming completely anteriorized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Iglesias et al., 2008</xref>), so we tested for possible functional interactions between beta-catenin signaling and trunk control genes by inhibiting <italic>ptk7/wntP-2</italic> along with <italic>APC</italic>. We could not detect any enhancement or suppression of ectopic pharynx formation in that assay, further suggesting independence between <italic>ptk7/wntP-2</italic> and <italic>APC/β-catenin-1</italic> signaling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s4">Figure 5—figure supplement 4C</xref>). These observations are consistent with the clear distinction between the <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> RNAi phenotype of ectopic head production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gurley et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Iglesias et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>) as compared to the <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> and <italic>ptk7(RNAi);ndl-3(</italic>RNAi) phenotypes of ectopic trunk formation without affecting the identity of the anterior and posterior poles. Together, these results strongly suggest that trunk regionalization can be separable from pole identity and that <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> likely do not operate exclusively through <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> to pattern the trunk and tail.</p><p>Regeneration can involve the re-definition of positional identity within pre-existing tissues, but the mechanisms controlling this process are unclear. We examined the expression and activities of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> in forming a mouth and pharynx (expressing <italic>laminin)</italic> within the pre-existing tail tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>). In amputated tail fragments, the mouth and pharynx were formed during the first 5 days of regeneration, with expression of <italic>laminin</italic> evident as early as 3 days. <italic>wntP-</italic>2 was initially expressed throughout the amputated tail, but its expression restricted posteriorly starting around day 2, reaching a minimum around day 4, and re-establishing to intact proportions around day 7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Petersen and Reddien, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gurley et al., 2010</xref>). <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression was initially absent in the tail fragments, emerged at day 1 in the far anterior then spread posterior to occupy the anterior half of the regenerating fragments by 4 days. <italic>ptk7</italic> expression remained broad in tail fragments through early times in regeneration and re-established a trunk-proximal domain evident by 7 days. Notably, the position of the newly regenerated pharynx correlated with a domain in which <italic>wntP-</italic>2 expression was reduced and <italic>ndl-3</italic> was elevated.<fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.018</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title><italic>ptk7</italic> acts with <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> to specify trunk position in regeneration.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Cartoon shows regions of trunk control gene expression and in uninjured animals. In situ hybridizations of regenerating tail fragments showing that pharynx formation (marked by <italic>laminin</italic> expression) coincides with early reduction of <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression and increase in <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression. <italic>ptk7</italic> is expressed broadly and re-establishes a trunk-centered gradient by 7 days. All images represent at least 4/4 animals probed except <italic>laminin</italic> (d0) and <italic>ptk7</italic> (d0, d3 and d4) representing 3/3 animals probed. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals form a single pharynx located too far posteriorly (7/8 animals, graph shows average distance between posterior pole and <italic>laminin</italic> expression domain normalized to animal length as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1A–B</xref>, error bars are standard deviations and asterisks shows p&lt;0.05 by a 2-tailed t-test. (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression is reduced in <italic>ndl-3(RNAi)</italic> regenerating tail fragments (10/14 animals). (D-E) <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression is expanded posteriorly in (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> regenerating tail fragments by 7 days after amputation (4/5 animals) and in (<bold>E</bold>) intact animals after 12 or 17 days of RNAi (25/28 animals). (<bold>F</bold>) Control or <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals were stained for <italic>ndl-3</italic> and <italic>collagen</italic> expression after 17 days of RNAi and optical sections were imaged of the body-wall musculature in the region posterior to the pre-existing pharynx. Simultaneous inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> increased the frequency of <italic>ndl-3+collagen+</italic> cells versus total <italic>ndl-3+</italic> cells found in the tail region (41 of 63 cells in <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals versus 7 of 32 cells scored in control animals, p&lt;0.0001 by Fisher’s exact test). Bars, 200 (<bold>A–D</bold>) or 400 (<bold>E</bold>) microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.018">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.018</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="jpeg" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig6-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.019</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title><italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> participate in positioning the pharynx during tail fragment regeneration.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Assay design used to measure pharynx position in (<bold>B</bold>–<bold>C</bold>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref> (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of pharynx placement phenotypes in 7 day regenerating tail fragments after inhibition of <italic>wntP-2, ptk7</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> singly or in pairwise combinations as indicated. The strongest effects were observed after simultaneous inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> or <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic>. Bars, averages; asterisks indicate p&lt;0.05 by 2-tailed t-test. (<bold>C</bold>) Dilution of <italic>ptk7+wntP-2</italic> dsRNA with control dsRNA caused a progressively weaker pharynx placement phenotype, suggesting a gradation of their activities affect trunk position. (<bold>D</bold>, left) <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals stained with riboprobes to several regionally expressed genes shows such animals form normal anterior and prepharyngeal regions, but have posteriorly shifted trunk and tail gene expression domains quantified in (<bold>D</bold>, right). Graphs show averages of at least 7 samples, error bars show standard deviations, and asterisks indicate p&lt;0.05 by two-tailed t-test. Bars, 200 microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.019">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.019</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig6-figsupp1-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig6s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.020</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Determining critical period for <italic>ptk7/wntP-2</italic> signaling in pharynx placement.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Measurements of pharynx position as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref> at selected days after amputation in regenerating control or <italic>ptk7(RNAi)</italic> regenerating tail fragments treated with dsRNA for three days prior to amputation or (<bold>B</bold>) injected with control or both <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> dsRNA only at the indicated days with respect to the day of amputation (day 0). Injection of <italic>wntP-2+ptk7</italic> dsRNA as late as 1–2 days after amputation can posteriorize the position of the regenerated pharynx. Graphs show averages of at least 4 samples, error bars show standard deviations, and asterisks indicate p&lt;0.05 by two-tailed t-test. Bars, 200 microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.020">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.020</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig6-figsupp2-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig6s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.021</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Examining the influence of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> on each other’s expression.</title><p>(<bold>A–C</bold>) Examining intact animals for regulatory interactions among trunk control genes. Uninjured animals fed with the indicated dsRNAs for two weeks prior to fixation and staining by (<bold>A</bold>) WISH or (<bold>B</bold>) FISH to examine effects on expression of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> or <italic>ndl-3</italic>. No treatment caused strongly increased or reduced expression except for <italic>ptk7</italic>+<italic>wntP-2</italic> RNAi which caused ectopic expression of <italic>ndl-3</italic> in the anterior tail region (A, 5/8 animals; B, 12/15 animals). (<bold>C</bold>) Animals were treated with dsRNA as in A and B, then analyzed by qPCR for expression changes to <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> following RNAi. Inhibition of each gene caused similar knockdown in either single or double-RNAi contexts. <italic>wntP-2</italic> RNAi caused a weak but statistically significant reduction to <italic>ptk7</italic> transcript levels, similar to WISH detection (<bold>A</bold>). <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic> RNAi did not significantly alter expression of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2,</italic> or <italic>ndl-3</italic>. Bars, 400 microns (<bold>A</bold>), 300 microns (<bold>B</bold>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.021">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.021</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig6-figsupp3-v2"/></fig><fig id="fig6s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.022</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>Measurements of the influence of trunk control genes on <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression in tail fragment regeneration.</title><p>(<bold>A–B</bold>) Animals were treated with the indicated dsRNAs for three days prior to amputation, regenerating tail fragments were fixed 7 days later, and stained for (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression or (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression. Measurements were made from the posterior tip of the regenerating animal to (<bold>A</bold>) the anterior edge of <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression or (<bold>B</bold>) the posterior edge of <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression then normalized to animal length. Graphs show averages and error bars are standard deviations. Asterisks indicate p&lt;0.05 by a 2-tailed t-test. Bars, 200 microns.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.022">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.022</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig6-figsupp4-v2"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>We next examined the functions of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> in positional information control within regenerating tail fragments. In tail fragments, inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic> caused a posterior shift to the location of the mouth and pharynx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1A</xref>), an effect enhanced by co-inhibition of <italic>wntP-2</italic> or <italic>ndl-3</italic> though not caused by <italic>wntP-2</italic> or <italic>ndl-3</italic> inhibition alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1B</xref>). Reduced doses of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> dsRNA resulted in intermediate placement phenotypes, and the distributions of placement phenotypes were not biphasic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1C</xref>), suggesting the activity of these genes could regulate pharynx position in a graded fashion rather than controlling a switch between two alternate organ locations. <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> tail fragments regenerated with posteriorly restricted expression of <italic>fzd4-1</italic> and <italic>wnt11-1</italic> and posteriorly expanded expression of <italic>sFRP-2</italic>, without strongly affecting the positioning of the brain (<italic>ndk</italic>) or pre-pharyngeal regions (<italic>SMU15014980</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2D</xref>). Together, these experiments suggest that <italic>ptk7,</italic> along with <italic>wntP-</italic>2 and <italic>ndl-3,</italic> has a primary activity in controlling the positioning of trunk/tail tissues in regeneration.</p><p>To examine the relationship between the expression and function of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> signaling in regional identity re-establishment, we analyzed the time of emergence and critical time for pharynx placement phenotypes in regenerating tail fragments. RNAi of <italic>ptk7</italic> for three days prior to tail amputation resulted in a posterior shift in the location of the newly formed <italic>laminin</italic> expression domain detected as early as 3 days of regeneration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2A</xref>). These results indicate that <italic>ptk7</italic> acts before day 3 of regeneration. To determine a lower bound for the latest time of action for trunk control genes, we performed timed delivery of dsRNA via injections performed at successive two-day intervals during regeneration then examined the position of the <italic>laminin</italic> expression domain 7 days after amputation. Injections of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> dsRNA only prior to amputation, or as late as day 1 and day 2, were capable of posteriorly shifting the <italic>laminin</italic> expression domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2B</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that <italic>ptk7/wntP-2</italic> signaling has functions in pharynx positioning after day 1 and before day 3, coinciding with the timing of <italic>wntP-2</italic>’s posterior restriction and <italic>ndl-3</italic>’s anterior expression. This occurs prior to the ultimate reestablishment of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression into finalized trunk, posterior, and anterior domains by 7–14 days, suggesting a separation between processes that control initial organ placement and ultimate proportion restoration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>).</p><p>The coordinate regulation of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> in regeneration led us to examine candidate transcriptional interactions among <italic>wntP-2, ndl-3,</italic> and <italic>ptk7.</italic> We did not detect strongly apparent changes to these expression domains after single inhibition of the other two genes by WISH, FISH or qPCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3A–C</xref>). We tested for possible mutual expression requirements in tail fragments, reasoning this might provide a sensitized context in which the expression domains normally undergo regulation. <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression was reduced in <italic>ndl-3(RNAi)</italic> tail fragments, particularly along the lateral edges (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>), and posteriorly restricted in <italic>ptk7(RNAi)</italic> regenerating tail fragments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s4">Figure 6—figure supplement 4A</xref>), suggesting that these genes can normally promote expression of <italic>wntP-2</italic> in regenerating tail fragments. By contrast, <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression was expanded posteriorly in <italic>ptk7(RNAi)</italic> and <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> tail fragments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s4">Figure 6—figure supplement 4B</xref>). We inhibited <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> in uninjured animals to determine whether this effect was specific for regenerating tail fragments. Such animals expressed <italic>ndl-3</italic> ectopically posterior to the pharynx at a time (by 12 days of homeostatic RNAi) prior to significant pharynx formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E–F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3A–B</xref>). Analysis of these ectopic <italic>ndl-3+</italic> cells by double-FISH revealed that the majority (41/63) co-expressed <italic>collagen</italic> and were located within the plane of the body-wall musculature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6F</xref>). These observations argue for a specific regulatory relationship in which <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> together suppress expression of <italic>ndl-3</italic> in the posterior. Alternatively, the nascent pharynx could exert influence over the expression of <italic>ndl-3</italic> in a manner indirectly controlled by <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic>’s suppression of pharynx identity. Together these experiments indicate <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> can directly or indirectly engage in regulatory interactions in homeostatic maintenance of tissue pattern and also in re-establishment of pattern in regeneration.</p></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>These experiments suggest a molecular model in which trunk identity and axis position are determined by low <italic>wntP-2</italic> activity signaling through the co-receptor <italic>ptk7</italic> and receptor <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic>, which together could provide competence for beta-catenin-independent outputs necessary for trunk and anterior tail patterning (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). <italic>ndl-3</italic> is expressed in the trunk region yet acts with the same sign as <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> to suppress posterior trunk expansion, either through a parallel or downstream process engaged in trunk suppression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>) or perhaps due to its ability under some circumstances to promote robust expression of <italic>wntP-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). In the tail region of uninjured animals and regenerating trunk fragments, high levels of <italic>wntP-2/ptk7</italic> activity prevent the acquisition of trunk identity and enable the formation of anterior tail tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>). By contrast, head fragments initially have lower expression of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic>, which could facilitate their formation of trunk tissue through regeneration. Amputated tail fragments would be expected to initially possess high levels of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> activity, but a regeneration expression regulatory program reduces <italic>wntP-2</italic> mRNA from the anterior to allow trunk regionalization to occur at an appropriate location. These models suggest that the expression status of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> could provide information about the presence or absence of pre-existing tissues used in determining regeneration outcomes. A previously proposed animal-wide gradient of <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Reuter et al., 2015</xref>) could set up the axis into distinct <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression domains refined by <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> repression of <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression. However, our experiments argue that a <italic>β-catenin-1</italic>-independent signaling output downstream of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> likely act to suppress trunk regional identity and thereby control placement of a trunk/tail boundary along the axis according to a gradation of their activities within the posterior. The identification of trunk expansion phenotypes independent of head/tail identity transformations suggests that whole-body regeneration involves a regulatory hierarchy of anterior/posterior pole formation followed by subsequent regional subdivision.<fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.023</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Model for <italic>wntP-2</italic>, <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> in control of patterning.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A candidate molecular pathway of action in which <italic>wntP-2</italic> signals through <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic> and <italic>Dvl-2</italic> to suppress trunk identity within the anterior tail region. The FGFRL <italic>ndl-3</italic> acts with the same sign as these components to suppress trunk regionalization and could act in a parallel pathway or modify the activity of the pathway through an unknown mechanism. <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> can inhibit <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression in the posterior of regenerating tail fragments and intact animals and <italic>ndl-3</italic> promotes <italic>wntP-2</italic> expression in regenerating tail fragments, suggesting the potential for feedback regulation within this pathway (not shown). <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> signaling is required upstream for expression of <italic>ptk7</italic>, <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> (not shown). (<bold>B</bold>) Model relating expression of pathway components to patterning functions. The highest region of expression co-expression of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> occurs in the anterior tail and trunk at a location where these genes prevent trunk fates in animals undergoing tissue homeostatic maintenance and in regenerating trunk fragments that form new tail tissues. By contrast, regenerating head fragments lack abundant co-expression of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic>, which we suggest is important for enabling the normal formation of trunk regional identity and regeneration of associated structures. Regenerating tail fragments would initially possess high levels of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> predicted to suppress trunk identity, but undergo a regeneration expression regulatory program that reduces <italic>wntP-2</italic> mRNA in this region, enabling trunk regeneration at a position that we suggest could be defined by a particular A-P location of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> activity present at an appropriate time in regeneration. According to this model, <italic>wntP-2/ptk7</italic> signaling provides information about the presence/absence of the trunk region used to control regeneration outcomes.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.12850.023">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12850.023</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-12850-fig7-v2"/></fig></p><p>Our results thus establish a link between Wnt, Ptk7 and FGFRL proteins in regeneration patterning and axis formation. In mice and zebrafish, Ptk7 deletion causes defects in axis formation including a lack of convergent extension within the trunk and tail and a mispolarized auditory epithelium in mice, similar to disruption of core planar cell polarity components that signal independently of beta-catenin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lu et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hayes et al., 2013</xref>). However, studies in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, zebrafish, <italic>Xenopus</italic> and mammalian tissue culture have found conflicting evidence that Ptk7 can also either promote (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Puppo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bin-Nun et al., 2014</xref>) or inhibit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Peradziryi et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hayes et al., 2013</xref>) beta-catenin-dependent signaling in a context-dependent manner. The regional identity defects we observe after <italic>ptk7</italic> RNAi in planarians are not obviously the result of defective planar cell orientations, are phenocopied by inhibition of a Wnt gene, and do not globally affect beta-catenin transcriptional targets or beta-catenin-dependent processes. We suggest that Ptk7 proteins can control tissue fate through an alternate mechanism, perhaps by coordinating the activities of cell cohorts within a field. Planarians and most other animals have expression of multiple Wnts in posterior domains, pointing to their ancient use in organizing the primary body axis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Petersen and Reddien, 2009</xref>). The use of Ptk7 proteins for trunk/tail regionalization could therefore have an ancient origin and allow posterior Wnts to produce distinct signaling outcomes for combinatorial pattern control.</p><p>We also find with <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> a second example in planarians of shared patterning regulation between Wnt and FGFRL factors. Whereas <italic>wntP-2/wnt11-5/wnt4b</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> restrict the domain of the trunk, <italic>wntA/wnt11-6/wnt4a</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Kobayashi et al., 2007</xref>) and <italic>nou darake</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Cebrià et al., 2002</xref>) restrict the domain of the head and brain. Intriguingly, in both cases, the FGFRL genes have most prominent expression in the anterior but act with the same sign as the Wnt genes to promote more posterior identity outside of the domain of their own expression. In mammals, FGFRL1 and Wnt4 are each required for formation of the metanephric kidney from intermediate mesoderm, suggesting this positive regulatory relationship is conserved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Stark et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Gerber et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Pattern restoration in regeneration has been proposed to involve intercalation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">French et al., 1976</xref>) or progressive specification of adjacent regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Roensch et al., 2013</xref>) to restore positional values across a field disrupted by amputation. In planarians, asymmetric wound-induced expression of <italic>notum</italic> provides information about wound site directionality used to program anterior-versus-posterior pole fates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Petersen and Reddien, 2011</xref>). By contrast, we find genes encoding signaling molecules that are constitutively expressed in body-wide mRNA gradients and are used for control of positional information in regeneration. Graded expression of paracrine factors across fields of cells could enable patterning over the large length-scales necessary for adult regeneration. The interactions between this tissue-wide positional information present at the time of injury, combined with wound-induced directional cues, could account for robust pattern control in regeneration.</p><p>Note added in proof: while this manuscript was under review, Sureda-Gómez et al. reported that wnt11-5 RNAi causes a pharynx duplication phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Sureda-Gómez et al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Planarian culture and irradiation treatments</title><p>Asexual and sexual strain <italic>Schmidtea mediterranea</italic> were maintained in 1x Montjuic salts between 18–20°C. Gamma irradiation (6000 Rads) was performed with a Cesium-137 source irradiator at least 24 hr prior to amputation to eliminate all dividing cells.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Gene sequences</title><p><italic>Smed-protein tyrosine kinase-7</italic> (<italic>ptk7)</italic> was identified through homology searches through BLAST on a planarian transcriptome database (Planmine, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://planmine.mpi-cbg.de">http://planmine.mpi-cbg.de</ext-link>) identifying a <italic>Schmidtea mediterranea ptk7</italic> homolog dd_Smed_v6_6999_0_1. <italic>Smed-wntP-2</italic> was described previously and cloned using primers 5’-TTAAATGTTCTAAGCCAAAACAACA-3’ and 5’-AAAACTTTTATGATCAATCTGAATGC-3’ (NCBI accession number: EU29663) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Petersen and Reddien, 2009</xref>). <italic>Smed-ndl-3</italic> was cloned using primers 5’-TTATTGACAGTAGGAACCAAAGCC-3’ and 5’-ATCCTGAATCAAGTCAACGCCA-3’ for dsRNA and riboprobe synthesis as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Rink et al., 2009</xref>). Unless otherwise noted, riboprobes for a 4313-bp fragment of <italic>ptk7</italic> were made from a PCR product cloned by RT-PCR into pGEM-T-easy vector using the primers 5’-GTACTACCTGCCGAAAGTATACA-3’, 5’-GCGCATATTCTATTGTGTAACGC-3’. In Figure S7, <italic>ptk7</italic> riboprobe was synthesized from a 2068-bp fragment using the primers 5’-CGACTGTTAGTTGGTTTATGGAC-3’, 5’-ACTTGCCTTCTCTTTGAGCG-3’. SMU15014980 and SMU15007112 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Robb et al., 2015</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smedgd.stowers.org">http://smedgd.stowers.org</ext-link>) expression patterns were identified by in situ hybridization screening from genes defined as BPKG22168 and BPKG1900 by prior RNA-seq studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Labbé et al., 2012</xref>). SMU15014980 was cloned using the primers 5’-GGATGCTTTTGCATTTTGCT -3’ and 5’-ATTGGCAAGAAAGCCATGAG -3’. SMU15007112 was cloned using the primers 5’-CCCCGTGTGGATATTTCAGT -3’, 5’-AGCAAAATCGGTTCTCCGTA -3’. For inhibition of <italic>ptk7</italic>, dsRNA was synthesized from a 1412-bp cDNA fragment cloned by RT-PCR into pGEM vector using the primers 5’-TGCTGGAAATAGTCTGTTGCAT-3’, 5’-AAGATGGAACCCCAATAGCC-3’. Control dsRNA was generated from a 1527-bp fragment of <italic>Photinus pyralis luciferase</italic> from the pGL3-control vector (Promega, Fitchburg, WI USA) (primers 5’-TATCCGCTGGAAGATGGAAC-3′, 5′-CGGTACTTCGTCCACAAACA- 3′). <italic>wntP-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Petersen and Reddien, 2009</xref>), <italic>ndl-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Rink et al., 2009</xref>), <italic>laminin</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adler et al., 2014</xref>), <italic>porcupine</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Rink et al., 2009</xref>), <italic>dmd-1, FoxA</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adler et al., 2014</xref>), <italic>smedwi-1, ndk, wnt1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Petersen and Reddien, 2009</xref>), <italic>collagen</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Witchley et al., 2013</xref>), <italic>chat, mag-1, cintillo</italic>, <italic>β-catenin-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>), <italic>APC</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gurley et al., 2008</xref>), <italic>wnt11-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>), <italic>wnt11-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>), <italic>wnt11-4/wntP-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>), <italic>wnt2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>), <italic>wnt5</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gurley et al., 2010</xref>), <italic>fzd4-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Petersen and Reddien, 2008</xref>), <italic>fzd4-2, fzd-1/2/7, Dvl-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gurley et al., 2008</xref>), <italic>Dvl-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gurley et al., 2008</xref>), <italic>axin-B, teashirt</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Owen et al., 2015</xref>), <italic>notum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Petersen and Reddien, 2011</xref>), <italic>sfrp-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gurley et al., 2010</xref>), <italic>sfrp-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gurley et al., 2010</xref>), <italic>sfrp-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gurley et al., 2010</xref>), <italic>DAAM1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Beane et al., 2012</xref>), <italic>ROCK</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Beane et al., 2012</xref>), <italic>vangl1, vangl2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Almuedo-Castillo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Beane et al., 2012</xref>), and <italic>ndl-4</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Rink et al., 2009</xref>) riboprobes and dsRNAs were described previously.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Fixations and stainings</title><p>Animals were fixed and stained as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Pearson et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">King and Newmark, 2013</xref>). In brief, animals were killed in 5% N-acetyl-cysteine in 1xPBS for 5 min and then fixed in formaldehyde for 20 min at room temperature. Subsequently, animals were bleached overnight (~16 hr) in 6% hydrogen peroxide in methanol on a light box. Digoxigenin- or fluorescein-labeled riboprobes were synthesized as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Pearson et al., 2009</xref>). Colorimetric (NBT/BCIP) or fluorescence in situ hybridizations were performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Pearson et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">King and Newmark, 2013</xref>). For FISH, blocking solution was MABT with 10% horse serum and 10% western blot blocking reagent (Roche) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">King and Newmark, 2013</xref>). Riboprobes were detected using anti-Dig-HRP (1:2000), anti-FL-HRP (1:2000), anti-DNP (1:2000), or anti-Dig-AP (1:4000) antibodies. Hoechst 33,342 (Invitrogen) was used at 1:500 as counterstain. Images of colorimetric staining were acquired using a Leica M210F scope with a Leica DFC295 camera and adjusted for brightness and contrast. Fluorescence imaging was performed on a Leica DM5500B compound microscope with Optigrid structured illumination system for optical sectioning or a Leica SPE confocal microscope. Images are maximum projections of a z-series with adjustments to brightness and contrast using Photoshop or ImageJ. Concanavalin A conjugated to AlexaFluor 488 (Invitrogen) was used to stain the epidermis as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Zayas et al., 2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Image analysis</title><p>For <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>, animals stained with NBT/BCIP for detection of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> were visualized with a Leica M210F dissecting microscope. Images were inverted and an intensity profile obtained from a segmented line drawn along a lateral region running from the anterior to posterior of the animal with a width approximately 1/6 of the animal width using ImageJ ('plot profile'). To make comparisons of intensity plots across animals of different sizes, position along the segmented line was normalized to its length. Background, taken as the minimum intensity along this profile, was subtracted, and the resulting values were normalized to the maximum intensity along this profile. This axis was divided into 100 equal sized bins to allow comparing intensity measurements across animals of different sizes, and the average normalized intensity was determined for each bin. These plots were compared for 4–6 animals stained with each riboprobe to generate an average and standard deviation of position- and global intensity-normalized in situ hybridization signal and plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>, Triple FISH was used to simultaneously detect expression of ptk7, wntP-2, and ndl-3 by obtaining maximum projections of 1-micron thick confocal images taken at 40x at 8 regions. The resulting three-color images were processed in ImageJ to convert to a merged grayscale image used for automated threshholding ('Auto Threshhold' Li's Minimum Cross Entropy method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Li, 1998</xref>]) and segmentation ('Analyze particles') using empirically optimized parameters (size=0.06–0.40 inch^2 in the image, corresponding to 24–166 microns^2 in the sample, and circularity 0–1.00). The resulting segmented areas were manually inspected to verify that the majority surrounded individual cells. Mean intensity per segmented area was determined for each channel and plotted using R (ggplot2) in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1A</xref>, density histograms were plotted to determine a cutoff for estimating high and low expression of each gene within each analyzed cell and used to classify cells as expression positive or negative. This assigned each cell to one of 8 classes plotted as a fraction of total cells in each region in a histogram in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1B</xref> and as a scatterplot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1C</xref>. Similar trends were observed when threshold was taken to be any of 10 different threshold values between intensities of 30 and 75.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>RNAi protocols</title><p>RNAi treatments were performed either by dsRNA injection or feeding. dsRNA was synthesized as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Petersen and Reddien, 2011</xref>). Unless otherwise noted, RNAi by injection was performed using a Drummond microinjector to deliver 5 x 32 nL dsRNA on three consecutive days, followed by transverse amputations and regeneration for the indicated number of days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1D,E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s2">Figure 1—figure supplement 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D,E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A,D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1A,B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figures 5—figure supplement 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A–D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">2A</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s4">4</xref>). For experiments involving RNAi by feeding, animals were given a mixture of liver paste and in vitro transcribed dsRNA, as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Rouhana et al., 2013</xref>). In brief, animals were fed every 2–3 days for either 1 week (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s4">Figure 5—figure supplement 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6E,F</xref>) or 2 weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3</xref>) and were maintained homeostatically or allowed to regenerate for the indicated number of days prior to fixation. For long-term RNAi treatment in the absence of injury, animals were fed a mixture of liver paste and dsRNA every 2–3 days for 2 weeks, followed by one dsRNA feeding every subsequent week (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>). For RNAi treatment in sexual <italic>S. mediterranea</italic>, animals were fed dsRNA every 2–3 days for one week and amputated transversely to create trunk fragments containing the pharynx and reproductive structures including the copulatory apparatus then fed dsRNA once per week for 62 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1C</xref>). For timed dsRNA delivery experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2B</xref>), RNAi-treated animals on days -2, -1, 0 were injected with dsRNA on three consecutive days, amputated transversely to create tail fragments on day 0, and animals fixed on day 7 of regeneration. For subsequent timed delivery of dsRNA, animals were amputated transversely to create tail fragments on day 0, followed by dsRNA injection for two consecutive days as indicated, and fixed on day 7 of regeneration.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Chemical amputation of pharynx in RNAi-treated animals</title><p>Animals were fed an equal mixture of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> dsRNA every 2–3 days for one week, amputated to remove heads and tails and allowed to regenerate for 20 days to produce an ectopic pharynx, then both the pre-existing and ectopic pharynges were removed by treatment with 100 mM sodium azide as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adler et al., 2014</xref>). Animals were then fixed either 2 days or 19 days later and stained with <italic>laminin</italic> and <italic>porcupine</italic> riboprobes to assess regeneration of the ectopic pharynx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>qPCR</title><p>Total RNA was extracted by mechanical homogenization in Trizol (Invitrogen) from three RNAi-treated intact animals, and purified in three biological replicates for each treatment. RNA samples were DNased-treated (TURBO DNase, Ambion) and cDNA was synthesized using SuperScript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen). qPCR was performed using SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems). <italic>axin-B</italic> mRNA was detected using the primers 5’-TTCCAGTTCAGGTCACATCG-3’ and 5’-CATTGACACCTTCCGAACCT-3’, <italic>ubiquilin</italic> mRNA was detected using 5’-AAATTCGCCTGCCTGTTGGG-3’ and 5’-CCGGTGGCATTAATCCATCTGT-3’, <italic>clathrin</italic> was detected using 5’-GACTGCGGGCTTCTATTGAG-3’ and 5’-GCGGCAATTCTTCTGAACTC-3’, <italic>wntP-2</italic> was detected using 5’- TGCTAAATCAACACCAGAATCAGCT-3’ and 5’- CACATCCACAATTACTATGCACCCC-3’, <italic>ndl-3</italic> was detected using 5’- CTCCCACAATTTATGAGTGCGGT-3’ and 5’- TCTTGGGCCAATTTTGAGTTTTGATCTA-3’, and <italic>ptk7</italic> was detected using 5’- GATCAAATCCCAAATCCAGTTC-3’ and 5’-GGGTTTCTGGGAGTTTATATCGTA-3’. Relative RNA abundance was calculated using the delta-Ct method after verification of primer amplification efficiency. p-values were computed from a 2-tailed t-test.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank members of the Petersen lab for helpful discussions and E Hill for the <italic>ndl-3</italic> plasmid.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf1"><p>The authors declare that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>RL, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>CPP, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidel</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez Alvarado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Selective amputation of the pharynx identifies a foxa-dependent regeneration program in planaria</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e02238</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez Alvarado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Types or states? Cellular dynamics and regenerative potential</article-title><source>Trends in Cell Biology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcb.2015.07.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almuedo-Castillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Adell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Dishevelled is essential for neural connectivity and planar cell polarity in planarians</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>2813</fpage><lpage>2818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1012090108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beane</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>A-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morokuma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemire</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Inhibition of planar cell polarity extends neural growth during regeneration, homeostasis, and development</article-title><source>Stem Cells and Development</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>2085</fpage><lpage>2094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/scd.2011.0605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bin-Nun</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Malyarova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>PTK7 modulates wnt signaling activity via LRP6</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>141</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.095984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blassberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tejada-Romero</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aboobaker</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>PBX/extradenticle is required to re-establish axial structures and polarity during planarian regeneration</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>140</volume><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.082982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cebrià</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Umesono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mineta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gojobori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Taira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Agata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Fgfr-related gene nou-darake restricts brain tissues to the head region of planarians</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>419</volume><fpage>620</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C-CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>pbx is required for pole and eye regeneration in planarians</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>140</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.083741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brubacher</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Newmark</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>A sex-specific transcription factor controls male identity in a simultaneous hermaphrodite</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>1814</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms2811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Transcription factors lhx1/5-1 and pitx are required for the maintenance and regeneration of serotonergic neurons in planarians</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>140</volume><fpage>3577</fpage><lpage>3588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.098590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aboobaker</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The TALE class homeobox gene smed-prep defines the anterior compartment for head regeneration</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e1000915</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraguas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barberan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Esteban</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cebria</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>egr-4, a target of EGFR signaling, is required for the formation of the brain primordia and head regeneration in planarians</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>141</volume><fpage>1835</fpage><lpage>1847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.101345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1976">1976</year><article-title>Pattern regulation in epimorphic fields</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>193</volume><fpage>969</fpage><lpage>981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.948762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyeler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Villiger</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Trueb</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>The murine fgfrl1 receptor is essential for the development of the metanephric kidney</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>335</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2009.08.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rink</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Beta-catenin defines head versus tail identity during planarian regeneration and homeostasis</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>319</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1150029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simakov</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Expression of secreted wnt pathway components reveals unexpected complexity of the planarian amputation response</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>347</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2010.08.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Daulat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Angers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciruna</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Ptk7 promotes non-canonical wnt/pcp-mediated morphogenesis and inhibits wnt/beta-catenin-dependent cell fate decisions during vertebrate development</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>140</volume><fpage>1807</fpage><lpage>1818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.090183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Skarmeta</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Salo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Adell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Silencing of smed- catenin1 generates radial-like hypercephalized planarians</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>1215</fpage><lpage>1221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.020289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Newmark</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>In situ hybridization protocol for enhanced detection of gene expression in the planarian schmidtea mediterranea</article-title><source>BMC Developmental Biology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-213X-13-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Agata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Wnt signaling is required for antero-posterior patterning of the planarian brain</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>306</volume><fpage>714</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2007.04.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labbé</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Irimia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DDR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Voisin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Blencowe</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>A comparative transcriptomic analysis reveals conserved features of stem cell pluripotency in planarians and mammals</article-title><source>Stem Cells</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>1734</fpage><lpage>1745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.1144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lhoumeau</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Puppo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Prébet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodjabachian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Ptk7: A cell polarity receptor with multiple facets</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1233</fpage><lpage>1236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cc.10.8.15368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>PKS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>An iterative algorithm for minimum cross entropy thresholding</article-title><source>Pattern Recognition Letters</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-8655(98)00057-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Borchers</surname><given-names>AGM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolicoeur</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayburn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessier-Lavigne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Ptk7/CCK-4 is a novel regulator of planar cell polarity in vertebrates</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>430</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seebeck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartscherer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>A pitx transcription factor controls the establishment and maintenance of the serotonergic lineage in planarians</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>140</volume><fpage>4499</fpage><lpage>4509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.100081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oviedo</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Morokuma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Walentek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kema</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gojobori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Long-range neural and gap junction protein-mediated cues control polarity during planarian regeneration</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>339</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2009.12.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>teashirt is required for head-versus-tail regeneration polarity in planarians</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>142</volume><fpage>1062</fpage><lpage>1072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.119685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenhoffer</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rink</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez Alvarado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Formaldehyde-based whole-mount in situ hybridization method for planarians</article-title><source>Developmental Dynamics</source><volume>238</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.21849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peradziryi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Podleschny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Borchers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolwinski</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Ptk7/Otk interacts with wnts and inhibits canonical wnt signalling</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>3729</fpage><lpage>3740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2011.236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Smed- catenin-1 is required for anteroposterior blastema polarity in planarian regeneration</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>319</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1149943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Wnt signaling and the polarity of the primary body axis</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>139</volume><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2009.11.035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>A wound-induced wnt expression program controls planarian regeneration polarity</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>106</volume><fpage>17061</fpage><lpage>17066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0906823106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Polarized notum activation at wounds inhibits wnt function to promote planarian head regeneration</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>332</volume><fpage>852</fpage><lpage>855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1202143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puppo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomé</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lhoumeau</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cibois</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gangar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lembo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Belotti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lécine</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Prébet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebbagh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>W-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodjabachian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Protein tyrosine kinase 7 has a conserved role in wnt/β-catenin canonical signalling</article-title><source>EMBO Reports</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/embor.2010.185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Constitutive gene expression and the specification of tissue identity in adult planarian biology</article-title><source>Trends in Genetics</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2011.04.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>März</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogg</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Grífol-Boldú</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Owlarn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Adell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Weidinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartscherer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Beta-catenin-dependent control of positional information along the AP body axis in planarians involves a teashirt family member</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.12.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riddiford</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Wnt gene loss in flatworms</article-title><source>Development Genes and Evolution</source><volume>221</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00427-011-0370-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rink</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez Alvarado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Planarian hh signaling regulates regeneration polarity and links hh pathway evolution to cilia</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>326</volume><fpage>1406</fpage><lpage>1410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1178712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robb</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotting</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez Alvarado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Smedgd 2.0: The <italic>schmidtea mediterra</italic>nea genome database</article-title><source>Genesis</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvg.22872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roensch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tazaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chara</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Progressive specification rather than intercalation of segments during limb regeneration</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>342</volume><fpage>1375</fpage><lpage>1379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1241796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouhana</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsthoefel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Agata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Newmark</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Rna interference by feeding in vitro-synthesized double-stranded RNA to planarians: Methodology and dynamics</article-title><source>Developmental Dynamics</source><volume>242</volume><fpage>718</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.23950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scimone</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapan</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>A forkhead transcription factor is wound-induced at the planarian midline and required for anterior pole regeneration</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e1003999</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vainio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassileva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Epithelial transformation of metanephric mesenchyme in the developing kidney regulated by wnt-4</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>372</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/372679a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sureda-Gómez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual-Carreras</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Adell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Posterior wnts have distinct roles in specification and patterning of the planarian posterior region</article-title><source>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>26543</fpage><lpage>26554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms161125970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tejada-Romero</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihaylova</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aboobaker</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Jnk signalling is necessary for a wnt- and stem cell-dependent regeneration programme</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>142</volume><fpage>2413</fpage><lpage>2424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.115139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogg</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Owlarn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pérez Rico</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartscherer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Stem cell-dependent formation of a functional anterior regeneration pole in planarians requires zic and forkhead transcription factors</article-title><source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>390</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2014.03.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vásquez-Doorman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>zic-1 expression in planarian neoblasts after injury controls anterior pole regeneration</article-title><source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e1004452</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witchley</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Muscle cells provide instructions for planarian regeneration</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2013.07.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolpert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1969">1969</year><article-title>Positional information and the spatial pattern of cellular differentiation</article-title><source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5193(69)80016-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zayas</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cebrià</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Newmark</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The use of lectins as markers for differentiated secretory cells in planarians</article-title><source>Developmental Dynamics</source><volume>239</volume><fpage>2888</fpage><lpage>2897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.22427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Opposing roles of voltage-gated ca2+ channels in neuronal control of regenerative patterning</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>15983</fpage><lpage>15995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3029-11.2011</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="article-commentary" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.024</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Sánchez Alvarado</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff4"><institution>Stowers Institute for Medical Research</institution>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your work entitled &quot;Wnt, Ptk7, and FGFRL expression gradients control trunk positional identity in planarian regeneration&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by Alejandro Sánchez Alvarado as Reviewing Editor and Fiona Watt as the Senior Editor. One of the three reviewers has agreed to reveal her identity: Yukiko Yamashita.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>In the manuscript by Lander and Petersen, the authors show that the freshwater planarian uses the kinase-dead WNT co-receptor, <italic>ptk7</italic>, to specify a novel trunk domain during axial regeneration. It has been a long-standing question as to how signaling pathways can act over long distances such as those across several millimeters of the planarian anterior-posterior axis. The work here begins to answer this question by identifying patterning molecules for large body domains. The authors further show that a previously known WNT molecule and an FGFRL molecule also play a role to pattern large domains around the central <italic>ptk7</italic> region. When knocked down by RNAi, these molecules and other potential positional controlling genes (PCGs) together with Ptk7 identified 4 genes (<italic>WntP2, ndl-3, Dvl-2</italic> and <italic>fzd-1/2/7</italic>) that potentiate the phenotype which appear to form a co-regulatory circuit that particularly affects the positioning of the pharynx and mouth. The authors nicely show that Ptk7 together with <italic>ndl-3</italic> or <italic>WntP-2</italic> are not required for extreme anterior or posterior pole identity, and that these genes function independently of β-catenin signaling. Finally, the authors show that pharynx positioning is dependent on this system during tail regeneration.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>Overall, the claims made in this paper are well supported and the data is novel and interesting. However, a more detail-oriented rewriting of this manuscript should be considered and the following major concerns should be addressed before moving forward with publication.</p><p>1) One point of confusion is that RNAi of <italic>ptk-7</italic>+<italic>WntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk-7+ndl-3</italic> are used interchangeably. Given the significant difference in penetrance shown in Figure 1—figure supplement 6, I am not convinced that these two contexts always generate the same phenotype.</p><p>2) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> nicely shows that <italic>ptk7, WntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression are affected by β-catenin RNAi. However, because the patterning of more posterior tissues appears to be controlled by <italic>WntP2, ndl-3</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic>, I think it is important to also show how expression of these genes are affected in posteriorized animals.</p><p>3) The claim (in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>) that <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression is controlled by feedback is not well supported. Another possibility is that the pharynx position dictates the posterior boundary of <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression, rather than feedback between Wnt signaling and FGFRL signaling.</p><p>4) Do head or tail fragments eventually form ectopic mouths/pharynges? If the axial patterning is altered, I would expect to see this during regeneration too.</p><p>5) The authors observe RNA &quot;gradients&quot; with their 3 main genes of interest, but what evidence do they have that this is a protein gradient?</p><p>6) If <italic>ptk7</italic> specifies &quot;trunk&quot; as the authors strongly state, then why no anterior expansion when trunk identity is removed? Brain should be assayed. Trunk expansion and not loss of trunk should give ectopic pharynxes, yet the authors report the opposite. Perhaps it is that <italic>ptk7</italic> restricts <italic>FoxA</italic>+ stem cells, and when knocked down, that population expands and induces another pharynx.</p><p>7) Dvl and <italic>fz1/2/7</italic> are stated to also enhance the <italic>ptk7</italic> phenotype, but were dropped from analysis. Why?</p><p>8) Almost no stains are quantified. RNAi efficacy is not measured by qRT-PCR or RNAseq as is standard in the planarian field. This would greatly help in making such statements as in “These results suggest that β-catenin upregulation can be sufficient for tail axis formation in conjunction with <italic>wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7</italic> expression. Taken together, normal levels of β-catenin signaling are important for the normal expression of <italic>pkt7</italic>, wntP-2 and ndl-3”.</p><p>9). In vertebrates, <italic>ptk7</italic> has been associated with WNT, semaphoring/plexin, and VEGF signaling, in addition to its known roles in PCP. None of this was tested here to bolster mechanism. Perhaps PCP defects can explain aspects of the phenotype. The authors state that the ectopic pharynxes are properly oriented, but many examples shown do not look that way.</p><p>10) More cell type markers are needed for tissues in different regions to conclude certain axial areas are not expanding/contracting.</p><p>11) Overlap in expression of <italic>ptk7, wntP-2</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> should be quantified. How is the overlap changing in different RNAi conditions? Why would these genes overlap in the cells that express them, should it be a binary expression state of muscle?</p><p>12) Are the ectopic pharynxes functional?</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12850.025</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p> <italic>Essential revisions: Overall, the claims made in this paper are well supported and the data is novel and interesting. However, a more detail-oriented rewriting of this manuscript should be considered and the following major concerns should be addressed before moving forward with publication. 1) One point of confusion is that RNAi of ptk-7+WntP-2 and ptk-7+ndl-3 are used interchangeably. Given the significant difference in penetrance shown in Figure 1—figure supplement 6, I am not convinced that these two contexts always generate the same phenotype.</italic></p><p>We have altered the text throughout to clarify the conclusions we draw from these two experimental contexts. We also performed additional histological analysis of <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals and also <italic>ptk7(RNAi);ndl3(RNAi)</italic> animals. Such animals have a similar frequency of forming ectopic pharynges (80% vs 90% of animals, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), a similar distribution of ectopic pharynx orientations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>), and a similar expression of axial markers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>) that show enlargement of trunk (<italic>mmp1, FoxA</italic>, SMU15007112) and reduction of anterior tail (<italic>wnt11-1, fzd4-1, Abd-Ba</italic>). These genes may act in other distinct processes in the animals or influence trunk/tail regionalization in subtly distinct ways, but based on these analyses we could not find any consistent differences in the <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi) versus ptk7(RNAi);ndl3(RNAi)</italic> phenotypes. We re-examined our scoring for formation of 1- versus 2- ectopic pharynges in these two treatments and found variability in this ratio across experiments, which we believe to be due to differences in feeding status and size of the animals. When we analyzed data from 8 experiments, we indeed found that <italic>wntP- 2(RNAi);ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals formed 2-ectopic pharynges at a higher frequency than <italic>ndl-3(RNAi);ptk7(RNAi)</italic> animals (25% versus 6% of the time). However, such animals presenting two ectopic pharynges did not appear different and the low frequency of such events in <italic>ndl-3(RNAi);ptk7(RNAi)</italic> prevented a detailed histological comparison of these groups. For clarity we now provide scoring information for ectopic tissue formation as a single graph (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>) and a separate measurement of pharynx angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>), as well as images of animals with ectopic mouths and ectopic pharynges for each of the experimental treatments tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>).</p><p><italic>2) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> nicely shows that ptk7, WntP-2 and ndl-3 expression are affected by β-catenin RNAi. However, because the patterning of more posterior tissues appears to be controlled by WntP2, ndl-3 and ptk7, I think it is important to also show how expression of these genes are affected in posteriorized animals.</italic></p><p>We tested <italic>APC(RNAi)</italic> regenerating trunk fragments and detected ectopic anterior expression of <italic>wntP-2</italic> and ectopic anterior expression of <italic>ptk7</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p> <italic>3) The claim (in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>) that ndl-3 expression is controlled by feedback is not well supported. Another possibility is that the pharynx position dictates the posterior boundary of ndl-3 expression, rather than feedback between Wnt signaling and FGFRL signaling.</italic></p><p>We performed experiments to identify the cell type that expresses ectopic <italic>ndl-3</italic> in <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals prior to formation of a fully-formed ectopic pharynx and find the majority are <italic>collagen+</italic> cells in the region of the body-wall musculature, a population of cells with hypothesized regulatory functions. Such cells are not known to actively contribute tissue to a regenerating pharynx, arguing against the ectopic <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression as marking the nascent ectopic pharynx itself. We removed the feedback inhibition model from the abstract and from the figures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>), and now discuss that model along with the possibility that the pharynx itself could control aspects of the <italic>ndl-3</italic> expression domain, as suggested.</p><p> <italic>4) Do head or tail fragments eventually form ectopic mouths/pharynges? If the axial patterning is altered, I would expect to see this during regeneration too.</italic></p><p>Head and tail fragments undergoing <italic>ptk7;wntP-2</italic> RNAi do not initially regenerate ectopic mouths and pharynges (by 22 days of regeneration), and we now elaborate on those results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F</xref>. Eventually, such animals do form ectopic pharynges if they are fed dsRNA over a long timeframe (74 days, 3 of 12 animals examined), but we attribute this to the homeostatic functioning of the genes observed in uninjured animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>). Our interpretation of these context specific functions for <italic>ptk7/wntP-2/ndl-3</italic> in suppression of trunk identity in regeneration is that these genes could signal context-specific information about the presence/absence of regions from the animal fragment relevant for reformation of the tail and we now elaborate on this interpretation in the Discussion.</p><p><italic>5) The authors observe RNA &quot;gradients&quot; with their 3 main genes of interest, but what evidence do they have that this is a protein gradient?</italic></p><p>Our analysis was restricted to detection of mRNA for these three genes and we edited the text to clarify this.</p><p><italic>6) If ptk7 specifies &quot;trunk&quot; as the authors strongly state, then why no anterior expansion when trunk identity is removed? Brain should be assayed. Trunk expansion and not loss of trunk should give ectopic pharynxes, yet the authors report the opposite. Perhaps it is that ptk7 restricts FoxA+ stem cells, and when knocked down, that population expands and induces another pharynx.</italic></p><p>We appreciate the identification of this wording issue. Our model is that <italic>ptk7</italic> negatively regulates trunk identity within the tail and we have modified the text to clarify the sign of this regulatory effect. The nature of this effect is directional, as we never observed formation of ectopic pharynges anterior to the original pharynx, which we suggest is due to the posterior regionalized co-expression of <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2.</italic> We examined the brains of <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals by detecting <italic>ndk</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>) and <italic>chat</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1A</xref>), and detecting <italic>cintillo</italic> expression that marks a subpopulation of lateral brain neurons whose numbers scale with the size of the brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1B</xref>). We did not detect any clear difference to the size or expression status of the brain by these criteria. We further examined the possible involvement of <italic>FoxA</italic>+ cells in the ectopic pharynx phenotype and could detect the expansion of the <italic>FoxA</italic>+ expression domain in fully regenerated <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> and also <italic>ptk7(RNAi);ndl3(RNAi)</italic> trunk fragments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). We were able to detect a region of ectopic <italic>FoxA+</italic> expression at an early time in the appearance of the ectopic pharynx, consistent with a mechanism in which trunk duplication occurs via the production or relocalization of <italic>FoxA+</italic> precursor cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>).</p><p><italic>7) Dvl and fz1/2/7 are stated to also enhance the ptk7 phenotype, but were dropped from analysis. Why?</italic></p><p>We focused the majority of our efforts in deciphering the functions for the regionally expressed signaling molecules (<italic>wntP-2</italic>, <italic>ptk7,</italic> and <italic>ndl-3)</italic> in order to account for the unidirectional nature of the regional expansion/duplication phenotypes, whereas both <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic> and <italic>Dvl-2</italic> are broadly expressed. We now include additional verification for the involvement of these factors in suppressing trunk identity similar to <italic>wntP-2, ptk7</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2</xref>). We now also discuss a possible molecular pathway of action supported by these observations, that <italic>wntP-2</italic> signals through <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic> and <italic>Dvl-2</italic>, but likely independently of <italic>β-catenin-1</italic>, to suppress trunk identity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>).</p><p><italic>8) Almost no stains are quantified. RNAi efficacy is not measured by qRT-PCR or RNAseq as is standard in the planarian field. This would greatly help in making such statements as in “These results suggest that β-catenin upregulation can be sufficient for tail axis formation in conjunction with wntP-2 and ptk7 expression. Taken together, normal levels of β-catenin signaling are important for the normal expression of pkt7, wntP-2 and ndl-3”.</italic></p><p>We now include scoring information for images presented throughout (see legends and/or text), quantification of pharynx orientation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>), quantification of trunk regional expansion and tail restriction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>), quantification of graded expression of <italic>wntP-2, ptk7</italic>, and <italic>ndl-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>), and cell counts for <italic>ndl-3</italic>+<italic>collagen</italic>+cells in the tail of <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals. We quantified efficiency of <italic>wntP-2, ptk7,</italic> and <italic>ndl-3</italic> RNAi by qPCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>).</p><p><italic>9). In vertebrates, ptk7 has been associated with WNT, semaphoring/plexin, and VEGF signaling, in addition to its known roles in PCP. None of this was tested here to bolster mechanism. Perhaps PCP defects can explain aspects of the phenotype. The authors state that the ectopic pharynxes are properly oriented, but many examples shown do not look that way.</italic></p><p>We identify <italic>ptk7</italic> and <italic>wntP-2</italic> as suppressing pharynx and mouth formation. Given that Ptk7 proteins can act as Wnt-coreceptors, and given the rarity of ectopic trunk phenotypes (not observed in previously published large-scale RNAi screens such as Reddien et al. 2005), this suggests a molecular pathway of action in which <italic>WntP-2</italic> signals through Ptk7 to inhibit trunk fates. We support this conclusion by finding similar phenotypes from inhibition of a frizzled receptor, <italic>fzd1/2/7</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2</xref>). These observations argue against a likely participation of Wnt-independent Ptk7 signaling (such as via semaphoring/plexin signaling or VEGF signaling) in trunk suppression. We tested several components of the Planar Cell Polarity pathway (<italic>vangl-1, vangl-2</italic>, <italic>DAAM1,</italic> and <italic>ROCK</italic>) because of its connection with noncanonical Wnt signalling pathways and could not find genetic interactions with <italic>ptk7</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s3">Figure 5—figure supplement 3</xref>). We also measured the orientation of the ectopic pharynx in all of our RNAi treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>) and found that the majority of such structures are indeed oriented obliquely. In some cases the pharynx was oriented toward the anterior, but the majority of ectopic pharynges in all conditions pointed toward the posterior (the arc from -90 to 0 to 90 degrees) rather than toward the anterior (the arc 90 to 180/-180 to -90 degrees), and the distributions of angles did not appear fully randomized (as compared to equal numbers of randomly selected angles plotted as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>, not shown). It is possible that a cell polarization pathway is involved in the regional identity determination controlled by these genes (and we now discuss this possibility in the Discussion paragraph two), but our data does not find evidence it is the PCP pathway. Alternatively, from the appearance of many of the ectopic pharynx phenotypes it seems that the structure grows in a confined manner that can result in the attainment of a particular angular orientation. Of note, animals with two ectopic pharynges always formed them oriented toward the posterior midline. We also note that the posterior and anterior pole identities in animals with ectopic pharynges were normal, suggesting that trunk suppression (and orientation of any ectopic pharynx) and body axis polarization are under distinct control mechanisms.</p><p> <italic>10) More cell type markers are needed for tissues in different regions to conclude certain axial areas are not expanding/contracting.</italic></p><p>We now include additional histological analysis, which totals to examining each body region (anterior pole, head, prepharyngeal region, trunk, tail and posterior pole) by detecting expression of <italic>notum</italic>, <italic>ndk, wnt2, mmp1</italic>, <italic>FoxA, wnt11-1, fzd4-1, Abd-Ba,</italic> and <italic>wnt1</italic> for both <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> and <italic>ptk7(RNAi);ndl-3(RNAi)</italic> animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>) and additionally <italic>chat, cintillo, mag-1</italic>, and <italic>wnt11-2</italic> and <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals. We also present two new markers SMU15014980and SMU15007112that label prepharyngeal and peripharyngeal cells that will be useful for future investigations of planarian axis transformations. We quantified the lengths for several of the above domains and found that <italic>ptk7</italic>+<italic>wntP-2</italic> RNAi and <italic>ptk7</italic>+<italic>ndl-3</italic> RNAi expands trunk tissue (expressing <italic>mmp1</italic>, <italic>FoxA,</italic> or SMU15007112) and restricts gene expression normally associated with the anterior tail tissue region (<italic>wnt11-1</italic> and <italic>fzd4-1)</italic>. The <italic>Abd-Ba</italic> staining also showed this trend but the staining was too faint for us to confidently assign a numerical length to this domain.</p><p><italic>11) Overlap in expression of ptk7, wntp-2 and ndl-3 should be quantified. How is the overlap changing in different RNAi conditions? Why would these genes overlap in the cells that express them, should it be a binary expression state of muscle?</italic></p><p>We now measure the overlap in expression of <italic>ptk7,</italic> wntP-2 and <italic>ndl-3</italic> by quantification of in situ hybridizations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). Quantification of colorimetric in situ hybridizations confirmed the graded expression of these genes as maximal in prepharyngeal (<italic>ndl-3</italic>), trunk (<italic>ptk7</italic>) and tail (<italic>wntP-2</italic>) regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). We also quantified expression of all three genes on a per-cell basis using triple FISH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). This broadly confirmed the domains of gene expression. We analyzed this data in two ways to support the existence of expression cell states of the three genes that populate the body axis. First, scatterplots of expression of pairwise combinations of the three genes show the existence of co-expressing cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4E</xref>). Second, we determined approximate distributions of particular expression states by applying thresholds for low- versus high-expression to bin each cells into one of 8 possible expression classes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>) and found that these populate the axis in distinct domains. These experiments argue for a complexity to the expression states of the genes. We tested for possible regulatory interactions among these genes in uninjured animals by colorimetric and fluorescence in situ hybridizations, as well as by qPCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplement 3A-C</xref>). In these experiments, the only strong and reproducible expression change we observed was the expansion of <italic>ndl-3</italic> into the tail region of <italic>ptk7(RNAi);wntP-2(RNAi)</italic> animals, and we confirmed that this expression occurred in <italic>collagen+</italic> cells of the body wall musculature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6F</xref>). The identification of more subtle effects on graded expression is an interesting topic and we suspect it will require the development of new tools to be applied to the planarian system such as single molecule FISH.</p><p><italic>12) Are the ectopic pharynxes functional?</italic></p><p>We imaged two-pharynxed animals exposed to calf liver paste and found evidence that both the pre-existing and ectopic pharynx could acquire food (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>, <xref ref-type="other" rid="media1">Video 1</xref>).</p></body></sub-article></article>