<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">eLife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub" publication-format="electronic">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">19942</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification of neuronal activity-regulated genes in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-12270"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="data-ro1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-35636"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>Reazur</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="author-12149"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Fang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-1263"><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3366-1780</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con4"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Brandeis University</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Waltham</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">National Center for Behavioral Genomics, Department of Biology</institution>, <institution>Brandeis University</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Waltham</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bellen</surname><given-names>Hugo J</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff3"><institution>Baylor College of Medicine</institution>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><email>rosbash@brandeis.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e19942</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>07</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016, Chen et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chen et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-19942-v1.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.001</object-id><p>Activity-regulated genes (ARGs) are important for neuronal functions like long-term memory and are well-characterized in mammals but poorly studied in other model organisms like <italic>Drosophila</italic>. Here we stimulated fly neurons with different paradigms and identified ARGs using high-throughput sequencing from brains as well as from sorted neurons: they included a narrow set of circadian neurons as well as dopaminergic neurons. Surprisingly, many ARGs are specific to the stimulation paradigm and very specific to neuron type. In addition and unlike mammalian immediate early genes (IEGs), fly ARGs do not have short gene lengths and are less enriched for transcription factor function. Chromatin assays using ATAC-sequencing show that the transcription start sites (TSS) of ARGs do not change with neural firing but are already accessible prior to stimulation. Lastly based on binding site enrichment in ARGs, we identified transcription factor mediators of firing and created neuronal activity reporters.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.001">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.001</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Author Keywords</title><kwd>RNA high-throughput sequencing</kwd><kwd>neural firing</kwd><kwd>optogenetics</kwd><kwd>chromatin accessibility</kwd><kwd>neural activity reporters</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research Organism</title><kwd><italic>D. melanogaster</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="par-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000011</institution-id><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiao</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>Reazur</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Fang</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>elife-xml-version</meta-name><meta-value>2.5</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Activity-regulated genes in Drosophila neurons differ from the well-characterized situation in mammals, and these genes provided a strategy to construct reporters for monitoring neuronal activity in fly brains.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Upon stimulation, immediate-early genes (IEGs) are induced rapidly and transiently without de novo protein synthesis in mammalian neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Fowler et al., 2011</xref>). This activity-dependent gene regulation is important as it affects the ability of an animal to convert transient stimuli into long-term changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Huh et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kandel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Nestler, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Spitzer et al., 2000</xref>). Hundreds of IEGs, including those specific to tissues and stimulation paradigms, have been identified in mammals since the discovery of the first neuronal IEG, c-<italic>fos,</italic> by Greenberg and his colleagues in 1986 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Greenberg et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Herschman, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Spiegel et al., 2014</xref>). Expression of these IEGs are induced within an hour, usually with big amplitudes (over 10 fold), and many IEGs are shared between different types of neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Spiegel et al., 2014</xref>). Functionally, these IEGs are highly enriched for transcription factors, which subsequently trigger a secondary transcriptional response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Spiegel et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">West and Greenberg, 2011</xref>). The secondary response genes (SRGs) in contrast take longer to induce (a typical assay is 6 hr post-stimulation), are involved in many different processes, are more neuron-specific and function at least in part to promote neuron survival, dendritic morphogenesis and regulate synapse formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bloodgood et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hong et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lin et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Not all IEGs respond to all types of stimulations, even the most robust ones like <italic>c-fos, Egr1</italic> and <italic>Arc</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bepari et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Fields et al., 1997</xref>). For example, different stimulation paradigm-dependent Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry routes initiate different downstream pathways and lead to induction of distinct IEGs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">West and Greenberg, 2011</xref>). Stimulations other than neural firing like growth factors also induce IEG expression, many of which are the same as those induced with neural firing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jones et al., 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Tullai et al., 2007</xref>). Depending on the induction dynamics, Tullai <italic>et al.</italic> divided the platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF)-induced IEGs in human T98G glioblastoma cells into primary response genes (PRGs) and delayed response genes (DRGs). Dramatic differences were shown between the two categories in terms of their functions, gene lengths, chromatin accessibility and RNA polymerase II occupancy at promoter regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Fowler et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Kim et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Tullai et al., 2007</xref>). PRGs are usually optimized for rapid induction (such as shorter gene length and more permissive chromatin at promoters), whereas DRGs are not different from other genes in the genome. Notably, PRGs and DRGs are induced independent of protein-synthesis (‘cycloheximide-insensitive’), whereas SRGs are protein-synthesis dependent (‘cycloheximide-sensitive’).</p><p>IEGs, or activity-regulated genes (ARGs; they are defined here as induced rapidly with neuronal activity, i.e., mostly within an hour, but without regard to de novo protein synthesis) are poorly defined in organisms other than mammals. Only three genes to date have been identified as responding to increased neural activity in insects: <italic>kakusei</italic> (in honey bee), <italic>stripe</italic> (abbreviated as <italic>sr,</italic> in honey bee) and <italic>hr38</italic> (in silkmoth and the fruit fly <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Fujita et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kiya et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lutz and Robinson, 2013</xref>). Moreover, only one genome-wide study using microarrays had been performed more than a decade ago to identify seizure-induced ARGs from fly heads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Guan et al., 2005</xref>). More high-throughput studies on <italic>Drosophila</italic> ARGs are therefore needed, not only for identification and to provide mechanistic insight but also to design new tools to serve as indicators of neuronal activity.</p><p>Here, we identified ARGs in a genome-wide manner, in fly brains as well as in sorted neurons; they included dopaminergic neurons (DA) and a subset of circadian-related neurons (PDF+ neurons). Fly ARGs vary with the individual stimulation paradigm and are surprisingly cell type-specific. Fly ARGs are also more functionally diverse and have longer gene lengths compared to mammalian ARGs. Chromatin at transcription start sites (TSS) of fly ARGs is more accessible at baseline than other expressed genes but does not change with stimulation. Lastly, we used bioinformatics to identify key transcription factors that mediate ARG activation. Based on these factors, we generated novel luciferase reporters for in vivo monitoring of neuronal firing.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Genome-wide identification of firing-induced ARGs in fly brains</title><p>To identify ARGs in fly neurons in a genome-wide manner, the pan-neuronal driver <italic>Elav-GAL4</italic> was used to drive expression of <italic>UAS-ChR2-XXL</italic>, to artificially fire neurons by illuminating flies with a blue LED (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Dawydow et al., 2014</xref>). A 30 s 10 Hz LED exposure was sufficient to induce a uniform seizure within seconds, and all flies were able to recover within 15 min. Fly brains were dissected either before (0 min), or 15, 30, 60 min after stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). Flies expressing only <italic>Elav-GAL4</italic> were illuminated in parallel and used as a control strain. RNA was then extracted from these samples and made into mRNA libraries for deep sequencing.<fig-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.002</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>High-throughput sequencing and optogenetics reveal ARGs in <italic>Drosophila.</italic></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Stimulation paradigm for <italic>Elav-GAL4;UAS-ChR2-XXL</italic> flies. (<bold>B</bold>) Volcano plots of individual genes (FPKM &gt; 0) with log2 fold changes (x-axis) against p-value (y-axis, exact test). Genes significantly induced (p-value &lt; 0.01 for both exact test and GLM) are in red. The smaller area with grey background is the zoom-in view with larger scales. N = 3 biological replicates. (<bold>C</bold>) Gene expression of <italic>hr38</italic> and <italic>sr</italic> in <italic>Elav-GAL4;UAS-ChR2-XXL</italic> and <italic>Elav-GAL4/</italic>+ (control) flies 0 or 60 min after LED stimulation. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM, n.s. represents non-significant. *p&lt;0.05, ****p&lt;0.0001, exact test. (<bold>D</bold>) Gene ontology analysis on <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic>-induced ARGs. P-value is the enrichment p-value, not corrected for multiple testing. FDR q-value is the corrected p-value for multiple testing using the Benjamini and Hochberg (1995) method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Eden et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Eden et al., 2007</xref>). Number of genes indicates the number of ARGs with the specified functions.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.002">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.002</ext-link></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD1-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.003</object-id><label>Figure 1—source data 1.</label><caption><title><italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs in fly brains.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.003">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.003</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig1-data1-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig1s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.004</object-id><label>Figure 1—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Light-induced gene expression.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Volcano plots of individual genes (FPKM &gt; 0 at baseline, FPKM &gt; 10 with stimulation) with fold changes (log2, x-axis) against p-value (-log10, exact test, y-axis). Genes with expression levels significantly changed (pf-value &lt; 0.01 for both exact test and GLM) are shown in red. (<bold>B</bold>) Expression levels of the four genes up-regulated with LED in control flies. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM, n.s. represents non-significant, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001, exact test.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.004">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.004</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig1-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>96 genes show significant increases in 60 min with p-value &lt; 0.01 of both exact test and general linear model (GLM) in <italic>UAS-ChR2-XXL</italic> flies (N = 3 biological replicas); very few genes show significant decreases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Ranking #1 and #2 are the previously identified insect IEGs <italic>hr38</italic> and <italic>sr,</italic> with a 90- and a 10- fold increase respectively, suggesting the stimulation paradigm is sufficient to fire neurons in the brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1-data">Figure 1—source data 1</xref>). The 30 s LED exposure affected many fewer genes in control flies: four were up-regulated, and three down-regulated with p-values&lt;0.01 by both statistical tests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1A</xref>, N = 3). 3 of the four up-regulated genes, <italic>CG13055, hsp23</italic> and <italic>hsromega,</italic> had induction amplitudes statistically indistinguishable from those of the <italic>UAS-ChR2-XXL</italic> flies and are therefore labeled as light-induced genes in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1-data">Figure 1—source data 1</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1s1">Figure 1—figure supplement 1B</xref>). However, they were not removed from the ARG list because light can induce neuronal firing and some of these genes are also induced by other stimulation paradigms (see below).</p><p>Gene Ontology (GO) analysis using GOrilla (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cbl-gorilla.cs.technion.ac.il/">http://cbl-gorilla.cs.technion.ac.il/</ext-link>) on the 96 ARG genes shows that polII transcription factor activity is the most enriched function with a P-value of 1.29E-4 computed according to the mHG or HG model, followed by steroid hormone receptor activity and MAP kinase activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). Several of these induced transcription factors encode proteins with high sequence identity to well-known mammalian IEGs: HR38 shows 67% identity to nuclear receptor subfamily four group A member 2 (NR4A2); SR has 82% identity to early growth response protein 3 (EGR3); CBT is 61% identical to Krueppel-like factor 11 (KLF11). Taken together, firing neurons with <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> identified known as well as novel ARGs in flies, and the enrichment of transcription factors in ARGs suggests some mechanistic similarity between flies and mammals.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Gene sizes of ARGs correlate with induction rates</title><p>To assess the kinetics of ARG induction and to provide a global view, a heat map across time points was generated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). The levels of most ARGs continue to increase until the last time point assayed (60 min); only a few transcripts like <italic>cbt</italic> (2.6 kb) reach maximum expression levels at 30 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Since shorter gene length enables the rapid induction of IEGs in mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Tullai et al., 2007</xref>), we examined the gene lengths of fly ARGs. Surprisingly, the average ARG gene is longer than that of all annotated genes as well as of all genes expressed in neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>, gene annotation obtained from FlyBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.flybase.net/genomes/dmel/dmel_r5.2_FB2007_01/fasta">ftp://ftp.flybase.net/genomes/dmel/dmel_r5.2_FB2007_01/fasta</ext-link>)). This is true even for some of the most robust ARGs; <italic>hr38</italic> is ~31 kb long, <italic>sr</italic> spans ~ 11 kb, <italic>CG8910</italic> is ~21 kb and <italic>CG11221</italic> is ~13 kb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>). In contrast, the canonical mammalian IEGs <italic>c-fos</italic> and <italic>c-jun</italic> are only ~ 3.4 kb and ~3.2 kb respectively. This is despite the fact that the average gene size of flies (~9.3 kb) is considerably smaller than that of mammals (~47 kb for mouse).<fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.005</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Gene sizes of ARGs correlate with induction rates.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Heat map of <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARG expression from 0, 15, 30 to 60 min (normalized to 0 min expression) post-LED stimultaion. Each row represents one gene. Data are averages of 2 biological replicates. (<bold>B</bold>) Gene induction profiles of <italic>cbt</italic> (gene length = 2.6 kb, red) and <italic>sr</italic> (gene length = 11 kb, blue) with LED stimulation in <italic>Elav-GAL4;UAS-ChR2-XXL</italic> flies (N = 2 biological replicates, abbreviated as rep1/2). (<bold>C</bold>) Gene length distribution of all annotated genes in the genome (blue), genes expressed in brains (gray, FPKM &gt; 0 at baseline, FPKM &gt; 10 with stimulation), and <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs (red). Only the longest isoform of each gene is plotted. (<bold>D</bold>) Correlation of <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs gene length (y-axis) and fold changes of 15 min compared to 0 min (abbreviated as FC15/0, x-axis). (<bold>E</bold>) Correlation of <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs gene length (y-axis) and fold changes of 60 min compared to 0 min (abbreviated as FC60/0, x-axis). (<bold>F–H</bold>) Expression profiles of <italic>hr38, sr,</italic> and <italic>CG14186</italic> from fly heads 0, 15, 30 and 60 min after LED stimulation. Nascent RNA levels are shown in green and mRNA levels in blue. Numbers to the right of the expression graphs indicate data range.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.005">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.005</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.006</object-id><label>Figure 2—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Gene structure of some long ARGs induced by <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic>, including <italic>hr38, sr, CG8910,</italic> and <italic>CG11221.</italic></title><p>Gene structures obtained from UCSC genome browser (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genome.ucsc.edu/">https://genome.ucsc.edu/</ext-link>).</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.006">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.006</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig2-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>To test if gene length affects ARG induction rates, we compared the fold changes of gene expression between 0 and 15 min (FC15/0) relative to gene lengths. There is a weak anti-correlation, suggesting that longer genes are indeed more slowly induced on average (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). This is not because overall induction amplitudes are smaller for longer genes, since the correlation disappears if fold changes between 0 and 60 min (FC60/0) are compared to gene lengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>).</p><p>To gain more insight into these dynamics, nascent RNA and mRNA libraries were constructed in parallel from fly heads using the same stimulation paradigm. Heads rather than brains were used because of technical considerations: the much larger amounts of starting material required for nascent RNA preparation are difficult to obtain with brain dissections.</p><p>Although <italic>hr38</italic> and <italic>sr</italic> mRNA levels peak at 60 min with little or no changes evident at 15 min and even at 30 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F,G</xref>), the nascent RNA data indicate that the enhanced transcription of both genes is obvious at the first 15 min time point and peaks at 30 min, 30 min before the peak time of mRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2F,G</xref>). For shorter genes such as <italic>CG14186</italic> (5.7 kb), the stimulation-induced increases are smaller at the nascent RNA level, presumably because much less time is required for transcription elongation and polyadenylation. More importantly and unlike the longer genes, there is no delay between the nascent and mRNA peak times for the shorter genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2H</xref>). The data taken together indicate that the long gene lengths of some prominent ARGs reduce the mRNA induction rates due to the time required for nascent events like transcriptional elongation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>ARGs induced by two additional stimulation paradigms</title><p>To test whether these ARGs are universal and respond to different stimulation regimens, we employed two additional paradigms: <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>mediated firing and high KCl-induced depolarization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). <italic>UAS-dTrpA1</italic> was overexpressed under the control of <italic>Elav-GAL4</italic>, and flies were stimulated in vivo by shifting the temperature from 18°C to 29°C to stimulate the temperature-sensitive <italic>dTrpA1</italic> cation channel. High KCl stimulation was done ex vivo by incubating dissected brains in 90 mM KCl. In this case, the voltage sensor ArcLight was used to confirm successful depolarization (<xref ref-type="other" rid="media1">Video 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Cao et al., 2013</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.007</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>ARGs induced by two additional stimulation paradigms.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schemes of two additional stimulation paradigms: <italic>dTrpA1</italic> and KCl. (<bold>B</bold>) Heat map of <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARG expression with 0, 15, 30 and 60 min temperature shift (normalized to 0 min expression). N = 3 biological replicates. (<bold>C</bold>) Heat map of KCl-inducd ARG expression with 0, 15, 30, 60 and 90 min KCl incubation (normalized to 0 min expression). N = 3 biological replicates. (<bold>D</bold>) Overlap of ARGs among the three different stimulation paradigms: <italic>ChR2-XXL, dTrpA1</italic> and KCl (90 min). (<bold>E</bold>) Gene expression of the 12 shared ARGs induced by all three stimulation paradigms. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001, exact test. (<bold>F</bold>) Gene expression of paradigm-specific ARGs: <italic>pk61c</italic> and <italic>skl</italic> are specific to the <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> paradigm; <italic>CG13054</italic> and <italic>grasss</italic> are specific to the <italic>dTrpA1</italic> paradigm; and <italic>CG13322</italic> and <italic>CG10383</italic> are specific to the KCl paradigm. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM, n.s. represents non-significant, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001, exact test.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.007">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.007</ext-link></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD2-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.008</object-id><label>Figure 3—source data 1.</label><caption><title><italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs in fly brains.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.008">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.008</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig3-data1-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD3-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.009</object-id><label>Figure 3—source data 2.</label><caption><title>KCl-induced ARGs in 60 min in fly brains.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.009">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.009</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig3-data2-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD4-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.010</object-id><label>Figure 3—source data 3.</label><caption><title>KCl<italic>-</italic>induced ARGs in 90 min in fly brains.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.010">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.010</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig3-data3-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD5-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.011</object-id><label>Figure 3—source data 4.</label><caption><title>Overlapped ARGs in brains.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.011">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.011</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig3-data4-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.012</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Fluorescence changes of ArcLight indicate successful depolarization of neurons with KCl stimulation.</title><p>Brains expressing ArcLight in PDF+ neurons were dissected and mobilized in chamber with AHL for recording with fluorescence microscope. KCl was perfused to the chamber at ~60 s and washed out at ~110 s with AHL. KCl stimulation is indicated with the black bar. N = 4 flies. A representative recording plot of multiple biological replicates is shown. Error bars represent ±SEM.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.012">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.012</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig3-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.013</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>qPCR verification of high-throughput RNA sequencing results.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) qPCR verification of the shared ARGs by all three stimulation paradigms. 6 out of 6 genes tested are consistent with high-throughput sequencing results. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM. (<bold>B</bold>) qPCR verification of stimulation paradigm-specific ARGs. Highlighted in red is the paradigm identified by high-throughput sequencing to induce expression of the particular gene. All genes tested are consistent with the high-throughput sequencing results. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.013">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.013</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig3-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.014</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>qPCR quantification of paradigm-specific ARGs in <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> flies with a 30 min LED stimulation followed by another 30 min recovery.</title><p>N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM, n.s. represents non-significant, *p&lt;0.05, two-tail t-test.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.014">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.014</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig3-figsupp3-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig3s4" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.015</object-id><label>Figure 3—figure supplement 4.</label><caption><title>qPCR quantification of ARGs induction under ex vivo condition.</title><p><italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> indicates dissected brains of <italic>Elav-GAL4;UAS-ChR2-XXL</italic> flies exposed to a 30 s LED exposure. <italic>dTrpA1</italic> indicates dissected brains of <italic>Elav-GAL4;UAS-dTrpA1</italic> flies incubated in a 29°C water bath. A.u. indicates arbitrary unit. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM. (<bold>A</bold>) qPCR quantification of the KCl-specific ARGs according to the high-throughput RNA sequencing results. All four genes tested are only induced by the KCl paradigm. (<bold>B</bold>) qPCR quantification of the shared ARGs by all three stimulation paradigms according to the high-throughput RNA sequencing results. All four genes tested are induced by all three ex vivo paradigms.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.015">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.015</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig3-figsupp4-v1"/></fig></fig-group><media content-type="glencoe play-in-place height-250 width-310" id="media1" mime-subtype="mp4" mimetype="video" xlink:href="elife-19942-media1.mp4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.016</object-id><label>Video 1.</label><caption><title>S1 Live imaging of Arclight in PDF+ neurons in response to KCl treatment.</title><p>To show KCl treatment can successfully depolarize neurons, Arclight was artificially expressed in PDF+ neurons (<italic>Pdf-GAL4;UAS-</italic>ArcLight). Arclight signal was monitored with fluorescent microscope while KCl was perfused into the chamber containing a dissected brain. Quantification of fluorescent intensity is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.016">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.016</ext-link></p></caption></media></p><p>Hundreds of genes are induced with the <italic>dTrpA1</italic> paradigm but many are also robustly heat-induced, i.e., they are also induced in control flies expressing only <italic>Elav-GAL4.</italic> Nonetheless, 97 genes including <italic>hr38</italic> and <italic>sr</italic> were induced by <italic>dTrpA1</italic> at 60 min but not induced or induced much less robustly in the control flies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Figure 3—source data 1</xref>). With KCl treatment, only 38 genes were significantly induced in 60 min, and most of them are stress-induced such as heat shock genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3-data">Figure 3—source data 2</xref>). <italic>Hr38</italic> and <italic>sr</italic> were also significantly induced by KCl but with much smaller increases (2.5 and 1.5 fold, respectively) compared to the other two paradigms (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1-data">Figure 1—source data 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Figure 3—source data 1</xref>). To accommodate genes that might be induced more slowly with the KCl paradigm, an extra 90 min time point was assayed (three biological replicas). Because many more ARGs (107 genes in total) were significantly induced and had bigger induction amplitudes at 90 min compared to 60 min (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4-data">Figure 3—source data 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>), this 90 min time point was compared with the other two induction methods.</p><p>Only 12 ARGs are shared by all the three paradigms (including <italic>hr38</italic> and <italic>sr</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D,E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5-data">Figure 3—source data 4</xref>). To verify this conclusion, qPCR was used on 6 of these shared genes, and the results of all six are qualitatively consistent with the high-throughput RNA sequencing results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2A</xref>).</p><p>The overlap between the three different pairwise combinations is larger: 13 genes are shared between <italic>dTrpA1</italic> (13% of <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs) and KCl (12% of KCl<italic>-</italic>induced ARGs), and 24 genes between <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> (25% of <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs) and KCl (22% of KCl<italic>-</italic>induced ARGs). The largest number (35) and fraction of genes are shared between <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> (36% of <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs) and <italic>dTrpA1</italic> (36% of <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs). These data indicate that many ARGs respond to firing independent of the stimulation paradigm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5-data">Figure 3—source data 4</xref>).</p><p>There are however some genes that are specific to the stimulation paradigm, consistent with what has been observed in mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bepari et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Fields et al., 1997</xref>). For example, <italic>pk61c</italic> and <italic>skl</italic> are induced only by <italic>ChR2-XXL; CG13054</italic>, whereas <italic>grass</italic> is induced only by <italic>dTrpA1; CG13322</italic> and <italic>CG10383</italic> are only induced by KCl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>). These stimulation paradigm-specific ARGs and six others were verified by qPCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2B</xref>), with conclusions qualitatively consistent with high-throughput RNA sequencing results.</p><p>Stronger stimulation paradigms, for example longer LED exposure for <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> flies, bigger temperature shift for <italic>dTrpA1</italic> flies or incubation with higher KCl concentration, may further increase the overlap among paradigms. To test this, the LED exposure of the <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> flies was extended from 30 s to 30 min. 2 out of 8 paradigm-specific ARGs that were negative with the 30 s exposure were positive with the 30 min stimulation, but the other six remained negative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplement 3</xref>). In addition, we tested by qPCR whether some of the KCl-specific ARGs are due to the ex vivo condition only used for the KCl-stimulation: 4 out of 4 tested are not induced by the other two stimulation paradigms performed under the same ex vivo condition, i.e., exposure of dissected brains to the LED or to temperature shift (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4A</xref>). In contrast, four common ARGs were stimulated ex vivo by <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> and <italic>dTrpA1</italic> in 60 min to levels quite comparable to those from the KCl paradigm at 90 min, suggesting that the different results are due to the different stimulation paradigms rather than ex vivo vs. in vivo stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">Figure 3—figure supplement 4B</xref>).</p><p>The results taken together suggest that most paradigm-specific ARGs will remain responsive to only one type of stimulation despite the fact that stronger stimulation will somewhat increase the overlap among the three paradigms, e.g., the distinction between the paradigms might be quantitative as well as qualitative. In any case, the data taken together significantly extend the list of <italic>bona fide</italic> ARGs in flies.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Transcriptome profiling in DA and PDF+ neurons</title><p>Fly brains contain many types of neurons with distinct properties as well as glia and other tissues (The <italic>Interactive</italic> Fly, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sdbonline.org/">http://www.sdbonline.org/</ext-link>). Transcript changes in specific neurons may therefore be invisible with assays from brains and heads, especially if there is significant cell-type specificity in the transcriptional response to neuronal firing. To address this possibility, we performed mRNA deep sequencing on sorted green fluorescent protein (GFP) labeled DA and PDF+ neurons expressing <italic>dTrpA1</italic> with or without a temperature shift, namely, the same <italic>dTrpA1</italic> paradigm used for brains. DA and PDF+ neurons are two distinct populations and serve different functions in flies. Each brain has about ~120 DA neurons and ~16 PDF+ neurons. Flies expressing only the <italic>GAL4</italic> drivers were used as a control for heat-induced genes.</p><p>Despite much less starting material than brains, expression profiles from both cell types are well correlated between replicates (R<sup>2</sup> &gt; 0.9 between replicates) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A,B</xref>). In contrast, baseline expression profiles among cells and tissues (brains, PDF+ and DA neurons) are distinct as expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref>). Previously identified cell-type enriched transcripts were used as markers to ensure that the correct neurons were collected. The housekeeping gene Act5C is expressed ubiquitously in brains, DA and PDF+ neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). The DA neuron-enriched transcript <italic>ple</italic> (encodes tyrosine hydroxylase) and the PDF+ neuron-specific transcript <italic>pdf</italic> are both highly enriched only in the corresponding neuron types, indicating the correct cell types were collected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Budnik and White, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Helfrich‐Förster, 1997</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.017</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Transcriptome profiling in sorted DA and PDF+ neurons.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Gene expression (log10 FPKM) plot among three biological replicates (baseline levels) in DA neurons. Only genes with FPKM &gt; 0.01 are plotted. (<bold>B</bold>) Gene expression (log10 FPKM) plot among three biological replicates (baseline levels) in PDF+ neurons. Only genes with FPKM &gt; 0.01 are plotted. (<bold>C</bold>) Expression levels of the house-keeping gene (<italic>act5c</italic>) and marker genes (<italic>ple</italic> specific for DA neurons and <italic>pdf</italic> specific for PDF+ neurons) in all three tissues. Numbers to the right of the expression graphs represent data range.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.017">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.017</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig4-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig4s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.018</object-id><label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Transcriptomes of brains, DA and PDF+ neurons are very distinct.</title><p>Baseline gene expression (log10 FPKM) plot of brains, DA and PDF+ neurons.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.018">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.018</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig4-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>There are many neuron-specific ARGs</title><p>85 candidate ARGs in DA neurons and 81 in PDF+ neurons are significantly induced in <italic>dTrpA1</italic> flies but not in control flies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD6-data">Figure 5—source data 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD7-data">2</xref>). There was also very limited overlap between the three sets of ARGs: only six genes are in common between all three sources, brains, DA and PDF+ neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A,B</xref>); 11 additional genes are shared between brains and DA neurons; seven between DA and PDF+; and six between brains and PDF+ neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD8-data">Figure 5—source data 3</xref>). Notably, half of the six common genes are among the 12 genes induced by all three stimulation paradigms in brains (<italic>CG14186, CG17778</italic> and <italic>l(1)G0148,</italic> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>), suggesting that these genes respond to firing in many and perhaps most fly brain neurons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5-data">Figure 3—source data 4</xref>). However, the other nine stimulation-independent brain ARGs are not universally induced, further indicating considerable cell type-specificity of firing-induced gene expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>). Previous work on <italic>hr38</italic> using in situ hybridization is consistent with this interpretation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Fujita et al., 2013</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.019</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Many ARGs are tissue-specifically regulated in response to firing.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Overlap of ARGs in different tissues. (<bold>B</bold>) Gene expression of shared ARGs induced in all tissue types. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM, *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001, exact test. (<bold>C</bold>) Gene expression of tissue-specific ARGs. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM, n.s. represents non-significant, *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001, exact test.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.019">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.019</ext-link></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD6-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.020</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label><caption><title>ARGs induced in DA neurons.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.020">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.020</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig5-data1-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD7-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.021</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 2.</label><caption><title>ARGs induced in PDF+ neurons.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.021">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.021</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig5-data2-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD8-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.022</object-id><label>Figure 5—source data 3.</label><caption><title>Overlapped ARGs in different tissue types.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.022">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.022</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig5-data3-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig5-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig5s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.023</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Not all common ARGs in brains are induced in DA and PDF+ neurons.</title><p>Gene expression of common brain ARGs in brains, DA and PDF+ neurons with <italic>dTrpA1</italic> stimulation. N = 3 biological replicates, error bars represent ±SEM, n.s. represents non-significant, *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001, exact test. <italic>Hr38</italic> in PDF+ neurons is below the expression cutoff (FPKM &lt; 10 even at 60 min after stimulation. Dash line indicates expression cutoff). <italic>Sr</italic> – insignificant increase in PDF+ neurons. <italic>CG30497</italic> – heat-induced in DA neurons. <italic>CG13055 –</italic> heat-induced in DA neurons, low expression and insignificant change in PDF+ neurons. <italic>CG14024, CG8910, CG42708, Mctp</italic> – only induced in brains. <italic>CG13868 –</italic> insignificant in PDF+ neurons.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.023">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.023</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig5-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig5s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.024</object-id><label>Figure 5—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Big overlap among heat-induced genes in different tissues.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.024">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.024</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig5-figsupp2-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Indeed, these data indicate that most ARGs are cell type-specific (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). For example, <italic>CG13054</italic> and <italic>grass</italic> are only significantly induced in brains and DA but not PDF+ neurons; <italic>Mtk</italic> and <italic>CG8407</italic> are only significantly induced in DA neurons; <italic>CG9313</italic> and <italic>DAT</italic> are exclusively up-regulated in PDF+ neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). There are also genes like <italic>JhI-21</italic> and <italic>CG10863,</italic> which show changes in sorted DA and PDF+ neurons but smaller or no changes in brains; this suggests masking/dilution effects in brains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). In contrast, almost complete overlap was observed for heat-induced genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2</xref>). In sum, a preponderance of cell-type specific ARGs suggests that they endow their neurons with specific functions and lead to different firing-induced consequences.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Promoter regions of ARGs are at permissive state prior to stimulation</title><p>Chromatin structure plays an important role in regulating gene expression, and promoters (TSS) of mammalian IEGs are usually located in open chromatin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Fowler et al., 2011</xref>). To address the chromatin states of fly ARG TSSs, we performed ATAC-seq in fly brains expressing <italic>Elav-GAL4; UAS-dTrpA1</italic> or its sibling control strain expressing <italic>Elav-GAL4; CyO</italic> before or 30 min after a temperature shift.</p><p>The TSS and its surrounding region (±250 bp) of all annotated fly genes are more accessible than other regions in the genome as expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s1">Figure 6—figure supplement 1</xref>). This region of ARGs also shows enhanced accessibility but does not detectably change with firing despite the increase in transcription (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). Even the TSS accessibility of top-ranked ARGs like <italic>hr38</italic> (rank #1) and <italic>CG7995</italic> (rank #6) shows no differences with firing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s2">Figure 6—figure supplement 2</xref>). This is in contrast to the TSS of heat shock protein genes (HSPs), which possesses less accessible chromatin than that of ARGs at baseline but opens substantially by 30 min in both the <italic>dTrpA1</italic> and control flies in response to heat (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). In fact, the whole gene body of heat shock genes opens with heat, consistent with what was shown previously at the <italic>hsp70</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Petesch and Lis, 2008</xref>).<fig-group><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.025</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Promoter regions of ARGs are at permissive state prior to stimulation.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Average chromatin accessibility at TSS of <italic>dTrpA1</italic>-induced ARGs in brains expressing <italic>Elav-GAL4;UAS-dTrpA1</italic> or <italic>Elav-GAL4/CyO</italic> (control) at 0 or 30 min of temperature shift. TSS is aligned to 0 at x-axis which indicates the distance from TSS in base pair. Negative numbers indicate upstream of TSS and positive indicates downstream. Same for all the graphs in this figure. (<bold>B</bold>) Average chromatin accessibility at TSS of <italic>hr38</italic> in brains expressing <italic>Elav-GAL4;UAS-dTrpA1</italic> or <italic>Elav-GAL4/CyO</italic> (control) at 0 or 30 min of temperature shift. (<bold>C</bold>) Average chromatin accessibility at TSS of heat-shock proteins in brains expressing <italic>Elav-GAL4;UAS-dTrpA1</italic> or <italic>Elav-GAL4/CyO</italic> (control) at 0 or 30 min of temperature shift. (<bold>D</bold>) Average chromatin accessibility at TSS of all expressed genes (FPKM &gt; 0.1) and ARGs induced with different stimulation paradigms. Data are the average of all different conditions (genotypes and time points) and no changes of chromatin accessibility were observed among these conditions.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.025">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.025</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig6-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig6s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.026</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Promoter regions of all annotated genes are more accessible in brains.</title><p>Average reads of TSS sites of all annotated genes in different genotypes (<italic>Elav/CyO</italic> and <italic>Elav/dTrpA1</italic>) and time points (0 and 30 min). Chromatin accessibility shows almost no changes under different conditions. TSS is aligned to 0 at x-axis which indicates the distance from TSS in base pair. Negative numbers indicate upstream of TSS and positive indicates downstream.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.026">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.026</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig6-figsupp1-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig6s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.027</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Chromatin accessibility of TSS of <italic>CG7995</italic> show no changes with firing.</title><p>Reads of TSS sites of <italic>CG7995</italic> in different genotypes (<italic>Elav/CyO</italic> and <italic>Elav/dTrpA1</italic>) and time points (0 and 30 min). Chromatin accessibility shows almost no changes under different conditions. TSS is aligned to 0 at x-axis which indicates the distance from TSS in base pair. Negative numbers indicate upstream of TSS and positive indicates downstream.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.027">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.027</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig6-figsupp2-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig6s3" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.028</object-id><label>Figure 6—figure supplement 3.</label><caption><title>Expression levels of ARGs at baseline levels.</title><p>Expression levels of all expressed annotated genes (FPKM &gt; 0.1), and ARGs induced with different paradigms. Only KCl-induced ARGs show significantly higher expression levels. Error bars represent ±SEM, n.s. represents non-significant, ****p&lt;0.0001, one-way ANOVA.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.028">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.028</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig6-figsupp3-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>Despite the lack of a firing-induced change in ARG chromatin TSSs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>), they are notably more accessible prior to stimulation compared to all expressed, annotated genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). Since baseline ATAC-seq profiles are robust and minimally affected by genetic background (unpublished data from Rosbash lab), baseline chromatin profiles from ARGs induced by the other paradigms were pooled for analysis. These ARGs, like the <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs, also show higher accessibility than the rest of the genome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). This is unlikely due to higher baseline expression levels; only KCl-induced ARGs show significantly higher baseline expression levels despite showing intermediate chromatin accessibility of the three firing paradigms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6s3">Figure 6—figure supplements 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). In conclusion, ARG TSS regions are generally more accessible at baseline, presumably to allow rapid transcriptional induction upon stimulation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Generation of luciferase reporters for neuronal activity</title><p>Since little was previously known about fly ARGs, no useful neuronal activity reporters comparable to c-fos have been constructed. We therefore used the information in this study to generate several luciferase reporters for monitoring neuronal activity in living flies. We used the online motif enrichment tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://veda.cs.uiuc.edu/cgi-bin/MET/interface.pl">http://veda.cs.uiuc.edu/cgi-bin/MET/interface.pl</ext-link>) to identify transcription factor binding sites in either the 1 kb or 5 kb upstream region of <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs; expressed genes (FPKM &gt; 0 at baseline and FPKM &gt; 10 with stimulation) were used as a null set for background subtraction. <italic>Lola</italic> (significance = 4.13E-07)<italic>, eip78C</italic> (significance = 5.92E-05)<italic>, relish</italic> (<italic>rel,</italic> significance = 1.78E-04), <italic>broad</italic> (<italic>br,</italic> significance = 6.62E-02, insignificant<underline>)</underline> and <italic>cf2</italic> (significance = 0.43, insignificant) were chosen to represent different levels of enrichment ranking, from high to low (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD9-data">Figure 7—source data 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD10-data">2</xref>). Three binding sites of each transcription factor were multimerized and inserted into a vector containing <italic>mCherry</italic> and <italic>luciferase</italic>, which originated from the Yin lab (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Tanenhaus et al., 2012</xref>), and transgenic flies generated.<fig-group><fig id="fig7" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.029</object-id><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Generation of luciferase reporters for in vivo monitoring of neuronal activity.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schemes of transgenes constructed for monitoring neuronal activity (top) and other transgenes crossed to be expressed in the same flies. Transcription factor binding sites include binding sites of LOLA, EIP78C and REL. Three of each transcription factor binding site were multimerized and fused upstream to the promoter and individually injected to fly embryos. These reporter-containing flies were then crossed to the existing <italic>Elav-GAL4, UAS-FLP</italic> and <italic>UAS-ChR-XXL</italic> (not in controls) flies. (<bold>B</bold>) Luciferase levels of flies expressing the constructed reporters exposed to a 30 s LED stimulation recorded every 10–15 min for ~4 hr. Gray indicates luciferase levels of control flies expressing all the transgenes in (<bold>A</bold>) except for <italic>UAS-ChR2-XXL.</italic> Red indicates flies expressing all the transgenes in (<bold>A</bold>). The experimental and control flies were put in the same 96-well plate and stimulated and recorded in parallel. The 30 s LED exposure is indicated by the black bars below the graphs. N = 8 flies. Representative images of multiple biological replicates are shown. Shaded regions represent ±SD.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.029">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.029</ext-link></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD9-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.030</object-id><label>Figure 7—source data 1.</label><caption><title>Motif enrichment in the 5 kb upstream regions of <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.030">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.030</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig7-data1-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p><p><supplementary-material id="SD10-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.031</object-id><label>Figure 7—source data 2.</label><caption><title>Motif enrichment in the 1 kb upstream regions of <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs.</title><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.031">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.031</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="docx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig7-data2-v1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig7-v1"/></fig><fig id="fig7s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.032</object-id><label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Luciferase reporters for <italic>br</italic> and <italic>cf2</italic> show no change with LED stimulation in both experiment (red) and control (gray) flies.</title><p>The 30 s LED exposure is indicated by the black bars below the graphs. N = 8 flies. Shaded regions represent ±SD.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.032">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.032</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig7-figsupp1-v1"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>To assay the reporters, they were crossed to <italic>Elav-GAL4;UAS-flp;UAS</italic>-<italic>ChR2-XXL</italic>. In progeny expressing all the transgenes, GAL4 is expressed pan-neuronally and activates expression of <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> to fire neurons. GAL4 also activates <italic>flp,</italic> which removes sequences between the two FRT sites in the reporter; this allows brain-specific expression of luciferase under the control of the enhancer, the transcription factor-multimer, and the promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). Adult progeny were subjected to a protocol like in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>: adult flies were subjected to a single 30 s blue LED exposure, after which their luciferase levels were monitored every 10–15 min for several hours with a top counter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Brandes et al., 1996</xref>). All flies expressing <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> showed seizure behavior within seconds of LED exposure as described above, whereas the control flies without <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> expression were unaffected.</p><p>The three transcription factors (LOLA, EIP78C, and REL) with high significance showed a dramatic increase in luciferase signal immediately after LED exposure, and the signal decayed in about an hour (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>). In contrast, the two transcription factors with much lower significance (<italic>br, cf2</italic>) showed no change (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>.). Although the luciferase levels are somewhat noisy, they show that the three transcription factors with high significance are rapidly activated in response to firing. We also note that the different reporters may be activated in different neurons, i.e., the results do not imply that we have identified a <italic>fos</italic>-eqivalent for <italic>Drosophila</italic>. However, they do indicate that the strategy is sound and should work for other activity-activated transcription factors and for the design of additional reporters, including for cell-specific neuronal activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Guo et al., 2016</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Using high-throughput sequencing, we identified ARGs in fly brains in response to <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic>, <italic>dTrpA1</italic> and KCl-induced neural firing. Each stimulation paradigm induced expression of about 100 genes, and there is substantial overlap between the 3 sets of ARGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>). The most robust ARGs are the two known genes identified previously, <italic>hr38</italic> and <italic>sr</italic>; they are induced dramatically by <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> and <italic>dTrpA1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). They are also induced with KCl albeit with smaller amplitudes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). 10 additional genes are also induced by all three protocols, and even more genes are induced by at least two paradigms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>). Although the results dramatically increase the number of common ARGs, there are also a large number of specialized ARG candidate genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>). Not surprisingly perhaps, KCl has the most different ARGs. This is presumably because it is the only in vitro stimulation paradigm and stimulates the whole brain including non-neuronal cells and tissues.</p><p>We also used the <italic>dTrpA1</italic> paradigm to identify ARGs in sorted neurons. Many of them are specific to neuron type, and even the most robust brain ARGs are not necessarily induced by firing in every region of the brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>). This is in contrast to heat-induced genes, most of which are shared by the three sources of RNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s2">Figure 5—figure supplement 2</xref>.).</p><p>Heat-induced gene expression unfortunately creates a complicated situation: some putative specific ARGs are also induced with the 18°C to 29°C shift in control (no <italic>dTrpA1</italic>) samples. These genes are thus excluded from the ARG list because they are defined as heat-induced by the cutoffs used in the analysis. Because it is possible that the temperature shift can lead to neuronal firing, e.g., by activating endogenous <italic>dTrpA1</italic>, there is currently no clear distinction between heat- and firing-induced genes. Future experiments with other tools like <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> may be able to provide more information. In any case, the neuron-specific ARGs probably contribute to different physiological responses, which contribute in turn to distinct behavioral responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Guo et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Ueno et al., 2012</xref>). The results also provide good candidates as neural activity markers, e.g., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>, and suggest that multiple genes should be tried, to accommodate cell type as well as firing heterogeneity.</p><p>Although the in vivo nature of our most important stimulation paradigms precluded using inhibitors to assay the dependence of ARGs on de novo protein synthesis (data not shown), the induction time scales of these fly ARGs, 60–90 min, resemble those of mammalian IEGs. A comparison between fly ARGs with mammalian IEGs therefore seems appropriate.</p><p>Whereas mammalian IEGs are highly enriched in transcription factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Spiegel et al., 2014</xref>), they are less enriched in the fly brain and sorted neuron ARGs: <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> induced ARGs contain only seven transcription factors among 96 genes; this is a much smaller fraction than in mammals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). KCl-induced ARGs show no enrichment in functions, and <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs in the cell types have a weak enrichment in different functions, such as steroid hormone receptor activity in brains, imaginal disc growth factor receptor binding in DA neurons and organic anion transmembrane transporter activity in PDF+ neurons (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). The weak enrichment suggests diverse ARG functions, which resemble more closely mammalian DRGs or SRGs rather than PRGs (see below).<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.033</object-id><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Gene ontology analysis on <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs in different tissues with GOrilla.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.033">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.033</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top"/><th valign="top"><p>Functions</p></th><th valign="top"><p>p-value</p></th><th valign="top"><p>Genes</p></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><p>Brains</p></td><td valign="top"><p>Steroid hormone receptor activity</p></td><td valign="top"><p>0.000536</p></td><td valign="top"><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>DA</p></td><td valign="top"><p>Imaginal disc growth factor receptor binding</p></td><td valign="top"><p>0.000843</p></td><td valign="top"><p>4</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><p>PDF+</p></td><td valign="top"><p>Organic anion transmembrane transporter activity</p></td><td valign="top"><p>0.000742</p></td><td valign="top"><p>5</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>Less transcription factor activity and more diverse functions are consistent with the fact that fly homologues of the two most universal mammalian IEGs <italic>c-fos</italic> and <italic>c-jun, kayak</italic> and <italic>jra</italic> respectively, are not induced or poorly induced under most conditions. This is especially true for <italic>kayak; jra</italic> is induced by both <italic>dTrpA1</italic> and KCl in brain but with quite small fold changes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2-data">Figure 3—source data 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3-data">2</xref>).</p><p>We also noticed that most fly ARGs show rather small fold-changes upon stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>). It is unlikely that this is due to brain tissue heterogeneity as similar results were obtained with the sorted neurons. A similar weak induction of seizure-induced genes was previously reported in fly heads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Guan et al., 2005</xref>). As only the first 60–90 min after stimulation was assayed, it is possible that the small fold-changes reflects a slower induction time course in flies than in mammals. Another possibility is that the nature of the firing, e.g., firing rate, has an impact on the induction amplitudes, time courses and even the genes induced. The differences between the three stimulation paradigms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>) indicate that this possibility may have some merit. Nonetheless and taken together with the stimulation-paradigm and cell type-specific induction of ARGs, the modest fold-changes at 60–90 min helps explain the long-standing failure to identify <italic>bona fide</italic> and well-accepted ARGs in flies.<fig id="fig8" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.034</object-id><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><title>Fold changes distribution of all ARGs.</title><p>X-axis indicates fold changes (log2) at 60 or 90 (for KCl) min. Y-axis indicates the frequency of genes. ChR2-XXL indicates <italic>ChR2-XXL-</italic>induced ARGs. dTrpA1 (brains) indicates <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced genes in brains. KCl (60 min/90 min) indicates KCl-induced ARGs in 60 or 90 min. DA indicates <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs in DA neurons. PDF+ indicates <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs in PDF+ neurons.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.034">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.034</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig8-v1"/></fig></p><p>Instead of having shorter average gene lengths like in mammals, fly ARGs (brain as well as sorted neurons) show even longer gene length distributions than average fly genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>). Several robust ARGs are above 10 kb with large first introns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2—figure supplement 1</xref>). For example, <italic>hr38</italic> is ~31 kb and shares high protein sequence identity with the mammalian protein encoded by <italic>Nr4a2</italic>; it spans only ~16.8 kb. <italic>sr</italic>, the shorter isoform of which is induced by firing, spans ~11.7 kb, whereas EGR3, the mouse gene that encodes a protein with high identity to SR, is only ~5.2 kb in length. Considering the much smaller genome size and gene size of flies compared to mammals and the potential slower transcription elongation rates in flies, the long gene lengths and large first introns of fly ARGs may counterintuitively serve to significantly slow down induction rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Ardehali and Lis, 2009</xref>). Another possibility is that the large gene size reflects important regulatory elements for firing-mediated transcription embedded in the introns of these genes. Perhaps they are relevant to the diversity and cell type specificity of most fly ARGs.<fig id="fig9" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.035</object-id><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><title>Gene length distribution of all annotated genes and ARGs.</title><p>All indicates all annotated genes. Expressed indicates genes with FPKM &gt; 0 at baseline, FPKM &gt; 10 with stimulation in brains. Brains indicate <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs in brains. DA indicates <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs in DA neurons. PDF+ indicates <italic>dTrpA1-</italic>induced ARGs in PDF+ neurons. KCl indicates KCl-induced ARGs in 90 min.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.035">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.035</ext-link></p></caption><graphic mime-subtype="x-tiff" mimetype="image" xlink:href="elife-19942-fig9-v1"/></fig></p><p>From this point of view, fly ARGs resemble more closely mammalian DRGs or even SRGs than IEGs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Spiegel et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Tullai et al., 2007</xref>). Mammalian IEGs are largely shared between different types of neurons such as excitatory and inhibitory neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Spiegel et al., 2014</xref>), but fly ARGs like SRGs appear quite tissue-type specific, i.e., many genes are only induced in one of the tissue types tested despite similar baseline levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Mardinly et al., 2016</xref>). This is in line with the fact that fly neurons appear quite heterogeneous, e.g., they have distinct transcript enrichment and electrophysiological properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Liang et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Nagoshi et al., 2010</xref>). Although unlikely in our view, it remains possible that PDF+ and DA neurons are outliers and that ARGs in most other neurons are less cell type-specific. Nonetheless, we hypothesize that specific ARGs are an important feature of neuronal identity and play a role in neuron-specific physiological properties. As an example, preliminary analysis indicates that the PDF cell-ARGs are a subset of the mRNAs that undergo circadian oscillations within these neurons ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kula-Eversole et al., 2010</xref>] and data not shown).</p><p>The non-identical ARGs with the different paradigms also suggest different mechanisms for responding to different modes of stimulation. A less stereotyped response may be generally characteristic of invertebrates. Even non-mammalian vertebrates may be quantitatively if not qualitatively different from mammals. For example, induction of IEGs like <italic>fos</italic> and <italic>egr1</italic> was also observed in birds and zebrafish but with smaller increases (about 4 to 6-fold) than human and mice (usually well above 10-fold) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bébien et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Burmeister and Fernald, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lopes et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mokin and Keifer, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Moore and Whitmore, 2014</xref>). However, more high-throughput data are required to determine if the non-mammalian vertebrates resemble more closely flies or mammals. In addition, different stimulation paradigms were employed in the non-mammalian vertebrate studies, making the data less comparable. In any case, one can imagine that mammals need a more potent initial transcriptional system than flies to respond to firing. Not only are mammalian neurons bigger with more and longer processes, but they also have much larger genomes (longer genomic DNA and more enhancers to bind); both of these factors may require higher levels of transcripts to generate a required higher abundance of transcription factors. The increase may be required to activate the thousands of enhancers in mammals rather than the hundreds in flies, and/or more structural proteins are needed to change the morphology of ‘giant’ mammalian neurons.</p><p>Nonetheless, one feature shared by fly ARGs and mammalian IEGs is the relatively permissive state of the TSS chromatin structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Fowler et al., 2011</xref>). ATAC-seq shows that the chromatin accessibility of the ARG TSS is higher than that of other genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>), and chromatin architecture contributes to gene expression regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Wu, 1997</xref>). Although no further opening is observed with firing, it is possible that more subtle changes such as histone modifications occur and are not detectable with ATAC-seq (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>). In the cases of mammals, histones around IEGs promoters are modified to be more accessible to transcription factors at baseline; the modification levels could be even higher with firing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Kim et al., 2010</xref>). In any case, the data taken together suggest some blurring of the distinction between IEGs and SRGs in fly ARGs: open chromatin and rapid induction but a diverse set of neuron-specific functions.</p><p>Finally, we successfully generated luciferase reporters for in vivo neural activity monitoring based on the <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>). Rather than using the regulatory region of a single gene to construct a reporter, we generalized a previous strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Tanenhaus et al., 2012</xref>) and used enriched transcription factor binding sites combined with FRT sites for cell type specific expression and a short-lived luciferase gene. This was not only to amplify the signal but also to avoid the situation in which a particular promoter is only responsive in certain neurons or to certain types of stimulation. We thought this was likely considering that ARGs are stimulation paradigm- and cell type-specific. Indeed, we tried many Janelia Research Campus GAL4 drivers, which use different regions of the <italic>hr38, sr</italic> and <italic>cbt</italic> promoters for neural activity monitoring, but they were all either unresponsive or generated very low luciferase levels (data not shown).</p><p>Two of the three positive reporters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>) work well for circadian monitoring of neuronal activity in PDF+ neurons (data not shown), suggesting the signal to noise ratio is sufficient for monitoring small subsets of neurons. This result and others indicate that our strategy as well as these specific reporters can provide the temporal and spatial resolution for in vivo monitoring of small numbers of specific neurons. The strategy also builds a foundation for future elaboration and optimization.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s4-1"><title><italic>Drosophila</italic> stocks</title><p><italic>Drosophila</italic> (RRID:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/FlyBase_FBst1021211">FlyBase_FBst1021211</ext-link>) were reared on standard cornmeal/agar medium supplemented with yeast under 12 hr LD cycles at 25°C. <italic>Elav-GAL4</italic> (C155) was obtained from Bloomington Stock Center. <italic>UAS-ChR2-XXL</italic> was a kind gift from Kittel Lab. <italic>UAS-dTrpA1</italic>was from Dr. Paul Garrity. <italic>TH-GAL4</italic> was described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Guo et al., 2014</xref>). <italic>Pdf-GAL4</italic> was described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Stoleru et al., 2004</xref>). <italic>UAS-mCD8GFP;Pdf-GAL4</italic> was described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Nagoshi et al., 2010</xref>). Flies expressing both <italic>GAL4</italic> and <italic>UAS-dTrpA1</italic> were reared at 18°C until tested. <italic>UAS-FLP</italic> (#55804) was obtained from Bloomington Stock Center.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Stimulation protocols</title><p>For the <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> paradigm, both the control and experimental flies were transferred from normal fly food to all trans-retinal (ATR) – containing food for one day and kept in dark until stimulation. ATR powder was dissolved in EtOH into 100 mM stock, and further diluted to 0.4 mM as final working concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Klapoetke et al., 2014</xref>). To fire neurons, 30 s 10 Hz 0.7 V blue LED with 5 ms pulse width was given to flies. Flies were allowed to recover in dark for 15, 30, 60 min.</p><p>For the <italic>dTrpA1</italic> paradigm, both the control and experimental flies were reared at 18°C and shifted to 29°C for 0, 15, 30, 60 min to fire neurons.</p><p>For the KCl paradigm, Canton-S WT fly brains were dissected in adult hemolymph-like medium (AHL) consisting 108 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 8.2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 4 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 1 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 5 mM trehalose, 10 mM sucrose and 5 mM HEPES and transferred to depolarization buffer containing 28 mM NaCl, 85 mM KCl, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 8.2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 4 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 1 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 5 mM trehalose, 10 mM sucrose and 5 mM HEPES (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Shang et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Wang et al., 2003</xref>). pH for both buffers was adjusted to 7.5, and mOsm to 265.</p><p>For <italic>ChR2-XXL</italic> and <italic>dTrpA1</italic> stimulation performed under ex vivo condition, fly brains were dissected in AHL and subjected to either a 30 s LED exposure or a 60 min 29°C water bath incubation.</p><p>For all experiments assayed from brains and heads, 8–10 brains (50% males and females) from ~7 day-old young adults were used for each condition. Brains were carefully dissected to remove all non-brain tissues, and only intact undamaged brains were used for RNA extraction. For sorted neurons, 20 young males and 20 young females were used.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>ArcLight imaging</title><p>Fly brains were dissected in AHL and then mobilized using a pin anchored to the chamber bottom laid with Sylgard (Dow Corning, Midland, MI) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Shang et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Wang et al., 2003</xref>). Depolarization buffer was perfused into the chamber using a gravity-fed ValveLink perfusion system (Automate Scientific, Berkeley, CA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Haynes et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Shang et al., 2013</xref>). Imaging was performed with an Olympus BX51WI fluorescence microscope (Olympus, Center Valley, PA) under an Olympus x60 (0.90W, LUMPlanFI) water-immersion objective, and captured using a charge-coupled device camera (Hamamatsu ORCA C472-80-12AG). The following filter sets were used for excitation and emission (Chroma Technology, Bellows Falls, VT): excitation, HQ470/x40; dichroic, Q495LP; emission, HQ525/50m. <italic>µ</italic>Manager was used for recording with 2 Hz with 4 x binning with 500 ms exposure time and 50 ms intervals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Edelstein et al., 2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>RNA extraction, amplification for sequencing libraries and qPCR validation</title><p>Fly brains or heads were isolated for RNA extraction using TRIzol. mRNA libraries were constructed following Illumina Trueseq protocol. Nascent RNA libraries were constructed as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Rodriguez et al., 2013</xref>). mRNA libraries from sorted neurons were prepared as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abruzzi et al., 2015</xref>). ATAC-seq libraries were done using Nextera DNA Sample Prep Kit. Libraries were sequenced using HiSeq, NextSeq or MiSeq sequencers.</p><p>For qPCR validation, total RNA was reverse-transcribed with random primer (Promega, C1181) and gene expression was then quantified with SYBR Green PCR Master Mix using primers listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11-data">Supplementary file 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Sequencing data analysis</title><p>RNA libraries were mapped to <italic>Drosophila</italic> genome dm3 using Tophat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Trapnell et al., 2009</xref>) with default setting (e.g. two mismatches allowed) and expression levels were quantified using Cufflinks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Trapnell et al., 2012</xref>). FPKM &gt; 0 for un-stimulated groups and FPKM &gt; 10 for stimulated groups were used as expression cutoff. HTSeq (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Anders et al., 2015</xref>) was used to produce raw read count for each genes. EdgeR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">McCarthy et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Robinson et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Robinson and Smyth, 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Zhou et al., 2014</xref>) was used for statistical analysis. N = 3 biological replicates for libraries from brains. N = 3–4 biological replicates for libraries from sorted neurons. p-value &lt; 0.01 was defined as significance except for PDF+ ARGs (p-value &lt; 0.05 due to slightly bigger variation). To distinguish heat- or firing-induced ARGs in <italic>dTrpA1</italic> paradigms, t-test was used among replicates between the experiment and control flies. ARGs are defined to be firing-induced only when P-value &lt; 0.05 and experiment flies show bigger induction than control flies. For ATAC-seq, Trim Galore (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/</ext-link>) is used to trim low quality bases (quality score &lt; 20) on either end of the reads and remove adapter/tagmentation sequences. Bowtie2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Langmead and Salzberg, 2012</xref>) was used to map the reads to reference genome with parameters ‘-D 20 -R 3 -N 1 -L 20’. Alignments below a score of 10 were discarded, and PCR duplicates were removed using Picard (version 1.119). Chromatin accessibility at TSS were pooled and averaged as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Menet et al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Generation of luciferase reporter flies</title><p>The cre-luc vector was a kind gift from Jerry Yin lab. The cre sites of the vector were swapped with binding site multimers (3X) of transcription factors including LOLA, EIP78C, REL, BR and CF2 using the primers in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11-data">Supplementary file 1</xref>. Transgenes were injected into w1118 flies with the P-element transformation service of BestGene Inc.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Drs. Oliver Hobert and Haosheng Sun from Columbia University for comments on an early version of the manuscript. We also thank Drs. Suzanne Paradis, Michael Marr, Nelson Lau, Patrick Emery and Leslie Griffith, for comments on a near-final version. Many thanks go to members of Rosbash lab for thoughtful discussion, and especially Kate Abruzzi for comments.</p></ack><sec id="s5" sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf1"><p>The authors declare that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>XC, Conception and design, Acquisition of data, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>RR, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con3"><p>FG, Provided advice and help, Conception and design</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con4"><p>MR, Conception and design, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="s6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="SD11-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.036</object-id><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><title>Supplementary tables.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Primers for qPCR validation. (<bold>B</bold>) Primers for reporter generation</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.19942.036">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.19942.036</ext-link></p></caption><media mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-19942-supp1-v1.pdf"/></supplementary-material><sec id="s7" sec-type="datasets"><title>Major datasets</title><p>The following dataset was generated:</p><p><related-object content-type="generated-dataset" id="data-ro1" source-id="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE83976" source-id-type="uri"><collab>Xiao Chen</collab><x>,</x> <year>2016</year><x>,</x><source>Genome-wide Identification of Neuronal Activity-regulated Genes in Drosophila</source><x>,</x> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE83976">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE83976</ext-link><x>,</x> <comment>Publicly available at NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (accession no: GSE83976)</comment></related-object></p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abruzzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zadina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>RNA-seq profiling of small numbers of drosophila neurons</article-title><source>Methods in enzymology</source><volume>551</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.mie.2014.10.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25662465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyl</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>HTSeq--a Python framework to work with high-throughput sequencing data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25260700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ardehali</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lis</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Tracking rates of transcription and splicing in vivo</article-title><source>Nature Structural Biol Biology</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1123</fpage><lpage>1124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb1109-1123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19888309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bébien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Becamel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Linares</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hipskind</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Immediate-early gene induction by the stresses anisomycin and arsenite in human osteosarcoma cells involves MAPK cascade signaling to Elk-1, CREB and SRF</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1836</fpage><lpage>1847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1206334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12660819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bepari</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamamaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nambu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Takebayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Identification of optogenetically activated striatal medium spiny neurons by Npas4 expression</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>e52783</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23300775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bloodgood</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trepman</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>The activity-dependent transcription factor NPAS4 regulates domain-specific inhibition</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>503</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24201284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Plautz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanewsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Straume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year><article-title>Novel features of drosophila period transcription revealed by real-time luciferase reporting</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80088-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8607986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Budnik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1987">1987</year><article-title>Genetic dissection of dopamine and serotonin synthesis in the nervous system of drosophila melanogaster</article-title><source>Journal of Neurogenetics</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/01677068709102351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3126282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burmeister</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernald</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Evolutionary conservation of the egr-1 immediate-early gene response in a teleost</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>481</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.20380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15562507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Platisa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieribone</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Raccuglia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nitabach</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Genetically targeted optical electrophysiology in intact neural circuits</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>154</volume><fpage>904</fpage><lpage>913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.07.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23932121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawydow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gueta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljaschenko</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullrich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Langenhan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kittel</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Channelrhodopsin-2-XXL, a powerful optogenetic tool for low-light applications</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>13972</fpage><lpage>13977</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1408269111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25201989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edelstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amodaj</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuurman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Computer control of microscopes using µManager</article-title><source>Current Protocols in Molecular Biology</source><volume>14</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/0471142727.mb1420s92</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20890901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yogev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakhini</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Discovering motifs in ranked lists of DNA sequences</article-title><source>PLoS Computational Biology</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e39</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17381235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Navon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinfeld</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakhini</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>GOrilla: a tool for discovery and visualization of enriched GO terms in ranked gene lists</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>48</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-48</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19192299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshete</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Action potential-dependent regulation of gene expression: temporal specificity in ca2+, cAMP-responsive element binding proteins, and mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience </source><volume>17</volume><fpage>7252</fpage><lpage>7266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9295372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Regulation of primary response genes</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2011.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22055182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Visualization of neural activity in insect brains using a conserved immediate early gene, Hr38</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>2063</fpage><lpage>2070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2013.08.051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24120640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziff</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1986">1986</year><article-title>Stimulation of neuronal acetylcholine receptors induces rapid gene transcription</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>234</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.3749894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3749894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Saraswati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Adolfsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Littleton</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Genome-wide transcriptional changes associated with enhanced activity in the drosophila nervous system</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2005.08.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16202711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerullo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>PDF neuron firing phase-shifts key circadian activity neurons in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e02780</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abruzzi</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Circadian neuron feedback controls the drosophila sleep--activity profile</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>536</volume><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature19097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27479324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Christmann</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A single pair of neurons links sleep to memory consolidation in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e03868</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.03868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helfrich‐Förster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Development of pigment‐dispersing hormone‐immunoreactive neurons in the nervous system of <italic>drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><volume>380</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-9861(19970414)380:3&lt;335::AID-CNE4&gt;3.3.CO;2-M</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herschman</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year><article-title>Primary response genes induced by growth factors and tumor promoters</article-title><source>Annual Review of Biochemistry</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bi.60.070191.001433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1883198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McCord</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>A biological function for the neuronal activity-dependent component of bdnf transcription in the development of cortical inhibition</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2008.09.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19038219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulanger</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Riquelme</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brotz</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shatz</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Functional requirement for class I MHC in CNS development and plasticity</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>290</volume><fpage>2155</fpage><lpage>2159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.290.5499.2155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11118151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollins</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiles</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year><article-title>Platelet-derived growth factor generates at least two distinct intracellular signals that modulate gene expression</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Symposia on Quantitative Biology</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/SQB.1988.053.01.061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3254779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kandel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>The molecular biology of memory storage: a dialog between genes and synapses</article-title><source>Bioscience Reports</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1014775008533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12168768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laptewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbara-Haley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuersten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Markenscoff-Papadimitriou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Worley</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreiman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Widespread transcription at neuronal activity-regulated enhancers</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>465</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20393465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunieda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Increased neural activity of a mushroom body neuron subtype in the brains of forager honeybees</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>e371</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17440607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klapoetke</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulver</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Birdsey-Benson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuong</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name><surname>Surek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Melkonian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantine-Paton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyden</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Independent optical excitation of distinct neural populations</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24509633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kula-Eversole</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Allada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Surprising gene expression patterns within and between PDF-containing circadian neurons in drosophila</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>13497</fpage><lpage>13502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1002081107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20624977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Holy</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Taghert</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Synchronous drosophila circadian pacemakers display nonsynchronous Ca²⁺ rhythms in vivo</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>351</volume><fpage>976</fpage><lpage>981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aad3997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26917772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloodgood</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Koon</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Activity-dependent regulation of inhibitory synapse development by Npas4</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>455</volume><fpage>1198</fpage><lpage>1204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18815592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abril-de-Abreu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Brain transcriptomic response to social eavesdropping in zebrafish (Danio rerio)</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0145801</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26713440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Activity-dependent gene expression in honey bee mushroom bodies in response to orientation flight</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Biology</source><volume>216</volume><fpage>2031</fpage><lpage>2038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.084905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23678099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mardinly</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrizi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Centofante</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazinet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzeng</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandel-Brehm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Adesnik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagiolini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Sensory experience regulates cortical inhibition by inducing IGF1 in VIP neurons</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>531</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature17187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26958833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Differential expression analysis of multifactor RNA-Seq experiments with respect to biological variation</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>4288</fpage><lpage>4297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22287627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menet</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pescatore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>CLOCK:BMAL1 is a pioneer-like transcription factor</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.228536.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24395244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mokin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keifer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Expression of the immediate-early gene-encoded protein Egr-1 (zif268) during in vitro classical conditioning</article-title><source>Learning &amp; Memory</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/lm.87305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitmore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Circadian rhythmicity and light sensitivity of the zebrafish brain</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>e86176</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24465943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kula</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tachibana</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Dissecting differential gene expression within the circadian neuronal circuit of drosophila</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19966839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nestler</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year><article-title>Molecular basis of long-term plasticity underlying addiction</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35053570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11252991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petesch</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lis</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Rapid, transcription-independent loss of nucleosomes over a large chromatin domain at Hsp70 loci</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.05.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18614012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Moderated statistical tests for assessing differences in tag abundance</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>2881</fpage><lpage>2887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17881408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Small-sample estimation of negative binomial dispersion, with applications to SAGE data</article-title><source>Biostatistics</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biostatistics/kxm030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17728317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Khodor</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vodala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Menet</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Nascent-Seq analysis of drosophila cycling gene expression</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>E275</fpage><lpage>E284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1219969110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23297234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Donelson</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vecsey</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Short neuropeptide F is a sleep-promoting inhibitory modulator</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2013.07.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24094110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mardinly</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabel</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazinet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Couch</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzeng</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Npas4 regulates excitatory-inhibitory balance within neural circuits through cell-type-specific gene programs</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>157</volume><fpage>1216</fpage><lpage>1229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.03.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24855953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lautermilch</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year><article-title>Coding of neuronal differentiation by calcium transients</article-title><source>BioEssays</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1521-1878(200009)22:9&lt;811::AID-BIES6&gt;3.0.CO;2-G</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10944583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoleru</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Agosto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Coupled oscillators control morning and evening locomotor behaviour of drosophila</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>431</volume><fpage>862</fpage><lpage>868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15483615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanenhaus</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>In vivo circadian oscillation of dCREB2 and NF-κB activity in the drosophila nervous system</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>e45130</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23077489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>TopHat: discovering splice junctions with RNA-Seq</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>1111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19289445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinn</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Differential gene and transcript expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with TopHat and cufflinks</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2012.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tullai</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullenbrock</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sholder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Immediate-early and delayed primary response genes are distinct in function and genomic architecture</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>282</volume><fpage>23981</fpage><lpage>23995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M702044200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17575275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kume</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kume</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Identification of a dopamine pathway that regulates sleep and arousal in drosophila</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>1516</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23064381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Axel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Two-photon calcium imaging reveals an odor-evoked map of activity in the fly brain</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00004-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12553914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Neuronal activity-regulated gene transcription in synapse development and cognitive function</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>a005744</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a005744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21555405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year><article-title>Chromatin remodeling and the control of gene expression</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>272</volume><fpage>28171</fpage><lpage>28174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.45.28171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9353261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Robustly detecting differential expression in RNA sequencing data using observation weights</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>e91</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24753412</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="article-commentary" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.039</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bellen</surname><given-names>Hugo J</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff id="aff4"><institution>Baylor College of Medicine</institution>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife includes the editorial decision letter and accompanying author responses. A lightly edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the most substantive concerns; minor comments are not usually included.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for submitting your article &quot;Genome-wide Identification of Neuronal Activity-regulated Genes in <italic>Drosophila</italic>&quot; for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been favorably evaluated by a Senior Editor and two reviewers, one of whom, Hugo Bellen, is a member of our Board of Reviewing Editors.</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>Chen et al. used three different neuronal stimulation methods and RNAseq to systematically identify Activity-Regulated Genes (ARGs) in <italic>Drosophila</italic>. The study identified 12 ARGs (including previously known ARGs, hr38 and striped) that overlap in the three paradigms but also revealed a large number of stimuli-specific ARGs, suggesting that neurons may respond differently to different stimuli. The authors further performed RNAseq on small groups of neurons isolated by cell sorting (Dopaminergic and Pdf neurons, stimulated by the dTrpA1-strategy) and found that although there were some overlaps, many genes were cell type specific. In addition, the authors investigated the chromatin accessibility of the ARGs pre- and post-stimulation and found that in contrast to mammalian IEGs that show some changes in chromatin structure upon stimulation, the fly ARGs are in an open chromatin state to begin with. Together with the findings that fly ARGs are not enriched for transcription factors and small genes, the authors find an interesting difference between mammalian IEGs and <italic>Drosophila</italic> ARGs, and conclude that fly ARGs are more similar to mammalian secondary response genes (SRGs) or delayed response genes (DRGs). Finally, using the information from these experiments, the authors generated five Luciferase-based reporters and show that three of them show some stimulation induced activation in vivo.</p><p>Overall, we feel that the manuscript is well conceived and well written. Identification of new ARGs and showing a proof-of-principal that this information can be used to generate new tools is valuable. In addition, pan-neuronal and subtype specific transcriptomic profiles of neurons treated with different stimulations are also unique and interesting datasets that can be further mined to extract interesting biological information. The finding that, in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, activity-induced transcription happens downstream of the level of chromatin accessibility will also allow researchers to begin to study the similarities and differences in the mechanism of activity-dependent gene activation between different model organisms. Finally, although not optimized yet, construction of several luciferase based neuronal activity reporter further adds value to this paper. As such, it is likely to be of broad interest and appropriate for publication in <italic>eLife</italic>; however, there are a few issues that must first be addressed:</p><p>Essential revisions (requiring experimental studies):</p><p>1) In all of the figures regarding expression profiling, there are no data confirming that the primary findings in RNAseq can be verified by other methods such as qPCR. We assume that the RNAseq was performed on biological replicates (although we cannot find such info in the Materials and methods). Even so we feel that having independent sets of data to backup these primary findings are critical. The authors should take several genes (top candidates from each of the stimulation paradigms that are shared and are unique) and perform qPCR or other assays to detect RNA transcripts (or protein if there is a change) to demonstrate that their findings are reproducible and can be verified by independent methods.</p><p>2) The authors find that although there are overlapping genes, ARGs found in different stimulation paradigms are significantly different. The authors speculate this could be reflecting some gene expression changes in non-neuronal cells (glia etc.), global changes that happen independent of neuronal activation (light-response, heat-shock response) or the difference in in-vivo versus ex-vivo experiments. One possibility that the authors do not discuss is the strength and duration of the stimulation. Based on the Methods section, the ChR2 paradigm stimulates the flies only for 30 seconds at the beginning and follow transcriptional changes, while dTrpA1 and high K<sup>+</sup> paradigms continuously activate the neurons for the entire duration (up to 60/90min). If the authors perform a longer stimulation in ChR2 flies, they may see more genes that overlap with the other 2 paradigms. Also, in order to determine if the difference between high-K<sup>+</sup> stimulation and the other two paradigms are simply due to differences in-vivo and ex-vivo sample preparation, the authors can perform an ex-vivo experiment for the ChR2 and dTRPA1 flies as well and see how that may affect the list of ARGs. Considering that additional RNAseq may require significant time, effort, and cost, the authors can select several high-confident hits from each of the paradigms (see major point 1) and test them via qPCRs or other methods.</p><p>3) In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>, the authors show that 3 reporters they generated respond to ChR2-mediated neuronal activation. However, they do not show how these reporters behave in the other two stimulation paradigms (dTrp1A, high K<sup>+</sup>). Was there a reason the author only focused on ChR2-ARGs? Is the binding site of Lola, Eip78 and Relish enriched in ARG genes activated by the other two paradigms? How do these reporters (and the two that didn't respond to ChR2-activation) behave when stimulated with dTrp1A and high-K<sup>+</sup>? Since a key conclusion that the authors draw from their RNAseq data is that stimulation paradigms make a big difference, the authors should test their reporter under different stimulation conditions. In addition, the authors should comment on whether their reporter signal is strong enough that they can be used to visualize neuronal activity in all (e.g. elav-GAL4) or subpopulation (e.g. TH-GAL4, Pdf-GAL4) of neurons.</p><p>Additional revisions (Textural changes/clarification):</p><p>1) Do any of the ARG genes the authors identified have known roles in neuronal plasticity? If so, what portion? This should be included in the Discussion.</p><p>2) We cannot find the information of how many flies or brains were used for each experiment. Also, were all of the flies of the same sex or a mix? How old were the flies when these experiments were performed? The authors should provide enough information so that others can replicate the findings.</p><p>3) For ChR2-flies, the authors state &quot;A 30-second 10 Hz LED exposure was sufficient to induce a uniform seizure within seconds, and all flies were able to recover within 15 min.&quot; For the dTrpA1 experiments, however, no phenotypic descriptions are provided. Did the dTrpA1 flies also show a similar seizure phenotype? If the flies do not show seizures or show a different behavioral defect during the stimulation, the two stimuli maybe acting on different neuronal populations (despite the two proteins being expressed pan-neuronally with elav-GAL4) leading to a difference in the ARG list.</p><p>4) The authors should state the amount/concentration of ATR that was fed to theChR2 flies.</p><p>5) In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>, Is the 'weak anti-correlation' between change in gene expression and relative gene length significant? What is the R value?</p><p>6) In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>, there appears to be a second peak of luciferase activity at the end of recording with the eip78C reporter. Is this typical? Background? Non-specific activation? Is the signal observed significantly different from the control (looks very similar)? Additionally, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>, both of these 'control' reporters seem to have less of a response compared to controls. Is there any possible explanation for that phenomenon? Is the difference significant?</p><p>7) Many of the experiments used a control with CyO in the background. While we understand that there are advantages to using siblings for comparison, balancer chromosomes often incur unpredictable phenotypes. Therefore, were any steps taken to ensure that the CyO chromosome was not significantly different from WT?</p><p>8) In the second paragraph of the subsection “Promoter Regions of ARGs are at Permissive State Prior to Stimulation”, what do you mean when you refer to &quot;all annotated genes&quot;? This phrasing is used several times throughout the manuscript, but is not adequately explained. Does this mean all fly genes, all ARGs or something else?</p><p>9) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>: Misalignment of &quot;Dissecte d Brains&quot; in A.</p><p>10) In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, were the 8 genes shown in E selected at random or was there a reason to leave out the other 4?</p><p>11) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>: The axes for A and B are not internally consistent; I believe that all coordinates should range from -5 to 5.</p><p>12) Formatting of Tables 9 and 10 needs to be adjusted. Also, since only 3 of the columns in both of these tables have different values, the tables could be shrunk down with the rest of the information (which is the same for all columns) described in a legend.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19942.040</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p><italic>Essential revisions (requiring experimental studies):</italic> </p><p><italic>1) In all of the figures regarding expression profiling, there are no data confirming that the primary findings in RNAseq can be verified by other methods such as qPCR. We assume that the RNAseq was performed on biological replicates (although we cannot find such info in the Materials and methods). Even so we feel that having independent sets of data to backup these primary findings are critical. The authors should take several genes (top candidates from each of the stimulation paradigms that are shared and are unique) and perform qPCR or other assays to detect RNA transcripts (or protein if there is a change) to demonstrate that their findings are reproducible and can be verified by independent methods.</italic> </p><p>Sorry for the confusion. Yes, all the ‘N’ mentioned in the manuscript indicates biological replicates. We’ve added this information in the both the text, legends and Methods sections.</p><p>To respond to your request, RT-qPCR has now been performed for verification purposes, and most of the genes tested are consistent with the sequencing results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>).</p><p><italic>2) The authors find that although there are overlapping genes, ARGs found in different stimulation paradigms are significantly different. The authors speculate this could be reflecting some gene expression changes in non-neuronal cells (glia etc.), global changes that happen independent of neuronal activation (light-response, heat-shock response) or the difference in in-vivo versus ex-vivo experiments. One possibility that the authors do not discuss is the strength and duration of the stimulation. Based on the Methods section, the ChR2 paradigm stimulates the flies only for 30 seconds at the beginning and follow transcriptional changes, while dTrpA1 and high K<sup>+</sup> paradigms continuously activate the neurons for the entire duration (up to 60/90min). If the authors perform a longer stimulation in ChR2 flies, they may see more genes that overlap with the other 2 paradigms. Also, in order to determine if the difference between high-K<sup>+</sup> stimulation and the other two paradigms are simply due to differences in-vivo and ex-vivo sample preparation, the authors can perform an ex-vivo experiment for the ChR2 and dTRPA1 flies as well and see how that may affect the list of ARGs. Considering that additional RNAseq may require significant time, effort, and cost, the authors can select several high-confident hits from each of the paradigms (see major point 1) and test them via qPCRs or other methods.</italic> </p><p>In response to these suggestions, we performed several experiments and described most of the results in a single paragraph in the text and added the figures as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s3">Figure 3—figure supplements 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s4">4</xref>. We added this detail, text and figures, so that the reviewers and editor can examine the results. However, we find the addition rather cumbersome. So we are happy to refer to these PCR data as data not shown if editor/reviewers agree. On the other hand, we are more than willing to keep all this information in the manuscript. This is your choice.</p><p><italic>3) In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>, the authors show that 3 reporters they generated respond to ChR2-mediated neuronal activation. However, they do not show how these reporters behave in the other two stimulation paradigms (dTrp1A, high K<sup>+</sup>). Was there a reason the author only focused on ChR2-ARGs? Is the binding site of Lola, Eip78 and Relish enriched in ARG genes activated by the other two paradigms? How do these reporters (and the two that didn't respond to ChR2-activation) behave when stimulated with dTrp1A and high-K<sup>+</sup>? Since a key conclusion that the authors draw from their RNAseq data is that stimulation paradigms make a big difference, the authors should test their reporter under different stimulation conditions. In addition, the authors should comment on whether their reporter signal is strong enough that they can be used to visualize neuronal activity in all (e.g. elav-GAL4) or subpopulation (e.g. TH-GAL4, Pdf-GAL4) of neurons.</italic> </p><p>The reporters were originally generated based on the bioinformatics on the ChR2-XXL induced ARG list, and therefore tested only with that same paradigm. The ChR2-ARGs were chosen because we think this is a more physiological way to fire neurons than the other two paradigms, which involved heat and high K<sup>+</sup> depolarization. For dTrpA1 at least, the data back this up with lots of heat shock genes induced by the temperature shift even without dTrpA1. We later found that the 3 positive transcription factors are also enriched for the other two stimulation paradigms. We didn’t test the reporters by monitoring ex vivo brains with the KCl paradigm. First, we are somewhat fixated on awake-behaving flies as we are developing these reporters and currently using them as a real time monitoring tool for living animals (see below). In addition, and from a more practical point of view, our top counter machine although very sensitive is not well-adapted to ex vivo monitoring.</p><p>In contrast and also as suggested, we tried the reporters with the TrpA1 paradigm (Experimental flies: Elav-GAL4;UAS-dTrpA1;UAS-FLP;reporters, control flies: Elav-GAL4;UAS-FLP;reporters). Somewhat surprisingly perhaps, all reporters including the two negative ones responded to the 21°C to 30°C temperature shift, without UAS-dTrpA1 as well as with (data not shown), suggesting that heat may increase the activity of many transcription factors. Although heat can also fire some neurons, the induction here is more likely due to heat alone since the levels of induction are indistinguishable between the experimental and control flies for all reporters. The observation also suggests that these reporters are not exclusively responsive to neuronal firing. However, we cannot at present exclude the possibility that this is an artifact, for example a temperature effect on luciferase reporter activity. We cannot sort this out within the time frame of returning the manuscript, so the assay of the reporters remains restricted to ChR2 in this paper, where fortunately we have convincing negative controls.</p><p>On the other hand, the three reporters have been tested under the control of Pdf-GAL4 since submitting this manuscript. We could not easily combine them with ChR2 in the PDF cells for complicated genetic reasons. However, a clear circadian pattern can be observed for both rel and lola but not eip78C, suggesting low EIP78C levels or activity in PDF+ cells. Importantly, the pattern is indistinguishable from our in vivo Ca++ reporter system (Guo et al. 2016). This indicates that the reporters “work” in small numbers of neurons and even respond to more natural firing conditions. These results will be reported soon in experiments that describe the firing patterns of different circadian neurons. We now make a bare bones “data not shown” statement in the revised manuscript to indicate that the reporters work in PDF neurons.</p><p><italic>Additional revisions (Textural changes/clarification):</italic> </p><p><italic>1) Do any of the ARG genes the authors identified have known roles in neuronal plasticity? If so, what portion? This should be included in the Discussion.</italic> </p><p>Many fly genes are involved in plasticity, with functions from regulating chromatin structure to post-translational modification. There are for sure some hits, but it is hard to say accurately what fraction they are.</p><p><italic>2) We cannot find the information of how many flies or brains were used for each experiment. Also, were all of the flies of the same sex or a mix? How old were the flies when these experiments were performed? The authors should provide enough information so that others can replicate the findings.</italic> </p><p>The information is now added to the Methods section.</p><p><italic>3) For ChR2-flies, the authors state &quot;A 30-second 10 Hz LED exposure was sufficient to induce a uniform seizure within seconds, and all flies were able to recover within 15 min.&quot; For the dTrpA1 experiments, however, no phenotypic descriptions are provided. Did the dTrpA1 flies also show a similar seizure phenotype? If the flies do not show seizures or show a different behavioral defect during the stimulation, the two stimuli maybe acting on different neuronal populations (despite the two proteins being expressed pan-neuronally with elav-GAL4) leading to a difference in the ARG list.</italic> </p><p>The stimulation paradigm used for TrpA1 shifts the flies from 18°C to 29°C. No seizures were observed. However, shifting to an even higher temperature causes seizures, suggesting a similar or overlapping set of neurons are stimulated in both cases. However, we avoided shifting to above 30°C to minimize effects from heat and stress. Although it is possible that the TrpA1 paradigm is not as strong as the ChR2-XXL paradigm, similar levels of induction were observed for the genes in common between the two paradigms.</p><p><italic>4) The authors should state the amount/concentration of ATR that was fed to theChR2 flies.</italic> </p><p>The concentration was and still is mentioned in the Methods section.</p><p><italic>5) In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>, Is the 'weak anti-correlation' between change in gene expression and relative gene length significant? What is the R value?</italic> </p><p>R<sup>2</sup> for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref> is 0.13, and for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref> it is 0.03. Although.13 is low, it is still 4 times higher than.03. In addition, the low numbers suggest that gene length is not the only factor that determines induction rate. We suspect that the low numbers are also influenced by the many genes with low fold-changes. Nonetheless, we recognize that this figures is marginal and are of course willing to remove it if that is the reviewer/editorial consensus.</p><p><italic>6) In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7B</xref>, there appears to be a second peak of luciferase activity at the end of recording with the eip78C reporter. Is this typical? Background? Non-specific activation? Is the signal observed significantly different from the control (looks very similar)? Additionally, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>, both of these 'control' reporters seem to have less of a response compared to controls. Is there any possible explanation for that phenomenon? Is the difference significant?</italic> </p><p>This is atypical, which was not described properly in the Figure legend. As mentioned (also added to the text), the reporters are a little noisy, which may indicate that they also respond to spontaneous firing. In addition, we have evidence that the reporters are regulated by other factors such as circadian rhythms (see above). We truncated the last time point of this graph in the revised manuscript so it looks less confusing. The 1<sup>st</sup> time point with low values was generated by a program error in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref>, which is now also removed. Neither the control nor the experimental flies respond to LED stimulation (indicated by black bars beneath the graphs) in the updated figure.</p><p><italic>7) Many of the experiments used a control with CyO in the background. While we understand that there are advantages to using siblings for comparison, balancer chromosomes often incur unpredictable phenotypes. Therefore, were any steps taken to ensure that the CyO chromosome was not significantly different from WT?</italic> </p><p>Gene expression of the CyO flies at baseline levels are similar to that of the TrpA1 flies, showing a very high R<sup>2</sup>. In response to heat shocks, they also show similar induction amplitudes. Lastly, the chromatin structure of CyO flies at baseline is also similar to the TrpA1 flies. Therefore, we believe that the CyO flies are not distinguishable from the gene expression point of view from our dTrpA1 flies.</p><p><italic>8) In the second paragraph of the subsection “Promoter Regions of ARGs are at Permissive State Prior to Stimulation”, what do you mean when you refer to &quot;all annotated genes&quot;? This phrasing is used several times throughout the manuscript, but is not adequately explained. Does this mean all fly genes, all ARGs or something else?</italic> </p><p>It means all fly genes. These features were downloaded from Flybase. The link for download is added to the manuscript now.</p><p><italic>9) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>: Misalignment of &quot;Dissecte d Brains&quot; in A.</italic> </p><p>Fixed.</p><p><italic>10) In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, were the 8 genes shown in E selected at random or was there a reason to leave out the other 4?</italic> </p><p>Sorry for missing the other 4 genes. They are now put back on.</p><p><italic>11) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>: The axes for A and B are not internally consistent; I believe that all coordinates should range from -5 to 5.</italic> </p><p>The axes are corrected. But since -5 to 5 makes the dots too clustered, we changed to -2 to 4.</p><p><italic>12) Formatting of Tables 9 and 10 needs to be adjusted. Also, since only 3 of the columns in both of these tables have different values, the tables could be shrunk down with the rest of the information (which is the same for all columns) described in a legend.</italic> </p><p>Thank you for the advice. The tables have been shrunk down as recommended.</p></body></sub-article></article>